Okay, sorry for that.
Little internet problem.
I was about this close to running slides.com off my phone, but he saved me with the ethernet
cable.
A couple quick announcements.
One thing I want to make sure you know is that the p-set this week is a little bit longer
than last week, but it's awesome.
It's really good.
It has you building full robots, doing things, and a lot of people build off this problem
set for their project.
We decided to not make it shorter and keep it.
I think it's pretty good.
I have a random question.
Just quick show of hands.
How many people have thought about the Roman Empire this week?
Okay, so that was ... I know who watches TikTok.
That's good.
My daughter made me ask that.
She's going to be happy that I went through with it.
If you didn't get it, you're better off.
Okay, so I want to continue on our conversation about kinematics.
In particular, you remember our plan here was to do basic pick and place.
Just very simple.
We've got a robot.
We've got a red brick.
We want to move the red brick from one bin to the second bin.
Our plan for that was to go through some of the mechanics of geometry, of kinematics,
of spatial algebra.
I tried to lift it a little bit above sine and cosine and talk about the algebra involved
in spatial geometries.
Then to actually write the code, the first step we do is we just forget about the robot
entirely and just imagine in the land of transforms what's the ideal place for my gripper to be.
We made some key frames for picking up, for clearing, for setting down.
Then we tried to compose that into a trajectory.
We were a little careful to try to interpolate that trajectory nicely, even in the rotations.
We had to use a proper slurp interpolation for that.
But then the problem, of course, is that that's in the gripper trajectory and ultimately what
we need to do is send position commands to the robot.
We started talking about kinematics, which is the mapping from joint angles on the robot
to, for instance, gripper end effector position.
We did that by just more kinematics, more spatial transforms.
We have a frame for every link.
The transforms between those frames are given as a function of the local joint angle and
you can just compose those transforms to go all the way up to the end effector.
The last step, which is the goal for today, is to actually take that all the way through
to the robot commands.
We're going to do that with differential inverse kinematics.
So let me say it even a slightly different way.
You'll understand why, I think, in some detail by the end of the class here.
But we have, from our previous work, x is the pose of the gripper in the world frame.
And we have a trajectory for it.
So we have it defined from 0 to 30 seconds or something like that.
And we need q as a function of time.
And really what we need is the desired q as a function of time, because that's what our
abstraction on the robot takes in, this iwa position command.
There's software running on the robot that's waiting for that message to arrive, which
tells me what's the desired position.
And I've mocked that with the hardware station.
So inside here is the plant, the geometry engine, but also the low-level controller
simulation, which is waiting for the same iwa position.
And even though it's spelled out here, we're just thinking of that as q desired.
That's the commanded position of the arm.
So we need to somehow go from the end effector pose to the joint angles in the arm.
And last time, we talked about the relationship between those two.
We talked about forward kinematics, which was the mapping to the gripper as a function.
We called it-- we annotated the function with the frame it was working on.
We called it the kinematics function here, which took the joint angles of the arm and
did that series of calculations to get to the end.
So to go the other way, what we need somehow is the inverse kinematics.
We need to somehow go from x through something like f inverse to get back to q.
Inverse kinematics is hard.
In general, it's very hard.
Often there are many solutions.
Sometimes there's no solutions.
The equations in here, even though they're a simple series of transforms, they have a
lot of nonlinear equations going on inside here.
It's a pretty nonlinear, non-trivial function of q.
So what we're going to do today, though, is solve that problem, but in a slightly roundabout
way.
We're going to do it on the differential kinematics.
So this is a complicated mapping, and we'll solve it nicely with stronger optimization
tools when we have them a little later in the class.
But for today, we don't need to solve the harder problem.
We can actually make it easy again by going into the differential kinematics.
So I'm going to write it at the high level, and we'll go through it in detail.
But roughly, vg is our spatial velocities, which is like the derivative of the poses.
This is related, as it says on the board there, through a simple relationship with-- well,
it's a non-trivial relationship to the joint positions, but it's a simple linear relationship
to the joint velocities.
So if I know instantaneously where the robot is, that's what q is, then this just becomes
a matrix.
And the relationship between vg and v is simple.
So I can instantaneously, if I know where the robot is, I can command a change in joint
angles that would cause the right change in joint velocity.
And it's not surprising that even though the map, the full kinematic map, is hard, the
differential kinematic map is easy.
Small changes here relate to small changes here, and you just have to know the derivatives,
basically, to make that work.
Now this is something we're going to work with easily.
And it's not perfect.
It has limitations.
But the limitations are clear because they come from linear algebra.
Yeah?
We're going to do it through as a dynamical system.
We're going to do it by incrementally, I would say.
And we will, of course, do it numerically, but incrementally maybe is the better view.
So our plan here is to go from xg as a trajectory to vg as a trajectory.
We're going to send this into a system that we'll call DiffIK.
You'll hear that a lot, the differential inverse kinematics.
And this is going to give us v, which is the joint velocities.
And then we're going to actually integrate that back, integrator, and get q.
So it seems a little roundabout, but it's going to be the way that I think sheds the
most insight.
And people do this in practice.
For many reasons, it's a very nice formulation.
It's a workhorse in robotics.
And again, the immediate reason, just to say it-- so this is a big nonlinear function,
hard to analyze, hard to invert in closed form.
There's some cases where you can, but oftentimes you cannot.
Once q is known, this is a linear map.
We know everything about it in linear algebra.
So to do this well and to understand all the details, we're going to-- because all the
details come up because of the complexity of 3D rotations, I promised you last time
that I'd say a few more words about 3D rotations and the different representations.
You guys were asking some good questions about it.
Let's just talk a little bit more about 3D rotations.
So there's a lot of ways to represent 3D rotations.
One of them is rotation matrices.
In the 3D case, that would be a 3 by 3 matrix.
Nine total numbers.
It's a very efficient representation because GPUs made it great.
You can transform-- you can push things through rotation matrices very fast.
But it's over-parameterized in some sense.
So we don't need nine numbers to describe a 3D rotation.
This is extra.
And in fact, not all nine numbers will work.
There are constraints on the nine numbers that make a valid rotation matrix.
In particular, if I call the rotation matrix R, then R needs to be orthonormal.
The rotation matrix needs to be orthonormal.
The simplest way to write that would be to say if I have a matrix R, then R R transpose
needs to be the identity.
This is all 3 by 3.
There's even one other constraint that comes in.
You want a regular rotation.
You want the determinant of R to be 1.
You don't have to know that.
But what's important is that if you just give me nine random numbers or you try to write
a program that's combing over-- searching over nine numbers, not all nine numbers are
sufficient.
They have to also satisfy some extra constraints to be valid rotation matrix.
So that's a burden to carry that around.
And if you're doing, let's say, even numerical integration of rotation matrices, if you're
not projecting back-- small numerical errors can leave these constraints behind.
You have to do projected methods and the like.
Let's contrast that with Euler angles.
And there's many-- you can write any permutation of rolls and pitches and yaws if you want.
But we always do the extrinsic roll, pitch, yaw when I talk about it.
It's one of the choices.
It is actually three numbers-- roll, which is rotation around x; pitch, which is rotation
around y; yaw, which is rotation around z.
This is great.
It's three numbers, no constraints.
So that seems smaller.
It's only better.
No constraints, that's better.
But there's a gotcha.
It's places where that rotation becomes-- that set of three numbers becomes degenerate.
And the way that people-- the best way to see this-- by the way, I've written this up
with links to more references and stuff in the notes.
But the classic example is gimbal lock.
I got about halfway through making a mustard bottle in Meshcat do all this.
And I was like, screw it.
There's so many good visualizations online.
And mine wasn't-- the mustard bottle was in the wrong frame, and nobody knows what the
x-axis of the mustard bottle is.
So I just picked up this website real quick.
This is pretty good.
So this is a spaceship, I guess.
So this is roll.
This is pitch.
Put it back to zero so pitch is clean.
Pitch is nose up, nose down, for instance.
And yaw is rotation around z, the nominal thing.
But because these transformations are chained, then things get more complicated when you
do them in series.
In particular, the weird case is when I pitch to 90.
Then you can see it with the visualization already.
But rolling does this.
Yawing also does that.
Because in that configuration, rolling and yawing do the same thing.
They cannot be distinguished.
But that also means there's some direction where you cannot move instantaneously.
There's a singularity in the translation between those numbers and a full rotation matrix--
from a full rotation back to those numbers.
You're kind of stuck.
The coordinate system becomes degenerate in that case.
Two of the numbers are representing the same rotation.
And therefore, there's no number representing one of the important rotations.
And there's theorems saying that you cannot perfectly represent in a singularity-free
way the 3D rotations with just three numbers.
You need four numbers to do it.
OK.
Another one that is super useful but also degenerate in this particular way-- in these
kind of ways-- is axis angle.
It's also three numbers.
No constraints, but degenerate in some setting.
And this is an x, y, z that we normally would write.
It's a three-dimensional quantity where the direction of x, y, z is the instantaneous
direction of rotation.
So that's the axis I'm rotating around.
And the magnitude of the vector is the magnitude of the rotation.
You can imagine if I want to just rotate from here to here, I can pick-- for any rotations,
you can pick up some single axis and rotate a scalar quantity around that axis to represent
those rotations.
OK?
Yeah.
Zero vectors is a good example of it.
We're actually-- we're going to ask you that one on the problem set.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
They're all very closely related.
The screw theory is more closely related to the angular velocity, which is extremely
closely related to this.
Yep.
OK.
Very tempting three numbers.
So the direction is axis of rotation, and magnitude is the angle.
And the last one that we use all the time here is the unit quaternions.
There's a quaternion algebra that I will not lecture about.
You don't need to-- I mean, you can just call methods in the software, and it'll just do
the right thing.
You don't have to know the quaternion algebra for this class.
OK.
So we have four numbers plus one constraint, which is that the four numbers are unit length
in total.
So we call them q, x, y, z-- sorry, w, x, y, z.
And I'll sometimes write q in front of them to remember it's a quaternion.
OK?
So I'll write that bigger and with less mistakes.
Hold on a second.
I'll just-- for now, I'll just say w, x, y, z.
OK?
And the one constraint is that the vector be unit length.
So w squared plus x squared plus y squared plus z squared has to equal 1.
That is the minimal representation that we have-- four numbers, one constraint-- that
is singularity-free.
It still has some quirks.
Like you can just flip your unit quaternion inside, and you get the same rotation.
That's not too bad.
So I'll tell you the most common things we're going to see when we want a vector representation
of our rotations.
We're going to choose these four numbers almost always.
That's the most compact.
OK?
But when we're just thinking about kinematics and multiplying, transforming, boom, boom,
boom, as soon as we get into that kind of space, we're going to go with the 3 by 3 and
not worry about efficiency as much.
We're going to just be able to just multiply these quickly.
The Euler angle and the axis angle are super useful to know about.
We used them already when we were doing the transform.
If you look in the code, we used both axis angle and Euler angle because it was convenient
to interpolate between these two with axis angle, and it was convenient to write some
of the other things in roll pitch yaw.
And the robot description formats tend to just ask for things in roll pitch yaw.
So it's good to know about them.
But the most important thing to know about them is that you can flip back and forth between
them.
OK?
They're mostly equivalent until you're in some singular sort of configuration.
OK.
So with that-- oh, yeah, please.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So you can uniquely define a rotation.
So every rotation has a rotation matrix.
That's OK.
Yeah.
This one is the one that's degenerate in some places.
And this is degenerate.
But all of these, I think, are complete-- those two are complete in some sense.
Like every rotation you can write as a rotation matrix or as a unit quaternion.
That is also true of Euler angles, but it's just that the maps between them can get singular.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yep.
So every-- yes, every rotation can-- has it-- well, you can have a unique choice of the
rotation matrix, yes.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
There's always patterns where things are equivalent.
But in general, no.
As I say, in general, no.
So the order of the rotations matters.
And even there's-- people will talk about extrinsic roll pitch yaw versus intrinsic
roll pitch yaw, which measures if you apply roll first or yaw first.
They're all different representations.
They're all equivalent, but they-- you have to be careful converting back and forth between
them.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Ah.
It's actually-- I didn't explain them.
And in some sense, they're like complex numbers.
They are actually the four-dimensional generalization of complex numbers.
So asking me to explain complex numbers quickly is kind of hard.
It's sort of magical algebraic properties that make them useful.
So it turns out that with those four numbers, you can define an entire algebra that captures
all the rotation.
Intuitively, you can think of this almost like axis angle, where this is a direction
and this is a magnitude, except that the whole thing is scaled very cleverly so that it avoids
those singularities.
Yeah.
I would say, when you're trying to initialize quaternions, set w to 1 and then set those
to be your direction of interest, and you'll be pretty good.
Or use Rolfe-Jaw and then convert to quaternion.
That's way better.
This one's less intuitive, I'd say.
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes, real-- yeah.
The interpretation as complex numbers, which actually, my favorite notes about that are
linked in the notes, if you like it.
Yeah.
So you would introduce complex numbers in order to understand it through that lens.
[INAUDIBLE]
Because w is implied.
I'd be happy to write it everywhere, but if I'd leave it off, then my shorthand is that
if I didn't write a superscript, then the relative frame is the world.
That's great.
Good to catch me on that.
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE]
That's true.
Yeah.
So some software uses x, y, z, w.
I mean, I learned the alphabet a long time ago, and I don't like that.
I think w, x, y, z is always better.
I'm sorry if you-- yeah.
But yeah, no.
Even inside, we use Eigen as a library in C++, and they put that in the last one.
But we do everything we can to hide that from you.
So it's always w, x, y, z for us.
It just makes more sense, right?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Why do they get the name?
I mean, so that is mostly true.
I think that's the right way to understand it.
But really, they're also elements from a four-dimensional space that live on this sphere in four numbers.
So yeah.
Where did w come from?
I don't know.
I bet that reference I linked would give you the history of it.
Yeah.
So this is where we care about being efficient, especially if we want to put it in a vector.
In fact, this is a great lead-in.
So for instance, if I'm listing the-- when I list the joint angles of my robot in my
Q vector-- I think I even have a slide for this.
Yeah.
OK.
So if I have the Q vector for ewa-- let me just-- before I even use that slide.
If the robot is ewa, then the Q vector is just the list of joint angles.
So it's going to be seven numbers.
It's a 7 by 1 vector.
So if you have a Q vector for a system that is just a single brick floating in space,
then the positions that define that are just the 3D rotation.
So if you ask for what is Q, and you ask for-- if you ask for what is Q for that, Q for the
brick, you'll also find out that it gets a 7 by 1 vector.
But that 7 by 1 is going to be x, y, z, Qw, Qx, Qy, Qz.
Positions and orientations in quaternion form is the way we choose to represent the
generalized positions of our robot.
So when we choose a vector notation, this is our favorite vector notation, as opposed
to sticking nine numbers and unrolling them, or picking one that could potentially be degenerate.
Now if you take and compute the transform, if you ask for the kinematics call-- so valve
body pose in world is sort of the how do you evaluate the kinematics given the context--
it's going to give you this back in 3 by 3 matrix.
What's actually the 3 by 4 matrix, which is the rigid transform, the 3 by 3 matrix plus
the vectors.
So in those two places right next to each other in the code, we choose quaternions for
this and rotation matrices for that.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Quaternions have their algebra that, yes, they compose nicely.
You have to learn that.
It's kind of its own algebra, but it does have the nice rules of composition.
So in this particular case, if you're calling the kinematics function, which is a valve
body pose in world, for a thing that just is a brick, then that function is actually
just implementing the change of rotations from a vector q into the 3 by 3 matrix.
That's the only work it's doing.
It doesn't have to do composition of frames.
It's just one frame.
But it still has to convert representation.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
So the differential kinematics, then-- so you see why this is starting to get subtle
is that this is potentially like a 3 by 3 matrix or a 3 by 4 matrix, for instance.
And this is potentially a 7 by 1 vector.
And so if we're thinking about the kinematics like that and we start thinking about the
gradients of that, then we have to be careful about the different representations.
So the differential kinematics are roughly just taking the partial derivative of that
kinematics function.
That's the object we want to think about.
But all the details of how you represent that-- by the way, we almost always call it the Jacobian,
kinematic Jacobian.
Well, the Jacobian-- any partial derivative in any discipline could be called a Jacobian.
But I guess in robotics, we just always call it-- when we say Jacobian with no other context,
it's almost always the kinematic Jacobian.
But all the details about this are about how did you represent Q and how did you represent
pose.
And there's details there that matter.
So in order to understand those details, we have one more thing to do, which is we have
to understand what are convenient ways to write the derivatives of rotation.
So you could imagine that I could write the time derivative of a rotation matrix.
That's a perfectly well-defined object.
I could have the nine values all changing with time.
And I could have the roll pitch yaw, roll dot, pitch dot, yaw dot, all changing with
time.
Those are all totally valid.
But in the case of derivatives of rotations, there is a canonical choice.
You can use three numbers.
And without any limitations, there's a uniquely good choice.
And we always use it.
And it's most similar to the axis angle.
And that's the spatial velocity.
It's approximately the time derivative of-- it is the time derivative of the notion of
rotation, but it's not the time derivative of the 3 by 4 matrix.
It's defined to be a 6 by 1 vector.
V of the gripper is the angular velocity.
And the translational velocity is a 6 by 1 vector with the angular velocity and the translational
velocity.
The angular velocity is always three numbers.
And you can represent it without any of the quirks.
And the people who think about geometry a lot or differential geometry a lot, that's
natural and obvious, but it's slightly non-trivial.
But basically, there's a couple of different ways to say it.
Actually, Tommy and I were arguing earlier today about what's the best way to say it.
But because Tommy loves differential geometry, if you haven't gone to his office hours and
asked him about differential geometry, you should.
So maybe the simplest thing to say is that you could think about angles actually wrap
around.
So they have a periodicity involved.
So if I rotate by 2 pi more, then I get back to the same angle.
So there's some quirks that come with that.
And that's like the pitch rolling in and out itself and everything like that.
Angular velocities can be unbounded.
More velocity means I'm going more that way.
There's no wraparound effects or anything like that.
That's maybe one of the simplest ways to see why the geometry of that object is different.
And it turns out that these three numbers, which have the interpretation-- the angular
velocity has the interpretation where the three numbers, the direction, is again the
instantaneous axis of rotation.
And the magnitude is the rate of rotation around that axis.
That's why it's most similar to the axis angle.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
That's what Drake follows.
I don't know if it's everybody.
I think people choose.
But we've tried to be-- everywhere you see it in this class, we've tried to be very consistent.
So here, three numbers are sufficient and efficient everywhere.
So you'll always see us using the angular velocity specifically.
Now angular velocities-- yeah, please.
[INAUDIBLE]
Correct.
OK.
Well, so if you think about some of the constrained representations, let's say the unit quaternion
has to live on the surface of a sphere.
So the geometry behind that-- you think about this as the tangent surface of the sphere--
is where the velocities live on.
And that is a well-defined object that is unbounded and perfectly well-defined.
So it's not-- I didn't pull a rabbit out of a hat.
It's actually the tangent bundle of these geometric quantities.
Very good.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
So you're absolutely right.
So the point here is it's a little weird.
So in fact, if I take q ewa, and I have seven numbers, and then I say, what's the generalized
velocity, v-- by the way, so I said, watch my notation.
So capital V with this script is spatial velocity.
Lowercase v in the same font is translational velocity.
The times v, times Roman, v is the generalized velocity.
There's three of them flying around.
It's almost always clear from the context.
But there are three v's flying around.
This is the one that corresponds to-- when I say generalized velocity or generalized,
that's like the joint angles.
And if you have to pack a free body into the joint angles, then you use quaternions.
And for velocities, you get a 6 by 1 list of numbers.
And so you're absolutely right.
It's a little weird that q dot would be seven numbers, but v is six numbers.
And so you have to watch that and treat that carefully.
So for the ewa, it'd be just 7 and 7.
But I'm sorry.
I wrote this completely wrong.
V ewa is 7 by 1.
It's v brick that's 6 by 1.
That was the whole point of writing that on the board, so I get that right.
6 by 1.
OK?
So this one, since these are all rotations, simple pin joints, all of their velocities
are still a scalar.
And I get seven numbers.
But since this one's using a quaternion representation, I only need six numbers to represent its time
derivative.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Correct.
Exactly.
Exactly right.
So just to say it out loud, since I'm on the mic here.
So yeah.
So in the six numbers, there are six numbers.
No constraints, no degeneracies.
It's three numbers, which is wx, wy, wz.
Whoops.
That's a z.
And that's the direction of instantaneous rotation.
And the magnitude of the vector is the rate of rotation around that vector.
It's actually-- it's interesting that any derivative of rotation can be represented
that way.
But you can always pick an instantaneous direction of rotation and a magnitude.
And even more so, which is actually what I was putting up here, it has nicely magical
properties.
So it has the same sort of algebra.
Addition in angular velocity has the same-- it works when the frames match.
Which is totally weird to think about, I've got a direction.
I've got instantaneous rotation around this.
I've got another direction.
I can just add them.
So that's non-trivial, but it works.
The additive inverse works.
So we have the same sort of algebra.
They're slightly more complicated.
There's some cross product terms that come in.
But it works.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Good.
So the question is then, so when I call-- you guys are awesome.
You're leading all of my slides here by a little bit here.
So this is your question from a minute ago, which is that actually there is a simple matrix
that transitions between the two.
So the fact that Q and V are not the same.
But there's a simple transformation that you can use that goes back and forth between them.
You can call map Q dot to velocity or vice versa.
And it's done efficiently and everything.
And then for your question, OK, so if I want to get a Jacobian in software, then the decisions
I have to make are, do I want the right-hand side of that to be multiplied by Q dot?
Or do I want to be multiplying it by V?
And you can actually just pick Jacobian with respect to variable.
And it's either Q dot or V. You can ask for either Jacobian.
And it depends on the application which one you want.
On the right-hand side, you can ask, do I want the Q dot kind of thing?
Or do I want the angular velocity?
And almost always, we were going to give you this-- that's why this one's called calc
Jacobian spatial velocity.
That means the left-hand side is going to be written in terms of spatial velocities.
If you hear the term geometric Jacobian versus analytic Jacobian, the geometric Jacobian
fits out spatial velocities.
Analytic Jacobian is more literally d forward kinematics dt.
But we rarely use that one.
It's almost always spatial velocity, because we always work in spatial velocities for velocity.
You can also notice just quickly with this up here, we really do lean into the monogram
notation for everything.
So it's a little annoying the first time you do it, but it keeps everything clean.
And the equations are correct.
That's good.
I have a couple like, check yourself, but I think you guys have checked yourself mostly.
So yeah, that makes sense.
There's an outlier here, but I think we all understand it.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
This would be-- in this case, it's just seven joint angles, rotation, rotation, rotation.
So the pin joints, so it's the angle of each of those joints, which is relative angles.
And this is the time derivative of those.
This is translation plus quaternion, translation velocity plus-- this is the spatial velocity
inside there.
OK, so we have a couple of different ways to get J. And again, all of the details.
The reason it's not just a simple time derivative is because of these rotation things.
In 2D, everything's just clean.
You just use beta.
None of this three numbers stuff, four numbers stuff.
Beta does everything you need.
And then rotation matrices are two by two.
They're simple.
There's a canonical choice for Jacobians.
It's just a little bit more work here.
All right.
So the rough idea for differential IK is to basically take J inverse.
So nominally, I want, say, my V desired, my generalized velocities, let's even call it
joint velocities, of my gripper here.
I'll take an inverse of that times my desired gripper spatial velocity.
This is the idea behind diff IK.
But let's be a little careful.
Every time you write an inverse, you've got to think about, am I allowed to take an inverse
of this?
Is that matrix invertible?
So what's the answer in this case?
So let's take for the EWA.
And I've got the gripper frame.
How big is this?
6, 7.
So that's not even a square matrix there.
So it doesn't have an inverse.
That's bad, and I shouldn't have ever written that on the board.
But we can do a little bit better by, if I just change that into a symbol of your choice,
I normally use the number sign, or the plus.
Sometimes I use plus, actually.
But what do I use?
Plus.
Let's go with plus.
Depends on the day.
But plus.
That's a pseudo-inverse.
Yep, Mohr-Penrose pseudo-inverse.
So if you call p-inv in MATLAB or in Python or something like this, that's going to give
you the Mohr-Penrose pseudo-inverse.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
In this particular case, so it would still have the same problems?
That's a good question.
So are there parts of the space where that would still work?
There's still redundancy, so I don't think it could.
I don't think it could.
It's just more hidden in that case.
The matrix would have to be--
[INAUDIBLE]
Right.
Because, in fact, a way to see it is that it's going to be this j times this n.
So it's going to be a low-rank matrix times this n.
So it won't be full rank.
It's a great question, though.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah?
The simple answer-- so the question is, what about a 6-degree of freedom robot?
The simple answer is yes, but it depends exactly on-- most of the robots that you can buy today,
if they have six joints, then you can actually-- that'll be full rank.
You can still get them into singular configurations.
If you were to-- you can't just take a random six links.
And for instance, if I just gave you a bunch of prismatic joints and then asked you to
control orientation at the end, that's not going to work.
But the standard revolute, 6-revolute, or the variations you see, yes.
And that's actually-- when you hear people talking about analytic IK, they're typically
exploiting the fact that 6 degrees of freedom can be controlled by six joints on a robot.
Yeah.
OK.
The pseudo-inverse-- how many people have seen-- used the pseudo-inverse before?
Yeah?
Do you know how awesome it is?
It's extremely good.
It's like a very-- I mean, you just called P-inverse.
It's a P-in, but you don't think about it.
But it's really smart.
So what can happen when you're taking a matrix and it's not square, and you're trying to
invert it?
I mean, basically, there's three possible situations.
You could have no solutions.
You could have-- I mean, if it's square, then you could have one solution.
Or you can have infinite solutions.
So the pseudo-inverse sort of does the best possible thing it could do in every situation.
If you have infinite solutions, it's going to give you one that satisfies it perfectly.
But in the null space of that, it's going to pick the smallest solution, the minimum
norm solution.
If there's a unique solution, it will return the unique solution.
It's just as good-- it's a little more expensive than calling inverse, but it's going to give
you the same numbers as calling inverse, up to numerical.
If there's no solutions, then it's going to give you a best effort solution.
It's going to get as close as possible in a least squares sense.
So that's really, really smart.
And we'll understand, I guess, from an optimization perspective, how to generalize that soon.
But let's appreciate it first.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, that's a great question.
So I understand how to do a pseudo-inverse with all those magical properties for a linear
transform.
But if it's a nonlinear map, then I don't know how to do the same stuff.
This is the result of linear least squares.
And nonlinear least squares is a lot harder.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Minimum norm.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
That's right.
It's a convenient property because that's what pseudo-inverse does.
But I think you're right to ask.
That may or may not be the right thing.
And we're going to generalize this so that we can be very explicit about what we wanted
to do when no solutions exist or when there's multiple solutions exist.
In fact, when multiple solutions exist, we should pick up-- it's better to not let pseudo-inverse--
I mean, as clever as it is, I'd rather say what I wanted to do in the null space.
And we can say that very explicitly.
And then also in the case of not being sufficient, like if I'm throwing a baseball at really
high speeds and I can't get it exactly right, I'd rather stop.
I'd rather not throw the ball, maybe, or something like that, rather than going off way off to
the side.
And that's actually-- that is true of real robot motions.
Typically, if you can't follow a trajectory, the one we use the most, it will slow down
and follow the actual trajectory as well as possible.
But it will not deviate from the trajectory because if you worked hard to make a collision-free
plan or something, you don't want to just have your low-level controller do that.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yep.
So this is-- so all great questions.
So what do I mean by best effort?
I actually mean that the reconstruction error of J times V will be as close as possible
to V in a least squares sense.
So I will actually take the norm, the L2 norm of the vector and the reconstructed vector,
and that norm will be minimized.
It can happen that you would not want to execute that motion.
That's why we're going to do better.
This is the intro.
This is the first-- this is like first controller.
[INAUDIBLE]
You can definitely just multiply the matrices and see what the difference is for sure.
Yep.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
That's true.
I would always stack them for-- in the generalized position, I would make that a vector representation.
So if you had three in the wrist or something like this, then maybe you'd get up to nine
or 10, depending if you've added a new-- but the generalized coordinate vector is always
a vector.
[INAUDIBLE]
So we want-- and this is a great question.
I mean, there's actually-- because these things are good for computing different quantities,
sometimes you actually compute multiple things.
Drake is going to do that in the background for you.
So if it ever does work to compute rotation matrices and you don't change the context,
then it will cache those.
And future computations will be faster because it already computed that once.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
For sure, prismatic joints can be simulated in Drake or in any software.
It's a standard thing.
Yes, there's definitely robotic arms that will have that.
I guess maybe the most common thing you'll see is like-- even if you took our EWA, some
people will put it on a linear stage or something like this to move around.
Those would be prismatic.
But absolutely, you'll see arms that are like the overhead arms that will have prismatic
joints moving around.
There's also-- there's very clever parallel mechanisms and the like.
OK.
I have a notebook that shows you the-- I'll just tell you what it shows you so I can keep
going here.
But you can plot-- so let me just say one more thing.
So your question also was, can I know when I'm going to get multiple solutions?
That's a good-- so let's just say, how do we know whether this matrix is invertible
just by looking at it?
The conditions on this getting a good solution are that the row rank-- it's full row rank.
So if you will find an exact solution if JG function of Q is full row rank.
So in this case, if it's rank is 6, then that means you can perfectly reconstruct this.
OK.
And pseudo inverse will find it.
So the rank is a very sort of Boolean quantity of the matrix.
And even before you drop rank completely-- like, in real robots, don't get rank 5.
They're not going to get rank-- but they're going to get something very close to rank
5.
And you're going to send extremely large velocities to your robot.
So the interesting thing is not when this becomes strictly non-invertible, but when
it becomes almost non-invertible numerically, such that when I ask for a velocity in some
direction that I can't go, I will send an enormous v.
When this thing becomes almost low rank, that's the condition to watch out for.
So if JG is full row rank, that's fine.
But the real thing you want to watch is the singular values of J. And if the smallest
singular value gets close to 0, that means there's some direction.
If you ask it to move in that direction, you're going to get-- when you take an inverse of
something close to 0, you're going to get something close to infinity.
And you're going to get very large velocities.
That's the problem.
So for instance, take my IWA, and I straighten its arms out.
That's the condition where my ability to move-- so if I ask it to move in a velocity like
this, it's going to say, I need extremely large velocities, because that lever arm is
so small, in order to move at the commanded velocity.
And you just don't want to send that to the robot.
So in practice, in the notebooks, if you want to run them, you'll see that I plot out the
lowest singular value.
And you can watch.
The arm gets straight.
The singular value gets close to 0.
And you're in bad shape.
So singularities are this thing that we think about a lot.
Sometimes we think about them in motion planning.
So we try to avoid straightening the arm.
It happens on-- so if you have a tele-op interface, and you're just messing around with your robot,
and you're, I don't know, trying to do something clever, then you're going to go, whunk, like
this.
And if your controller isn't protecting you from that, either bad things will happen,
or the robot will power down, or fault, or something like that.
So you have to-- you kind of have to think about this when you're writing your low-level
controller.
But people get funny about thinking about singularities.
It's not a black hole.
It's not like the robot explodes.
It's really-- so OK, here's a way to phrase that question.
Is it the math that's breaking?
Or is it the robot that's-- is it physically something that's stuck in the robot?
And it's really sort of the math.
It's the map from end effector to joint angle that's breaking.
So the thinking in end effector coordinates fails when you get into a singularity.
It's not the right place to think about it.
But the robot can perfectly go through singular configurations, as long as you're not thinking
in end effector space.
And to make that point, let me jump to this.
I made this super simple example.
It's a two-dimensional robot.
The kinematics are perfectly clean.
It has a singular configuration, which you can see in two lines, when the arm goes straight.
But I'm going to play basically a sine wave and go in and out of-- I can make it-- I can
go and make it in and out of singularity.
It's no problem.
We can write down exactly what the Jacobian does during that.
And the singular value gets to 0 and back out again.
And that's fine.
Nothing explodes.
It's perfectly good.
But what's happening there?
It's kind of-- it's an interesting-- you have to sort of think
through that.
So the map that says, if I'm perfectly straight-- no, I'll stop it.
I think it's going to be annoying.
I'm perfectly straight.
The map says there is no velocity I can execute that will make my hand come closer to the
base.
But there's clearly a velocity-- there's clearly something I can execute to get me closer to
the base.
What's up?
What happened?
Yeah.
Second order.
Yeah, you got it.
So instantaneously, the velocity at that moment, even though the command's going through, the
velocity going towards the base is 0.
But it can instantaneously accelerate towards the base.
So at the next time step, it's a little bit more.
And then it's going to go through.
So you have to look at the second derivative to get out of that particular one.
Or you just send sine waves in.
If you think in joint space, then you're immune to that mapping, of course.
So once you're in the six-dimensional land, then derivatives make sense.
You can just take simple derivatives.
I don't have to explain the different representations and stuff like this.
So you can really just take J dot.
And there's a canonical choice for J dot once you have J.
That's good.
Yeah.
Yeah, I'm going to stop there.
So this is the makings of a controller.
Now we have the basic idea that we're going to write this diff_ik controller, where if
you put on an input port the desired spatial velocity, a 6 by 1 number, and you tell me--
in the thing that implements the system, you tell me what the robot's like.
I will call calc Jacobian spatial velocity.
I'll take an inverse, and I'll compute this velocity out.
So let's do that.
It's worth doing.
I'm just going to send a simple feedforward constant command in spatial velocity here.
I just said a constant spatial velocity, and I gave it a little bit of a twist just so
it wasn't just going straight down or whatever.
But I just send move your hand down in this translational velocity and a little bit of
angular velocity, and it does its thing.
And it's just a few lines of code.
In Drake, when you write the system, you make a new system.
You basically have to declare the input ports, the output ports, and then you make your little
output, which just calcs the Jacobian.
You get the spatial velocity.
I just hard-coded the desired.
I take a p_inv, and I set the output.
And I've done the work.
Yeah?
OK.
We're going to make that a little bit better and a little bit more general in a second
here.
One more detail that I left behind here.
So how did we go from this to this?
I had a piecewise pose trajectory that we computed by composition of transforms and
then slurping them together.
But how did I go from this to a derivative of that?
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
You can do it-- we don't have to fit anything.
You can do it perfectly.
And it's just the same math of all the spatial derivatives and spatial quantities.
We do know the entire function.
So actually, so far in the code, when we put this together, we actually represented this
as a piecewise pose trajectory.
We called that, which was doing linear interpolation for translation
and quaternion slurp for rotations.
And this is one of the trajectory classes in Drake.
It turns out you can just-- and I called this xg trajectory in the code.
Since these are such common operations, the trajectory classes all support the types of
operations you want to run on them.
So you can just say equals xg traj dot make derivative.
And it does exactly the spatial operations needed.
They map from the quaternion slurp into a perfect piecewise-- this one is a piecewise
polynomial now-- which is linear interpolation in spatial velocity.
And it just comes out of the same types of transformations-- no, that's a bad choice--
of conversions that we used to go back and forth between the different representations.
So let me just show you real quick, since I've got it open here.
This is my first crack at the gimbal lock.
I've got a mustard bottle.
It does all the right things, but I'm like, no one's going to know what I'm talking about.
So I canned that.
I'll make it better tomorrow.
So now let's just think about putting that whole thing together.
So we have the sketch with key frames.
We're going to make the gripper frames.
This is the code I showed you before.
Just a composition of all the different pick, pre-pick, place, pre-place.
I set the timings.
I set the initial gripper position, the initial object position, and a goal object position.
OK.
Visualize them for fun.
Then we're going to turn those into trajectories the way we did before.
Run those through.
30 seconds to execute.
Visualize them.
That was this visualization we said before.
And turn those into trajectories.
Draw those trajectories.
You can turn the orientations into trajectories with Slurp.
Make my little open/close gripper command.
I'm going to do make derivative.
Get the translational.
And then basically the pseudo-inverse controller.
Let me even put this up slightly cleaner on here.
So the pseudo-inverse controller has a vector input port, which is the spatial velocity
commanded coming in.
VWG.
It's six elements.
It takes in the current IWA position.
That's a seven element vector input.
It has one output port, which is the IWA commanded velocity, which is seven numbers.
And to evaluate that output port, you call it calc output.
So anytime somebody asks for my output, it calls calc output.
And I get VG and Q from the input ports.
I set the positions of my internal plant to Q so that I can do kinematics at that state.
I get my calc spatial velocity, JG.
I had to do one little hack because otherwise it wanted to move the-- it gives me the Jacobian
also of the fingers.
And I wanted that to be separate.
So I just pulled off the fingers elements of my Jacobian.
I didn't pull off the fingers.
I removed the rows of the JG corresponding to the fingers.
And then I computed the pseudo-inverse and set from vector.
And you put that-- that's just this code you saw right here.
OK, I get excited.
I know that's a little anti-climatic.
But it takes a second, and then it'll--
beautiful.
Actually, I don't know why Meshcat doesn't update in that case.
Here we go.
OK, so everything is computed directly.
This is a simulation now, not just a plan playback.
You can tell there's the contact forces between the gripper and the brick.
OK, our first end-to-end system.
We've got all the pieces together to do that.
Ha ha.
That's the least impressive thing I've ever been clapped for.
But thank you.
OK, and it's fairly simple.
You have the trajectory source, which we computed.
It goes into the pseudo-inverse controller.
Our integrator, which is just an object.
And that goes right into the EWA position command.
And then we have a simple little WSG command.
That's the whole thing.
Questions about that?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
There is no acceleration compensation here.
So what would go wrong?
So if I were to choose a trajectory in my gripper frame--
this is a really good point.
Since I ignored the arm completely when I made my gripper frame,
if I accidentally put a desired gripper that was at arm's length,
for instance, then this controller would not do good things.
I would not run that on the robot.
I would not give you a teleop device and tell
you to run it on the robot.
We're going to make a better one now.
So I guess in the beginning of the next lecture.
So just to forecast that, this pseudo-inverse
is magical because it's actually solving an optimization problem.
You can think about this as it's actually
solving that least squares optimization problem I
spoke to a little bit.
And we can take an optimization perspective to generalize this.
So if we want to solve a slightly bigger optimization problem,
that we say be as close as possible.
But if you have extra degrees of freedom,
then here's what I want you to do.
Or if you get close to singular, don't do this.
We can start putting guardrails in.
And I'll tell you an optimization view of making a better version
of that controller.
And that one you could hammer on.
And it'll be pretty robust.
Other questions?
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yep, so mathematically, the code defines continuous derivatives.
And you just define a dynamical system
that has continuous derivatives that are one,
that are the magnitude of the input.
And then underneath Drake, whenever
there's a continuous time system,
then it's always running some integrator.
And there's a suite of integrators you pick from.
By default, I put this in--
whenever you're using the hardware station,
there's just doing a fixed step integration
with certain-- like a forward Euler.
Actually, it's not.
I think it's fourth order, but fixed time step.
But you can easily switch between-- you can do Runge-Kutta.
You can do a stiff solver, whatever.
There's a suite of integrators you can pick from.
So when we make a more advanced optimization-based version,
then you have to be a little bit careful about that.
Because if your optimization-based thing
becomes-- it's expensive to compute,
and your solver starts trying to integrate at high accuracy,
then it could solve a lot of optimization problems
to move a red brick.
And you want to avoid that.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
So let me just say that a little bit more carefully.
So the sixth degree of freedom arm
has an analytic IK solution when you have six revolute joints.
But it's not actually--
it's not always unique.
There's still multiple solutions.
I think there's eight.
Tommy would know exactly how many solutions
there are in the sixth.
And so you still have to make some choices about,
do you want your elbow here, do you want your elbow here,
and stuff like this.
And that would be a direct IK solution, which implies
something, of course, if you were going to do diff IK,
it would also be well-behaved.
But that would typically circumvent the need for diff IK.
And you go straight for IK in that sort of setting.
If you were to--
if you had a trajectory in end effector Q,
you could come up with a trajectory out of it.
I guess you'd have to interpolate carefully around
that.
Otherwise, you could get into the same things.
But it's really the mapping from velocities
that gets problematic.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Six degree of freedom robots are terrible.
No, sorry.
They're mathematically beautiful.
But if you have a six degree of freedom robot that
picks something up, you're going to be so frustrated that you
can't get around or do--
it feels extremely limiting once you
have kinematic constraints.
So I was being a little dramatic.
But I really think seven degree of freedom
is common because you need it.
In fact, I think probably the robots of 2025 or something
are going to have even maybe another wrist joint
or something.
I think most of the robots today are meant for picking things up
from above.
And it gets really frustrating to put a kooka in the sink.
It's just really frustrating.
And then if you pick up a spatula and try to--
it's terrible because you've got not only six degrees of freedom
or seven degrees of freedom.
And you have a long wrist.
Then the kinematics are very hard to find solutions.
OK.
Good.
We'll do the optimization view next time.
[BLANK_AUDIO]