All right, welcome back, everybody.
We're starting the next phase here of our journey.
We're going to start transitioning
into manipulation in Clutter.
And I'll tell you the implications
of that in the next slide.
Quick admin announcements.
So we're getting closer to where we're
going to start defining projects.
And you'll have a project pre-proposal first,
where some people submit the pre-proposal, get a rubber
stamp, and then they're good.
But the pre-proposal is a chance,
if you haven't already, to give us
a draft of what you're thinking and get some feedback
before we lock it in with a more final proposal.
So the first pre-proposal is due on October 20,
which seems like infinitely far away,
but it'll be here before you know it.
So start thinking about who your project groups are.
If you're in CIM and you look around your CIM recitation,
that's the ideal setting for all the CIM content.
To have a group inside one recitation is ideal.
Not required, but ideal.
And if you want feedback from us beforehand, some of you
have been coming up and asking after class, which is great.
Sometimes-- actually, today is the one day
I have to leave right after class.
But almost always, I'm here after class.
And then-- just a second--
or even I'll come early before class if you want to talk,
or send me an email, or send the staff an email.
We'll definitely-- this is a good time to be just
throwing ideas off us.
[INAUDIBLE]
No, sorry.
It definitely does not need to be a novel.
The rubrics for the project are on the website.
As we get a little bit closer still, I'll go over that.
But absolutely, finding a paper and reproducing it
and understanding it is great.
But the partnering is what we wanted
to at least put in your head.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so one is fine.
You can work by yourself.
That's great.
Two or three is great.
I think more than three starts to get harder.
So we normally say two or three is ideal for a group.
Great, and you've already been looking a little bit
at the projects from last year, so you have a sense.
But you're not going to feel restricted to robots
on a table this year, because we're
going to have a lecture right before your pre-proposals are
due with mobile robots doing all kinds of stuff.
Assuming I can get mobile robots to do all kinds of stuff
in simulation in time, hopefully.
OK, so let me just sort of step back for a second
and just think about what have we done so far
and why are we going to do this next.
Remember, I tried to tell you that I've
tried to organize the course.
We basically now have established
a very basic capability, and now we're
going to try to address the things that were limitations
of our previous approaches.
So we started with a quick lecture on hardware basics
just to help you appreciate what we're
commanding and controlling.
And then we talked about the basic pick and place
where we assumed the known pose was given to us,
and we assumed we knew the object,
because we had to pick the grasp relative to the object model.
And then we were able to do kinematics and Jacobian-based
control to do a full manipulation task,
but with some big assumptions.
And then last time, last week, we
talked about geometric perception,
which was the entry-level perception, which
if we have a model of the mustard bottle, for instance,
and you see a mustard bottle in the world,
we can use ICP and the variants, and some
of the important variants, to try to estimate the pose.
That removed the biggest assumption, I would say,
of assuming someone knew a priori where the pose was,
and we brought in a little bit of perception.
But that pipeline was still assuming a lot.
So in particular, the known object appears a lot there.
We assumed we knew the objects.
We want to do more complex scenes with many objects
and more diverse objects, where potentially you don't even
have a chance of knowing a perfect model of the object
we're manipulating.
And that's going to change the requirements
on both the control and planning stack and the perception stack.
But to start into that, we can still just say,
we're going to do a basic sort of pick
and place kind of operation.
I want you to think, by the end of the course,
of manipulation as way more than pick and place.
We do-- like tying shoelaces, I think,
is a better example of what manipulation
is than pick and place, even though a lot of robots
do pick and place.
So as kind of a way to structure that, our next sort of task
is based around this idea of building a little clutter
clearing station.
So we did this in the early days of the manipulation team
at TRI.
And the reason for it was because this
was just at the dawn of deep learning solving a lot
of computer vision problems.
And still today, but today we are more often
using pre-trained models than back then.
We really needed to generate a lot of data
and a lot of diverse data of robots' hands
around novel objects in both sim and in real.
So we just devised this very simple--
and other people have definitely done this too--
simple setup where you have two bins.
And their job is just to pick all the stuff from the one bin
and drop it in the other bin.
But we assume nothing about the objects in there.
And in general, we just threw whatever objects we wanted
into the bin.
And we got a lot of diversity from that.
If you watch this closely enough,
you'll see it's mostly pick and place.
But this system got to the point where
we could do some more subtle things.
Like I bet-- OK, there's a banana still.
But I bet to get the pillbox out of the corner,
it's going to go in and do--
it can't grasp that probably in first shot.
I think it just ended.
Am I that unlucky?
Like the whole video was playing for a minute and a half.
And as soon as I say something, it stops.
Yeah?
Yeah, it turns to [INAUDIBLE]
Ah, yeah, yeah.
So yeah, OK, it's possible that it missed that one.
Or that it was occluded or something like that.
Good eye, though.
He says it didn't move the pill bottle.
Skipped it.
There's also-- there's a little rubber duck that has like--
looks like Spock from Star Trek.
And I don't know.
It always ended up on the floor.
I don't know.
There was no-- you know, it was just
supposed to do this, but it seemed
like with high probability, it would
throw Spock onto the floor.
It must have been something about the geometry
or the compliance or something.
But I thought it was hilarious.
OK, so of course, we can do this in simulation too.
So this is my little--
let's see.
Look at that.
I haven't started it.
Not from the beginning here.
OK, so we're just going to start with random objects.
These are familiar objects if you've played with the YCB
object data set.
They all have ridiculously big mesh texture files.
But cameras, just like we set up before,
but now we have random objects.
And we're going to sit there and build not only the bits we've
done before, but we're going to generalize our perception
system.
We're going to talk about the more complicated simulation
that happens here.
And we're going to build a higher level state machine
to think about the logic of, OK, I missed something.
Let's go back and pick something up again.
So it brings up a little bit of some of the task planning too.
OK, so the first question you get
if you're trying to-- in simulation,
and you sort of saw it at the beginning of my animation.
But the first question is, how do you generate
diverse random simulations?
And the problem in its full glory
is actually fairly hard.
But if you're willing-- in this sort of clutter clearing setup,
and actually in a lot of robot experiments,
people that have been training deep learning perception
systems from simulated images and the like,
it's a fairly common workflow to generate random environments
by basically dropping things out of the sky.
So if you want to come up with a random distribution of clutter,
this is a pretty good way to do it.
And it's for a few subtle reasons.
One of them is that--
so basically, this is relying on the physics engine
to come up with the-- you give it
random initial conditions, but the physics engine
is really finding the static equilibrium of postures
for you.
And physics is a powerful thing.
And it's well-defined, almost always,
except for when objects are in deep penetration.
So if I were to just start the physics engine
with all of the objects completely on top of each other
at 0, 0, 0, then I don't know what it would do,
but probably things would be flying off
in different directions because of numerical instabilities.
Because really, the context solvers
shouldn't be asked to solve that problem.
That shouldn't happen in reality.
So a common heuristic is to--
so you'd like to start objects out of penetration.
And that's sort of hard in this--
if I had to pick configurations here that
had to be all out of penetration,
that would be a tough-- that's a puzzle to solve.
And we can do that with optimization.
If I have time, I'll talk about that.
But it's just much easier.
The script here is very simple.
You basically pick-- this is just all foam bricks,
but I'll show you it works more generally.
Pick an object, go up a little bit from the bin,
pick a random translation, a random pose,
and then lock that one in.
Now go up a little bit higher so that you're
pretty confident that you're not in an intersection.
Pick a random position and random pose.
And you just make a stack that is safely out of collision.
And then you let physics do the work, which in some ways
is a really clever--
like I say, physics is pretty good.
I mean, it's solving a really hard problem
by solving governing equations.
You can do that with arbitrary objects, of course.
So this is the YCB objects.
It's this pretty famous--
I mean, it's almost a folklore thing where--
so the Yale, Cal, Berkeley, there
were investigators from all three schools
that decided that we should make a common data set.
We should just agree.
They bought a bunch of objects on Amazon.
They scanned them and offered the scans
as part of their paper data set.
And they said, here's the part numbers.
If you contact us, we'll give you a copy of those,
or you can just order them online.
And so we have this data set of people that--
lots of people could work with the same objects.
Super useful.
It sucks that now the packaging has changed.
So you can't get that Cheez-It box.
You can get one with low sodium.
But it's still pretty good.
It's still pretty good.
So if you can find a vintage Cheez-It box that
matches the YCB, you could probably
get some money for that on eBay with the robotics market.
But you'll see a handful of these objects
that I use over and over and over again,
because they're the canonical ones.
And if you drop them out of the sky, you get things like this.
And it just works fine.
I always think it's funny.
It's like the central limit theorem at work,
even if it's like spam cans and mustard bottles.
But that's just uniform.
That's a uniform sampler.
And just-- there you go.
And you get these pileups.
So that works fine.
And of course, it works fine in 3D.
So this is me dropping things out of the sky,
putting a camera right above, and generating
a picture of the bin like the overhead camera would see.
And when we get to some of the deep learning-based perception,
we'll use this as a data set.
I just dropped it like 10,000 times.
I just made 10,000 images.
And they're all labeled from random initial conditions.
And that's a pretty good data set to train cheese-it box
detectors in clutter.
So that's very easy to say.
Just run it in the physics engine.
Just drop your assets in.
It's a few lines of code.
But when I got to this part, I was like, OK,
I have to tell you a little bit about contact simulation
because there's so much behind that little drop the spam can
thing.
There's so much smarts there.
There's so much subtlety there.
And some of it, you'll find yourself
in a situation where if you know this, you will persevere.
If you don't know this, your objects
will fall off the table or out of your hand
or explode into space.
So I want to spend a day talking a bit about contact simulation.
And just maybe to make the point,
I can even show the notebook here.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
So that's the 2D one.
It works fine.
Mix the video.
Here's the 3D one.
It really is a few lines of code.
I just-- if I can make that a little bigger here.
I just actually make this scenario file.
And I just said for one in range 10, pick a random object
and drop it into the file and then load it.
And then we set a random initial position.
And that's a few lines of code.
And what you get out is the scene.
But if you draw the contact force vectors,
you realize that to find a static equilibrium
of this system, the contact engine is actually
doing a lot of work.
It's solving for a lot of contact forces
to find a static equilibrium.
This is solving good physics problems.
And so let's just dig a little bit
into what that problem is that it's solving
and some of the subtleties about how it solves it.
So we talked already about spatial quantities.
We talked about positions and poses and rotation matrices.
We talked about spatial velocities.
Today we need to add spatial force.
Today we're going to start talking about forces.
So what's a spatial force?
Force is force.
What's a spatial force?
So a spatial force is a six-dimensional quantity.
We start with this, which has three components that you
would sort of expect, but also has three components.
This is the sort of translational.
And this is a 3 by 1 rotational.
Just like the spatial velocity vector
has angular velocity and translational velocity,
the forces have that too.
We're going to annotate this the same way.
Forces, we like to have names on their own.
I'll label everything in a second here.
So we write the expressed in frame down here.
For consistency, with the other notation,
it's still expressed in--
there's never a relative or measured in frame for forces.
We don't need that.
Forces are forces.
And this is the point that the force is applied.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
We often name the point with the body name,
as well as the point name, just to remember that it's
a force being applied on body B at point C.
It's a recommendation sort of.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
Because you're going to find yourself with a point on body
A that's coincident with a point on body B.
And there's equal and opposite forces.
And if you don't remember to sort of which one you're
talking about, it gets confusing fast.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so good.
So what the heck is a rotational force?
Let me just finish writing it here.
This is a torque, yes.
That's why tau for torque.
This is name C and BP.
I'll just bring this a little wider.
[INAUDIBLE]
What's that?
Yeah, this is an important spatial quantity.
So we have an entire algebra.
The question is, why would you mix this up and put this
together?
You're going to see, I think, in a very simple example.
It may be a compelling reason why to do it in just a second.
But our entire spatial algebra is
going to be defined really in these six dimensional spaces.
Just like it made sense to do angular velocity as well
as translational velocity.
And it turns out, if you want to summarize--
for instance, if the real world only
applies Cartesian forces--
maybe you could say--
I know it's just going to do it, I think.
It's probably a weak connection.
If the real world, you say, maybe only applies forces
that are translational, then you still
want to have the concept of a rotational force or torque
if you want to summarize the translational force
at a different point on the rigid body.
And this thing, this spatial force, is also known as wrench.
You'll hear it called wrench commonly.
I think I remembered to put the--
yeah, OK.
So instead of writing it all on the board, it's in the notes.
And I'll just put it up on the screen.
But basically, we have the same sort of algebra rules.
So spatial forces add when they're
applied to the same body in the same frame.
So the only thing that's different here
is the name of the force.
They're applied at the same--
I should even say at the same point on the same body
in the same frame.
Then you can add forces together.
You can shift spatial forces to a different application point.
Turns out, the translational force just shifts.
But you start getting cross products,
which you'll probably remember, r cross f kind of math
from physics.
You get cross products when you shift the point of application
of a force.
We're going to see that in a second here.
And then actually, for basically all the spatial quantities,
if you want to change that expressed in frame,
you do that by multiplying by a rotation matrix.
And that's it.
That's right in the notes.
But we're going to use these in a second.
So having this beautiful algebra sort of concept,
we can now do more complicated things in complicated systems
by just applying these rules efficiently over and over
again.
So let's do that in a very, very simple example.
So-- whoops, forgot to erase that one.
Well, it looks pretty close to what I was going to write.
So simple free body diagram.
Let's say I have a box sitting on a table.
I should use multiple colors of chalk.
Call this body B. And I'll put its frame here.
And I'll even assume that the center of mass
is right at the origin here.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
And I'm going to just set it on the table like this.
And I'm going to think about--
I'm going to start by summarizing the contact
forces between the box and the table with two forces, one
at each corner.
We'll see if that's sufficient and talk
about that in a minute.
But we'll call this contact force 1.
I'll call it F1.
And it's going to be applied in a coordinate frame 1.
And it's applied at this point C1.
Maybe I should call it BC1, follow my own advice.
It's a lot of symbols.
A lot of symbols.
This one I really don't like, but it really matters.
Otherwise, you're going to make--
in fact, when I was cleaning up the notes today,
I found a mistake in one of my examples.
And it's because I had tried to shortcut the notation,
and I made a mistake.
So we'll call this one force 2.
And apply it at coordinate frame C2.
So I'm calling this coordinate frame C2.
OK.
And then, of course, we have the force of gravity here,
mg, which I'll call force of gravity.
So let's just think about the statics problem here,
static equilibrium.
So when this is completely at rest,
then we should be able to solve, knowing
what we know about forces and force balance,
we should be able to solve for the contact forces
here that would satisfy the fact that that block is not moving.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
We're going to generalize this.
So that's good.
So let me assume it for now.
But the one reason to assume it is that actually most
simulators assume it.
Most simulators, when they're trying to summarize the contact
between two bodies, they will summarize that
with a small number of points.
It'd be more elegant to have an entire pressure distribution.
It just makes the math a little bit more complicated.
And certainly, this is sufficient to describe
equilibrium.
If you think-- if you want, I could put a little foot
on the--
on here.
And then it would be real.
You could make that physically true.
OK, so--
[INAUDIBLE]
Ask--
Yep.
[INAUDIBLE]
Good.
So why does it matter?
Yeah, so we are going to choose to get ahead.
So first of all, it gets a lot more complicated than this.
So even just on the board in the--
well, in the previous slide, it's
going to get a lot more complicated.
Yeah, and so for instance, one of the ways
we're going to define a good grasp
is a grasp that can defy the maximal adversarial wrench.
If someone were to come up and knock your--
try to apply a force or something,
then you want to pick a grasp that
tries to avoid the biggest possible wrench.
And that would be a surrogate for not knowing
very much about your object.
So a good place to put your finger
can be decided based on thinking about the relative force
balances and things like that.
That's a great question.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
It should go real speed.
You're saying that the blocks look like they fell slowly?
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh.
Oh, I see.
For the arm, yeah, that was just because we haven't done
motion planning yet, basically.
The defy k thing, I was just being conservative
and trying to make it move slowly and avoid cameras
and stuff like that.
But we're going to have better tools, yes.
And we'll just hopefully be whipping around and probably
throwing objects out of the hand and stuff like that.
Last year also, if you noticed in the projects,
there was a surprising number of people
that wanted to throw or whip or crush or whatever things,
which is cool.
Yeah, I'm good with that.
Someone says, we're going to do darts
and we want to do it on the real robot.
I was like, whoa, not my real robot.
But that can be a fun thing to do.
And the robots are just capable--
like, the KUKA is actually speed limited.
It's not a super fast robot.
That's not its finest attribute.
But probably just enough if you put
a little bit of a lever on the end to throw a dart.
Yeah.
But I don't support that for final projects.
OK.
So let's start being a little bit more careful here.
So f of gravity here, if I were to write it in--
it's sort of best defined in the world frame
and applied at the body frame here,
where the center of mass is.
Because in that frame, it's easy to just say
it's actually a six element vector that has no torque.
This is my slightly more precise version
of just writing negative mg there.
Actually, in the spatial notation,
it lives in a six dimensional space.
The contact forces are actually most naturally described
in the contact frame, which doesn't look very
different than the body frame and the world frame
in my first example.
But it will look much different later examples.
So because it's most natural to say, for instance,
that in this frame of contact, which
will move with the possible contact locations,
that, for instance, the force can never pull on the contact.
It can only push.
So in the contact frame, by convention, the contact frame--
the z direction is aligned with the contact normal.
So we have, for instance, that f of some i in the contact z
applied to whatever body is going
to be greater than or equal to 0.
Because you can't pull on--
contacts push, but don't pull.
And I'm assuming that the ground is just locked in.
It's not a body.
But if it was two bodies colliding,
then I would have a comparable contact frame
on the other body, which this is also true.
But it would be a different frame,
so equal and opposite frame.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Good.
I'm going to tell you how to define the contact normal
in a second.
I've got a picture that will help with that.
There's a general way to do that.
But that's a great question.
He says, you just said normal, but you put it
in a place that has a corner, which doesn't--
the normal might be poorly defined,
or you have to think about something
more complicated in the corner, which is a good point.
But there's a fairly clean way to define that.
So then if we want to do our general multibody algorithm,
or our basic free body diagram computation,
then we can just apply the rules of spatial algebra.
And basically, the step one would be--
I'll do it over here.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
We're going to put all the forces
in the same expressed-in frame.
I'll just do it in frame B, just to keep--
I could pick any one of them.
I could pick world.
I could do anything.
But let's do--
so for instance, I can just use that algebra and say,
force 1 written in body B, taken at point C1,
is just rotated by the rotation from C1 to B of F1, B1, B, C1.
I keep trying to make it better.
It's not an I. It's a 1.
And I could do the same thing for contact force 2.
But what is that doing?
That's just saying that there's a force here
that I can express it in the frame of B.
And the same way with positions and velocities,
it'd be expressed in frame.
I'm still applying it at this force.
So it actually-- if those two were not aligned,
it would rotate the force.
But it doesn't actually have a cross product or anything
involved yet.
The force is still being applied here.
I'm just going to choose numbers that
were relative to that coordinate system instead
of this coordinate system.
And then the second step would be to apply them
all at the same point.
Now, that sounds totally weird until you understand
that for rigid bodies, if I were to apply a force here,
that's indistinguishable from me applying a different force
at any other point on the body, a force and a moment,
potentially, at any other point in the body.
So if you apply a force here, I could apply a different force
and moment here that would have exactly the same effect.
From the point of view of the rigid body,
it's completely indistinguishable
from applying this force I have here.
So I'm going to use that.
And that's what the rules of spatial algebra
do is they show you exactly how to do those transformations.
And I'm going to say, well, I'm going to take it
as if I was pushing here.
I'm going to make a comparable force and moment and torque
here.
And then same thing, this one, I'll move that to here too.
And once they're in the same place,
now everything has to balance.
They can add or subtract when they're in the same place.
So this is where I get my translation.
1 is-- it doesn't actually affect the translation 1.
b 1, 1, b.
But this is where the cross product comes in.
So tau b 1, b equals tau 1.
I hate all the symbols, but it really does make a difference.
, That's a cross product, a vector cross product.
These are both 3 vectors, and so that's a vector cross product.
And this is just in simpler free body diagrams,
you probably would have just written this as r cross f.
That's the standard.
I'm producing a moment around the center of mass.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Nope.
Because if you shift frames, then you
are going to potentially make it look like a force again.
[INAUDIBLE]
I see, you want the comparable thing.
It's not that way.
So applying the torque is almost a construction
that makes sense for rigid bodies.
As you said in the first thing, three dimensional forces
are real.
Torques are our summary of the effect of a body.
So they do act a little differently.
They don't compose in the way--
I agree there could be a nice symmetry if that was true,
but it's not.
They're different qualities.
And then, now we could solve for the contact forces if we like.
That must be for the--
to put things in balance by just saying,
now that they're in the same frames,
then f1 b b plus f2 b b plus f--
actually, I could even do this in the big one all at once.
I could do the components, or I could just do the whole thing.
So big F, gravity, b, that has to equal 0
if I'm in equilibrium.
So it says I'm in static equilibrium.
So that's six equations in its full glory,
one for each row of those.
In 2D, I guess you could say it's three equations,
because there's nothing out of plane
that would make any difference.
But in 3D, it's six equations.
And so it's interesting.
If you think about it and work it out,
I won't write everything out on the board.
But you can guess what the solution is for that.
So you'd probably think that this force had better
have magnitude mg divided by 2.
And this one had better be mg divided by 2,
assuming this is nicely in the center.
And that's what falls out of this.
But you have to understand, actually,
that the component that balances the z force, the z equation
in this, that only tells me that the sum of those two vectors
has to equal mg.
It doesn't say anything about the relative magnitude
of those two vectors.
It's actually the torque balance,
the fact that you have to have zero net torque, the thing
with the cross product, which says
if that body's in the middle, then they
will have equal magnitude.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So that's a good question.
So some people-- so some simulators, for instance--
or yeah, it's really a kind of a simulator thing more than a math
thing.
Since point contacts are maybe a poor summary of a contact
of face-on-face contact, some people
will have the ability to produce frictional torque right
at your point contact.
Maybe that'll make more sense when I put the friction
cone up in a second, because then we'll see it right there.
But it's true that sometimes people model that.
But that's really meant to model the effect of many forces
in a patch.
It's an approximation for that.
OK, so what about the horizontal components of the force?
Oh, sorry, yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
So you go through and you calculate
all kinds of contacts that are potential contacts.
And then in the rigid body algorithm
that does this recursive step through,
it summarizes things into a common frame
and does all the algebra in the common frame
and iterates through.
So that's what makes things efficient and elegant.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
So I've only so far said what happens in equilibrium.
And in that case, the forces are whatever they need
to be to keep things at zero.
We're going to see more complicated cases where
maybe there is no force that can stabilize, for instance.
And you have to make a choice.
What's the force going to be?
For instance, already here, we haven't
said what the horizontal component of the force is.
The force balance equations just tell me
that that magnitude and that magnitude
have to be equal so that it's not sliding.
But any magnitude of any size, as long
as they're equal and opposite, would
keep this block at rest.
So we need some rule to say what's
the magnitude of that horizontal component.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So that was just simulating forward.
And the simulation, because there's dissipation
and physics is clever, settles into a static equilibrium.
And you have to be careful in your simulator
to make sure that that is true, that everything converges
nicely.
But if you simulate the governing equations correctly,
it should do that, as long as there's any dissipation.
Every once in a while, actually, if you
watch the full simulation of the falling, dropping the bin,
I kind of was a little sloppy with the initial condition.
So sometimes, the mustard will hit the edge of the bin
and then fall forever because there's nothing else below.
So it actually doesn't converge to an equilibrium
because there's something falling to negative infinity.
And at some point, it'll crash, actually,
which is-- I don't like that it crashes.
But don't simulate it for more than 20 seconds,
if that happens.
OK.
All right.
So let's think about the horizontal component
because that gets us into friction.
And this is really a fundamental concept
that you must know if you're talking about manipulation,
which is this concept of a friction cone.
So maybe we'll see it by putting our box on a ramp now.
And now, our contact--
if I still have little feet on the corner here,
I'll still call this C1, C2.
I still have body 1 in the body frame here.
But now, if it's going to be in equilibrium,
I have to do a little bit more work
to make sure I have defined that horizontal component
in the contact frame.
And it turns out the most common model of friction
is Coulomb friction, which says that the magnitude
of the horizontal force is proportional to the magnitude
of the normal force in the contact frame.
So Coulomb friction-- if I can write it in shorthand here
first here, so this is the magnitude
of the tangential component is proportional to the magnitude
of the normal component.
That's not using my whole notation yet.
I'm going to make it in the proper frame in a second.
But the normal, we say, is always positive
by our definition.
That's our z component.
And so we're saying the xy component is actually--
this is in the Euclidean norm--
is proportional to this.
And that proportion is called the friction coefficient.
[WRITING]
Almost always mu.
[INAUDIBLE]
What?
This is a scalar in this case.
This is the magnitude.
So yeah.
That's why I wanted to use my whole thing.
But in shorthand, the magnitude of the normal,
this is a vector.
This is a scalar, actually.
So if I were to write it out, maybe it'll be more precise.
If I say of some thing in the contact z,
that's definitely a scalar.
Apply, let's say, a body B, it's actually going to be--
[WRITING]
So in 2D-- oh, sorry.
I didn't see your hand.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yep.
So this is some sort of a norm when I put these up.
And this just means it's the L2 norm, which means
I want to take a square root.
It's this thing squared.
The only other ones we'll ever use here, I would--
and I probably can't even think of a time in this class
where I use a different norm.
Did I just never write that?
Is that just confusing?
But sometimes I would use a 1 for the L1 norm,
or an infinity for an infinity norm.
Yep.
But if you were to Google LP norm, for instance,
that would tell you the story, where p is 2.
OK, so the geometry of this thing
is the geometry of a cone.
So if I were to draw f of icx, f of icy, f of icz here,
then the elements of that three-dimensional vector
that satisfy this constraint live inside a cone.
It's like an ice cream cone to the origin.
So when f of z is 0, these two must be 0.
There's nothing below.
It can't be negative.
And as f of z gets bigger, I can have bigger resistive forces,
which makes sense.
If you push down on something and then try to slide it,
that's going to be--
it's going to be able to resist more
than if you are gently touching something and try to slide it.
It actually makes some of these statics problems
very geometric, actually, and dynamics problems
very geometric.
Because if you want to ask, for instance,
is the box going to slide or is it
going to stick as a function of the ramp angle,
then I'm going to draw it a little bigger here.
So I've got a ramp.
I've got a box.
I've got friction cones now, which in 2D just
look kind of like that, I guess.
And I've got a force vector coming down.
I'm going to use lots of colors today.
And I've got a force coming down.
That's straight down.
So it turns out, with our spatial algebra--
or classic physics, but the spatial algebra just
makes it neat, clear in my mind--
we can move these forces as if they
are being applied at the body location.
And so they'll have some interpretation like this.
And they'll add.
So the condition-- I've got to finish my punch line.
The condition here on whether this thing has a force that's
inside the friction cone that can resist motion
is actually the geometric condition
of whether the opposite force of that
is inside the friction cone.
If there is a force that could be picked out of that cone--
like any of these are possible admissible forces--
if there's one that could be picked out of that cone,
then there'll be an equilibrium.
So in this case, maybe the way I drew it,
it's going to just a little bit slide.
It's not quite enough.
If I made the friction coefficient bigger,
then I could resist that.
If I made the normal force bigger, I could resist that.
Or if I-- no, that's not true.
Because that would also increase this.
If I made this thing larger, that's why it's geometric.
And that's why it's beautiful is that they would go up together.
Or if I made the ramp smaller, then that could be inside there.
So it becomes very geometric.
Sorry, what was your question?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yep.
So oftentimes, the normal force is determined first.
And then that defines effectively the height of the cone.
Not always.
Typically, they're actually solved all jointly.
But that's maybe the easiest way to think about it,
is that the normal force determines
the horizontal forces.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
So good.
So the laws of-- so the question is,
how do you actually pick one if maybe there's
a set of possible choices?
So typically, there's not a set of possible choices.
We have principles that tell us which one to pick.
There's some caveats to that.
But the first thing is, if the contact velocity, which
is the velocity at the point of contact, is 0,
or can be made 0, then the contact--
the frictional force would be whatever
causes the balance.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
I was thought about writing that out in symbols.
But I decided this one I should just write in words,
because I wanted to find another frame for contact velocity
like that.
But tell me if that's clear.
So if there's a sticking mode, where
if you're in sticking mode, it will choose the choice out
of this necessary to satisfy the equilibrium conditions.
If it's not 0, as soon as you're sliding at that point,
then we have the principle of maximal dissipation,
which means your contact force will be the biggest
force possible in the opposite direction of your movement.
It will always be the largest force in the cone opposite
to the velocity.
I promised to not write too low.
Moving up the board is kind of a cheat.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
That's the basic principle.
Now, Coulomb friction is not complete.
You can find cases where this is not enough principles
to fully define the forces, and you have to pick one.
Here's my favorite example.
Classical mechanics is just not good enough.
Thinking about things as rigid bodies is not good enough,
maybe I should say.
It's not like the physicists didn't do their job.
It's just that the level of modeling of rigid bodies
doesn't capture everything.
So take a four-legged table.
Four legs on the ground.
So if you balance gravity, then the sum of those four forces
have to be equal to the opposite of the gravity.
To balance torque, that tells you
kind of what at least three of the legs have to be doing.
But actually, it's ambiguous how it's
distributed across those four.
If you had three-legged table, everything's clean.
You have a four-legged table, then it's ambiguous.
The laws of minimum action and maximum dissipation
don't tell you how those forces are distributed,
which is funny, because then if you push the table,
that means that the frictional forces are undefined.
So it could go this way.
It could go that way.
And physics just doesn't tell you.
Coulomb rigid body physics just doesn't tell you which one.
You have real tables that have real--
so there are one table legs a little shorter than the other,
or there's microscopic.
The real table doesn't do that.
The real table picks one, but it's at a level of modeling
that we are not capturing in this.
So what does our solver do?
It picks the one in the middle.
Almost always, we're solving optimization problems.
So kind of picking the least norm solution
tends to be the same, the right thing.
[INAUDIBLE]
Probably.
So I'll say it back to you in my words, though.
I think what's going to happen is
it's solving an optimization problem, typically
in velocities and forces.
And if there's multiple solutions,
it will pick the one that makes the norm of the velocity
and forces equal to 0, depending on if you're solving it
in the primal or in the dual.
So its interpretation probably has something like--
it probably has an interpretation
that you could talk out like that.
But I think what's precisely happening
is that in the velocity space, probably a minimum norm
solution.
OK.
So this friction cone idea is key.
We're going to use this a lot.
Again, how do we pick up grasps?
We're going to think about putting our friction cones
to resist wrenches in the same way
that there might be good places to put your friction cone,
good amounts to squeeze that will change the ability
to resist an adversarial wrench, like the rigid body
wrench, not a monkey wrench.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
So basically, any force that's inside the friction cone
is a possible force.
You have additional constraints of like the normal force
can only be so big, given that it's
being powered by gravity here.
So the magnitude of that force is determined also
by the balance equations.
Well, here's a good question.
Test your intuition.
So in this setting, I have this brick, and I have a ramp.
So we said it was mg over 2 for the flat case.
Is this force bigger?
Are they the same?
[INAUDIBLE]
They're not the same.
OK, we got both answers.
You have to read the notes to find out.
[INAUDIBLE]
You don't have-- there's an asymmetry here, right?
That's not pushing like this.
Pretty clean in the algebra.
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE]
Good, yeah.
So I drew this in 2D, and I made it exact in this.
And in 3D, it really is the shape of this ice cream cone.
The square root here gives me conic sections
that look like this.
But oftentimes for optimization, or for faster simulation,
or something like this, it actually
can be useful to approximate this
with a polyhedral approximation of the friction cone,
where you write this as--
because some of these square roots
are kind of a nasty thing.
So sometimes you'll use a polyhedral approximation
of that friction cone.
And I could say a lot more, or I don't
know how to say a little more than that.
But that comes up naturally in a lot of optimization
formulations.
This would be the--
for instance, if you write a linear complementarity problem,
you might have heard of linear complementarity problem, LCP,
which is a way to do simulation.
The fact that it's a linear complementarity problem
is because we made a polyhedral approximation of the cone.
If you wanted to do a full second order cone version,
then it would be a nonlinear complementarity problem,
which is much harder to solve.
But that's just bonus.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
So this is a gross summary of the surface materials.
The only way that the surface materials come in
is by picking mu.
And so you need to go to a deeper level of detail
to capture-- to get over some of the abnormalities of the model,
the insufficiencies of the model.
It's also interesting.
So if you look in the robot description files,
for instance, you can pick--
you set a mu for each body.
But that's weird, because mu is really
a property of the pair of materials, right?
Rubber and glass, or whatever, these things
are pairs of materials.
So there's always a little bit of a hack in the middle,
where you say, well, I've got a mu of 10 and a mu of 0.3.
And I'm going to use a parallel resistor theorem or something
to put them together, just because it
would be a pain to label every pair of materials.
But that's what's happening.
So you typically put one per body,
even though that doesn't really make sense.
And there's also-- you'll see sometimes
mu static and mu dynamic, right?
So you can have static friction or dynamic friction.
It's kind of interesting, but actually, the friction
you get once you start sliding tends to be lower
than the sticking friction.
So if you make a plot of contact velocity and the total force
you'd get out, let's say the normal force--
let's see, the friction, F tangent normalized by F normal,
something like this, then it would--
you'll see plots that look like this.
You'll have a mu static, where if the velocity is 0,
you can get any force in that range.
But as soon as you start sliding,
then you'll have a mu dynamic that's actually lower.
Dynamic.
That's lower.
And that's a better model of what's
happening in this Coulomb friction.
And then you'll see people make--
they make stiff approximations of that sometimes.
So you'll see models that look like this, for instance.
They're smooth but stiff approximations of that.
But oftentimes, for first order, just make them equal.
You're fine.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Because you can satisfy all the equations by putting, say,
all the force on three legs, and the last leg
doesn't need to do anything.
Or you could put it on the opposite three legs,
and the first leg doesn't need to do anything.
And then that's just normal force, let's say.
You could satisfy all the torque and z balance
by putting on any three legs, for instance.
So now when you push, you'll get different forces
depending on which of those choices you made,
which will possibly cause a moment or not.
And they're all admissible by the Coulomb model.
[INAUDIBLE]
That's the extreme.
Of course, it would be--
you could have any linear combinations of those.
That's just-- I'm trying to make an extreme case.
But you--
[INAUDIBLE]
That is one solution.
But all the equations are also satisfied.
Everything that we said that defines physics
are also satisfied if you put all the weight on three legs,
any three legs.
And therefore, when you push, you
might get no friction on one leg,
or you might get all the friction,
you know, which could cause rotation or not.
Kind of annoying.
There's other things, too, that if I was a better chalkboard
lecturer, I should learn to do this, the Pan-Levay paradox.
So--
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, I can cheat?
I can buy something on Amazon to make me a Pan-Levay paradox
guy?
Yeah.
Yeah, I don't know how to do it.
I won't try.
Probably doing it above my head wasn't the best place to start.
So no one liked the fact that I chose the contact points
to be at the corners.
Let's dig into that a little bit.
I'm glad you didn't like that.
I'm glad you called me on that.
But simulators do that.
And simulators have to make a choice.
And actually, it's kind of a gross part of simulation.
It tends to be a thing that leads to sadness.
Like when robots pick up objects, and then they go,
phew, you know, it tends to be--
there's a couple of things that can go wrong.
But this is one of them, a big one,
which is that you have to come up with an algorithm that,
given--
well, so here's the first thing, I guess, to say is,
like, penetration happens.
That's the word everybody uses.
I sounded out of context.
But there's-- you will--
so if you're simulating real systems
with numerical algorithms, bodies will overlap.
That's called penetration in the computational geometry world.
And that happens.
And you have to deal with it.
So if I have a box on a table, then it's sort of easy.
I could pick almost any two points
and find its force balance.
Of course, I need one to be on at least the right side
of the downward force and the left.
But what if I'm on the edge of a table now?
So if I start putting my box kind
of on the edge of the table, now it's
getting a little bit more subtle.
The position of this box relative to this box
means that probably I need to pick a point right here.
I could pick something else on this side.
What happens if you're a little bit in the corner?
Because your simulator took a numerical approximation
of the dynamics.
And so you're like, I'll exaggerate it.
Hopefully it doesn't get this bad in simulation.
But you're like this.
So where do you put the contact forces?
Simulators have to sort of pick.
I'm going to put one here.
And it's not that hard for any one image
to pick a few contact points.
Even in 3D, you get much more complicated geometries
intersecting and stuff.
But you always look at pairs of bodies.
And you could come up with some rubric to pick those points.
Here's the hard part.
While you're simulating, as the bodies move,
you'd really like those points to move smoothly.
And it's really hard to find one algorithm that always
finds a consistent set of points,
even as the bodies kind of are moving around
relative to each other.
And if those points jump discontinuously,
then your forces can jump discontinuously.
And that's when things go surprise.
So I actually made some slides about that.
I meant to show this before when you asked.
So how do you define the normal vector first in the broader
case, even at corners?
It turns out that you're always thinking about a normal vector
between two frames.
And so you take the sign distance
between two bodies, which is well-defined.
We often call it phi.
So these two bodies, that would be the sign distance.
And the derivative, the gradient of the sign distance,
is a nice working definition of the normal vector
that works even in corners.
In general, you just need to be a sub-gradient of that.
It's the vector that goes between the two points.
The distance is a scalar.
The gradient of that is a vector that moves along there.
And the interpretation of it being a gradient
also works if you're working directly in Q, not just in 3D.
So it has a generalized coordinates.
And then for the tangential coordinates,
you can just pick any basis on the orthogonal plane.
And sometimes you pick many of them for the polyhedral
approximation.
This would be like the polyhedral approximation
does something like that.
So when this is going on--
I already showed you that, but just think about this.
So if we use that as a heuristic--
so it works beautifully when things are out of contact
or when they just come into contact.
But everything-- and I could put up a different proposal.
And everything breaks when you start getting
into the deep penetration.
And here's a picture to make that--
so if you pick the point of maximal penetration,
the deepest point in the body, which
is a hard computational geometry thing to do,
but if you could do that nicely, and then you
took the gradient of that as your definition of the normal,
then that's going to push you like this.
That would be my instantaneous choice of a point.
Let's just say I'm going to pick only one point,
just to keep it simple.
One point, I'm going to try to push in that direction.
I'm going to call that my normal.
But here's what happens.
If you watch that as the bodies overlap,
your maximal point gets closer to the other face.
So the closest face that would allow you to exit
changes discontinuously.
That make sense?
You were closer to the side.
You're closer to the side, so you should definitely
put your normal force pushing out like that.
And then all of a sudden, when you go past the diagonal,
you're closer to the top.
Boom.
Context simulation has a big discontinuity,
and things get bad.
So it looks like the gradient of that looks like this,
as soon as you cross that boundary.
And if you cross it just a little bit,
maybe you don't notice.
You cross it a lot, you notice.
So when people are doing point contact, one thing
I've learned, actually, over the years,
to just-- I actually make my contact--
you'll notice some of the contact geometry that we use,
if you look closely at it.
I actually take a box, and I'll just put it--
we'll make it a little bit smaller on the inside,
call that a box.
And then I'll put some extra spheres of radius
almost 0 in the corner.
Just to say, always put contact points here, please.
And then do whatever you want with the rest of it.
But at least put contact points here,
and that makes things a lot more stable,
if you're using point contact simulation.
One of the things that was kind of an innovation in Drake,
in the contact engine, was this model
called hydroelastic contact, which
is the obvious thing, in some sense.
But it's the thing that--
making it computationally efficient enough
to run all the time at real rates
is what was maybe a bigger deal.
So now, instead of taking just a point contact or a few points,
we take a surface integral across the surface.
And even when you're in penetration,
we define a pressure field, which
defines a surface of--
the surface of overlap.
And we integrate numerically.
We make a new mesh on the fly, and we
integrate across that to get nice, smooth contact forces.
And that's all happening on every time step,
on every geometry pair, and everything like this.
So you get these beautiful simulations
with nice, smooth red contact vectors.
And like the-- yeah, I'll show you a couple of examples.
If you do this now, then these are the contact forces
that you get out with that extra computational geometry work.
And things suddenly get smooth.
And that made a big difference in our ability
to do sim-to-real transfer in Drake.
[AUDIO OUT]
So it's actually a lot of work under there
to make that all work, because all the possible geometry
pairs, whether it's a generic mesh or a sphere or whatever,
they all have these relatively complicated intersections.
And the shape of that intersection
depends on the relative stiffness of the bodies.
So there's a lot of things going on behind there.
And that's when you get these animations that we like,
which is like the dexterous hand picking up the mug.
And you'll see the entire contact patch
that we render sometimes.
And normally, you wouldn't see that.
That's extra math that we're doing behind the scenes
to make that really stable and good.
This is all-- you can turn all this on in MeshCat.
In fact, it'll happen automatically.
So you'll see any level of these rendering,
that's the entire pressure field.
When you see red arrows, you're seeing hydroelastic.
When you see green arrows, you're
seeing the old point contact model.
I'm porting the note-- oops, that was funny.
I'm actually porting-- so hydroelastic
was a little too slow last year.
And it's fast enough this year.
So I'm like one--
not even a whole lecture ahead of you--
porting the note to use hydroelastic for everything.
So you're going to see a few green vectors.
And then if you download it again the next day,
it'll be gone.
It'll be red.
But hopefully, you won't have to experience green vectors.
You can watch even the interaction of the bowl
with the table, for instance.
You get contact patches that are right
around the rim of the bowl.
It's a lot of geometry that's happening.
And one of the things that we are proud of--
this is another cool example.
You can actually mate LEGOs.
And it's just the physics of it will hold it together.
And the contact forces that come out
are just rock steady and stuff.
So most simulators don't have contact forces visualization
on by default, because they're crazy.
And ours was for a long time, too.
But we have ours enabled by default, just so you're like,
hey, you guys should really see these contact forces.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
So there's two different questions there.
Can you control the stiffness and damping?
Then absolutely.
There's a dissipation quantity that they all
have proper mechanical units.
There's a stiffness you can set for each body.
And then when they overlap, there's
a pressure field equation that defines the surface of balance.
How does it correspond to real?
I think it's intended, absolutely,
to correspond to real.
But there's typically some sim to real gap still.
Like if you took exactly the material properties of rubber,
you might get something that's a little bit--
I would hope it's perfect.
But that's the kind of place where
you might expect to cheat the numbers a little bit
to get a better match.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
You have to say that one again.
Sorry.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK, so the comment was that you have some anisotropic,
or some mud, or something like that.
Might be you have different friction properties
at different points.
So there's no sampling that happens here.
It actually is doing the computational geometry
of triangular meshes, and computing those things,
and taking integrals cleanly.
But if you had a surface that had different friction
properties, I think in practice what I would do today,
I would just drop a handful of different collision geometries
down there that had different coefficients and stuff
like this, and approximate it that way.
We could, of course, generalize it to that.
But we haven't put that level of generalization in there.
[INAUDIBLE]
I think intellectually there's no sampling.
Of course, you solve for vertices first,
and then you use that to compute the triangulation and stuff
like this.
But I think the mathematical model that
is being achieved by that code is
that you're taking an integral over the surface.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yep.
Yes, so the question is, could you ever
have sort of pass-through effects?
So OK, so Drake supports-- and so this is all rigid body.
And this is suitable.
These are actually compliant rigid body,
because you're allowed to penetrate a bit.
So it's suitable for objects that mostly keep their shape,
but could be squishy.
But if you had a really plush toy or something like that,
we actually have a soft body simulation
for that, which does finite element method.
And that could be suitable for things like cloth or something
like that.
But we actually don't advertise cloth support yet,
because exactly because of these pass-through events.
And we know how to--
the simulation community knows how to do that.
But you just have to do extra logic to prevent pass-through.
Because if your normal suddenly pops out the other side,
then that can be bad.
So this one, I don't think it would be devastating.
If you had enough mass of your pepper still on the first side,
then it would probably be almost unnoticeable.
So we don't feel like a sucking sound
when you happen to hit the table or anything like that.
But you could have more dramatic events
where you actually just pass through.
So if your simulation time step was too big,
you would just enter-- or your stiffness was too low.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
We summarize the integral of the pressure field in a wrench.
That's one of the reasons.
So that's kind of why I showed this partly,
is that it's beautiful to say that the integral over that,
it gives you a total wrench.
Good.
I'm going to stop there.
Think about your project groups.
think about your projects, ask us questions,
and we'll see you Thursday.