All right, welcome back everybody
If anybody's out there, so I'm I could use the Ethernet cable if anybody's back there in the booth
But somehow my Wi-Fi is not working again
Okay, so today we're transitioning into perception so let me even just as a quick setup right
Last time we built an almost complete
Manipulation system if you will right we we had our hardware
abstraction our hardware simulation
And we built on top of that
Our differential inverse kinematics block which
Well after some integration
sent us IWA commands
IWA positions
The diff IK block needed to know the current IWA state so we had an important line here
Okay, but the whole thing was predicated on
Something over here, which just had a gripper velocity trajectory coming in
Okay, and although that's
That's a complete closed loop system
Hidden inside when we designed the gripper trajectories and the and then differentiated them to get the gripper velocities
We made a big assumption, which is that we knew where the red brick was okay?
So everything was sort of based on this
someone told me exactly where in the world I needed to reach to and
That's just not good enough right at some point. We have to now
Use our sensors to figure out where the brick is to do the work so so far. We assumed a perception Oracle, right?
someone you could just query and tell us where the
object was in the world frame and
We were using
some of the the the cheat ports like we could tell
The body pose directly from of any object in the world right in our hardware station
And so the goal today is to stop using those cheat ports and start using cameras instead and close the simplest loop we can
around that whole system
That they could actually be run on a real robot
So I'm going to download
Ridiculously big mesh cat animation over my why over my phones
5g and burn my data plan for the month, but hey there we go
It's ridiculously big just because the mesh the the
The YCB objects if you know what these are these this is a mustard bottle from the YCB objects, okay database a
Little funny here, okay
The meshes or the sorry the material files the texture maps for these files are like 50 megabytes
So it takes a minute to download okay? This is roughly what we're doing almost the same as what we did last time
The big difference is that we're going to have cameras now in the scene these are cameras I
brought some I don't always have cameras in my pocket, but
Today I do okay. Yeah, they're like this okay. This is the 415. This is the 435 real sense cameras
Okay, you just USB plug them in
You're good to go. They're amazing depth cameras. I'm going to tell you a little bit about them today, okay?
What's going on here?
But that's what you see in the scene are these depth cameras sprinkled throughout a bunch of them actually we put three on each bin
You'll understand why
Okay, and then mostly this is just the same kind of thing we did before where we start off we figure out
Where the mustard bottle is that's the role of perception
We then we do our standard gripper trajectory and make our move from part a to point B now
What the heck is this thing that's getting left behind?
Okay
That thing is a point cloud
Which is computed by reading the cameras at time zero?
okay, and
Doing some initial processing on the data that you get back from those cameras in order to make the decision about where to grasp
Okay, so I bought at the moment of perception. I went ahead and you know put those in
Okay, I have observations like this
And then I have a model of what those I expect those observations to be and they end up matching
Okay, we'll do all that and by the end of the lecture
Okay, so we had gonna think in terms of these point clouds today
Okay, so oh no not again
All right, so like I said today is the first day of perception
We're gonna do a lot of perception throughout the course today is kind of a more geometric view of perception
we're not just learning a deep network that goes from image to
Whatever representation we want we're gonna start by doing the geometry version now
even though
Going from image with through a deep network directly is I think by all accounts
That's the best way to do things today
There's still a lot of the a lot of perception tools that have baked in them
Whether they're neural network or not some of the fundamentals of geometry
It focus it builds beautifully on what we did last time. I think I'm in the kinematics
okay, and if you're if you're interested in ideas like neural radiance fields or
putting baking 3d priors
Geometric priors into your neural networks and everything like this. This is going to be the foundation you need to do that kind of work
So today we'll do it's a slightly old-school version of perception, but it's the foundation
Okay, so we'll do incremental iterative closest point. Yes
We will you will tell you to talk about where nerf comes into the stack later. Yeah, there's places where it makes a lot of sense
Okay, so
Everybody knows about the deep learning revolution. I think a few less people
Realize how much of a geometry revolution we've had at the same time
Okay, and it's it was powered partly by deep neural networks
But even before that it was powered by I don't know autonomous driving companies
Really caring about where the pedestrians were in the space people building a lot better sensors
I mean virtual reality and augmented reality were a big driver, too
Okay, and we started getting pretty incredible things that had no no neural networks involved
Okay, this is even I don't know eight years ago or something like this dynamic fusion where we could we started having
algorithms that could run in real time and
build
instantaneous 3d
Reconstructions of the perceptions they were seeing and track, you know people moving around
Building sort of these beautiful 3d models and that was a culmination of
algorithmic work of new sensors
And in particular the sensors were not only higher quality, but they were faster
Faster to the point where if the world doesn't change too much between each frame then you can write a simpler algorithm to do
Tracking and reconstruction. Okay, so there's just this massive revolution in geometry that's happened sort of alongside
the deep learning revolution and
Interestingly, they've come together. So now, you know, there's people baking in geometric priors into neural networks and the like
Okay, so it started with
Sensors that were thinking, you know, maybe autonomous driving related. So you see a valedine actually spot has a valedine you can stick on top
Of it. It's still a
relevant sensor today. These are our lidars laser being shot out and
Bouncing back and estimating the distance from each point of light to the to the target
Okay, and some of these reconstructions are just absolutely amazing
You'll see an autonomous car driving through, you know City Street and hundreds of yards into the future
You can see like a cat walking around the bush or something just incredible what kind of resolution and range that those sensors
have
That's like the Luminar particularly a 500 meter range crazy. Okay
Indoors though, you'll tend to see a different type of laser scanner
These Hakuyu's were were very very popular are still very very popular for
Sort of indoor navigation where the lighting conditions are not as severe. The payloads can be a lot smaller
The energy budget is maybe smaller. Okay
But lidar is definitely one of the tools that sort of enabled this sort of revolution
but alongside that were cameras that
Didn't only return depth, you know lists of numbers that are just the depth but were coupled
RGB
Red green blue, you know color images with depth images and you get those in a handful of different ways
some of them are
actually just using stereo processing of the
depth of the RGB images, so
If you take an image with your right eye and an image with your left eye and you know the relative
Position of your eyes you can do some quick stereo matching
It says well this block over here looks a lot like the blocks on over here
And therefore the depth of that those pixels must be at a certain range. Okay
People do that now on FPGAs for instance on specialized hardware
So that you can package it nicely into a into a block that basically is just outputting both an image and a depth
This is the Carnegie multi-sense is actually the head that we carried around in Atlas the entire time
you'll see
Bumblebee point grades from bumblebee. There's a lot of
Systems that are doing like that. Okay, let me go through the first round first
Okay
another line of the
Tools like this the connect sensor was a big deal when that came out not only because it worked very well
but because it was so inexpensive right so somehow the
Home entertainment gaming world kind of revolutionized robotics by building a sensor that we needed. Okay, that was fantastic
the first version of connect worked with
Structured light so it's actually about as simple. I remember I mean this was an idea for
Decades and decades. Okay, but it became practical with the Microsoft Connect where you actually just project patterns
The patterns will deform on the object you can back out from the geometry something about the depth
Axion there's a bunch of different hardware manufacturers that that built
Structured light based depth cameras
The ones that I showed you here like the 415 will talk the most about is actually
Projected texture stereo. Okay, the problem with just taking two camera images
If you're looking at a white wall, for instance, there's nothing to compare and contrast between the two images
Okay, so but if you put if you project
In infrared for instance that you know something that will just put a little bit of a pattern
Then you can even in low contrast situations. You can get depth to come back out
One of the reasons that's nice compared to some of the other options like the time of flight. I'll show you next
Is that these these cameras can work even if they're looking at the same scene and they won't interfere with each other
Right. So sometimes some of these cameras if they're sending out pings or something like this
They can actually actively interfere with each other unless you synchronize them very very carefully
One of the projected texture you can just point them and forget. Okay
And then these days there really is a massive movement that was powered by deep learning
Which is you can just go straight from RGB
Okay
So a lot of times even if you only have a cell phone camera and you don't have it
Actually the cell phone cameras have depth sensors a lot of a lot of true depth on the iPhone for instance
Okay, a lot of times you can actually build beautiful 3d models even from a single camera
You don't even need the stereo pair. There's there's enough cues, of course from movement and other things, but there's also
There's additional information that can be available if you
Read everything on the internet. That's not what's happening in this particular one. This is a
Neural radiance field we'll talk about later
But just to say this is one of the first videos of the neural radiance fields showing that just from taking camera images
You could stitch together a camera image
And generate new images from new viewing angles
And there's also lines of work in
Monocular depth that for instance will just have
You know a very clever thing to do for instance is to drive a car around with two cameras on it
And then just use the second camera to
Use stereo matching from there, but just learn a model
From the single camera to the depth and then you can just
You know use stereo matching from there, but just learn a model
From the single camera to the depth
And then you know when it's time to make a hundred million of them because you're gonna
Make it into a product you just take away that extra camera and just use the learned mapping from
Image to depth
So monocular depth is a
Surprisingly effective technology now
Okay, now is a good time if you have a question or anything
[inaudible]
I don't actually know what's in the iPad so the
I know that there's a true depth sensor here if you look at you know at the back of these there's
They're projecting something here and they have the ability to do
You do have a depth camera on your iPhone
I don't have an iPad to look at
[inaudible]
Okay so the question was the second question was about the lidar on spot so typically the
The velodynes on a car or on spot I didn't the spot I brought did not have a
Velodyne on it it just had the surround cameras
But yes typically those are scanning lidars and you have to do some
Careful work to think about blurring from fast motions and timing it with the spinning laser
That's true
[inaudible]
I think I think spots pretty good yeah
Okay so oh yes please
[inaudible]
Yes
So the so the question is you know I mentioned FPGA and the Carnegie head
Yes I think that basically if you're doing block matching stereo that's the simplest algorithm
And it's they're doing more than that in those heads but that's I think the the essence of the
Of the hardness in the computation is that you're doing a relatively simple computation taking
An 8x8 block of pixels comparing it to another 8x8 block of pixels but you have to do that for
All possible pairs in a row for instance like this so it's a it's a very trivially parallelized
Operation and in order to get operating at full frame rates I mean computers have gotten faster
And faster but it's just a beautiful solution for specialized hardware yes yeah
[inaudible]
Depends on the technology so so like Nerf out of the box the neural radiance fields
Don't have scale unless you do some work a priori to tell them about the relative poses
You can run a different geometry processing algorithm first most of the projected texture
Or or anything that's projecting light actively does have absolute scale
They do have maximum range and minimum range so a lot of them are actually it's kind of it can
Be frustrating to use them you know you put a beautiful sensor on your wrist and then you
Realize that the minimum range of like the d415 is 0.3 meters or something like that so
You know the last when you're when you're getting close to the object that camera becomes blind
To the in the last 30 centimeters
Okay alongside this you know many sources of camera input we also have a
A lot of different ways to store that data when it comes in lots of different 3d representations
A bit like we talked about representations of rotation there's a there's just a handful of
Different formats for instance and some of them are good for some kind of type of computation
And some are good for the other and you can convert you should expect to convert back and
Forth between them and figure out which one's best for for particular sources so
The image the the image that you get directly out of a depth camera
That has rgb you think of that as an rgb plus d image
So it would have four channels some the first three are color values the last one is just the
Depth and at every pixel that's kind of the output of these cameras by default okay so that's you
Know one depth per pixel right we're going to take those rgb images which is a perfectly
Good representation and convert them into colored point clouds okay
So while this is a you know four by size of the image representation a point cloud is a list of
Points in 3d possibly annotated with color values or normals or other attributes
If you compare that to some of the ones you might have seen from a
Graphics software or graphics course you'll see you'll see things like you know triangle meshes
Or there's volumetric meshes triangle meshes are surface meshes
And you can you can have volumetric meshes in addition to surface meshes
You can think about sine distance functions as a representation
And increasingly now people are choosing to store those in neural networks so
NERF the neural radiance fields I was mentioning before
Is almost a sine distance function we'll get to the nuances of that when we get closer
Okay but this would be I mean we're going to we're going to go into each of these when it becomes
Most relevant but I want to just sort of get the the landscape out here first okay
You can also see voxel based representations
Some type of occupancy grids
Okay there's lots of different ways to represent 3d
Data like this okay some of the algorithms were the you know will will really more naturally
Fit with one versus the other and most of the time you can go back and forth yeah
Oh no I think by default the depth channel is the same size as the RGB
The depth always will give you something that will have some minimum range some maximum range and some
Resolution inside that range of course but you should think of it as an image that has
For every pixel a depth specified so in that sense the resolution is the same yeah
Yep yep you should think of every pixel being labeled yeah
So there's a lot of algorithms in fact the one we will talk about today doesn't use color
To start okay but you can potentially do better if you also include color values
Some algorithms will only use the d part in fact I would say many of the algorithms before
Deep learning really came in would would have only very limited use of the RGB values because RGB
I mean computer vision is hard let me just let's just take a second to think to remember why computer
Vision is hard right so if I take two slightly different images okay of a similar scene if the
Lighting changes at all right the color values are going to go are going to be wildly different for
Pixels that correspond to the same point in real space or if I take the same object and put it in
Two different rooms right the same point on the same object is going to come up with very different
Color values okay but having said that if you were to I remember the time when I was I was
With my students and we were you know enjoying how well RGB techniques were starting to work
And I said okay today if you were to pick if someone could only give you depth or only give
You RGB what would you pick and nowadays it's RGB all the way RGB is so much more informative there's
So many things you can't see through a depth camera that you can see in RGB and humans of
Course are very very good at that so I so I think if you have a method that's only limited using
Depth it's probably limited it's probably not the state of the art okay
All right so let's dig in sort of this part of the pipeline first go from RGB to point cloud
And start seeing the connections between the geometry of these camera representations and
The geometry of spatial transforms and the like and how do we write optimization problems over them
Okay maybe I'll do it over here
So this is maybe not a super popular view here but
I could you could argue that perception is just a hard kinematics problem at least the problem
The first version of perception we're going to do today okay it's certainly a controls problem but
But even before that we're going to think of perception today as a kinematics problem
What do I mean by that okay so let me say I've got an object
In space okay so I'll do 2d objects here because my artistic abilities are limiting in that way
Okay so let's say I have an object in space and it's got some
Coordinate system some canonical coordinate system I'll say this is my
Coordinate frame o and this will be the x and this will be the y axis okay
And I'm going to say the first thing I want to do is represent this geometry I could represent it as
A series of bases for instance that would be most similar to the triangle mesh in 2d it would just
Be line segments okay but instead I'm going to use a point cloud representation of that object
Okay so I want to represent this object with a series of points on the boundary
They're going to be points in now for my example here a 2d space
And they're going to be written in the coordinate system of the object
Okay so I'll call those points the model points
Sort of my model of the object and
And I'll write them as points right p for point here if I have model point i here
And I'll say that they're my model exists in the objects frame okay position of the object
Of each point in the object frame
So
Okay now I have a camera that's kicking out some other points hopefully they're
Relatively similar okay similarly spaced but maybe I have something that is coming out
Like this okay
By the way you rarely get all the points from the camera but we'll assume that for just to start
And I'll call these my scene points
S-I for scene and I get what I get out of my camera is the scene points in the camera frame
And let's say I took great care when I mounted my camera
So maybe we can say that the location of the camera in the world is known
If it's bolted to your hand or something like that that could be
Also just a forward kinematics problem to figure out where the location of the camera is yeah
It can be absolutely if it's if it's bolted to the robot
Then you would you would definitely be as a function of the joint positions
Right so far this is just a pose not a rotation or not a velocity okay
So the challenge
The goal of perception in this case
Is to figure out
The transform of the object in the world we have a lot of the pieces we have
Points in the world we have camera points in the world a lot of points
And scene points and then we have the camera's location yeah
The point cloud is a 2D world so there are not like the normal world
And you can take the point and 3D camera
Great great yes so
So the point cloud resolution so that's a really good question so the question was
You know the camera I think of a camera image is giving me points in a 2D picture
Right but if I have a depth channel inside that
Then it's the first step that I didn't I should have said is I'm going to take those 2D points
In in the camera and I'm going to project them into a 3D point right by just applying
My in my camera frame that's easy I just say that it's at some depth in the in the immediate frame
Now there's a couple steps that go involved that are involved in that so first of all there's like
Intrinsics in the camera you have to take out any distortion from the lens or something like this
But this is something we know a lot about it's still a pain but it's but it's something we know
A lot about and then the other thing is the extrinsics which is to take those points in the
Camera frame and bring it into the world frame and that would be this this xwc that's the camera
Extrinsics okay good but all those are are quite doable to go from the 2D picture with a depth
Channel into a 3D point yeah okay but there's another step yeah go ahead
So let's say this is exactly the right the same object right that my model my model was perfect
Right so and that my sensor had zero noise okay there's still things that can get in the way
Right which is that like those points might have been sampled in different places along the you
Know there's there's reasons why that's almost never going to be perfect but as a toy problem
To start I'm actually going to say let's consider the case where we've just taken the model points
And translated it someone translated them through an unknown transform and we're going to try to get
That back okay that's the easy case and we'll look at the harder case where there's noise and
Outliers and other things in between great question okay there's another thing that we have to assume
To well that we will assume to get started okay these are all just yellow dots okay and these are
All just yellow dots and your incredible brain knows how to map the you know knows that this
Yellow dot probably corresponds to that yellow dot okay but if it's just a list of numbers on
The computer that mapping the correspondence it's called between those points and this points is not
Given and in general it has to be acquired by some sort of logic you have to figure out which of
These if you just have a pile of points over here and a pile of points over here figuring out those
Correspondences is a massive part of the problem okay but let's just start by assuming that someone
Said that the i-th point here matches the i-th point over here and we'll solve the second part
Of that problem in a second yeah
So so it let's say i had a cad model i could take these points directly from the cad model
So if that's so helpful that's why i'm using the word model sometimes the way you get it is you
You know put your your object down in a nice situation and you get one scan and then you use
That as your model for finding it in other things okay but but think of this as like you've got a
Cad model and then this is the real object out in the world that i got returns from that's the scene
Okay so step one
We'll assume known correspondences
Sometimes the word i feel like i forget to define it but it's just the mapping i would
Define it in symbols in a minute but the mapping from those points to these points are the
Correspondences right
Okay so in that case you can sort of see that we have a nice little kinematics problem an
Optimization problem we know that
The i-th point of the model should correspond with the
Oops zero m i that's the model in object frame mapped to the world frame should correspond to
In the simple exactly one-to-one correspondence problem
These are the obvious kinematic equations okay and in this these are all known
Are given and this is the unknown
So the question becomes how do i extract the pose
Given a list of you know for all i a list of many correspondences
Now if we dig in just a little bit to the pose representation you remember from our
Spatial transforms that doing this is equivalent to both the translation plus the rotation
Okay i'm leaving off the w for my shorthand but w is everywhere okay so really if the unknowns are
Both the translation inside there and the rotation the rotation you'll remember we have
Lots of choices about how to represent that this is always three numbers basically in 3d
In 2d it'd be the two numbers here we have many different ways we could possibly represent the
3d rotations but somehow we need to search over these okay and that's the question
So solving this is is actually an inverse kinematics problem right we're trying to figure
Out given the given the the data the points in space we're trying to back out the orientations
And rotations this is an inverse kinematics problem
Now let's stop and think for a second here so last time we didn't actually do inverse kinematics we
Did differential inverse kinematics i said inverse kinematics is harder we're going to defer that to
Later but this time we're going to go directly i haven't written any differential kinematics yet
I've just written a kinematics problem so this is like you know the positions and orientations
Inside here is like our generalized coordinates that we're trying to back out so what is the
Difference why am i why did i advocate immediately diff i k for moving the arm around but i'm saying
We're going to have to solve the full inverse kinematics problem for this one
Yeah
I think that's right so he says you don't have the ground truth right so
Effectively the the magic that happens in the in the robot case is that you know the initial
Conditions and you want to change those initial conditions you have an initial
Q and you're making small changes to that so you have a place to linearize around
Okay in perception you know at least once you have to wake up and figure out where the objects are
You don't have an initial unless someone gives you a good initial guess then you could be in
The land of differential kinematics inverse kinematics okay but we're saying you know at
Least once you have to figure out the hard problem find the needle in the haystack potentially okay
Now once you solve that once i actually would advocate differential inverse kinematics if you
Wanted to track for instance if you want to do real-time tracking then by all means you should
Be thinking about gradients and the like okay but the one-time problem is a little bit it must be
Solved i guess in the perception case fortunately this is not some complicated chain of of equations
That can lead to lots of uh of non-linearities and local minima and stuff this is about the
Simplest inverse kinematics problem we could have to solve and we're going to see it has
Beautiful structure and good solutions okay
Okay so let's start um we get to pick a rotation representation now
The the derivation i'll do would go through fine for at least for quaternions
And we're going to do rotation matrices here just because i think it's a little bit
It's obviously a linear equation in a three by three matrix here so it's just a little easier
On the board um so so let's let's say even though this is my spatial algebra rotation
We're going to represent this with three by three matrices for for the purpose of this
And this is three by one numbers
Yes you have a question
So um you know i've got a mug here at least once i'm going to say you know i'm going to build a
CAD model or whatever i'm going to pick an origin of my CAD system and i'm going to just define an
Object relevant model of this i think that is the natural like if you think about what you would
Have to do to build a model and write some coordinate system the natural thing would be
To attach your coordinate system to the object itself okay and then the question of then is of
Where it is in space becomes what's where is that object in space that's the second transform i think
Yep
Yep so uh pick the bottom corner you know it's it's just like if you were in solid works
And you were you know you have to just start drawing lines you got to pick a zero zero
Somewhere okay and all of your points are sort of relative to that zero zero it doesn't matter if
You put it in the middle it doesn't put it in the matter in the bottom corner but it's just the frame
Of reference that you're going to define those points relative to each other thank you that's
Good question okay so so now to solve this problem we want to back out those nine plus three numbers
12 numbers in order to make those equations match okay a little annoying that i picked the
Divider right there let me slide that out
Okay that's the game how do we do it
So first of all
Do you see even though it's it doesn't look quite in the normal way but do you see that's just a
Linear equation right so this is you should see that this is like ax is approximately equal to b
Right except in this case the x would be my three you know three positions and then the the 12
Rotation coordinates all stacked in one line if i just flatten those into one vector the a
Has a bunch of stuff about the pmi in here flipped around a little bit and shifted okay and this has
Got the psi over here inside that okay but it really is just you could just rewrite that you
Know if i flatten that out into a big a matrix that's your data matrix big b matrix okay and
You're trying to solve a least squares problem to back that out almost almost yes
So this is the scene points you know in the
I guess in the camera it also is going to have inside it the the x
Wc which is i guess given right in this bright pink thing on the top
That's the that's the right hand side yeah and then the rest of it is decision variables which
Are just multiplied by the pm so if i just try to solve ax equal to b i just tried to take an a
Inverse what's wrong with that right if i have any number of so you need a some number of points
We'll ask you on the p set exactly how many points you need for that to be well defined
Okay you need some number of points for this to just to have a unique solution okay but most of
The time you're going to be in a situation where you have many points many more than 12 points
Let's say well you know if each point contributes three things so you know many more than four
Points hopefully if you're at the four point room you know find another camera or something right
Okay so if solving that with exact equality would be very brittle for all the reasons we brought up
A minute ago right if there's any noise if you sampled uh slightly different points on the
Surface just because of the word the position of your camera or something like that that's not
Going to be a good way to go so we're going to solve this again in the least squares sense yeah
Yeah i was thinking about that myself
Oh look at that
Wow it used to be like i had options 1 through 32 but now it actually just says chalkboard and
Center light turn on i don't know that's good they just upgraded that this year
Okay that was way too easy i should have done that before yeah
I'm sorry
This is a i'm i'm using this as an abstract so so i could i want to when i see this
I think of a you know a standard linear algebra problem where typically in linear algebra when
People write this they will use a and b matrix and what i was trying to convey is that the
Problem we have with different variables that are you know rooted in geometry could be interpreted
As our standard ax equals b where the a matrix is populated with the data from pm
Okay and the b matrix is populated from psi right yeah
That's exactly the so you got it right so so the reason i said almost he says is this going to give
You a valid rotation matrix right so what i really want to write in an optimization world is i want
To minimize the difference between the right and the left hand side this is basically my ax minus b
Okay but i'll say p plus r p o m i minus
Psi that's already rotated into the world frame okay
Sum over i i'm going to minimize this over pr that's almost what i want to say okay that's
Like the least squares version of that fitting but there's one important detail which is that not all
Nine numbers you can't pick arbitrary nine numbers and get a valid rotation matrix
Okay so what i'll do is i'll write in here r has to be part of s03
As a constraint this is the special orthogonal group
Three okay and you're going to understand it completely it just says it's a valid rotation matrix
One way to write that is with additional constraints on the optimization problem
So i can i can write this you know in the shorthand but what i in order to implement that
What i would actually do is write the things that define a valid rotation matrix
First of all r transpose has to be r inverse that's one constraint that makes a valid
Rotation matrix and the other one is the determinant of r has to be positive one
So this is the optimization problem we're working on yes
[inaudible]
It's a good that's a good question so it turns out that this constraint by itself
ensures the determinant is either plus one or minus one but the minus one case can get you
That would be called an improper rotation which is a rotation plus a reflection
So if you want to stay with the proper rotations you need the extra constraint that's a good
question. In practice we often we will drop this and then check for reflections
afterwards and flip it back because this is an ugly constraint in general
In fact if you think about this so this we said is in the decision variables the inside of this
is a linear function which means the squared is a quadratic function so you should be thinking
I've got you know a quadratic bowl like this that's a good case. What are these in terms of
the constraints? I told you quadratic programming is beautiful if you have it but it's defined when
you have linear constraints. Are these constraints linear? Right this is not a linear constraint
It's also a quadratic constraint the way you can see that is you multiply by both sides you say
R times R transpose equals I would be an equivalent writing of that and so the decision variables
have to be zero or one to make all of the nine elements match okay but those are each of those
the entries in this matrix is the squared of the original decision variables okay so this
is a quadratic constraint. This constraint turns out to be cubic in the three by three matrices
in two by two matrices it's just it's actually the same as it's a quadratic again okay but that
can be in general cubic. So those are less good but it turns out that you know we have really
really good solutions to this. This is like one potentially ugly hard class of optimization
problems where this one we just we nail it okay. Let's actually do the 2D example. I think it's
useful to understand the optimization landscape. What are we setting our code up to have to solve?
Okay so let's say we're going to do the two by two version of it so in that case
a two by two rotation matrix you'll often see it's cosine theta negative sine theta
sine theta cos theta. We could try to search directly for theta but to keep our analogy to
the 3D case what I'm going to instead do is I'm going to just name a variable. I'll call it
what did I call it a for cosine theta so b for sine theta and also I'll parameterize my matrix
as a negative b b a. Again I'm going to search over a and b. This is a trick that you can't quite do
in so in 3D if I would have had I could have done a b c d for instance like this.
It just happens that in 2D I know there's not enough degrees of freedom. I know that I can
solve away c and d so I haven't done that but in 3D you don't get that same luxury.
That was your question was it?
Okay we'll come back to it when it when it makes sense then. Okay all right so
so let's just multiply this out so what does r times r transpose equal i look like? Well that
looks like a negative b b a times the transpose of that a negative b b a
and that implies in order for this to equal 1 0 0 1 that implies a squared plus b squared has to equal
1 and it says that a b minus b a has to equal 0. Okay so that's a two quadratic constraints that
define the rotation matrix being a valid rotation. Okay and this is the same thing is happening in
3D you know same same type of thing but you just have more equations flying around. It happens if
you wanted to say that the determinant of this equals positive 1. In this case it's the same as
this right this is also the determinant of r equals plus 1 and that's because I took out the
improper rotations by my parameters roughly. Okay so yes.
Yep yep sorry that's that was just me spelling it out but you're right that's trivially true.
Yep also because I did the change of variables. Okay so I made a animation of a visualization
of this okay so what I want you to think of is a objective that's a quadratic bowl
and a constraint that is this quadratic constraint. So what does that look like?
It went out of order but here it is. Okay this is what it looks like. Okay so I took a few points
and I made it I made a you know my quadratic objective and I can and I just I took my points
and I just rotated them I'm just trying to back it up bring it back so I can actually dynamically
rotate what those points are. Okay and it's moving around and my goal is to find the bottom
of the quadratic bowl but it has to be on this constraint so if you look down from the top
this is the unit circle constraint which looks like a cylinder I mean I project it up okay so I
have to find the lowest point on the on the parabola that intersects with the red constraint
and it turns out in the case where there's no noise the minimum is always going to be on the
manifold right because the best rotation that you could find is going to have it's going to be a
valid rotation. Okay so in this case is actually the good case now as soon as you add noise that
the parabola could move off the unit circle and you're going to need to project it back onto the
unit circle that's the fundamental geometry of this problem. It's also it's very it's a
very famous problem it's the point correspondence problem the Waba problem there's it comes up in
all kinds of fields it's a famous problem of this solve a quadratic objective onto the
unit circle or the SO3 constraint. Okay
interestingly yeah go ahead
it's only a little bit hard so it is harder to do
basically I don't know that I don't have the simple relationship to just know that this is
negative sign and theta so I would have to use nine numbers instead of I just used two numbers here
in three by three I'll you know have a b c d e f right
and then the the r transpose r is still quadratic the determinant is cubic
for a three by three matrix yeah okay but the geometry is roughly the same yeah yes
that's this constraint and the determinant constraint so yeah
yeah okay interestingly let me just get one thing more thing in and then so interestingly
we could have parameterized the whole thing directly with theta okay that's only one
variable in 2d of course in 3d we'd pick quaternions or we'd pick one of the other
representations in this case it's maybe illustrative to see that if we just did it in
terms of theta what does that cost function look like I threw that on the plot too
no but okay
and it is similarly beautiful and good okay so now there's no constraints I don't if I were to
just parameterize it with theta then I would always get a valid rotation out I don't need this
so I could just write my objective but the objective is no longer quadratic it's a
it's a non-convex objective it's got sines and cosines in the middle of it
and the sines and cosines multiplied out you get you get cosine squared whatever you know
to the second power gives you a cost landscape that looks like this and if I you know move my
theta that rotated the two relative to each other then the minimum moves correspondingly
luckily you know all of the minima are good in this case they're all just two pi off so just
you know similarly this is a good optimization if I start with an initial guess and I and I go down
then I'm always going to find a good answer in the no noise case things are going to behave
differently not only when you have noise but also when you have additional constraints like for
instance if you don't want to penetrate if you don't want your object to penetrate the world or
something like this that becomes a harder constraint and we'll choose we'll see the
differences between those representations more yeah
in the two by two case it is quadratic in the three by three it's not quadratic
but what we're going to do is ignore it the rotation matrix is sufficient to get determinant
plus or minus one we're going to solve if our if our determinant was minus one that we're going to
we're going to multiply by a negative one in one of the in one of the yeah so basically it's whether
you have a right-handed rule or a left-handed rule if you end up with a left-handed rule you flip it
back to a right-handed rule and you call it a day yeah so that's how we get around that one but
you're right it's cubic okay so that was just searching for rotations I left out the the
in this simple example I left out the positions but one of the most important insights I want you
to take away today is that actually you can separate solving rotations from solving for the
translations okay why is that so registering the points the key the key insight and we already had
it in the first lecture about spatial transforms remember I made you I did a check yourself kind
of thing saying the position the the position of b relative to a only depends on the rotation
between those two frames not on the position because it's already it's already a vector
the base of that vector is is you know in rooted in the coordinate system so the
the relative positions of two points only depends on the rotation
so
the trick is if you just try to fit every point by itself then then you have to solve for the
translation and rotation separately but if you just take the difference between two points that
quantity does not depend on the translation of the object you could take an object you know
I don't know in in building 32 or an object here okay and the the absolute
translation does not affect the relative point only the orientation
so the trick is you subtract out some nominal point in the middle of your point cloud
from all your points you solve for the rotations and then at the end now that you know the rotations
you can easily figure out the positions okay you can solve for the rotations separately
you guys didn't look like you got that I mean I'm not trying to but you didn't look as happy as a
as a you know on average let's just say yeah yes
that is true that is true
so so so you said it almost right and I have to re-say it for the people on the video so
so we're going to take the the model point cloud we'll find the centroid of the model point cloud
and write all of the model points relative to the model centroid and I'll take the central I'll take
all those scene points I'll take the scene centroid and write all of theirs relative to
the scene centroid and then I'm going to try to take those relative coordinates and rotate them
until they match and now I have an easy problem to just snap the positions into alignment so it's
a two-step process yes so so the question is why an arbitrary point so it the key insight is that
it's the relative points that that match it turns out there is a right kind of a natural point to
pick which is the centroid because then it actually just drops right out of the out of
the equations in a beautiful way yeah yeah it's the average of the points it's literally the
average of the data points yeah yes in 3d also it's only rotations that affects the relative
points if you have a you know this point relative to this point then it the only thing that changes
that number you know changing the coordinate system doesn't you know the location of the
coordinate system does not change the relative number it's only the rotations
in 3d it works fine yeah okay so quick quick quiz so
what happens if you have a symmetric object right so I drew one in sort of intentionally
that had a you know an asymmetry there what if it was a box
so so she says it's impossible to know you know if it was if it was four ways symmetric
in an actual box then it's impossible to know but so you're right of course but the thing I just want
to make sure it's clear that so far I've assumed known correspondences so in the case of known
correspondences there is no symmetry it cannot be right if someone told me that this point
corresponds to that face and there is always a unique solution right and the reason that's sort
of maybe puzzling is I'm showing you these plots that look like they have a unique solution
even in the case of something that has symmetries and the reason for that it's not a it's not a trick
that function doesn't change if your object suddenly becomes symmetric it's because it's
the known correspondences case okay let me let me keep moving a little bit so I want to get
through a couple things all right and we'll ask you a couple questions about uniqueness and the like
on the problem okay is that is that a basic idea clear if someone gives me the correspondences
then I have a very good algorithm which is just solving this that that can can find the optimal
solution in fact even the solving the quadratic thing projecting onto the unit circle you don't
have to just you know solve and then project you actually can solve it beautifully and it turns out
the solution is given by this by the singular value decomposition okay so the the wobble problem is
famously solved by the singular value decomposition if you have extra constraints then you're going to
use extra machinery typically a very powerful way to write that is as a semi-definite program which
we'll get to later okay but but these kind of quadratic constraints are a particularly nice
case of a semi-definite program okay but in in the in the unconstrained case or you know only this
constraint this is like the the svd if you know the basic picture of the geometry of svd right
it's about finding the coordinate you warp it to the circle you rotate it and you warp it back
okay well that warping to the circle is exactly the warping that happens
of projecting onto the unit circle okay so it's it turns out to be exactly related to the svd
okay so equipped with that we now have the most important
algorithm for sort of geometric perception which is the iterative closest point
the biggest assumption we made so far was this known correspondence
right someone told me the the relative correspondences if i instead have to solve
for the correspondences then then i have an extra work to do and just to give my
notation let's define a correspondence vector okay
so i'll use a correspondence vector c one for it's the length of num points times one okay
the num points by one vector and the ith element takes an integer value and i'll say
the ith element is an integer j if
point si corresponds
to model
point mj
and now i was careful that to choose that so it doesn't have to be a one-to-one mapping
right i'm going to try to power through a little bit more so it doesn't have to be a
one-to-one mapping there could be model points that don't have a corresponding scene point
which is important because oftentimes if you have a camera you're just looking at one side
you're not going to have scene points all the way around the object okay but we're saying that every
scene point corresponds to a model there's other choices people sometimes make where the
where you assume that every model goes to a scene and that all of them have implications
but in this we're going to choose it like like this okay i could then just write my optimization
i'm going to search over x
using that notation minus p si squared but now i have to search i have to find both ci
which is this discrete thing right this is an it's a function on the elements of one to
num model points
that's the set that lives in so it's kind of a weird thing to optimize over and x in se3
so how am i going to optimize that right it looks like kind of a quadratic objective but with a
combinatorial aspect of it of trying to figure out all these correspondences simultaneously and you
can do that we've had paper that does that kind of thing where we're trying to do the
combinatorial search at the same time as the continuous search but it's very expensive optimization
so the icp algorithm famously does it by by splitting it into two parts
so
in many optimizations kind of like this it's often the case that if you fix one set of variables then
the optimization is easy fix another set of variables the other optimization is easy and
then you end up with natural algorithms that alternate between the two optimization problems
and that's exactly what we'll do here because if the correspondences are known then the
optimization is exactly what we did a minute ago that's the point registration with known
correspondences and it has a beautiful solution and then the other side of it is if the transform
is known then finding the corresponding points is just a nearest neighbor problem okay so if we have
an initial guess for x then we can find what they step one solve the nearest neighbor problem
so c our new ci is going to be just be the
we can just try all the possible correspondences basically i'm going to say
x p o n j argmin over j
minus psi squared so in the if for a small point cloud you can just literally try all the possible
correspondences for this when x is known you can just measure the distance and take the smallest
one okay when it gets bigger you start using efficient nearest neighbor data structures
like kd trees and stuff like that okay but this is a fast nearest neighbor query
and then the second step is given correspondences
solve for x and then you just repeat until the convergence okay
so let's see what that looks like so i did not stand in the middle of here right here
okay so this is the kind of plot i'm going to show you here so this was the known correspondence one
i picked a lovely salmon color for the random object with random points in 2d and known points
and then i rotated it and translated it by some random quantities and got my blue scene points
in the first step we have a known correspondence problem and the registration just works exactly
okay that's the known correspondence version now if i take another point another example here with
my scene my my model points and my scene points if i start the iter the icp algorithm then i think i
can just step through here we go okay the first thing is i do is i solve that given that initial
guess which was a bad initial guess i you know this is the initial guess here i just compute
the nearest neighbors for every um every scene point i find the nearest point okay and then i
given those correspondences i try to solve for the new optimization and it doesn't do very well
because my correspondences were all wrong but the hope is that it gets you closer okay and then i
get a new chance at my correspondences and many times this converges beautifully in a small number
of alternations because you know at some point your correspondences are correct and you snap
right into place yeah yes um so just like uh you can separate translation and rotation scaling can
be separated too and the trick is so just like the observation is that um the the relative positions
only depend on rotations it turns out the difference of of distances only depends on scale
so if you if you play that trick one more time you get something that only depends on scale so
you can fit scale first and then fit rotations and then fit translations i actually cite that
in the notes because i think that's part of the story yeah
yes good so so this algorithm can absolutely get stuck in local minima i i you know there's a in
the in the code you can play with it's just random so the fact that it's mostly translation
it's probably because i wanted one that fits on the slide but i didn't think of it that way now
i feel like i picked a bad example but uh yeah so so it but it absolutely can get stuck in local
minimum yes if you pick the wrong correspondences you make not enough change you could get the same
correspond same wrong correspondences back and that will never leave right uh so there are many
ways and we're going to talk about those more next time but there are many ways you can try
random initializations of correspondences but you can also there are more robust methods that can
they can try to avoid some of those local minima yeah
so and we're going to talk about noise uh also next time it's actually it's a fairly subtle
question and i had a i had a slide i blew past real quick but uh just to show you some like real
world noise is is extremely structured so if you think about noise as like adding gaussian values
to all of those values independently that's not the way cameras have noise cameras tend to have
like this is the actual depth image and this is like the the depth image you get out of a camera
they have dropouts like pixels that are just mixing and missing in the middle they will have
swaths of like a shiny material might have very noisy things and then they have a lot of noise
shiny material might have very noisy things and a you know a flat material could could not so so
the the answer to your question requires thinking a little bit about the types of noise yeah
yep just alternate back and forth between when x is fixed the problem is easy its nearest neighbors
when the correspondences are fixed then the problem is easy it's this wobble problem
that's true you're solving many optimization problems in the loop the one the this one is
so easy that it becomes an svd it's a called svd so it's i wouldn't even call it an optimization
problem in the implementation it's very fast even for very big point clouds but yes it is it is
alternating between those and let me just i'll take home with one more example here so yeah these
are i've got lots of examples of real noisy things but you're gonna play with the bunny because
everybody who ever does icp makes the stanford bunny snap into alignment with another stanford
bunny that's just like you know early in computer graphics the stanford bunny sort of did a
winner take all thing and it just won out and there's everybody uses the stanford bunny okay
so you'll do that on your problem set but just to show you even in the examples i i i showed you
like the loading a dishwasher for instance if you watch carefully at what happens so there was a
perception system that tried to figure out where the mug was to begin with okay but as the robot
moves even in this sort of state-of-the-art perception system okay uh state-of-the-art a
few years ago i guess but um watch this that was running icp i mean that wasn't the icp updates but
it actually when it goes there it has a model of the mug back back in the day okay and it actually
tried to align the model of the mug before going into to close the the difference between the
faraway cameras rough estimate of the where the mugs were and actually making the pick
and people still do that today leslie and tomas we were in a meeting with leslie tomas the other
day and they're like we're going to do icp for this and and the young students were like okay
that's kind of old school but uh but it still works like it still works really well yeah
yep so this is part one part two is like how do you do more robust versions of this with partial
views and outliers and noise yep so we're going to talk about that next time good i'll answer you
I'm sure you can come out a bit of effort.