Okay, I got my, I always wait till the 35 happens,
but it's 35, here we go.
Welcome back.
Again, I got lots of good feedback on the survey.
Thank you for doing that, keep it coming.
I will try to not write on the bottom of the board.
If I do, you can shout at me.
Some things are kind of baked into muscle memory,
and I will try to write bigger, and I will try my best.
And I think about the Roman Empire every day,
every single day, for sure.
Okay, so I also got some feedback about just the pace,
and some things are new.
Could you go through a little bit more detail
on these things?
So today, it's kind of nice.
I took a little longer than I meant to last time,
so we're gonna still do differential inverse kinematics,
but with optimization this time.
But that gives me a chance to kind of go into
some of the optimization.
This is the first time we're gonna use optimization
more heavily in the course, and we'll use it
throughout the course.
So it'll give me a chance to sort of slow down
and do the optimization introduction properly today,
which I think is great.
And I'm hoping that I'll say enough about linear algebra
for those of you that are experts.
It will still be satisfying, but if you're new,
it'll still be, it'll take you through some of the steps.
Okay, so the recipe, you know well now.
I've shown it a couple times, right?
We had our basic pick and place idea.
We went through the spatial algebra.
We made a gripper plan.
We talked about forward kinematics.
And then we talked last time about
differential inverse kinematics.
Okay, and in particular, I thought I'd up to do this.
So we talked about how taking the inverse there
is in general not, it shouldn't even be written,
really it should be a pseudo-inverse.
Okay, and I wanna start today by talking about
the pseudo-inverse through the lens of optimization.
I told you about all the magical properties it has.
Okay, and then when we see it through the lens
of optimization, then we'll be able to extend it
and see how we make things more robust
to actually run on the real robot.
Okay, so.
(marker tapping)
Right, so there's various ways that we'll write
optimization problems, mathematical programs.
I might write minimize, maximize,
or just if there's no objective, I could just say fine.
My goal in the pseudo-inverse is really to find me some v
such that JG of Q, V is approximately equal
to the spatial velocity of the gripper that I want.
Maybe I could even write desired here.
Okay, that's sort of the beginnings
of a mathematical program, but this approximately equal
needs to be made precise.
And how are we gonna formulate that?
How are we gonna think about that?
Importantly, when Q is known or measured,
this is a linear equation.
Right, this just becomes a matrix.
So it just becomes the stuff of linear algebra.
This is just AX is approximately equal to B.
It would be the way you'd see it in linear algebra.
A is my Jacobian, B is my desired,
but let's just think about it even in the purest form.
We can forget about robots for just a moment
and think about AX equals B.
Super common in linear algebra.
And actually, you probably have seen it in linear algebra.
You've probably thought about it,
but let's just think about it a bit graphically
'cause I wanna make these things visually compelling,
I think, for you.
So super simple to think about the scalar case,
but helpful, I hope.
Okay, so I just even said little aX,
so that's a scalar, approximately equals B.
Then the picture is very simple, right?
I have X here.
I've got some line that goes through the origin.
It has slope A, and if I pick a B, I don't know, here,
then I want this solution here, right?
The place where aX equals B.
So, and in particular, the solution is simple
in closed form.
We know that it's gonna be B over A.
So I wanna make that approximately equal.
In this case, it was exactly equal,
but I wanna think about the generalization of that,
a slightly more expressive way to write that.
Let's write minimum over X, aX minus B squared.
Okay, now that's a precise thing,
saying that I have a quadratic cost function,
the squared term here,
and certainly if I can make aX equal to B,
then the cost is zero, and that's as small as a,
this is always gonna be a positive number,
and if it can be made zero,
that's the smallest it could be,
so that's clearly the minimum.
So the minimum of this, if aX can be equal to B,
which it can in the scalar case, right,
then it would be this.
But think about the picture that's happening there.
I'm gonna go to the bottom of the board,
but the board is lifted,
so I think that's still legit, yeah?
Okay.
So X, and now, let me plot the cost on this axis.
Okay, so, and I'll pick a couple different values.
Let's just set B equal to one,
and I'll plot it for a couple different values of a here.
But if a is one,
then this is gonna look like a quadratic function.
Imagine that's a perfectly symmetric parabola.
My drawing's not perfect, but.
Okay, and it also obtains a minimum, of course,
when aX equals B, when X is B over A.
Okay, so we've changed this picture into this picture,
saying, I wanna find the bottom of that bowl.
All right, so does this always have a solution?
Yeah.
Right, so every time you see a in the denominator,
which is the same as taking a Jacobian inverse, right,
we gotta watch out for things,
if a were to go to zero, bad things could happen.
And I also said, you know,
it's gonna be very rare to go exactly to zero.
It's more like you get close to zero.
Let's just think about what's happening
as a gets closer to zero.
So this is my a equals one case.
Okay, if I were to plot, I don't know,
a equals two, or a equals, sorry, a equals a half,
then I'll get, well, let's just do it out.
If I did a equals half, so I get a squared,
X squared minus two, aBX plus B squared, right?
So the steepness of this parabola goes like a squared.
If I choose a to a two, I actually get it to be
a much less steep curve, right?
I'm sorry, if a equals a half, is that wrong?
Then the optimum becomes two,
but the parabola shifts out, okay?
If I did four, let's say,
if I had a equals a fourth,
I'm gonna get a picture like that.
It attains its optima,
that's supposed to hit the bottom down here, okay?
But it's just getting flatter and flatter and flatter,
and the solution is running off to the right, right?
So that seems kind of simple and trivial,
and that's what's happening in the scalar case.
That's exactly what's happening in the Jacobian case,
when you get close to a singularity, okay?
So I want you to see all the way through to that
in a second.
And how are we gonna fix it?
There's a bunch of different ways to fix it,
but maybe the simplest way that I can see already
in the scalar case would be to start adding constraints,
okay?
So what if I don't wanna send,
or I don't wanna send a velocity command
of very, very large to the robot?
So even if the optimal solution,
in order to match my desired velocity,
if that optimal solution is too far to the right,
maybe I don't wanna send that to the robot.
So once we've got this language of optimization,
we can start doing more interesting things.
So I can do min over x,
ax minus b squared,
but I can add a constraint saying,
but I don't want x, let's say,
I want x to be less than or equal to two.
Do your best to follow the command,
but don't send velocities bigger than two, okay?
And this seems arbitrary sort of here,
but these are really,
this is like a velocity limit
that comes from your actuator.
You really do have velocity.
Or maybe you make it a little conservative.
You make it a little less than the true velocity limit,
'cause you don't wanna send big velocity commands.
Okay, and if you can solve this, which we can,
we can solve these nicely.
Certainly in the scalar case, it's trivial,
but in the bigger case,
it's also computationally very efficient to solve these.
Then we're gonna be able to send more reliable,
avoid sending very large numbers to the robot.
So my statement is preferring this
of being explicit about saying,
I want Ax to be close to B.
Do your best effort,
but I'm allowed to add extra constraints.
That's better than saying Ax must be exactly equal to B,
which is too explicit of a,
it doesn't leave me any room for satisfying other things.
(air whooshing)
Is that picture kind of clear?
Simple in the scalar case, okay.
In the matrix case, it's the same.
It's just you could get confused more easily, I think,
but the pictures,
the geometry of the optimization is the same.
So now we wanna say Ax minus B squared.
Okay, so I'll say for instance,
minimize over X, Ax minus B squared.
We'll add constraints in a minute,
but let's just think about that version of the problem.
Analogously, if I were to multiply this out,
I get X transpose A transpose Ax
minus two X transpose A transpose B.
A transpose B plus B transpose B.
Those middle terms,
I can combine the two middle terms because it's a scalar.
So the transpose is equal to the number.
That's why I get the minus two there.
Okay, so the picture you should have in your head then
is that this is gonna be now in more dimensions.
Let me see if I can get even more 3D here.
So a little slant here, a little slant here.
This is X one, X two.
This is my cost here.
And I've got some sort of a parabola still,
something like that.
It obtains its minimum at a point.
So depending on the properties of A, which we'll look at,
if it can drive this completely zero,
it might be able to drive this,
it might be able to obtain the minimum at zero.
And that's the point in X one, X two,
that it obtains that minimum is the solution
that makes Ax equal to B.
Okay, but A of course could be not full rank
or something like this, and we'll try to look at that.
The shape of that parabola,
I mean, it's gonna be potentially sort of slanted
based on this term.
It could be lifted off the bottom with this term,
but really the shape of the parabola
comes from the quadratic term,
the same way that we looked at just the squared term
to understand that curvature.
So even if A is not a square matrix,
it could be six by seven, for instance, okay?
A transpose times A is a square matrix,
and it's a real matrix, a real number,
no complex numbers anywhere here.
This is, and it's symmetric because of the A transpose A.
So we know it's well-behaved in a lot of sense,
it's got real eigenvalues for instance, okay?
And it's the eigenvalues,
so just to say that on the board if that helps,
A transpose A is real and symmetric.
So it has real eigenvalues.
(board clacking)
So the picture of a quadratic bowl is reasonable, yes?
(audience member speaking faintly)
They're all real to begin with in our case.
So in the general linear algebra case,
I would use a Hermitian transform
since it's gonna be a Jacobian coming from real robots,
I'm just gonna treat it as real, thank you for asking.
And that's also why I'm willing to say
it's real and symmetric, you know?
It only is by assumption I guess
in the pure linear algebra case.
And it's the eigenvalues that tell me how elongated the,
you know, if I were to draw this thing from above,
over here, right?
So if I were to look down from above,
this is now X1, X2,
then I'm gonna get some sort of, you know,
quadratic, I'll just draw it around the origin
to keep it simple here, but it's gonna look like
I'm looking down into a bowl,
these are level sets of that bowl, contours of the bowl,
okay, and the axes that define,
I'll tell you the elongation,
these are the eigenvectors of A transpose A,
and the scaling there, it goes by the eigenvalues,
larger eigenvalue means it goes up steeper,
so it's actually shorter in this bowl, okay?
A small eigenvalue means that it's elongated here,
grows up very slowly,
and that's exactly this picture here, right?
As the A gets smaller,
then this thing is gonna get stretched
and stretched and stretched, right?
And potentially, if the B is not zero,
you know, if that was a little bit offset,
then as I stretch it, it's also gonna,
the origin of that point is gonna be racing away
from the origin of the coordinate system,
it's gonna be asking me for large velocities
to achieve the right end effector,
the commanded IR end effector,
but this is the picture you should have in your head
about the math that's happening,
is that it's a quadratic form
that's getting flattened and shifted away,
running away from me.
Yeah?
(audience member speaking)
So in this picture, is it clear?
So if, as the,
as A gets smaller, X star is also getting bigger.
So I, just because I used eigenvalues and eigenvectors,
and I just was thinking about this,
I drew this around the origin,
but as soon as it's not around the origin,
then the same thing's gonna happen,
these terms, you know,
it's like having the A in the denominator,
so the steady state is gonna be running away.
That's why I tried to draw this,
because that's the intuition,
it's gonna, you have A in the denominator,
so it's gonna go to infinity like that.
Is that sort of a helpful picture?
Remember, actually, I said,
I said don't just think about the rank of your Jacobian,
think about the singular values of your Jacobian, right?
And I can connect that here, if that's useful, right?
So if I were to say that A is a singular value decomposition,
I'm assuming, again, assuming it's real,
so I have real singular values here.
If you know SVD,
if you should know SVD at some point, it's great,
it's a very powerful thing, okay?
But even if you're not,
if you don't have all the geometry of SVD,
it has this, it's a way to factorize a matrix
into two unitary matrices.
These are unitary,
meaning that U, U transpose equals I, okay?
And this one in the middle here is a diagonal
matrix with the singular values on the axis.
(marker tapping)
So what I said is if your singular values
get small, close to zero,
then that's the case you have to worry about
because you're close to losing rank
and you might command big eigenvalues.
I'm sorry, you might command big velocities.
And that's exactly analogous to what I've said here,
that if the eigenvalue,
if the singular values go close to zero,
then that's the same as the eigenvalues
of A transpose A going to zero.
With the unitary matrices,
you have that A transpose A
is still just U singular values,
I'll just write squared.
(marker tapping)
So when the singular values go to zero,
which is a singular value I can understand
even for the six by seven matrix,
and that corresponds to the eigenvalues
of the square matrix going to zero,
which is exactly what makes this thing expand.
Yeah?
(student speaking)
Yeah.
So I think we're gonna make it explicit by the constraints.
So we're gonna say exactly what,
we're gonna write these optimizations
such that even if this becomes
the singular values go close to zero,
it will not violate our velocity limits.
So therefore that takes the relative,
you know, the sort of subjective part out of it.
(student speaking)
That make sense?
So when your Jacobian loses rank,
your quadratic function races off
and that's the optimal value of trying to,
if you just tried to minimize this,
it would be asking for X to become very large.
(student speaking)
You don't look as happy as you could.
Okay.
If it's helpful, I mean,
so the singular value decomposition
is actually all immediately accessible to us now.
If you wanted to derive the singular values,
we've basically done the right things.
So in particular,
if you wanted to find the minimum of a quadratic form,
even in the scalar case,
how do you do it, right?
So min over X, AX minus B squared,
the slightly more general way to do that
in the unconstrained case is to take the gradient of that,
of this thing,
(student speaking)
and I want to figure out,
the minimum is gonna be where the gradient equals zero.
Okay, so I'll take the gradient of this thing,
which I get,
2A squared X minus 2AB equals to zero.
If I have to find the place where that's equal to zero,
this tells me quickly that X star equals B over A
just by finding the X that makes that equal to zero.
Yeah.
(student speaking)
I'm about to do it in the matrix case.
And then that operator is gonna be a vector
or a matrix, yeah.
I could have written that with a simpler derivative
in the scalar case.
I will try to repeat the questions.
That was another feedback.
I know that, I normally do that, but yeah.
So he asked why use the partial derivative notation
in this example.
It's overkill in this example, but it will generalize.
Okay, and then in the min,
(student speaking)
X, AX minus B case,
it's the same machinery to find the minimum
of this quadratic bowl.
I'll just take the gradient of that middle term,
which is now the gradient with respect to a vector
of a scalar, which gives me a vector out.
And you have to get a little bit used
to the matrix math stuff, right?
So if you haven't done a lot of it,
there's a couple of things that make it easier.
But it turns out the gradient of this thing is also,
very analogous to this.
It's two X transpose A transpose A,
and then minus two B transpose A.
I set that equal to zero.
Since A is a square here, it's A transpose A,
I know that it's gonna be positive definite or zero.
So I know that my bowl's going up, it's not going down.
(students breathing)
And the solution to that,
I could also just take the transpose,
but the solution to that is, plus a transpose,
is that the optimal value is A transpose A inverse,
A transpose B.
And this thing here, there's various forms of it
and everything, but this thing here is basically
what you get when you call the pseudo inverse.
The reason that the pseudo inverse has magical properties
is because it's actually solving
that slightly richer specification, AX minus B.
So when there's zero solutions,
it finds the closest X star to minimize AX minus B.
X star to minimize AX minus B.
I said it minimized something in the least square sense,
this is exactly what it's doing.
When it has one solution,
then it will return that solution.
So it's as good as calling an inverse.
When it has infinite solutions,
then you're relying on the way you take the inverse
and you'll get,
the math will get you the closest to zero,
but we're gonna talk about that, we're gonna settle that.
(student speaking off mic)
That's true, so there's slightly more robust ways
to write this that handle the case even when this is zero.
Yeah, yeah, I just did the simplest version, but yeah.
(student speaking off mic)
I mean, in practice, we're gonna set up
the optimization problem so this never happens,
is the real, I think the answer for this class.
So we're gonna put, I think if you've left
your optimization landscape to have zeros in some direction,
then you haven't fully specified your problem.
So I'm gonna recommend that you look for those directions
and add some extra terms into them,
and there's an elegant way to do that.
Yes.
This one?
That one up there, yeah?
It's a transpose of it,
but they're the same since they're a scalar.
Good call, yeah, so the question was,
why did I write it there, why did I write it there?
I guess my brain is inconsistent, but those are equivalent.
It would have been more beautiful
if I had written it the same way two times.
Yeah.
Great, great questions.
So the natural thing that we're leading to here
is just like we could avoid things going to infinity
by adding constraints,
we can do the same thing now in the matrix case.
(pen scribbling)
So the more general version of this will be minimize over x.
Let's say, well, in this case,
I can do ax minus b squared,
subject to cx less than or equal to d, okay?
And let me just take a moment
to give you the language of optimization.
So these are my decision variables.
Trying to find x.
This is my objective.
These are my constraints here.
You can read this as subject to,
is the way I would typically spell it out.
Yeah.
(student speaking)
So, well, this is a vector.
This is element-wise inequality of a vector.
Yep, element-wise inequality of a vector.
Yep.
And I've pulled this out of a hat,
but I'm just saying there's a natural generalization
of that idea.
Certainly, if I wanted to write vector x,
every element of a vector x less than or equal to two,
I could do that with this form.
Okay.
And even, you know, if I were to write this out,
there's a slightly more generic way to write that.
If I were to say,
min over x, x transpose qx,
plus b transpose x, let's say,
plus c, that's just maybe slightly more general than this.
Okay.
So in this case, these are quadratic objectives.
And these are linear constraints.
So problems in that form,
where you have a quadratic objective
and a linear constraint,
that falls into the land of quadratic programming.
(tapping)
You'll hear me use,
everybody call it QP.
Okay.
QP, QP, yeah.
I was just about to say that, yeah.
So quadratic program,
the word quadratic programming is not limited to PSD,
but if, you know,
Q is symmetric and has real eigenvalues,
say lambda of QI is all greater than equal to zero,
positive semi-definite case,
then we call that a convex quadratic program.
Those are the ones we want.
The non-convex quadratic programs,
solving them can be NP-hard.
You know,
hard.
Yeah, okay.
And in general,
but the convex ones, we have very good solutions.
So that's all the bowls that are going up, good.
Bowls going down, bad.
Well, you know, bowls going up or down in some directions,
bad.
When they're all going up, great.
Because then the minimum is the, you know,
the place where the gradient obtains a minimum
is the solution.
If it's going down and you have constraints,
then you have to potentially check the intersection
of your upside down bowl with all of the constraints.
And since there can be exponential number
of those constraints,
that's where the hardness comes from.
So up is good.
Yeah.
That makes sense.
So we've just upgraded our class of problems
from just calling pseudo-inverse
to calling a quadratic program.
So we get to be able to,
you know, put guardrails on our Jacobian controller.
I should have said this earlier,
but I forgot, so I'll skip it.
Okay, so,
when I, if you look at like the Drake website,
there's kind of three things we say it does.
One of them is systems, modeling dynamical systems,
block diagrams, you know, being able to compose them,
do interesting operations on them.
Another one is specifically the physics engine.
We're really proud of the physics engine inside Drake,
which is just one of those systems,
the multi-body plant and scene graph,
but two of those systems.
Okay, but the other thing it does,
which is pretty unique,
is gives you a nice library
for solving optimization problems.
Okay, and the language looks something like this.
So you can just say, ask for a mathematical program.
So mathematical program and optimization problem
are almost synonymous.
I mean, if I had a problem that didn't have an objective,
and I said, find an X,
subject to some constraints,
I would call that a mathematical program.
I might not call it an optimization problem.
The mathematical program is a little bit bigger of a name,
but almost exactly the same as optimization, okay?
So you make your mathematical program.
You just say, I've got a new decision variable, X, right?
And then you can just start adding constraints.
Add constraints, you can type in,
in natural, numpy kind of form, your constraints.
This isn't the most,
this is using a symbolic engine to make it.
If you are trying to make things run super fast on a robot,
you might avoid the symbolic computations
and write it differently, but,
and then you just call solve,
and it gives you a result, okay?
There's actually lots of good tutorials.
This is just to pull one open here.
This is the QP tutorial right in Drake.
It's not in Course Notes, it's in Drake,
but you should know it's there.
And just to give you an example here,
that's another example, just new mathematical program.
I've got three decision variables,
started adding some quadratic costs,
and add a couple of different things, okay?
You run it, and for quadratic programs,
it basically instantly will find a solution
for pretty big problems.
And then I worked hard on this this summer,
so here you go.
So now you can render it in LaTeX.
That's cool, right?
Yeah?
Yeah, they should be polynomial time
in the size of the, I mean, in everything,
in all the relevant quantities, yeah.
(audience member speaking indistinctly)
Yep, so actually, so the question was,
why choose the L2 norm, and why maybe,
so the L1 norm would give a linear program
instead of a quadratic program,
which could solve even faster.
In fact, one of the, the last version I'll show you today
is a linear program, and it does solve a little faster,
but these are so easy problems
that it doesn't make a big difference.
Yeah, I think, mostly I was trying to connect back
to the pseudo-inverse, and I think this is a natural choice,
but it's not a uniquely good choice.
Good question.
Okay, so let's think about now,
just make the connection back to the Jacobians and the like.
So we have this new power of doing quadratic programs,
and it's okay to write a little system in Drake
that solves this basically on every time step.
That's okay, these things solve fast,
and we do it all the time.
So the question is, what's the right set of costs
and constraints to write?
So using our Jacobian syntax again,
if we're doing something like find me a velocity,
joint velocity, remember this is joint velocities,
okay, that minimizes the difference, let's say,
between the actual end effector, if I took that velocity,
versus the desired end effector,
if I took that velocity squared.
That's the analogy, yeah.
What is a quadratic?
I mean, I think I tried to define it,
so it's any mathematical program here
where the objective is a quadratic function
of the decision variables, and the costs are linear.
That's what defines the quadratic program.
And then again, the convex quadratic program
is if Q is positive definite, positive semi-definite.
Great question.
He says, so let me get to that part.
So the natural thing that we would do here
would be, for instance, V min, V max,
if these are like joint velocity limits, right?
This would be a more robust way to sort of solve that.
I'm gonna address your point very clearly in a second.
And first of all, I wanna point out,
even before I address that point,
I wanna point out that this is actually stronger
than if you were to, let's say, optimize this
and then just clip the values.
You might think, I'm just gonna find the minimum value
of this with pseudo-inverse,
and then if something was too big,
I'll just go element-wise and clip it, okay?
But that is not as good as solving this
subject to those constraints.
We could probably make a picture for that, right?
So let's say I have X1 in here, X2 in here.
So I'm saying these are my valid constraints.
So you're allowed to be sort of anywhere in here.
Those are the good places
that satisfy the velocity limits.
Then, let's see, what if your objective,
if this told you to do something like,
what do I have to do here?
Maybe something long like this.
Okay, so the minimum of the unconstrained problem
would be here.
But if I were to just solve the unconstrained problem
and then clip all the values,
I might end up kind of at this point.
But actually, the lowest,
if these are the contours of the cost function,
I could possibly do better by coming up here, yeah?
Did I say that well enough?
I could get lower on the quadratic bowl
than the one that would be just happened automatically
if I clipped after the fact.
So it's better to solve these simultaneously.
And that gets even more true
as I add more interesting constraints.
I hope I said that right, yeah, okay.
All right, so but let's just visualize now,
and I tried to make you understand the geometry of that.
So the geometry is overloaded,
but there's a geometry of the optimization problem also.
Okay, so let me show you the geometry,
just like I like to print the mathematical program
as a LaTeX, I also like to plot everything I can, okay?
All right, check this out.
So here we go.
And actually, just to remember what this is,
you remember this example here
where I was going in and out of singularities?
So what I did is I took the EWA, which has seven links,
and I just welded all but two of the links
so that the EWA is effectively this robot, okay?
And that's what you're seeing now in this visualization here.
There's, it's like the EWA is effectively
that kind of a robot, okay?
So that's just here for reference.
And then I took the objective, this objective,
and I just plotted the quadratic bowl, okay?
So the x-axis here is velocity one,
the y-axis is velocity two,
and the z-axis of the green thing is the objective.
And then I took and plotted the constraints in red.
That's actually when a constraint is violated, it's shaded.
I have a little, that's just a plotting bug.
Forget about that corner, okay?
They're just linear constraints, okay?
This is what the landscape looks like.
So it's interesting, yeah.
So in this picture, so what matters is
what's the bottom of the quadratic bowl, okay?
And so what it would mean would be,
if the command I sent, if I just solved this,
would be outside of those constraints,
it would be sending a velocity that is greater
or less than my joint limits, my joint velocity limits.
So what I wanna do is solve the optimization problem
subject to those constraints.
Okay.
Ooh, look at this.
So this is what happens as you go in and out of singularity.
That make sense?
It's going in and out of singularity
just like we did last time.
And what's happening is when the thing gets singular,
it goes flat.
And the minimum it obtains runs away to infinity.
And it actually flips sign when you go to the other side,
which would be bad too, right?
So you want to go negative infinity velocity
and then instantaneously positive infinity.
Not the kind of thing you wanna send to your motors, right?
This one still, as I've written it, is discontinuous.
It jumps from here to there,
but at least it's not sending massive velocities.
I'll just run it one more time
'cause I worked hard on that.
Okay.
You see this?
This is the minimum value that it was,
that's the solution to the quadratic program.
And it stops at the boundaries
because of the constraints.
Yeah.
- So what if I'm changing the value here
or is this a function?
- Okay, so if this is a function,
so I was plotting it as if it's a fixed value.
I'm just commanding a fixed value.
I see.
It could be that I could have changed it
as a function of that.
And in fact, I didn't do that.
I was just, I didn't do that.
That's great.
That would be a nice addition.
I could do that.
Thank you for pointing out that.
I didn't even think of doing that.
Yes.
- So what if I'm changing the value here
and I'm changing the value here?
Do you think that the value of the function
is going to be the same as the value of the function?
- That's a great question.
So he says if you're solving a lot of these problems
simultaneously, why do you want to solve them
from the, you know, every time as if you just woke up
and had a new problem?
Because the problem data is only changing a small amount.
So that would be, so you can do,
you can warm start your solution, that's what it's called.
You basically save the results of some computation
on the previous.
You would warm start your solver for the next time.
That's absolutely a good idea in this case.
But these problems are so fast that you don't have to.
Yeah.
(audience member speaking off mic)
You can put a lot of these things in
and we're gonna put a few of them in in a minute.
Yeah, so the question was like,
what about jamming into a table, force limits,
things like that.
How much can you put into the QP?
And there's limits and you take approximations,
but you can put a lot of things in there.
(audience member speaking off mic)
I just said VG desired to a constant for the visualization,
but I should make that function of time.
That would be better.
Okay, cool.
So,
let's do that now.
Let's see what other constraints could we add in here
that sort of work.
So, the first one you might think would be,
let's say position and acceleration constraints.
Those would be useful.
If you had joint limits you wanna satisfy,
and subject to that, how would you do joint limits?
I mean, meeting Q can only go to a certain amount.
I'll start a fresh board.
(coughs)
Because now I'm gonna have multiple velocities
flying around.
I'm gonna have my current velocity
and my proposed velocity.
So, let me rewrite it like this.
So, how about if I minimize over my next velocity?
So,
the velocity I want to achieve versus the one I'm in,
which I'll call V.
I wanna solve this subject to some desired squared,
same as before.
(tapping)
Velocity limits.
Then it's sort of,
the way we would typically do something like that,
is we would take sort of an Euler approximation.
So,
the N in the constraint.
Thank you.
Yeah, good call.
So, what I'm gonna say is if I know my current velocity,
then I'm gonna say that Q at N,
Q next is gonna be approximately equal to my current Q
plus some time constant times my VN.
This would be like a backwards Euler integration.
So,
call that a time step.
Could be a characteristic time constant of my manipulator,
but more often it's the sampling time I'm calling diff IK.
Okay, and then I can just write,
again,
linear constraints 'cause Q is data,
not a decision variable.
H is fixed,
and VN is a decision variable.
So, that's still a linear constraint,
and that allows you to obey joint limits.
And you could do more
if you wanted to do acceleration limits.
So, the time derivative of V is limited.
Then I could do something like VN minus V
divided by H
is in my acceleration limits, right?
So, this is joint position limits,
joint acceleration limits.
(marker tapping)
Now, you asked about force.
So, force limits can also be done
with the same basic approach,
but you have to use the manipulator equations.
You have to use the dynamics equations,
which again can become nice
or can be linearized to be nice
if Q is known and V is known instantaneously,
then you can figure out how tau,
the torque applied, can change as a linear constraint.
You can do that.
Yes.
That's what I was trying to draw here,
would be if you solved it without this
and then just projected back to the solution,
you might get a suboptimal thing,
which doesn't look so terrible maybe in that simple picture,
but it gets arbitrarily bad
in more complicated cost and constraints.
Yep, good question.
Okay, so that still works.
Another thing maybe you implied, Yishan,
was the collision constraint.
If you had a geometry constraint in the world
that was not necessarily involved,
like the distance between my end effector and...
So one example that you've seen at TRI, for instance,
is you've got a bimanual thing
and we're trying to tele-op them
and we don't want the hands to run into each other.
So in our differential inverse kinematics,
we put a collision avoidance constraint,
which takes the current.
If you look at the current Q,
you compute the distances between those bodies,
you linearize them to get the Jacobian,
and then you make this exact kind of approximation.
And you can put collision avoidance constraints
in this, if I case, which is pretty slick.
Yes.
Yes, we're gonna solve these at 100 hertz, for instance.
You don't have to solve it
maybe at the 10 kilohertz motor level,
but something like 100 hertz would be totally reasonable.
I mean, I think we end up solving them
higher than that, 500 hertz or something.
Yes.
So, yeah, so once I start thinking about putting this in,
this becomes Q measured, right?
So it's my current measurement of the robot.
In fact, actually, the EWO will filter
some of those positions for us,
so we actually get pretty clean signals off.
If I was building my own robot
and I had wires coming out of the motor
and I would have to write a filter
before I put it into this, you're right.
Otherwise, we would send,
or you could filter on the output,
but typically I would filter Q
and send a smooth version of Q in.
But that is true.
That's a concern that you would have to address.
So the EWO driver is sampling at a high rate
and filtering at a high rate
and then sending us relatively lower rate signals
over the network interface.
So that's probably a big reason why they're,
and they need the filtering for their controller too.
So that's why we get these nice filtered signals out.
Yeah.
(audience member speaking indistinctly)
So if you had an external force,
we'd have to decide exactly how you're gonna model that.
But typically that is only accessible to these controllers
if you free a joint torque.
So it would actually come in,
you would need some model of what this human is
and what the response needs to be.
But ultimately that would be very similar to a torque limit.
Yeah.
It would be mapped possibly through a Jacobian
to turn it from a torque back into a force at some point.
We're gonna go into a lot of those details
when we do control, like impedance control and the like later.
Yeah.
(audience member speaking indistinctly)
This is very much like an MPC with time step up one.
So this is better.
So MPC is model predictive control.
Sometimes we do, for control,
we do something that looks like this for many time steps.
The magic, so one is a magic number in the MPC sort of sense
because I know Q exactly for one.
But as soon as it's two,
then I would need to predict forward Q
and I would have a decision variable
that enters my non-linearity.
So these problems, many of these problems
are only linear in the one step case
and they're not linear or quadratic in this case,
in the many step case.
Yeah.
The one is really the magic number here.
(audience member speaking indistinctly)
Oh, I'm still gonna get to that.
I promise I haven't forgotten.
Yeah.
But let's make that point now though.
So one of the problems would be
if I worked really hard and I planned a path for my robot,
okay, and then suddenly I run up against joint limits,
this is gonna do its best effort,
but it won't necessarily have the same,
take the same path through space.
It might actually, if I hit a joint velocity limit
at like joint three,
then it could actually cause my hand
to deviate the desired path, right?
And that is something that we will try to remedy by the end.
(audience member speaking indistinctly)
Okay, so this is a pretty rich sort of language.
It's only good up to the linearizations,
but the big point is that
when you're doing the one step thing,
you're really making instantaneous decisions.
And even the ugly stuff that the world throws at you
is kind of simple.
You can linearize them in the one step case.
But really all we've talked about here is outer limits
sort of to protect us
if we were gonna send very large velocities.
But we also, like I said,
you kind of don't wanna leave the problem under specified.
If you have a zero,
if no objective in some direction,
it's kind of feels like you haven't done your homework.
Just pick.
If I have many ways I could solve the problem,
why don't you tell me how to solve the problem first, okay?
So there's a really beautiful thing that people do
about on the other side, which is redundancy.
So for infinite solutions.
So for instance, if I have a seven degree of freedom arm
and I have some goals here,
it might be that there's a manifold of possible joint angles
that could accomplish the same end effector.
That's kind of an easy thing to think about,
but hard thing to do.
I have at least seven degrees of freedom.
But it's actually also true in velocity space.
That same kinematic redundancy
manifests itself in velocity space.
There could be many velocities that I could command
that would all make the hand move in the same six
'cause I'm only commanding six variables
and I have seven velocities from which to decide it.
So really it seems like there should be
something else I can do.
And there's a beautiful idea from robotics,
from kinematic theory.
Task prioritization via the null space.
Okay, so basically,
the J, if it's six by seven,
then it has a null space.
So there's extra degrees of freedom
and the linear algebra setting tells us exactly
what those extra degrees of freedom are
that we haven't fully specified in our objective.
So that tells us exactly the place that we can work
with our extra solutions to add our preferences in.
And you should.
Don't let the solver pick for you.
So whenever J has a null space,
then you can put,
people would call it a secondary objective
in the null space of the primary objective.
That's why I call it task prioritization.
Okay, so for instance, if we call P
some orthonormal basis,
not the orthonormal basis,
a and orthonormal basis,
(keyboard clicking)
of the null space of J.
And there's a couple of ways you can do that.
I mean, modern linear algebra packages
typically just have that,
you just ask for the basis of a null space.
But typically in robotics papers,
we would have written,
we'd write something like the pseudo inverse form of that.
We'll give you a P.
Yeah.
(audience member speaking)
So far we're talking about the objective function,
the null space of the objective function, that's right.
In particular, I'm talking about the null space
of the Jacobian,
which has a very physical manifestation.
Okay, then if I originally had this problem,
problem,
I'm gonna forgo the Gs,
just not because I'm not a gripper,
but just because I wanna be a little consistent here,
but, and not write as much.
But I could put a secondary objective
by putting, by pre-multiplying
by this null space projection thing.
Okay, and maybe I have like J2 over here, okay?
Maybe, and V2 that I had,
I'll call it J2 on the bottom
so it doesn't look like squared.
This would be like a secondary objective.
So what this is saying is basically,
this, do anything you can to reduce this,
and then in the null space of that constraint,
in the place where, if there's any axes
where the coordinate system is flat,
then we're gonna add only in that dimension,
this extra objective.
Yeah.
Is it matrix?
Yeah, you're right, I shouldn't have written that.
What did I mean to write?
I guess I just wrote it like,
I was trying to make it too cute.
Good call, I wrote that wrong.
I was summarizing, and I wrote that bad.
This is the one I was gonna work towards here.
So, and I'll tell you what this means,
but we could have made it work in the other case too,
but you're right, I wrote that incorrectly.
So, so this would be saying I want V to be close
to somehow spring times some position.
This would be my standard joint centering constraint.
It wasn't supposed to write at the bottom of the board.
This one can't move.
This is a very common secondary objective, okay?
Which basically says, do everything I can to do this,
but then I'll pick some desired Q,
maybe my comfortable position of my arm,
and in the null space of that primary objective,
I want to be as close as possible
to the null space of that, to my desired position.
Does that make sense?
And actually, in bigger problems,
so an EWA has seven joint angles,
and typically you're commanding six things,
so you don't have a lot of room to play with.
But if you go to like a humanoid,
this becomes an extremely powerful toolbox.
So when we were working with Atlas, for instance,
we would do things like the primary objective
is to keep the center of mass in some regular,
you know, we command where the center of mass should be.
In the secondary objective, we'll say move the arm around.
You'll see Spot do this, for instance,
if you command the arm to go forward,
it'll lean backwards, right?
And that second arm has plenty of degrees of freedom
to work with to move the second arm,
and then maybe your left arm is in the null space of that,
right, and you can make an entire hierarchy of priorities
where each of these Ps becomes the null space
of all of the objectives that came before it.
Yeah.
(audience member speaking)
Yeah, yeah, so I went off my plan.
What do I want exactly?
(audience member speaking)
Yeah, I put the norm of that is the standard thing.
Yeah, good call.
Yes.
(audience member speaking)
Say it a little louder.
I would say that this represents the secondary task.
I want V to be close to some spring times
the difference in my position.
This secondary task, if I were to just add it in directly,
would interfere with the first task.
So what I do is I project that down
so that it's only everything that is outside
the null space of the primary task gets turned into zero.
So it's only in the directions that are completely flat
that I allow this thing to take a value,
and it takes enough of a, since this thing is,
this joint centering is typically
your last constraint always,
and it's just round in every direction.
So it will take any direction that's completely flat
and give you some objective.
Yeah.
(audience member speaking)
So I guess, so I would think that this is, again,
gets to the frailty of rank and null space, right?
Because in the singularity,
you're never gonna get to perfectly zero.
So I think this would typically not pick a,
I mean, you're gonna have some thresholds
in your eigenvalue library about where you say
your null space is, you know.
So, but I don't think you wanna use it in that space.
I think you probably wanna not go into the singularity.
That's a good question, though, yeah.
(audience member speaking)
That's exactly right.
This is the task, and then it projects it
down into the null space.
(audience member speaking)
Yeah, so I said it more quickly than I meant to,
but I think of this as, this is just a gain,
like a stiffness.
That's lower than I wanted to write.
Okay, but, so if I were to, if I had a physical spring
that was pulling me back towards a nominal joint position,
it would take that form.
So this is just a way to write an objective,
a lot like a proportional control
that would just drive me back in that direction.
Yeah.
(audience member speaking)
Yeah, we would typically, this would have units,
you're right, so it shouldn't just be stiffness,
it should be a stiffness, a scaled stiffness
with the units of the matched velocity.
There's a characteristic time constant in that.
(audience member speaking)
I should have written it carefully there, I hope.
I just called it a proportional gain.
I didn't call it a stiffness there, yeah.
Yes.
(audience member speaking)
That's a great question.
So what about having just a small constant here?
I think that gets into the game of cost function tuning.
It's kind of the game people play
in reinforcement learning these days.
So you start putting a lot of those costs in
and you start turning the knobs,
but I don't like playing those games.
I think it's way cleaner to put it in the null space.
In practice, so you'll see there actually is
a small constant in front of this,
but that's for a subtle reason,
which is because if I write this,
everything is perfect, everything is clean.
As soon as I started combining this with other constraints,
the constraints can actually interfere
with the null space logic.
So then you still put a small gain in front of there
in order to accomplish that.
But I still would prefer to do the clean projection
so that changing numbers here really doesn't interfere
with my primary objective.
Yes.
(audience member speaking)
Maybe I don't completely understand the question.
So let me say it my way and then if I don't answer you,
then not.
So imagine in two dimensions,
if my primary objective would look like a trough.
Is that kind of sort of clear?
If I had something that looked like this, okay.
Then what happens if I have my secondary objective,
this one is gonna be sort of full.
The joint centering is nice as a last objective
because it always looks like a bowl.
What this P projection is gonna do
is it's gonna say any direction
that has curvature here is gonna be zero.
So now it's gonna test my artistic abilities here,
but it's gonna somehow turn this into something
that's only adding content in that other direction.
By multiplying by P, it's gonna kill all the terms
that are in the direction that is curvature,
and it's gonna add curvature in the place
where there's no preference in the first objective.
That's the picture you should have.
And it gets more and more complicated in high dimensions.
But multiplying by P turns this into this.
Because P is a matrix that will zero elements
that are along the eigenvalues that have,
the eigenvectors that have non-zero eigenvalues.
So you have to, solving this is one way to get it,
but you have to find that matrix
which does exactly set those, make those values to zero.
But that matrix exists,
and there's good algorithms for finding it.
Yeah?
(audience member speaking)
Yep.
So I speak to that.
So this is, so because you can put constraints in,
it is possible when the constraints are active
that the null space could,
this secondary objective could interfere
with the first one.
It's kind of like, you hope that doesn't happen very much,
but it can happen.
So that's why we multiply this by a small number.
Now, I typically multiply it by 0.01,
and never touch it.
I don't wanna, I hate cost function tuning.
And the motivation for that is that
it really should only turn on
when you're in these active constraints,
and the active constraints have to be in such a way
that they're pushing against your orthonormal space.
So I kind of put that in as a protection.
(audience member speaking)
It's subtle.
So the question was, could I change k
so that the epsilon term was not possible?
You absolutely could, but it could be configuration
and constraint dependent.
So in order to sort of pick k once and fix it,
and then be able to mess with other things
without affecting that, this is the choice.
Yeah.
(audience member speaking)
We're gonna see some very similar things
when we start working with Jacobian transpose and torques,
and the like later.
This is effectively a PID controller at the last level.
So do everything smart, and then in the very last thing,
do a PID control.
This is P control.
(audience member speaking)
I'm sorry, say it again.
I see.
So IK has, so he said maybe we could do IK,
and then just a P controller.
Not that you can't do that, but you have to be,
you have to get your IK solution to be consistent
so that it never pops between multiple solutions of IK.
The differential form is always smooth and nice,
and thinks about your current configuration,
and looks for incremental changes.
That's what makes the differential IK more valuable.
Let me move on a little bit.
I got one more thing I wanna make sure I say,
and then I'll take as many questions as we have time for.
And I'll stick around after.
But I love the questions, I do.
Okay, so yeah, the last,
so partly 'cause I promised you like four times
that I was gonna answer this question.
So I kind of have to do that.
So the way we actually, the default diff IK in Drake,
when you call, so in the notebooks of this chapter,
you'll see we wrote a few pseudo-inverse controllers,
which have the simple form.
We have a few that implement some of the versions
we wrote on the board.
But then the last notebook just calls add diff IK,
which is Drake's, the one we use on all the robots,
version of diff IK.
And that has a slightly different form.
And I'll explain it to you.
So it's a linear program, it turns out.
So we say max, we're gonna choose V next, and alpha.
We're gonna maximize alpha, subject to JG V next,
equals alpha VG.
(keyboard clacking)
One, plus all of our additional constraints
that we talked about.
(keyboard clacking)
Okay, so let's just think about what's that doing.
First of all, I think you have to convince yourself,
so alpha you should think about as a velocity scaling.
So it's as if, so I want the commanded velocity
to be equal to a scaled version of the actual velocity
to be equal to a scaled version of the commanded velocity.
Okay, so translational velocity,
certainly you can make it smaller
by scaling it with a scalar.
Angular velocity, you should just check yourself.
Multiplying by a scalar, an angular velocity is okay too.
Remember the angular velocity vector has the interpretation
where the direction is the instantaneous axis of rotation
and the magnitude is the rate of rotation.
So scaling, multiply by a scalar
is just reducing the rate of rotation, okay?
So what this says is if I've commanded
an end effector velocity to go like this,
you must stay in the direction of that spatial velocity.
The end effector must move in that direction.
But you're allowed to slow down.
You can't speed up.
Alpha's gotta be between zero and one.
Can't go the opposite direction,
but you're allowed to slow down if necessary.
Now I said equality is too rigid.
I said that early on in the lecture, right?
You don't wanna put the equality
'cause you can't necessarily find it.
But in this case, alpha equals zero
and Vn equal to zero is always a valid solution.
Okay, so the worst case is if you get up against something
you can't do, it will stop, which is pretty reasonable.
Yeah?
So this has the nice property
that if you've done a really careful motion plan
for your hand or something like this,
you're trying to maybe slide along a table
or something like this,
your end effector command will be obeyed,
but it will slow down as necessary
to satisfy the constraint.
Now if you stop, you're stuck.
You have to somehow, it's not gonna get out
of singularities like that or anything like this.
You'll have to go back and make a new plan to get out.
Okay, but it's more common to see this thing
slowing down your command in order to not collide
or something like this.
Yeah, did you have a question?
You're good, okay.
Okay, good.
Satisfied?
All right.
Yes, yes.
(student speaking off mic)
Right, so in the case where I've got a trajectory of this,
which maybe came out of,
I made my piecewise pose,
I took my derivative of my piecewise pose,
I got a VGT,
then this is really going to only instantaneously follow.
The interesting thing is if you just blindly played
that velocity trajectory forward,
it could be that my velocity command changed.
The integral would be wrong,
but maybe I'll get to a point
where it's commanding a different velocity
and it would get out of singularity or something like this.
But this is not handling any of the higher level logic.
Maybe I didn't quite hear the meat of the question.
So I didn't do that for VG in the other program.
I did that for interpolating the joint velocities.
I could have done it for VG,
but the thing I wrote before was saying that VN was like V+,
or QN was like Q plus HVN.
I did all of the Euler interpolation stuff in joint space.
It's not that I couldn't have done something similar there,
but that's not what I did.
So this is a pretty solid implementation.
You won't break your robot.
You might not follow things perfectly.
You might get behind the additional logic,
but you can send these commands to the robot.
QP is solved beautifully fast
and they're pretty easy to write.
And you know what a quadratic program is.
This one, by important observation,
I guess this is actually,
there's not a quadratic objective.
This is a linear objective.
So this is actually a linear program,
which has even stronger solvers.
(marker tapping)
But these problems are so easy that it doesn't really matter.
Okay, good.
- Is that simulation you showed?