So task and motion planning is actually, well, let's see, it's a place that I think I would
like to grow the class. I'd like to maybe even move this up in the syllabus into some
of the more core material, because I think if you have this in your toolbox, then you
can program more and more complicated things. And the state machines that some of you have
been using will get you so far, but not to loading a dishwasher, for instance. It's also
a topic that there's some really good research being done on campus. So Leslie and Tomas
in CSAIL are leaders in this field. And Brian Williams also, who's an aero-astro in CSAIL,
does some really nice work on a version of this problem. So there's a lot of expertise
on campus if you get excited about these kind of topics. Okay, so let me try to set it up
relative to what we've talked about before. And then remember, the plan is for me to talk
for the first half, and then Boyan's going to talk for the second half. So I'll try to
not talk too long. So remember, I used this as the example to motivate task-level planning
before. When we were trying to load the dishwasher, this is, now that you've seen it and now you've
thought about it, think about writing a state machine that would think about all the possible
cases that this system might have to potentially be in. Maybe there's plates on top, maybe
there's mugs on top, maybe there's the dishwasher's open, maybe it's not. It would blow the stack.
You'd have an enormous state machine. And the way that the size of the state machine
tends to grow as the number of tasks accumulate and the number of possible transitions accumulate,
it can grow very, very badly. Okay? So in that project, we did not write a big state
machine. We didn't write a big behavior tree. We used planning. And just to remind you that
the way it looked back then was we defined task-level actions, right? And they were finite.
There was a list of things that we programmed with different skills or different actions
that would do things like open the dishwasher door, close the dishwasher door, start the
dishwasher. We even loaded a soap packet if we needed to. Okay? And each of those was
implemented in this sort of abstract class of an action primitive interface. Okay? Which
had just a few sort of reasonable is candidate, get outcomes. We'll talk about those again
in just a minute. Okay? What's interesting is to, so let's just think about is candidate
for a second. So asking, could I run this skill right now? Or more carefully, if I was
in this state, could I run this skill? That's potentially in a very advanced query of trying
to understand when it's suitable to be, you know, to try to open the dishwasher door could
involve solving intelligence or something. This is, but in this context, we have simplified
the problem down so that the state is actually a discrete finite state. Even though the problem
is very complicated, we, in that example, coded the state of the dishwasher as things
like the number of clean items we've already put away, the number of, there's a few things
that are more continuous value, but they were still sampled in a sort of slightly subtle
way. But mostly I want you to think about this at the high level, that those choices
were enumerated into a discrete set. And we could do search on this task level objective,
primarily with graph search, a more advanced form of graph search and incremental type
of graph search. But we roughly turned this into a big graph search problem in order to
decide what we were going to do next. Okay? You know, there was really enumerate, explicit
enumerations, enums of the different states that the system could be in. Okay? And that
is an instantiation of this bigger idea from AI planning. You know, STRIPS is the language
we mentioned very quickly before. It really is, it's a, you know, longstanding tradition
of how to write planning problems, planning descriptions, where you can list initial state,
all state, set of actions. For each action, you list the preconditions, you list the effects
of the action, and this defines a planning problem. And the, you see the action primitive
interface is candidate is exactly the preconditions that you would see from STRIPS. And get outcomes
exactly represents the effect set of this, of that action. And just defining that, where
the, if you can write the preconditions and the effects on a discrete state space, then
you're in the land of AI planning and things. We have very strong tools for that.
I mentioned quickly PDIDL before, the planning domain definition language, which you should
think of as an extension of the STRIPS vocabulary, where there's concepts of like, there's an
object oriented sort of concept in there. There's, so there's now then the notion of
object instances. It's a more expressive way to write big, discrete planning problems.
But it can, if you chose, the winning planners that use PDDL actually do not typically do
standard graph search anymore. But you could convert this into a very big graph search
and do graph search on it. The winning planners do much more heuristic search on a factorized,
considering the factorization in the problem.
And then if you have this high level planning power, then you can accommodate some of the,
so we've made it weak in the sense by having to discretize the world into a handful of
finite buckets. And that weakens our ability to describe all the things that could happen
in the world. But you can overcome some of that with feedback and online replanning.
So in the dish loading example, we would reevaluate our discrete symbol grounding of the world
every time we took an action. And if something changed, we could handle unexpected outcomes.
So that was the example I gave of that is that someone came and closed the dishwasher
door and it would realize that, realize its preconditions were no longer met, choose a
different path through the discrete search space to continue.
Okay, so let me transition to that in a second. So there are cases, so this was a case where
despite its complexity, we were able to get very far by doing things with discrete graph
search first, and then filling in the details with motion planning second. And then the
coupling between that, any gaps in the coupling between the discrete planning and the continuous
motion planning were overcome with feedback. But there are similar problems where that's
not good enough, especially if you have longer term consequences of your actions that you
really cannot decouple the motion planning from the task planning, hence the name of
the lecture.
So Kalen Garrett, a recent graduate from Leslie and Tomas's group, had a number of nice examples
that told that story. I'll use one of his here. I think he's talking, but here we go.
So imagine we just have a little suction gripper, and the problem was to move the red object,
the A, onto the red region. The B, let me do that again. Yeah, movable blocks, placeable
regions. If you think about the continuous values of that problem, there's a continuous
state that represents the location of the A block. There's continuous state that represents
the location of the B block, where they are in the world, where the gripper is in the
world. The only reason that you have to move the A block first, whatever, is because of
the continuous location. There was a block that was impeding my ability to solve the
simple version of the problem. I wanted to just pick up this block and put it in this
region. There was a different block that was in the way. Because of its continuous value,
I had to make a different set of, I had to order my discrete actions differently. Does
that make sense? The coupling between the discrete and the continuous exposed itself
that it really affected what your first action should be. So the planners, these stronger
task and motion planners, will solve that harder version of the problem, where they
jointly solve for the discrete path through the graph, and the continuous actions of the
manipulator, task and motion planning.
Here's another example that, let me talk through it again. So this is the PR2, the much-loved,
no longer with us, PR2 that Leslie and Tomas used to use constantly. The PR2 slowly went
out of existence. They bought every spare part on eBay possible, and it's not around
anymore. So this task is to pour the contents of the blue mug into, I forget if it's the
white or the red bowl, but basically pour that out. So you would think the simple strategy
would just be, okay, first I have to pick up the mug, then I take it over and pour it.
But because of the location of the green block at the initial time, and the kinematics of
the arm, it was impossible to pick up the blue cup from an orientation that would later
allow you to pour at an angle that would get it in. But these were the kinematics of the
robot, the joint limits, the size of its hand, were affecting the order in which you had
to execute things. You wouldn't have even needed to pick the green block if it wasn't
for the kinematic limits and the continuous variables.
So that's just another example here of, see the green blocks in the way. But the stronger
task and motion planning algorithms will solve that big version of the problem with a sample-based
planner. So I want to tell you just quickly a couple of the ideas from task and motion
planning and make sure I leave plenty of time for Bojan.
So there's a nice survey that Kalin and company wrote about integrated task and motion planning.
It's not that old. It's still quite very relevant. So I'd strongly recommend it if you want to
get a more encyclopedic coverage of this kind of material. But actually one of the things
that they do in that survey is they make a taxonomy of the different approaches that
people have taken to task and motion planning. So TAMP is what all the cool kids call task
and motion planning. And I think the choices they made about the X and Y axis of the little
grid are useful to understand.
So I'll give a couple examples that I hope tell the story clearly. But let's think about
sequence first versus satisfaction first. Roughly speaking, if I were to make choices
about all of the continuous variables in my search problem, then I can reduce the problem
back to a discrete graph search. And that would be sort of solve the continuous problems
first and then go to the discrete.
There's similarly, you could try to solve for a discrete path problem and then try to
fill in the details of your motion plan. Now of course, because of the task and motion
planning coupling, you can't just fix the high level sequence and then solve for the
continuous. But some of these strategies really dominate by thinking about first let's pick
a discrete set of actions, try to fill in the continuous thing. If I got a violation,
I was not able to find a solution on the continuous problem, then I'll go back and revise my discrete
plan. But in some of these problems, the discrete rules, people love their discrete planners,
they're very strong. Let's try to find a way to jam continuous reasoning into the discrete
planners.
Similarly, there's some people, and I would probably put myself in the second class maybe,
which is we love our continuous trajectory optimization, right? And we can find ways
to jam discrete stuff into our continuous trajectory optimization. And so those are
sort of the top and the bottom axes. And the interleaved are the people that are maybe
trying to do a little bit more of let's do a little bit of planning, incrementally build
my long term plan, and incrementally call my motion planner, and try to do a little
bit more explicit coupling.
So I thought I would pick two instances here that are two of my favorites here. So the
logic geometric programming is people like me that think about trajectory optimization
first and try to put some discrete planning into the trajectory optimization framework.
And then Padiddle Stream, which was Kalen's work, is a little bit-- it's interleaved,
but I would say it's still coming a little bit more from the sampling first and putting
motion planning into the sampler.
OK, let me tell you just a few things about logic geometric programming. First of all,
it's awesome. There's just very compelling examples. This one's from Danny. This was
actually follow on work that connected its perception and other things. But the basic
idea that a trajectory optimization is solving for these very multi-step processes that are
making long term decisions between multiple arms that need to coordinate in order to accomplish
a task.
Like that was put the yellow block on the red thing. Pretty similar to what we talked
about before, right? But where you had to move block A to get block B there. But these
are solving definitely multi-step handover kind of problems from a description which
is not imposing that the system must make a handover. That is discovered as part of
the sequences discovered along with the continuous motions.
OK, so I think I could tell you the gist of how that works because I've already told
you about kinematic trajectory optimization. So my toy version of kinematic trajectory
optimization didn't even have a robot. It just had a point that was going around the
red obstacle. And we wrote optimization problems which had a cost. In this case, it was just
the shortest path kind of cost. Even a weird one in the square.
OK, I started at the x start. My final thing was x goal. And that last one is just the
constraint that said for all n, I want to be outside the obstacle. And more generally,
I might write that as minimize x0 to xn. And it's important to realize I had to make a
choice on the number of steps I'm going to optimize over.
The sum over n. Maybe I've got some-- I'll use l for my loss function. And yeah, I'll
stick with x since that's on the board. But it could probably just be my joint angles,
for instance. Maybe it's xn plus 1 and xn. I wanted to have that. n equals 0 to n minus
1. Subject to-- generally, I might have constraints of the form like this, for instance. And then
I had my initial condition, my final condition, right?
What logic geometric programming is doing is solving a more complicated version of this,
which I would call hybrid kinematic trajectory optimization. There's many different names
for it. But if you've taken underactuated, you'll recognize hybrid trajectory optimization.
This is a longstanding thing from more dynamic systems, in hybrid systems. But this is a
kinematic version of that.
So in hybrid kinematic trajectory optimization, I'll do it in a step. Let's call this like--
I'll even call this action number 1. And then I'm going to have a second problem, which
is action number 2. And for action number 2, I'll similarly write out my new n decision
variables. Maybe it's even m decision variables. No need for them to be the same. And I'll
have a loss function that's l subject to g and subject to x0 equals something, xm equals
something, right?
Think about it making just a complete copy of this algorithm. But perhaps when I'm taking
action number 2, I'll have a slightly different set of constraints here. Maybe action number
1 represent move the arm without an object. And maybe action number 2 might be move the
arm with block A in the gripper.
So maybe if I know that block A is in the gripper, then I'll have a constraint here
saying, for instance, the q of my robot or my gripper equals the q of block A for all
of the steps m.
And then maybe I've got an action number 3. You get the point here. But I've got an action
number 3, which is move with block B. And I've got all the same things, but my g here
would say that the q of the robot has got to equal the location of block B, that block
B somehow moves with the robot.
So I could solve those. If I knew the sequence a priori, I could solve those one at a time.
I could say, I'm going to move block A. I'll run that first problem. And then I'll stop.
And I'll take whatever the situation is right now. I'll try to move block B. I'll solve
that second problem from the current initial condition.
But if you want to solve them jointly, if someone has told you already, given the sequence,
if I said, I want to do a sequence which would be, I'm going to move, let's say, action 0.
And then I'll do action 1. I'll move block A. And then I'll do action 0 again, because
I need to move my robot over to where the block B is. And then I'll do action 2.
If someone tells me what the sequence is going to be, then I could solve that whole problem
jointly as a single trajectory optimization problem, where I could just accumulate all
the costs into one big cost for all the problems.
And add extra constraints, saying that x0 from-- let's say xn from action 0 has to equal
x0 from action 1.
I'll use the constraints of the initial condition of this problem
to match the final condition of that problem.
I'll take the initial condition of this problem
And I'll just make constraints that link these two together.
Is that clear?
xn of action 1 has got to equal x0 of action 0 second time.
And the decision variables that I'm handing to my optimizer
now is a sequence of x's for this action, a sequence of x's at this action,
a sequence of x's for this action.
Each of those is a sequence of decision variables
that I'm handing the solver.
And then I've got a bunch of constraints, which
allow those optimization problems to couple each other,
so that the final condition of this matches the initial condition of that,
so on and so forth.
That's a much bigger optimization problem.
It's potentially harder for the solver to cope with,
but it fits still directly into the nonlinear optimization framework,
if someone gives me the action sequence.
And that's what you'd call a hybrid trajectory optimization,
a hybrid kinematic trajectory optimization problem.
And it turns out solvers can do pretty well with that.
You can add-- I just used making the initial and final state
match as the only requirement, but you could do more requirements.
Like for instance, if I'm going to pick up the object,
if I'm going to transition from moving the robot to picking up the object,
then probably the final state of this had better put the robot
where the object is, for instance.
You can put the necessary constraints that
couple those problems that were previously independent into one.
Now why is that better than solving them independently?
Because those continuous variables at the interface,
if I had to solve this a priori before I even started moving,
in order to solve this problem, I would have to make an arbitrary choice
at the initial location of that object.
I would have to lock in the continuous variables at each of these interfaces.
But here it's free to solve for a trajectory only under the constraint.
Not that it's at a particular goal, but just
at a goal that's good enough to start up this optimization that's
consistent with that second optimization.
So this is the optimization beginning of task and motion planning.
And those problems are well understood and good, again,
if that action sequence is given.
Not just you need to know the number of them,
because you need to know how many decision variables,
and you need to know the order of them.
The second thing you can do is then formulate-- now
this is the continuous optimization people sticking some discreteness in.
OK?
Let's do a search, a higher level search,
that tries to permute the different possible discrete sequences.
OK?
And for each of those, we'll solve the continuous optimization problem
underneath.
And if we're smart about it, we don't have to solve all of the possibilities.
We can use bounds on one solution to rule out
some of the permutations of this.
OK?
So we saw that a little bit when I talked about branch and bound
for-- I talked about it only quickly in the trajectory optimization.
But for those of you that know it, I just want to connect to that.
But there's a standard approach to mixing
some of these discrete and continuous optimizations.
It's very well understood and gives strong guarantees
when the subproblems are convex.
That is not the case, necessarily, in logic geometric programming.
Nevertheless, you can set up a strategy
where you solve a relaxed version of the problem at each time step.
And then you try to refine your solution in order
to search for this action sequence.
That's the discrete decision.
And at each level, you're solving continuous optimization problems.
So in my mind, what logic geometric programming does very well
is it does this branch-- it sets up this branch and bound over action
sequences.
It solves very efficiently the hybrid kinematic trajectory optimization
problem.
It does use non-convex solvers that are going
to have local minima and everything like that.
So there are no guarantees.
But in practice, there's a lot of impressive results.
And I think the thing-- my favorite part of the logic geometric
programming approach-- so when we have done, in my group,
mixed integer branch and bound type algorithms for, let's say,
footstep planning of a humanoid, I've been, I think,
a little stubborn about saying I want to take the problem instance
and I'm going to hand it to Garobi or some well understood solver.
And I want to come up with exactly the right problem instance
that I can hand to that-- there's a clear problem
instance of mixed integer convex.
I'm going to formulate that instance.
I'm going to hand it over.
Mark Toussaint and company, they didn't use Garobi.
They wrote their own solver on the end.
And they made every-- took every advantage of that.
Like anything you could do that would avoid
solving the big problem downstream, they would take those shortcuts.
So for instance, it might be that if action two required
solving a kinematic trajectory optimization problem that would say,
move my bag over to here, I could do an inverse kinematics query
and understand very quickly that I can't even
reach the bag after action zero.
And I don't even have to solve the kinematic trajectory optimization
problem.
So there's a lot of very clever heuristics
in there that leverage the kinematic problem in order
to prune more and more branches of those trees.
And I think that's what made it scale particularly well.
Questions about logic geometric programming?
This is, I think, one of Mark's favorites,
Mark Toussaint's favorite version of it,
where he picks up a stick and moves the box.
However, it's pretty slick.
There's also one I couldn't find quickly this morning
where it grabs a hockey stick and pulls something from far away.
That's a pretty good one, too.
Yes?
For the heuristics that prune the thing, how's that different from just hand-carving
the-- what was described earlier of just like--
OK.
So the question is, so I think there are general heuristics just based on geometry,
reachability of kinematics and stuff, which feel a little less bespoke
than saying, does the dishwasher open at a certain time or something like that.
But he still has to define the different actions.
And that is the analogy to deciding that there's a move the mug now.
The way that they decided, though, is by, in the subproblem,
writing a constraint saying that the pick up the mug action
means that the mug is welded to the hand for this part of that--
during that action.
So the encoding of semantics into the optimization
happens by the definition of each subproblem.
Yes?
I guess in this type of example, would there be one that like,
it's a [INAUDIBLE]
Let's see.
Probably go to the stick is one, move the stick is two.
And then probably the third one is when it's in contact,
I guess three.
If I had to guess.
And then maybe a move away is even four.
But small number.
Yeah.
I think these are solving impressive, but maybe not super long duration horizon planning
problems.
The sequences tend to be 10-ish steps or less, let's say, not hundreds or thousands.
The thing I worry about with these kind of methods is local minima.
So I think the branch and bound performance will eventually-- so you can make stronger
or less strong branch and bound type approaches.
But I would worry more about local minima in this.
OK.
Let me quickly talk about Pudittal stream.
Leave time for William.
So Pudittal stream is a different example.
So this is now coming more from the sampling-- or it's from the logical planning, symbolic
planning side of the world, and pushing down and bringing a few of the motion planning
ideas up into the sample-based planning.
And so integrating symbolic planners and black box samplers.
And don't tell Kalin.
But I'm going to talk about it in a pretty different way than I think Kalin would talk
about it.
So this is just an example of it doing cool things.
It's like put all the objects in the bowl that is most similar to its color.
These are advanced, long horizon tasks that they're able to solve with this.
But the way I want to think about it-- I hope it's OK-- I want to put it in my language,
which is the graph of convex sets language.
So if you remember, the graph of convex sets was this idea that you could take the standard
shortest path on a graph problem and expand its vocabulary by saying, every time you visit
a discrete set, you're allowed to pick one element from a continuous valued function.
And we tried to say that the set of those was convex.
So the shortest path problem, if you say I want to have a source here and a target here,
the shortest path might be choose this real value, continuous value, this continuous value,
this continuous value, this continuous value.
And in the case of a graph search, where we have convex regions, we've been working on
ways to make that solve with optimization.
Pudittal stream does not make any assumptions about the convexity of those sets.
It's solving a harder problem.
And it's doing it with sampling instead of with optimization.
And the reason I want to draw this is because this is how I think about the way Pudittal
stream works.
So one of the key observations in this kind of mixed continuous and discrete planning
is this.
So if you were to give me the path, if you were to tell me already I'm going to take
this path of sets, then the optimization problem is easy for us because it becomes a convex
optimization problem.
It's only the continuous values that have to be decided.
Similarly, if you were to choose the continuous values, the problem is easy.
It becomes a discrete graph search.
Either one of those is easy.
It's only when you put them together that it's hard.
What Pudittal stream is doing, in my mind-- so I have this picture of a graph here-- is
it's sampling.
So the streams in Pudittal stream are samplers, black box samplers.
You can think about it for any set here.
Every time I evaluate the stream, I pulled one more sample out of that potential set.
The samplers, the streams, the samplers that are used in Pudittal stream are inverse kinematics
queries or even a collision-free motion planning.
Like GCS, you could say that if I'm in this set, one point in this set might correspond
to an entire trajectory of a subproblem.
So what Pudittal stream does is it-- well, let's see the straw man version of what Pudittal
stream does, which Kalin uses as a straw man-- is that you could just pick a bunch of random
samples, evaluate your stream 100 times for each set, and then make your edges from all
of these points to all of these points.
And you have just a really big discrete graph search problem.
Similarly, for all the quadratic set of points here, I have to make all the edges here.
And you'd get a really big graph search problem.
But that would be a way to take your mixed discrete and continuous problem, sample, and
turn it into a big graph search.
And if you love the power of symbolic graph search, then that can get you far.
Now Pudittal stream is much smarter than that.
It doesn't do that as the-- you'd add potentially not only a lot of samples, but a lot of irrelevant
samples.
Because if the optimal path is up here, you're still making a bazillion edges down here.
So what Pudittal stream is doing is-- well, there's a handful of different strategies
in the Pudittal stream family, I guess.
But they interleave the symbolic planning with the continuous sampling.
So basically, think about like an A star type algorithm for graph search would expand only
a frontier of possible sets.
The high likelihood sets that have a likelihood of getting you to the goal with the path are
worth sampling more.
And so you add more samples.
Every time you add a new sample, you connect it up with its parents, whatever.
You do make the graph much bigger.
But you can do selective sampling in order to scale this to much harder problems.
And that's what Pudittal stream is doing.
So each sample, again, would be calling an entire collision-free motion planner, for
instance.
So it's doing like this.
But it's finding solutions to very, very hard problems.
That's it.
OK.
So-- oh, I have to say one more thing.
We will soon have GCS trying to solve TAMP problems.
That's a goal.
Sava's here.
This is-- think about the-- let's see.
Think about-- I changed this into a-- but the picture of the suction gripper picking
up block A, moving to block B. This is just a top-down view.
OK?
So this is the suction gripper here, the arm.
These are the boxes.
They have to move from here over to here.
That's a combinatorial plus continuous planning problem.
And what's interesting is the scale of it is there's lots of boxes and lots of possible
permutations, lots of possible paths.
And there's some initial success suggesting that keeping it in the graph of convex sets
kind of framework, we can maybe solve the global optimality in a few seconds.
So that's work that I hope we'll have a lot to say about soon.
OK.
Bojan, let's take over.
By the way, I appreciate everybody coming.
Tell your friends that next semester, Bojan will be presenting for five minutes, at a
random five minutes, during every lecture.
So you must come always to all the lectures to see him.
OK.
There you go.
Oh, yeah.
Good, good.
Don't pull.
There you go.
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the second half of the lecture.
First, I really appreciate that a lot of people showed up today.
So you actually should do a show up in every single lecture so you don't-- yeah.
So in this part of the lecture, we're going to talk about some recent progress in robotic
research that is doing planning with large language models.
And this is closely related to the advancement in natural language processing.
So we've just talked about task and emotion planning.
But in traditional task and emotion planning, what concerns these problems, like those Ross
just represented, they are more like some kind of puzzles that requires a lot of logic
and motion reasoning.
Well, in this part of the lecture, we are going to talk about what if we plan like humans?
What if we have priors about each discrete action, the description of the tasks?
How do we humans plan?
So here are some examples.
I spilled my drink.
Can you help?
If you spill your drink, how would you do it?
You will definitely find something to try to clean it up.
You might want to go to the kitchen to find some napkins, wipe and throw it to the recycle
can.
Yeah.
And also, so we all want future robots to help us in daily life.
And we should be able to communicate to robots.
And the robots should be able to complete the task we design.
For example, whenever we want to ask a robot to clean up the spilled Coke, the robot should,
if it's like a human, it should say, OK, I should generate this sequence of actions.
And I should try to accomplish them one by one.
So for example, you may want to-- if you've spilled Coke, you definitely put your Coke
can in your upright position and find some napkins and wipe the table and throw everything
away.
So it turns out we humans always love to use language as abstractions to specify tasks
and to specify plans.
And when you think about it, you actually-- when you do a complicated project, you also
communicate with your friends about all those kind of plans with language.
It turns out humans' activities on the internet produces a massive amount of knowledge in
the form of text.
And that could be really useful with the power of deep learning.
For example, on the right of the slide, you will see if I don't know how to make certain
dishes such as egg fried rice, I'll be able to Google online.
And they will tell me step-by-step instructions.
So before we dive into how we solve these problems, let's talk about large language
models.
So I'm sure a lot of people have heard of language models these days.
And many of you might have played with it.
So for those who don't know, I'm going to give you a short introduction.
What is a language model?
Language model is a task of predicting what word comes next, given a context.
For example, we have a sentence here that says, "The students opened their and asked
you to predict the next word."
And you will immediately have a list of candidates in your mind.
And if I give you a word, you may say it's likely or unlikely.
For example, if I say, "Apple here, opened their apple," you will see this is clearly
not very reasonable.
And you won't put "apple" there.
Instead, you might put "books" there.
Because you have an internal language model in your mind.
More formally, it is like, given a bunch of words we provided as a context, you will be
able to predict the next word, which is x t plus 1 here.
And this is called language modeling.
So you can also think of this as a system that designs a probability of a piece of text.
For example, let's say x 1 is my first word, x 2 is my second word.
And if you use all these conditional probabilities, you're able to chain them all together and
predict the joint probability of a piece of text that actually makes sense.
Like there is a probability here, x 1 to x t.
So how can we use this?
So the highlight here is that whenever you have an internal language model in your mind,
given some task-- not some task, but given a piece of text, you are able to predict what
is likely coming up next.
So first of all, if you have a fixed list of options, like what Russell said here, like
we just designed a piece of text describing action 1, 2, and 3.
For example, action 1 is move the arm without the object.
If you already have a fixed list of options, you can use a language model to evaluate its
likelihood.
For example, if my spilled my Coke and my available actions is like eat an apple, and
second option is like find some napkins, you'll obviously see that finding napkins is more
likely coming up next, given the context.
So a second way we can utilize this is that if we have all the vocabulary in English,
we can actually also sample with our likelihood model.
So as I showed here, with a trained language model, it will assign a probability to each
word in English dictionary.
And then you can sample from that distribution and generate options.
That is how text chatbots works.
And you actually are already using language models every single day.
For example, when you type, Google knows to suggest you something, because it already
has a language model that, based on people's history, can predict what's likely coming
up next.
And when you use Google to search, when you type something, it also suggests a bunch of
possible options.
Then, OK, now everybody knows what a language model is.
Then we are going to dive into large language model.
So we've already seen a lot of neural networks these days.
And many of them we've presented in this lecture are millions of-- let's say a million, five
million parameters that are already considered large.
But this really, really large language models of 540 billion parameters, and you can't use
your tiny GPU to even inference on these models.
So why do we have these huge language models?
It is because if we train them on the entire internet, we can incorporate a lot of human
knowledge into them and use them to do interesting things.
So for example, you can use large language models to write essays for you.
For example, I once wrote a blog about computer science schools ranked by BOBAs.
And I actually used a GPT-3 to help me writing it, because my English is bad.
And this is one example of how to use it.
So you just type in best computer science schools ranked by BOBA, home blog, and write
the first sentence.
It generates things for you.
And it knows that Berkeley has 20 BOBA show-offs in front of it.
You can also use it to complete your homework.
For example, I took this essay--
[LAUGHTER]
I took this essay prompt from one MIT class that is Minds and Machines.
And given the prompt, it somehow knows to write something reasonable about that.
And I highly suggest everyone to try that.
[LAUGHTER]
And with this, language models can actually also do question and answering really well.
This is a really recent work from OpenEye that's using chat GPT.
So you can ask it all kinds of questions.
And it can answer really well for you.
So before the age of deep learning, these question-answer models aren't that good.
As we dive into the age of getting to the age of really, really big language models,
they're getting better and better.
It can answer really all kinds of questions.
And it actually can relate to previous context as well and can give you a really realistic
experience just like you are speaking with some humans.
This is-- turns out large language models are really powerful planning.
For example, in the most naive way to use this, you can ask it just for a plan of how
can I do something.
So give me a list of items I will need to make a cup of coffee.
And it will show you something.
For example, give me detailed robotic instructions to make a cup of coffee in the kitchen.
It will give you a bunch of instructions.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- Detailed robotic instructions matter?
[END PLAYBACK]
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah, I still converse like a human.
And I will talk about this problem later on.
So these large language models are really powerful.
And we really hope to use them for robotics.
So however, when I try to use them, it's actually very hard.
Because whenever you ask it to, I spilled my drink.
Can you help?
GPT will tell you you cannot-- you could try using a vacuum cleaner.
Well, OK.
And one funny fact is that when I was doing research as undergrad, one of my friends was
playing with large language models in his project.
He asked the language model, give me instructions to get a cup of-- give me a cup of coffee.
And the language model tells him to go to a cafe.
So we need to have more control about what we can get from the large language models
to allow us to do actual robotic tasks.
And one core challenge is that our robots can only do a fixed number of commands and
need a problem broken down in actionable steps.
So actionable is critical here.
This is not what large language models usually output.
For example, in this task, we have action 1, 2, 3.
And there are different skills, but it's just three actions.
We don't want large language models to arbitrate things.
We want it to choose.
So we need large language models to speak robotic languages.
So solution 1-- so we can propose that we can just bind each executable skill to some
text options, for example, whereas what we already have here is we have all three actions,
and we wrote a description about that.
And if these skills are actually real-life skills, you can expect the language models
to give a reasonable guess about how to generate a sequence of actions like what we did here.
This is doing the classification, so it's also easier.
We have more control.
So basically, as we see, language models can predict the probability of the upcoming task.
So what you do is you give it instruction, and you can evaluate the likelihood, the log
likelihood, log probability of each option coming up next in the form of text.
So this is exactly what a lot of people tried before.
So let's say we have a bunch of available options on the right that we can actually
use a robot to execute.
Let's say we already coded a skill.
We can use large language models to complete this, just like how we did in an essay, for
example.
We can put an example on the table and prompt it to say, I would want-- and it will be able
to predict the likelihood score for each option.
There is a second solution.
That is, we can also prompt the large language model to output in a more structured way,
so not just random, actuarized instructions that are long paragraphs.
And then we pass the more structured output, because as soon as they are more structured,
it's easier for us to pass.
So then there's come to this important skill called few-shot prompting of large language
models.
So what is few-shot prompting?
As we just said, large language models can just finish an essay and try to predict the
upcoming text in the most likely way.
So what if I engineer my context before in a structured way?
For example, here I type the United States, and I type this arrow that maps it to Washington,
DC, the capital.
And then one type of food the country is famous for, and the tallest-- the highest mountain
in this country.
So I gave it three examples-- United States, China, and Japan.
And I prompted it to complete the essay for France.
And you will see it actually outputted the capital, the food, and the tallest mountain
in that country.
So that is one of the-- so the highlight here is that large language models can just, given
a context, we can-- if the context is in a structured way, it can copy the logic and
extrapolate to what we are querying next.
So this is called few-shot prompting.
So how can we prompt large language models to do structure planning?
So one immediate way to do this is I give it a few examples of a structure plan here.
And then I give it new instruction.
So I ask a GPT-3 here to generate a plan for bring me a banana from banana lounge.
And it turns out, OK, it doesn't have knowledge about banana lounge, but somehow it gives
a reasonable plan.
We will be able to play GPT-3 for planning at the end of the lecture if we have time.
You'll be able to try all kinds of tasks.
OK, so given this, so we already know-- now we know what large language model is and how
can we use for task planning.
Then it remains to combine this kind of new capability and connect them to-- make them
actually executable in real life.
So the first paper I'm going to mention is a do-as-I-can, not as-I-say paper.
It is from Google Robotics and Everyday Robots.
And so now we know large language models can do planning for robotics.
The problem is that large language models are not grounded in real world.
They don't know what's actually possible from a state with a given embodiment.
So let's say I already have a bunch of skills.
Let's say I train everything either with learning or I have a motion planning algorithm that
can give me a plan, like given current observation.
We have a bunch of skills, each tied to a language description that we can classify
from with the thing we mentioned before.
So now we have this problem that large language models aren't actually grounded in real world.
Maybe my language model will say, I would like to find-- I spilled my Coke.
And obviously, there are a lot of options available.
For example, I can either find some napkins, or maybe I need to first go to somewhere else
to find napkins.
Or I can also, instead of finding napkins, maybe--
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
And maybe you have multiple options that leads to the success or completion of the task.
However, what's immediately in front of you may not be valid with respect to every single
option.
For example, let's say you want to find some-- you can pick up napkins directly, but there
is no napkin in front of you.
Then you shouldn't execute this task at all.
Instead, you should go to find some napkins, maybe in the kitchen.
So your plan should also be grounded from current state.
And when we talk about grounded from current state, it's helpful to mention a concept called
affordance.
So what is affordance?
It is saying that with respect to a certain task we desire, how likely it is for me to--
or in terms of cost, how costly it is, how likely it is for me to accomplish it from
my current state, and so on.
So for example, we've all learned a little bit of our reinforcement learning.
And we know that what a value function is.
Whenever a current state is likely to lead to a higher expected return from the future
when a state is more likely to lead to a successful completion of the task, we say a current state
is of higher value.
And in this paper, they used the reinforcement learning in combination with large language
models.
They first trained reinforcement learning from pixels.
Then with the value function from the reinforcement learning algorithm, we can actually calculate
if the skill is actually somewhat executable or likely to lead to success from a current
observation that is directly from pixels.
And so RL provides kind of task-based affordance.
And they're encoded in the value function.
So what we can do is now we have a list of options.
And our language model gives us a prior probability based on the previous context.
For example, my task, the description of my task, and then what I've already planned before.
And then we can also calculate another probability from our current affordance from the value
function of the reinforcement learning algorithm.
For example, we can do multiple things at a time.
For example, how would you put an apple on the table?
Obviously, for a language model, it seems that find an apple and pick up the apple are
both valid options.
They are both likely coming up given the context of this task.
But if I don't have an apple immediately in front of me in my field of view, it will realize
I cannot directly pick up an apple at a certain position.
So if we ground position making by both language models and value functions, we will be able
to get a more reasonable guess.
For example, if I don't have an apple in front of me, I will prioritize finding apple first
instead of picking up an apple directly.
Is it hard to learn a value function in the space of words with the basis function being
the language model?
Basis?
Oh, you mean like state based on?
Yeah, yeah.
How do you-- I mean, learning a value function that works for apples and goats and all these
things seems really hard.
Oh, yeah.
So actually, I think one thing I don't really like about-- like, I won't say one thing I
won't really like.
I think it's one limitation of what the vanilla approach in this paper is that they train
the separate-- they actually train it with imitation learning for many of the skills.
And they train one imitation learning policy for every single object.
That is, they need some humans to collect the data for multiple days for your water
bottles and for another water bottle, we'll hire another guy to collect it for another
day, something like that.
But I think one hope people are-- one thing that people think they have hopefully solved
in the next few years is that instead of doing this kind of thing, we just have one huge
value function model that can take in a current image observation and a piece of text embedding
and output things.
But the problem is that turns out all this kind of skill learning are in domains where
data is extremely expensive.
You either hire humans to do it, or you're training simulators, like, store for many,
many days to get this kind of thing.
So yes, it is currently a big challenge right now.
But I think people propose a solution.
It is just the data is not there yet.
OK.
[INAUDIBLE]
So usually value functions is just conditional observation, or someone says state.
So it is like they actually have one value function, like the function itself, for each
of the skills, options.
And then for each of the skills, you look into its value function, and you evaluate
it by evaluating at the current observation.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
So in this setup, you need 50 value functions, although I said in the future, you may just
have one that also can take on text.
Yeah.
Any other questions?
Good.
Everyone is with me.
And then, so let's see how does this work.
So in this slide, the authors are asking you to accomplish some really long, hard, and
tasks that involves, like, nine steps here.
And it says, I threw my Coke on the table.
How would you throw it away and bring me something to help clean?
This looks weird, but it's kind of deliberate to confuse the robot.
And the robot just kind of sees accordingly.
You'll be able to see that at the very beginning, it finds that finding the Coke can is very
likely at the first step.
And it's also executable because it's navigation, so it just chose that task.
And then-- oh, by the way, if you didn't see, the blue bar indicates the likelihood score
from language, and the red bar indicates the likelihood score from affordance.
So you will see that-- so let's go to the fourth picture.
If you look at that, you will realize that the affordance for dumb is actually extremely--
the affordance for everything else is extremely high.
No, sorry.
I picked the wrong one.
Let's look at number five.
That model might suggest that actually immediate finish, but my affordance would suggest that
many other options are really available for me to accomplish.
And these two things together grant an entire plan for this low-horizon planning task.
But do you have to predict the future observations then?
No.
>> How can you plan for the fifth one if you don't know what the image is at time zero?
>> If it doesn't know the images at time zero, I think-- so I think one assumption that this
type of work often assumes is that your language model is reasonable enough, that your plan
generated by language model is already reasonable.
And then what the language model sees is that at the time step five, it will see human instructions
and robot.
I would find a cocaine, pick up the cocaine on to step four.
And so it sees a history of task plans like before, but not observations.
So this somewhat requires the language model to be good.
If the language model is not good enough, you cannot trust it.
>> So I guess at the same time, are you saying that [INAUDIBLE]
>> Yeah, currently this is set up in this paper, although there are future works that
improves upon this.
So nobody asked about this, but another thing people might ask is that how does it incorporate
feedback in the scene for a stronger way.
So it is like, for example, if I found certain tasks to be invisible, how can I adjust my
plan accordingly?
So this requires a feedback step from the environment that requires more information
than just affordance.
For example, let's say I try to open my door with my key.
I saw my key is in my pocket, but it turns out it's not.
So in my mind, I kind of know I need to adjust my plan accordingly and replant.
So actually some follow-up works of this have proposed that we can do it, like we can prompt
a large language model to do some interesting inner monologue.
That is like, they have a success detector that detects certain expected events actually
didn't happen.
For example, the fact that my key is in my pocket is not there.
Then it will just insert one line in the prompt here saying that, oh, I found something.
It's not actually there.
And then a large language model kind of incorporates that feedback and adjusts its plan in the
future accordingly.
So that is the magic of prompting large language model.
Another interesting thing that people always do is that language models are very tricky
and they are really naughty.
And to make them actually plan good things, sometimes you need to give them some good
incentives.
For example, here I just say, let's say we are trying to accomplish a really, really
long horizontal scale.
If you directly ask a robot to give it an instruction, it will avoid giving you a really
good sequence of actions.
Instead, what you do is you insert something like a chain of thought.
You say, now, after, like humans, I fill my code, after this instruction, I write this
sentence.
Let's think step by step.
And then generate a plan, and you will find the quality of the plan significantly improves.
Another thing is that you can have chain of thought, which is saying that instead of saying,
let's think step by step, I give a few demos saying that, OK, someone spilled their code.
I need to find something to wipe the table and finally throw everything away.
So if you give it a few examples of this and now give it a new instruction, it will actually
learn to follow the structure and generate a chain of thought, a new chain of thought
for the new task.
And it actually also helps it generate a plan better.
So it is really naughty, and you need to find-- there are a thousand tricks how to prompt
it to generate nice things.
Is it used in this case?
I think I--
Yeah.
In the latest version of the SACAM paper, they added chain of thought where I added
line of reasoning to help language models do better.
But I think this can be a non-generating instruction, and it's better to fix the problem
of spilling.
Yeah.
Oh, no.
It is-- oh, sorry.
Sorry.
I misinterpreted your question.
So the point I'm making here is that if we want to add a chain of thought prompting to
this, this is orthogonal to whether we are doing generative planning or classification-based
planning.
So if you look at this-- so when it came out, it actually really impressed me, because this
make a future of-- future with home robots more likely.
Because they-- sorry.
I spilled the drink.
Can you help with that?
Large language models may hold the key to unlocking such tasks.
SACAM, when tasks--
We're not going to watch the entirety.
--followed by picking up the Coke.
Or just look at--
I spilled my Coke on the table.
How would you throw it away and bring me something to clean it up?
The robot considers different skills that are available to it and selects the best one
according to the SACAM process described above.
It uses the affordance model as well as the language model to score the available options.
The algorithm starts by finding a Coke can, which is then followed by picking up the Coke
can.
Once the robot accomplishes that part of the instruction, the skill is appended to the
prompt, and the method continues with the next set of skills.
On the right, you can see different skills being considered and their scores by the language
model, the affordance model, and the combination of the two.
Each skill, once it's chosen and executed, gets appended to the prompt, which then allows
the model to generate the next part of the solution.
In this case, the robot ends by finding a sponge, picking it up, and then in the seventh
step of this extended plan, it brings it to the table and puts it down.
Since the robot doesn't have the wipe table skill in its repertoire, it finishes the task
at this point with a termination.
Next, we show two other un-narrated examples of tasks that Seikan is able to accomplish.
Because now the large language models are able to parse really, really complex human
instructions.
You can see examples here, like you give the instruction, like, "I just worked out.
Can you bring me a drink and snack to recover?"
So you can input with our human language.
We are not going to watch the entire video.
Let's just assume this is finished successfully.
So as you just saw, because we want to emphasize the capability of large language models for
planning this paper, we have to have a bunch of skills associated with each executable
option.
And that is one of the hardest parts that I hope we will solve in the next decade.
And then I think we can dive into my paper.
It's also with Robotics at Google and Everyday Robotics when I was interning.
So we've just saw Seikan.
It is amazing.
But Seikan didn't tell you that you hard-coded all object locations.
If you move the object a little bit, it doesn't work anymore.
And it assumes that all the objects are available in the thing.
If you remove something, it will not be able to find the alternative thing.
Also, it has no perception.
You have to let it know where objects are and what objects are available.
And by the way, it only can deal with around 30 objects.
So this is quite limiting.
And also, because of this, you have no perception.
And you have a finite list of executable options.
So in this project, I'm trying to significantly expand the capability of Seikan.
So previously, as I mentioned, Seikan has no perception system.
So it is not grounded with what's in the thing and where they are.
So in this project, what we do is we can just let the robot navigate the thing, look around,
take a lot of pictures.
And then with the open vocabulary detector, that is, whenever it sees a new image, let's
say it saw this bag, this table, it will do this kind of class agnostic regional proposals,
like crop these bags and the table out, and store their locations, three locations.
And we do multi-fusion such that we build a single presentation of this entire scene.
And then whenever the human asks it about certain object-- for example, I want a bag--
and then it will query this single presentation using the visual language models and find
its correct location, and also tells me whether it is actually in the scene or not.
So for example, here, it just proposed a bunch of objects in the object section at Google.
There is this Coke can, this cheap bag, some trash cans, and the yellow sign there.
You can actually query with it all kinds of nature language input object names.
You can query the plant, like potted plant, green plant, it's all fine.
And it will be able to find that object.
So this is open vocabulary detection.
This is a valid paper.
So basically, if you know visual language models, basically, this clip model can give
you a likelihood score between text and image describing-- the score describes how closely
does the text describe the image.
And then we build on that.
This paper proposes open vocabulary detection, where I combine object proposal, and we can
query everything with text.
For example, for the crocodile there, we can query it with toy, green toy, or toy crocodile.
And it will be able to estimate the likelihood score for that.
So how can we ground planning with scene?
So now the robot has been navigating the scene, and I give an instruction called recycle the
Coke can.
So what it would actually do, just like humans, I would immediately have a list of items in
my mind that I should plan with.
So somewhat like an established planning domain, I propose this object.
This actually might-- this skill might need a Coke can and a recycle bin.
And then, because I already built this open vocabulary context, I'm able to find this
location of the Coke can and recycle bin in the scene, and how can I approach them?
And then, because I have this object-- I have these objects, we can generate executable
options.
For example, let's say you-- let's say you-- the most naive way to do this is with templates.
That is, for every object, I generate options that is go to something, pick up something,
put down something.
But you can actually also generate it with large language models as well, if you have
the skill to execute them.
So this is really powerful.
For example, I tried before with large language models.
If you just give it a few demos like we did with the country and the food and mountains
before, you can let large language models to generate possible options.
For example, for knife, you can generate peel, cart, and different type of options.
So it can get more powerful.
Then given all these options, we can do scene-aware context-aware planning.
That is, what's available in the scene, what is not.
And then I can do this kind of planning.
Sure.
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, like available objects?
Yes, actually, also done with large language models.
I give it a few examples of instruction followed by a list of objects involved, instruction
of a list of objects involved, and I can propose it really reliably.
For example, we will be able to play with this at the end of the class, I think.
So it is like, for example, I just give it-- I don't know, like throw the Coke can in the
bin.
It's like Coke can, bin.
And then when it actually-- it's really, really powerful, because when I test it with really
weird, wild task for a robot, for example, fillet a fish, it actually proposed cutting
board, a knife, and a fish.
So it's all about large language-- prompting large language models here.
Every single step can be done with large language models here, except actually executing this
is why we still need to carefully-- we need to start in this class really hard, because
it is unsolved.
It's really hard.
Then compared to Seiken-- so above, it is Seiken, where I use language models and value
functions to find the most likely action among a fixed set of candidates.
So what we can do here is that we can actually propose executable options in the framework,
and we can also use affordance as before and try to find the most plausible action among
the candidates we generated.
So although the skills we have is still limited, in this case, we are able to expand the comparability
from a finite set of skills to infinite, because now we can navigate to arbitrary objects.
Previously, everything had to be card coded.
Now, like in the Google Kitchen, I'm able to ask you to go to-- I ask you to find Band-Aids
for me.
I heard myself find some Band-Aids or find some medicine for me.
It will propose I should go to the first aid station and then navigate there.
There is options that are previously not available in the original Seiken paper, and we are doing
that here.
And you will be able to see the-- Sorry, I should-- So this is-- So this is the-- So
this is-- So this is one task that's not achievable by Seiken before, because it just doesn't
have a lot of-- doesn't have this concept of a brown-- a woven basket in mind, because
it's not in their hard-coded list.
And here, I'm showing that with my new framework, it is able to achieve this task that's unachievable
before.
>> Brown multigrain chips in the woven basket.
The robot proposes two objects, woven basket and brown multigrain chips, to look up in
the same representation.
As visualized in the map at the bottom right, both objects are found and localized.
The robot then plans and does a task by combining large language model and affordances as visualized
on the top right corner.
To wash an apple, the robot proposes three objects, apple, tab, and sink.
Training a policy to wash items is beyond the scope of the project, so a simpler pick-and-place
version of the task is demonstrated here.
The robot correctly picks up the apple and puts it in the sink.
If we are unconstrained by available manipulation policies, we can lift the constraint on large
language models, and then it will output steps like turn on the tab as next action.
>> And the last one is also water the potted plant.
So all these tasks are previously unachievable by Seiken, because they have to have a finite
list of objects, while we don't.
So although this is really powerful, you know that we always need to bind available executable
actions to our language options.
And that is one of the hardest challenges now, and I think it's an exciting area of
research.
Once we can solve that problem, combined with this, we can actually have real everyday robots.
And then there is one last paper, which I'm going to go through very shortly.
Basically, with really powerful language models, you are able to synthesize programs, and you
can execute them as programs.
But I think we are running out of time, and I hope to show everyone some interactive demos.
For example, this is my chat GPT demo.
This is a conversation model.
So right here, I'm giving you a step-by-step instruction to make Beijing Kouya.
It's like deliberately confusing it by mixing two languages.
And it kind of gives me this instruction.
And you can ask a crazy thing.
Someone even built a virtual machine inside it, because you can CD into something and
can generate what's inside the directory, your home directory.
You do conversation with it, like make directory, and it will output what's in the directory
is your newly created folder in it.
It's really crazy.
You should play with it.
It's free.
And then this is not free.
I paid a little bit for it.
So this is GPT-3.
So here is what we actually used in the second paper in my follow-up.
So basically, I give it a bunch of demonstrations.
These are the few short examples.
And before the class, I just tried bring me a banana from the banana launch.
And it's kind of generated the things.
Although in the actual paper, we use a much bigger, even bigger language model compared
to GPT-3 here.
And in the context, I give 10 demonstrations that have a great variety.
Here it's just pick and place.
I think it's still really powerful.
So what about-- let's try something.
Let some students suggest something.
Who wants to suggest a task for you to play?
[INAUDIBLE]
Folder laundry?
I see.
Is this a correct way to spell laundry?
OK.
[LAUGHTER]
Well, at least it says fold.
But like in-- yeah.
I got the results on that.
On charge GPT.
OK.
So I'm going-- yeah.
I asked for step-by-step.
Yeah.
You kind of need to-- it's naughty.
And then you're prompted to--
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah.
This is just the most naive demo.
But with more templates, you'll be able to-- if you give it more diverse demos, it will
also be able to generate more diverse things as well.
For example, here you already know that I need to use action fold.
OK.
Let's try something else.
You can also type things like-- I don't know.
Let's try this.
I'm thirsty.
Help me out.
Ah.
How about solve a Rubik's Cube?
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah.
I'll probably ask you to find someone who knows how to solve Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try this.
I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
It's not bad.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
If you coded this kind of skills with the trajectory planning algorithm, maybe I will be able to
solve it.
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah.
Also, feel free to play with chat GPT.
You can find all kinds of crazy stuff.
What do you want to ask?
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Exactly.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So I'm going to try to solve a Rubik's Cube.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
So why is that I can-- instead of using doc, I can use my code.
And the chat GPT actually gave him a bunch of answers, saying that because the code,
it has first, and it's a valid alternative to doc to make this dish.
[LAUGHTER]
So you can actually, yeah, scan it.
Awesome.
Yeah, feel free to--
[APPLAUSE]
People can come up and play, I guess.
Yeah.