It'll be due in another week from Friday.
If you have questions about your projects,
whether you should run things on DeepNote
or on your local machine, if you have trouble installing stuff,
just ask.
Consider, by the way, asking-- if you're asking questions
about Drake, you can ask them, of course, on Piazza.
We'll try to answer them.
I love it when people ask them on Stack Overflow,
because then we get questions that--
it kind of builds up the answer base in general,
so we don't answer the same.
There's like a wealth of answers on Piazza
that are locked away from previous years.
If only those had been on Stack Overflow,
then the question would already be answered.
And consider checking Stack Overflow.
The question might already be answered.
OK, so today we're going to start
talking about motion planning.
I think we've already motivated it fairly well.
I'll remind you that one particular motivation was
we built this clutter clearing example where
it took the YCB objects from one bin,
dropped them off in another bin, and I got it
to some moderate level of robustness,
like it would run all night long and wouldn't crash.
But there were some pain points.
There were some failure modes in that.
And the biggest one, I would say,
the one that was most painful to watch for me
was that it would occasionally do a couple very
bad things with the simple version of planning
we did, which was just sort of straight interpolation
of the end effectors.
Occasionally, it would smack into the cameras.
Admittedly, I did put the cameras, like,
right in the middle of the workspace
to try to make the point clouds good,
but it would occasionally smack into the cameras.
The other thing is that if it happened
to pick something that was sort of right in this bin
and right in this bin, it would try to almost drive itself
through the base of the robot.
And differential IK would do its best,
but sometimes the robot would almost fold in on itself,
and it would get out of whack, and it
was kind of not very pretty.
So there was a recovery maneuver in there that would just say,
well, things are bad.
Let's just go back to home and then start again.
Both of those we should expect to be
able to resolve with some better motion planning,
and that's a goal for this week.
We're going to talk about the two mainstream approaches
to motion planning, I would say.
One of them is really much based on optimization.
We'll talk about that a lot today.
We'll talk about the sampling-based version
of motion planning a bit on Thursday.
And I think there's some work that
tries to bring them together where
you can try to get some of the best of both worlds.
But one of the other sort of, let's say,
high-level motivations for the lecture
here of using optimization for motion planning
is that it can make a difference.
This is an example from DexEye.
It's a company.
They're in town here, and they're
kind of a spinoff from MIT.
They've got robots that make salads and do
all kinds of food preparation.
You might have seen it in some of the kitchens around here.
For them, their business model is roughly,
how many salads can I make per hour,
or how many sandwiches or whatever we can dish out.
So for them, it's not just about not running into cameras.
They want to eat every ounce of performance out of that robot.
And the rate that they can move food
is partly due to how fast you can move food that it doesn't
fall out of your gripper.
It's partly due to the velocity limits on your robot,
acceleration, even jerk limits on the robot,
torque limits on the robot.
These are dynamic limits that are hard to think about.
And when you're doing well, you're
almost always moving up against those limits.
And it was just fairly recently that we were actually
working with them, and they started doing trajectory
optimization to improve their scooping.
And their success story was they're moving twice as fast
now, and they can earn twice as much money or something.
I don't know exactly the business model,
but it's something like that.
And that's true in a lot of applications.
But I think it's very nice to think about not only planning
motions that are good, but that are riding up against the limits
and getting every bit of performance out of your robot.
OK, so I want to get into planning
and that sort of example first by thinking
a little bit about the nonlinear optimization
view of inverse kinematics.
So let's start with solving IK.
Let's solve it well and understand
some of the subtleties of that cost landscape
and understand why it's going to set us up
for understanding the motion planning version.
OK.
So I know you guys are very familiar with this
at this point, but we've been saying
that forward kinematics is the function, some kinematics
function that takes the joint angles
and moves it over to the gripper.
And inverse kinematics, we say, could be, for instance,
trying to do an inverse of that.
Of course, that is a definition of inverse kinematics.
But we'll try to talk today about how that might not
be the right way to write it down, first of all,
explicitly thinking about it like this.
Maybe this object should never exist in code directly.
And that maybe this isn't as rich of a specification
of inverse kinematics as we want.
So there's a lot to know about this problem.
Even when we talked about differential inverse
kinematics, we saw some of the subtlety.
We tried to use the gradients of this.
We observed that the Jacobian matrix wasn't always full rank.
So that implied even locally, it could have many solutions,
for instance.
It could have zero solutions, depending on what's happening.
So this is not necessarily a great function.
And you could think about that.
If I have a desired pose of my robot,
maybe with seven degrees of freedom,
I've got many possible solutions with my elbow, for instance,
that could get me the same pose.
And you could certainly ask for poses that have no solution.
If it's too far out of the workspace, there's no solution.
And everything in between can happen.
But this is obviously such an important problem for robotics
that there's a long and storied history of solving inverse
kinematics problems.
We'll do the optimization-based version in a second.
But let me say a few things about the history of that.
So one thing you should know is that there's
a special case for a six degree of freedom
manipulator, a standard sort of SCARA sort of manipulator.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
I always try to do it.
But we normally do our own.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, I see.
I have been not putting that mic on just
because we've been using the audio from this one.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
So you could take-- just saying a robot has six degrees of freedom
is not enough.
But there's a standard revolute sort of version
of a standard six degree of freedom robot arm
that is sort of a special case of this problem.
If you have a six degree of freedom robot arm,
then with all revolute joints or there's
a few cases that are well understood,
then actually people have an exact understanding
of that inverse map.
So in this case, there are sort of closed form solutions.
And in particular, there's finitely many solutions.
So you can't actually do-- it requires seven degrees of freedom
to do what I did with my elbow.
In six degrees of freedom, you can do this or this.
You can count how many possible solutions there are.
You can enumerate them.
And people use this often.
You might have used it before.
Most often, if you're like in the ROS world for robotics,
you might be using it through IKFast.
It's a common, familiar ROS package that is basically
using the closed form solutions of the-- it's actually a compiler.
So you tell it the description of the robot,
and it'll compile down these solutions when it's possible.
It doesn't enumerate all of the solutions.
It has some heuristics to pick its favorite solution.
But it'll give you one when it exists.
It's super powerful.
If you look at the work behind IKFast,
actually, you might be surprised where it comes from.
But it actually comes from algebraic geometry.
So it's the study of polynomials and polynomial equations.
That comes from a deep history, I'd say,
of algebraic geometry or kinematics.
So it turns out that the kinematics of our robots
can be described perfectly as the solution
to polynomial equations.
And you can take-- that's a fundamental math question now.
How do you find, given some complicated
polynomial equations, how do you find the zeros, for instance,
of the polynomial equations?
And there are math packages that will do that.
Some of them have been optimized for the kinematics case.
And they can solve really interesting and cool problems.
So for instance, if you think about a four-bar linkage,
and you ask, if I change the angles of this four-bar
linkage in 3D space, what is the path that
can get curved out by the end effector, effectively,
of this four-bar linkage?
It can curve out crazy paths.
But those are actually the solution
to a set of polynomial equations.
And even the manifold of solutions
can be returned by an algebraic geometry package.
And in fact, they even have ways where
you can design your four-bar linkage in order
to be able to execute a certain kinematic path.
So there is a history there of very powerful tools
for understanding this problem.
I would say in the '80s, 1980s, and '90s,
these were mainstream things.
It's not the main topic of inverse kinematics now,
because although these are very powerful,
as I'll try to convince you, this is, I think,
still a slightly limited view of inverse kinematics.
Only trying to invert that function f
might be an insufficient description of the problem.
Really, what I want to do is I want to think about--
I want to find a solution that gets my hand here,
but I also want to respect my joint limits.
So joint limits already complicate a lot of this math.
If you're in the land of polynomials,
people like equality constraints in polynomials.
You don't like inequality constraints in polynomials,
and joint limits are inequality constraints.
And so that gets you into semi-algebraic geometry,
for which there are many less results.
But you might also have things like collision avoidance
constraints.
Oh, that really screws things up.
So I want you to know that if you
want to design a steward-go platform,
there's a right set of tools to do that.
But for the more general problem,
we're going to turn to more flexible but less
reliable solvers.
So let's think about inverse kinematics as an optimization.
This is just a fun demonstration of doing
interactive versions of the inverse kinematics
problem on our humanoid.
And I'll show you the KUKA version
of that running on my computer here in just a second.
But instead of-- let me even just put this back so you
don't watch that too much.
Instead of writing this, you remember,
even for the differential inverse kinematics,
we recommended trying to solve an optimization problem
so that we could put limits on and things like that.
So instead of solving this, what I want to start thinking about
is, what if we say I want to minimize over a Q?
Maybe I want to find a comfortable Q, something
close to some desired-- in my IWA,
I always pick the initial condition to be something--
I guess my arm is not quite in IWA,
and my shoulder is certainly not what it used to be.
But OK, so I pick some comfortable position
and call that my nominal position.
And when I'm trying to choose between all
the possible solutions, I'd like to pick one
that's close as possible to my friendly, happy position,
as opposed to picking one that goes like this.
And so I'll do something like this.
But then I'll say, subject to the idea
that my forward kinematics satisfies this solution.
But then I'll also say, plus joint limits,
collision constraints.
OK.
If I only had this, this would just
be a slightly more general view of that problem, which
tells me what to do if there's multiple solutions.
This gives me an objective that would define my solution
if there's multiple solutions, define which one I pick.
But then because we've moved to the language of optimization,
we can also do other constraints.
So this is the object I want to study for the next little bit.
Questions about that?
What does that look like as an optimization?
This is a quadratic cost, which we like in general.
It's the nice, simple-- it's even
a positive definite quadratic.
So that seems good.
But this is a non-linear, non-convex constraint
in almost every case.
Joint limits are simple, linear, but collision avoidance, again,
are very non-linear constraints.
So we're quickly in the land of non-linear optimization,
non-convex optimization.
The picture is-- the non-convexity
is coming from the constraints, not from the objective.
But the picture is kind of still like what
I was talking about here, where you could expect your optimizer
to find minima, but it won't necessarily
find the global minima.
Right?
This is kind of the picture I want to have in your head.
Really what's happening is the picture
is a little bit more like there's a big quadratic form,
but because of the constraints, I'm only allowed to go here.
Maybe I could go here.
And I could go potentially-- the thing that defines those sets
is so complicated that I can't expect
to get to the best version of it.
But intuitively, it's really-- it's
the same as having a landscape like that.
So how do we solve that problem?
And how do we connect it to what you already know?
We have differential inverse kinematics, right?
So how does differential inverse kinematics work?
We solved that reliably with convex optimization.
And we did that, even with some of these other constraints,
by taking a linearization of these constraints.
That was the differential IK version of it.
In fact, the way we often solve this
is actually very much like solving the differential IK
problem over and over and over again.
So when you use the nonlinear solver,
we tend to use for these problems is SNOPT.
Although some people think IP-OPT is better.
I actually believe them, but I think it's-- you pick
your weapon, and you learn how to use your weapon very well.
And so I've used SNOPT more, so I can make SNOPT do good things.
And other people who use other solvers
know how to do that better.
But this is just the name of a commercial solver.
It's a semi-commercial solver.
And it is solving using sequential quadratic
programming.
So actually, when SNOPT is solving a problem like this,
it's actually effectively solving a differential IK
problem multiple times and trying to rapidly move
to a solution.
So the differential IK work that you've already done
is happening behind the scenes.
So this gives us a really potentially rich language
of costs and constraints.
And we're going to look at some of the cost
landscapes and everything.
But this is what we're talking about for ATLAS.
So maybe we have somebody saying,
I want my hand to be at a certain place.
That's what this little marker is doing,
is that someone in the interface is just
pulling around the hand.
But ATLAS also had joint limit constraints, collision
avoidance constraints, even self-collision avoidance
constraints.
We needed a lot of things like gaze constraints.
So the way that you move your hand maybe
should be subject to where your cameras are.
And you want to pick up things you can see,
which turned out to be a really funny thing for ATLAS
because the first version of ATLAS, its head was like this.
It could see here.
And its hands could reach down here.
And the place where you could reach,
where the cameras could see, was surprisingly small.
It was really irritating.
They changed-- if you look at ATLAS now,
they kind of took the arms off, flipped the shoulders around.
And now it looks a little like an ape.
But at least it can reach where it can see.
That's good.
When we were doing it on the humanoid,
we wanted it to also keep the feet in the same place.
We didn't want the feet to move around when
we were solving the IK problem.
We also had, for instance, the center mass
had to be inside the support polygon
so the robot didn't fall over.
But these are just a list of more and more things.
And once we've gone over the hump of saying
we're going to solve a non-linear, non-convex
optimization, then it opens up a huge library
of these types of constraints you can add.
You still want to add things that
are smooth and nice functions, but it really
opens the floodgates.
So let's think about it for a couple simple examples.
So let me even run interactive IK for this simple robot here.
Which, by the way, I always run on M1.
Except for people who are like, oh, it doesn't work on M1.
It works on M1.
So here's my interactive inverse kinematics in MeshCat.
So I've got my KUKA IWA, and I'll just
move around the end effector positions.
And there's a couple of points I want to make here,
is that it's solving-- and it certainly
can solve at real time rates.
I think the delays here are probably
more the network or something than the solver.
It can definitely be solving fast enough.
But every time I move the sliders,
it's like it's waking up for the first time
and solving a global version of the problem.
So the way that can get you is if you just
do that, for instance, there's no real guarantee
that it's going to find smooth solutions.
As I move it around, I might get it
to jump between different solutions.
Probably if I move it towards itself,
it'll start jumping around.
Whoa, whoa.
Right?
That was cool.
I mean, that's a lot to ask to move right through yourself.
But OK.
I mean, it's finding the solutions.
It's pretty impressive.
But I wouldn't execute on the robot, right?
OK.
So the cool thing is, though, when
you start adding more and more of these constraints,
it gets more and more powerful.
So here's now the same interface, but I put a pole.
Like, if someone put a pole in front of your robot,
you should be mad.
That's not a reasonable thing to do,
but it's kind of a reasonable demo for the IK here, right?
So now I've done almost exactly what I wrote here.
In fact, the joint limits, but also the collision avoidance
constraints.
And the fun case, I guess, is when
I try to make the robot move that way,
what's it going to do, right?
So I guess that should be positive y.
It's trying to reach.
It's trying to-- oh, and then it snapped over, right?
Again, don't execute consecutive poses on the robot.
But as an independent solve, it's pretty good, right?
It's reasonable to be that there's
some places where it's not going to be happy with the solution.
In fact, so the solver will say, in that place where
it couldn't find a solution-- it actually did well that time.
I'm like, I wanted to make my point.
OK, there.
Yeah, right there.
The solver will say, in that case, IK failure.
It knows that it failed.
So that's comforting, I guess, a little bit.
OK, so this is a pretty powerful toolbox.
But let's see what we can do with it.
One of the most important lessons I want to give you here
is that actually this specification is, I think,
in addition to not being what you want because it didn't--
if I just solved this version of the problem,
it didn't account for these.
But there's another view I want to give you,
which is that saying this is almost always more than you
need to say.
OK, for most manipulation tasks, picking a desired grasp
and constraining the robot reached to that grasp in XYZ
yaw pitch role is overly specifying the tasks.
And as you use optimization more,
you will learn that writing a minimal version
of this constraint that is only constraining exactly what you
need and no more will open up the flexibility for finding
solutions.
And it's sort of a better way to write your inverse kinematics
problem.
So let me make that point here with this version here.
OK, so now I have the robot is supposed
to be grabbing the cylinder.
And this time I put the sliders on the cylinder
instead of on the robot.
Now my objective-- so I'm not worried
about the inertia of the cylinder in this case.
My inertia is just to have the cylinder somewhere in my hand.
But I'm saying that the location along the cylinder
shouldn't matter.
And the rotation-- I picked the cylinder
so I could argue that the rotation shouldn't matter.
So if I write the problem right, as I move the cylinder around,
the robot actually shouldn't move until I get to the end.
And then it has to follow.
See if I can see this from a different angle too.
And similarly, it should be willing to rotate itself.
There's no reason why it had to come in at exactly
some orientation.
Any orientation where the cylinder
is in the middle of the hand should be sufficient.
So when you want to level up in your inverse kinematics,
you should write just the very minimal version
of that constraint.
Does that make sense?
So how would you write that constraint?
What is that particular constraint?
How would you author it?
What does it look like?
This is how I did it.
There's various versions of it.
But what I said was I want a constraint that says--
so the decision-- I should have written a q in here.
That would have helped.
But the decision variables are inside the thing that
defines my relative transforms.
G is the gripper frame.
C is the cylinder frame.
And what I said is that there's going
to be two points on the gripper frame
that I would like to be inside the cylinder.
So in the cylinder frame, this is the center
of the cylinder in x and y.
And the cylinders are by default along the long axis,
almost in every robotics package, I guess.
So if I'm saying I'm between 0.5 and 0.5,
that's just saying there's some point of interest
on the gripper frame that I would
like to be on the center line of the cylinder,
but anywhere between the length of the cylinder.
And then the points I would like to place there
are two points on the gripper frame, which,
remember, the gripper frame here-- I grabbed this old
picture just so you remember that RGB, right?
So the y-axis is the one along the gripper.
So 0.1 puts me somewhere around here in y.
And then I did z, a small number,
and a negative number, a small negative number, which
is this and this, so along that blue axis.
Is that clear?
So what I'm saying-- I guess I have a round chalk here, right?
Because I've got a gripper frame.
I'm going to pick up-- this is hard.
OK, I've got a point right here and a point right here
that I'd like to be inside the chalk.
And that's enough, right?
That means that I'm going to be aligned with it,
and I'm going to slide along.
We actually have ways to write orientation constraints
directly, but I thought this was a little bit easier
to put on a slide and consume.
Just think about points, putting a point
on the line of the cylinder.
And if I put two of them, I constrain myself
exactly the way I want and not in other ways
that I don't want.
Cool.
And so that works pretty well.
And I think it's a general strategy for picking up
objects or whatever, depending on what your grasp selection
strategy was.
But you should try to get one that
allows you to have that extra flexibility,
because there's going to be many more solutions.
Yeah?
Did you have a question?
[INAUDIBLE]
But only in the one axis.
That was my goal, right?
So it's true that I could have allowed grasps like this.
I chose not to.
I wanted it to be like this, but it's
free to rotate in that axis.
So I guess it constrains two of the rotational degrees
and leaves one free.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
So that's our language.
In fact, it's a rich language.
So this actually translates directly in code.
We can just say, add a position constraint.
It uses the multibody notation.
You say, I'm in the gripper frame.
I'd like my Q point, which is this,
to be in my other frame, which is the cylinder frame.
So there's a pretty direct mapping
from that math into the code.
OK.
And we actually have a pretty rich library
of costs and constraints.
Add position constraint, position costs,
orientation constraints, orientation costs,
the gaze target constraints, all the things we've used
in the past.
There's ways to just take your frame logic,
your points in one frame need to be
something related to some other points in some other frame,
and add that as a cost or constraint into this problem,
and then hit Solve.
And you're good.
The one that I used-- I mean, there's actually--
there's some pretty interesting ones, actually.
The one that I used in the collision avoidance constraint
is a minimum distance constraint,
which is the most complicated one that's
in there, which just adds a single constraint saying
that all of the collision pairs in the world
are at least some minimum distance apart.
And it's written in a particular way.
I mean, you could write it yourself.
But the difference between a thing you'd write yourself
and what's happening in here, this
is leveraging the more advanced features of collision detection
so that it can-- objects that are far away
get called immediately with axis-aligned bounding boxes.
And then it's doing some clever smoothing
as the two objects that are the closest switch,
if you switch from being as closest to the table
between closest to the laptop, that
would be a non-smoothness in the cost landscape.
And it tries to smooth that out.
And there's a lot of details behind there
to make that work pretty well.
It's still not bulletproof, because it's
a complicated landscape.
And that's kind of what I want to tell you next,
is just let's just think about the landscape that's
happening in these problems.
So first, I'll just show you.
We use this a lot, actually.
And my favorite one was-- they gave the DARPA Robotics
Challenge.
We had to do a number of things.
The robot had to drive a car, right?
And the government furnished us with an atlas.
We won the right to get an atlas.
And then they told us we had to drive a car.
And they gave us a small car.
It's a Polaris, right?
They gave us an enormous humanoid.
And then they gave us a tiny car.
And we had to invent rich inverse kinematics just
to figure out how to fit the robot in the car, right?
And it turns out, it didn't really
fit behind the driver's seat.
You had to sit kind of in the middle,
and kind of on the passenger seat,
and put your leg across the console,
and go like this, and drive like this.
It was awkward and embarrassing.
And we actually fell out in the process one time.
But that's how we turned the steering wheel, see?
And we did all the workspace analysis and everything
using this inverse kinematics pipeline.
But the good thing is, it's such a general pipeline
that once we had it working on atlas,
we had a chance to work with the NASA Valkyrie robot.
And everything just worked.
It's just the same code.
You just flip out the atlas model at the beginning,
put in the Valkyrie model, and we could do all the same stuff.
So it's a pretty powerful tool chain.
So let's just appreciate for a minute what's
happening in the geometry.
And so I want to visualize a few simple configuration space
regions.
So the example I carved up here to try to convince you of this
is, let's just take a two-link arm.
I'm going to make theta 1, theta 2.
I'll call it L1, L2.
And then at the bottom of this two-link arm--
I have some colored chalk here somewhere--
I'll make a hand that has radius r.
And then, like a jerk, I'm going to put this robot
in a constrained environment with walls
like this that are just w apart.
OK, and this is the simplest possible kinematics problem.
It's one where--
[LAUGHTER]
And we can solve it in closed form.
We can say, I know exactly which angles are
going to be in collision and which would be out of collision.
Because if I just take the x position of that,
the p of the gripper in x is just going to be L1 sine q1
plus L2 sine q1 plus q2.
And I want this to be in the limits
where the sphere is not intersecting with the wall.
So it works out to be that.
OK, and if you plot that region, which I've done here--
and I could change my lengths and my radius or whatever--
it gets funky, right?
This one is as simple as it gets,
but it's not some simple convex region, right?
The landscape that my inverse kinematics tools
have to work around is on the-- I'm sorry
if I didn't say this clearly.
The region in the middle is the feasible region.
And the way I could plot it in Desmos,
I plotted the two infeasible constraints.
But this region in the middle is sort of the feasible region.
0, 0 is feasible, right?
And as I move it around, the shape of my feasible region
can change pretty dramatically.
Whoops.
So that would be if the walls are crushing the robot.
So that's-- OK.
That's a toy example.
Let's do it for the IWA.
I wanted to-- I spent some time trying
to figure out how to visualize this for you.
This is the example I came up with.
So I actually am going to lock out four
of the joints of the IWA and just plot three of them,
because I can make animations in three dimensions.
So I'm just going to leave the three of the IWA
that are in the plane.
And then I'm going to ask it to reach into the shelf.
And I'm going to do the same thing we just did with that.
But I'm going to do it with the real geometry of the IWA,
all the real collision geometry of the shelf and the IWA.
And this is what it looks like.
What the-- OK.
So the inverse kinematics problem has two bits.
So let me try to make this-- help you make sense of this.
So the first thing was I wrote an objective saying
that I want the hand to be-- a point in the hand to be--
a point in space to be in the hand.
And that constraint is this green region
that would be an annulus all the way around.
It's truncated only by the joint limits.
So this would be the-- it trying to go like this, like this.
It's in the plane.
And I got to work on my shoulder mobility
before the next time I give this lecture.
So that's the feasible if the shelf wasn't there,
which is already sort of a terrible thing.
Like that's a scary kind of landscape.
It would be smooth if I plot-- the way I made this was I just
sampled a bunch.
And I called marching cubes.
And so it's a slightly bumpy version of the true surface.
By the way, SNOPT, our inverse kinematics code,
does find the solution.
If I find an optimal solution for this,
I use this as the initial guess.
And it found its way into that nook and cranny
to find that solution, which I showed you in the picture.
But what's this thing?
This thing is the marching cubes version of the configurations
where they're in collision or out of collision.
So this is the boundary from where
you switch from being in collision
to being out of collision.
And it's horrible.
It's absolutely horrible.
And in fact, if you want to find the solution,
it has to be feasible.
It's tucked down in this little-- whoop, there it is.
That's that question we're asking SNOPT
to find an answer to for us.
So when SNOPT fails, be nice.
It's a really hard problem we're asking.
In fact, let me even just show you-- I also
got a little crazy with this.
So let me show you the cost landscape
we actually give to SNOPT.
So if I can move this over.
So this is the same problem.
But I'm going to actually plot it.
We don't give the boundaries just as true/false things
to SNOPT.
We make smooth-- the minimum distance, right?
It doesn't have a cliff that it falls off
when you're in collision and not.
We have the minimum distance function,
which tells me how far I'm in collision
or how far I am away from collision.
So that becomes a smoother function.
But you can look at all the pieces of this.
So first, the objective is beautiful and smooth, right?
It's my quadratic, which has some goal back
at the comfortable position.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Awesome.
So I'm plotting in 3D because I have three joint angles.
So it's not Cartesian xyz.
It's q1, q2, q3 are defining the three axes of this plot.
Thank you for asking that.
So the point there means a particular choice
of joint angles.
And we're trying to-- yeah, perfect.
Thank you for asking that.
And so this is telling me I have a favorite joint
angle, which is my comfortable home position.
And I'm quadratically penalizing things away from it.
And the solution turns out to be here
on the landscape, that blue.
But if I start turning on the constraints here--
let's turn them on one at a time here.
The position constraint, which was that annulus,
I don't give it that annulus directly.
I give it the xyz location and ask
it to be inside the constraints.
So if I plot the xyz, the way I plotted this here
is for each of the constraints, I
plotted a region which is red if it's infeasible
and blue if it's feasible.
But it's a smooth function, you see?
So it's only got a small annulus of possible feasible solutions.
But they are the level set of some curve.
So SNOPT knows it needs to get this function
to be inside some band.
And it's allowed to use gradients and the like
to try to move me down into that band.
But there's also a-- so in y, it's
trivially true because the robot can't move in y.
So all of the joint angles are satisfying in y.
And then in z, there's also another band.
And those two only intersect in a small little thing.
It's using the gradients of those individual functions
to try to find it.
But it's a nightmare of a problem.
The bounding box constraint was just the joint limits.
And then the minimum distance constraint
is the big scary one, right?
It's a little bit less scary when
I show you it as the full distance computation instead
of just the clips.
But it's still a hard problem for SNOPT to solve.
So be nice to your solver.
It's solving a hard problem.
Questions about that?
IK is-- I think it's a workhorse.
You'll use it in-- mature manipulation tools
will use these queries.
They can be made fairly robust.
But even the best people in the field
still complain about IK failures and the like.
So there are problems that we would
like to be able to solve in this kind of space
that we can't quite solve.
Can't solve reliably enough to ship, let's say, in a product.
There are versions of this that try
to solve the global optimization problem.
We have one of them implemented in Drake.
You can play with it if you want.
It consumes a smaller vocabulary of possible constraints
that we know how to do stronger optimization on.
But it's-- and it solves much slower.
It would not solve at interactive rates.
It solves for the dual arm.
It's less than a minute, but it's more than a second.
OK.
So kinematic trajectory-- let's take-- this
is a good time to take a quick stretch, yeah?
Before I jump into the trajectory optimization
version.
And feel free to think about questions
while you're stretching.
I love that.
The landscape isn't just hard for SNOP.
It's apparently hard for Safari.
Your web page is using significant energy.
Closing it may improve the performance of this device.
That's just drawing it, not even solving for it.
OK.
So my promise at the beginning was
that we were going to stop smacking into the shell--
into the cameras and the like.
And we're just talking about inverse kinematics so far.
But my claim now is that if you understand that,
you've actually solved a lot-- you've gotten yourself most
of the way to solving trajectories.
OK.
And the idea is pretty simple.
Let me use that simple landscape.
You know-- oops, that was-- my pendulum landscape
where I had a bunch of feasible solutions.
And so far, I've been saying, find me
a point somewhere in this landscape that
satisfies some criteria.
OK.
The motion planning problem is going
to be, find me a bunch of points that all satisfy the criteria.
Right?
Maybe they satisfy-- you could put different costs
and constraints on the points.
OK.
And you're going to put some sort of conditions
that sort of ask these to have some continuity between them.
That's the main thing I want you to think
about when you're thinking about extending inverse kinematics
into kinematic trajectory optimization
is, I'm just going to find many points
and ask them to be connected by a curve.
OK.
Remember, my inverse kinematics solve, as I pulled it around,
there wasn't any guarantee that it would find smooth solutions.
It could go like this, and then suddenly like this.
Right?
So I'm asking it now to just not only find independently
good points, but to actually have them connected
by some simple constraints.
OK.
So maybe I'll even show you it working,
and then we can get back to how it works.
So this is kinematic trajectory optimization.
Let's do the reaching into the shelves example here.
OK?
Which is this one.
OK.
You understand, I think, how to write an optimization
to find a hand in this pose or in the red pose.
But what it's found this time is a sequence
of poses that goes from one to the other.
OK.
And I can just move along that as a trajectory
that goes back and forth.
OK.
And I'll do it in a slightly different order here.
But I can also do, for instance, the clutter clearing example
here.
So remember, the problem that I had
was if I was reaching here, I might sometimes
smack into the cameras going around.
OK.
So now I find solutions.
I actually thought it was going to find a solution
inside the camera.
It found a solution that went around the cameras.
I mean, it's my fault for putting cameras right
in the middle of the reasonable space.
OK.
But it satisfies all the constraints.
And finds a nice smooth motion.
And you can put velocity constraints on the start
and the end if you want.
OK.
So let's look at this a little bit more carefully.
So the collision geometry that is using in that minimum distance
constraint, I can turn that on.
This is what it looks like.
OK.
So I have a simpler geometry for the robot.
I just made boxes.
OK.
And I put a big sphere for the hand.
Because not only because the hand is--
I mean, the hand could be a box.
That's fine.
But it's going to pick up some things.
So I wanted to have a conservative region.
Probably the mustard bottle would snip outside there.
I'd still smack into it.
I could have done a better job on that.
It was late.
Actually, it was early.
OK.
But within that approximation, it
does a pretty good job of solving the problem.
I have to say, writing up these examples
was a nice reminder not only of how well it can work,
but how annoying it can be when it doesn't work.
So let me show you, I guess Mark Riebert would
call it the unvarnished truth, or somehow the dirty laundry,
if you will.
OK.
So it's not quite-- the code, I think,
is fairly clean in the sense that you just
add the natural costs and constraints to the curve.
So you basically say, I'm going to make a kinematic trajectory
optimization.
I'm going to add my joint limit constraints.
I'm going to add some velocity limits.
Those just come straight out of things.
I think it's fairly readable.
I'm going to say, I want my start
to be in this position constraint,
my end to be in some position constraint.
It's all very natural, easily justified.
The only cost is shortest path.
I basically say, I want the time to be small,
and I want the distance to be small.
And this is a strong recommendation
I want to make to you in life.
Don't jam all kinds of things into your objective
and constraints.
Be very minimal in the way you write your constraints,
and try to write exactly the cost function you want.
If you start cost function tuning, life gets sad.
Some of you know what I mean.
RL, in particular, has that trap.
OK, here's the one thing I don't like about the example
as it is.
I actually call solve twice.
I first solve with pretending the shelf is not there.
And then I solve again using that as an initial guess
to give the shelf that is there.
If I don't do that-- let's see if I can adjust that enough
to-- let me just take that out and see what happens.
This is the shelf example.
OK, to be fair, it said it fails.
I would never have executed that,
but it just was unable to find a solution.
In fact, I can do less severe things to it.
So trajectory optimization failed.
SNOP was unhappy.
It was able to satisfy the constraints.
It wasn't-- I wasn't surprised and thought
I should execute it.
But it didn't solve the problem I asked it to solve.
In fact, if I even change the sphere on the hand
to be a box, then if you think about what happens,
if my straight line trajectory-- or if the shelf wasn't there,
it would go from here straight through to down here.
OK?
If I have box collision for my hand and box for the shelf
and it goes into penetration, there's
nothing that will help it know which direction to get out.
So this was my intuition, which made me say, well,
if I put a sphere on there, then it'll
have some sense of which it could move in directions
to get different-- but this is the dirty laundry, right?
So let's just see what happens if I take that off.
Oh.
Oh, no, it still failed.
OK.
What did it do?
Crazy.
But this curve, actually, is the visualization of the solve
as it's happening.
So if I were to run it again, you'll see--
you can actually see it struggling.
It's like trying all kinds of crazy solutions.
Woo.
How did it solve it pretty well that one time?
I should have left it and looked at that,
but clearly I just got lucky.
What is that?
Oh, no, no.
Oh, I see.
I've seen that one before, too.
So it went up, down, OK, whatever.
The point is, I think these tools work extremely
well when you have a reasonable guess,
but they're not solving the really global optimization
problem.
OK, yes?
Can we add time to the collision between the curve
and the collision and the object that kind of avoided it?
For sure.
So the way-- in fact, I had to be a little bit--
so I make this minimum distance constraint,
saying that I want everything to be at least one millimeter out
of collision.
And this is my-- ignore-- don't even
consider bodies that are more than 10 centimeters out.
But I had to actually go through and say,
I want you to evaluate that constraint at 25 points
along the length of the trajectory.
But I could have added that at just the beginning,
at just the end, and I can choose where to add it.
The particular parameterization I've
implemented here for the kinematic trajectory
optimization-- I'll say a little bit in the next bit--
but it actually separates out the path
that it's optimizing from the time parameterization
of the optimization.
That allows us to write a few things and more things
convexly.
So that's the only subtlety to your question.
So yes, you can definitely say, like,
halfway through the execution, I don't want to be in collision,
but later I can.
And there are other formulations that might be more natural
if you know that you have a ball, for instance,
flying through the air and you want
to grab it at a certain thing.
Maybe you don't use that separate parameterization.
[INAUDIBLE]
You can write combined constraints even
in this formulation, too.
I emphasize the things that could be convex
when they could be, which is the reason.
But you could certainly write the non-convex constraints
on this solver.
I worked pretty hard on this.
I would say I got a little obsessed with this,
trying to make this good, partly because last year I
didn't have this for you guys, and I
felt that a lot of projects would have benefited from it.
So this is actually-- the code that's running this is going
to-- I'm going to push it to Drake
and go through code review on it this week.
So it should be locked in.
It's got full test coverage.
It's pretty mature and good.
[INAUDIBLE]
When I don't solve it twice.
Yeah, so if you do nothing, then it's just going to take--
I mean, it's just going to pick q as some slightly non-zero
trajectory just to avoid the local minima that often happen
at 0.
But basically, it's a default trajectory.
It knows nothing about your problem.
So for the second problem, actually, I
didn't have to solve it twice.
But I can actually show you--
yeah, uncomment this to see the initial guess.
I thought that-- I didn't know you were going to ask that,
but I thought it was interesting,
so I put that in just in case.
So I just made this as an initial guess.
I just made a trajectory that went from here to here,
just a comfortable position.
I only rotated the base.
And the reason I needed to do that at all
was because the solver kept trying
to go the other way around.
It would be like, here, and hang itself, basically.
So I'd be like, OK, I have to at least tell it
I want it to go that way.
And that was enough, and it found good solutions.
[INAUDIBLE]
The question is, why did I pick that particular cost?
So I did minimum time and minimum path length.
There's a couple other formulations
that are naturally convex in this parameterization.
So I biased myself towards the convex objectives.
But acceleration, we don't know how to do convexly, ironically.
You would think if you could do one derivative,
you could do two and three.
But we know how to do positions and velocities.
We don't know how to do accelerations,
because t squared makes things non-convex, roughly.
So that is reflecting a bias, not just as a roboticist,
but as the guy who had to type the code in.
And I know that makes the solvers better.
I think there are other ways that I
will talk about at some point, that you can minimize
acceleration convexly if you choose.
There's a-- after you've optimized your path,
if you lock the path and then just optimize the trajectory,
then you can put even more constraints on accelerations
and the like and optimize that.
So for instance, like the DexEye use case,
I would recommend to them to solve the best optimization you
can with the weaker constraints.
But then at the last instant, solve it again
with the path fixed.
And you're just going to make sure you're
moving exactly along the rails of that path.
So there's a whole toolkit here.
And yeah, I think a lot to know, but it's good.
Questions, other questions about that?
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
That's a great question.
So I have done nothing in this formulation
to talk about uncertainty.
It's just hard, don't be in the object or not.
It is super useful to talk about uncertainty.
And there are some forms of uncertainty
that you can put in in nice ways and convex ways and the like.
Typically, Gaussians are a good thing.
But if you move a complicated robot,
it doesn't stay Gauss-- distributions don't stay
Gaussian and the like.
So yes, there's a topic that I would
lump under belief space planning or planning under uncertainty
or planning for information gathering that
would address that very nicely.
But it typically means higher hardware optimization problems.
Yeah.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
That's a really good question.
So can you solve this fast enough to solve it online?
So that idea would be called model predictive control, MPC,
if you see that name.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
You roughly re-solve at each time step with the shifted data.
You know, you're kind of moving as you
know that you've executed.
I would say I don't have evidence for this example
one way or the other, because the MPC problem,
it would be bad.
It would be naive to solve the problem from scratch
every time step.
You want to use your previous solve not only
as an initial guess for the other solve,
but typically there's a lot of problem data
that your solver collects while it's solving that first one
that you want to pass.
That would be called a warm start for your solver.
You say, I'm going to solve an almost identical problem.
I just change it a little bit, reuse as much as you can.
And so in that regime, I do think
this would be real-time compatible.
But again, it's going to be limited to local changes.
If it suddenly had to go a different way around the bin
or around the cameras, you can't guarantee
it's going to solve that.
In fact, in general, solving the nonlinear optimization
on the fly is a little risky, I'd say.
For Atlas, for instance, we did great trajectory optimization
offline, but we didn't do it online
because we didn't want to be running along with Atlas.
And all of a sudden, it says, I can't find a solution.
What are you going to do, right?
So we didn't consider that robust enough.
The people who do MPC in line would typically
restrict themselves to convex problems.
Actually, there's a ton of autonomous driving companies
that are solving the nonlinear version on the fly, which
is terrifying.
So maybe it can be made robust enough.
Typically, it's in some envelope where
it's been sufficiently vetted.
So let me tell you a little bit about the way
to write these continuity constraints.
Yeah?
I think I said most of my dirty laundry.
There's probably a little bit more dirty laundry.
It's a pretty good example.
So how do I write these continuity constraints?
So remember when we did the piecewise pose, when
we designed our key frames by hand
and then just interpolated between them?
We interpolated those using-- the class was piecewise pose
because that was trying to do something
clever about the quaternion interpolation on the rotation.
But in general, this is a piecewise polynomial.
In those cases, it was typically a cubic.
And it's often called cubic splines.
And so roughly speaking, for each interval of the piece,
for each piece, a piecewise polynomial
would just say I've got some coefficients
that I'm trying to fit.
These are my decision parameters in this case.
Times my coefficients, which would typically
be something like this, i to 0 to 3,
something that is just a polynomial in time
around some nominal-- relative to some starting
place in the segment.
And it's just a linear coefficient
on some nonlinear function of time.
This is a way to just say I've got some polynomial in time,
which the parameters of that polynomial, this is like t
plus 2t squared plus 3t cubed or something like that.
The extra logic of making it a piecewise polynomial just
says I'm going to make some intervals here.
And in each interval, I'll ask this
to be a polynomial of degree 3, this
to be a degree 3 polynomial, this degree 3 polynomial.
And you could put constraints on that make them smooth.
So this is just a piecewise polynomial representation
of a trajectory.
If you ask in your optimization formulation,
if you represent this as a piecewise polynomial,
and instead of choosing q at time 0 and q at time t
or whatever as your decision variables,
you make the coefficients of this spline
be your decision variables, then that's
going to parameterize a curve through space.
And the decision variables fit right
into our optimization problem.
I can make the forward kinematics at a certain time,
find the alpha that makes the forward kinematics
at a certain time, satisfy my objectives and constraints.
I don't feel like everybody's with me.
If I said, right now I'm saying I want f kinematics,
let's say, at time 0, I've got this
as a constraint in my optimizer.
I can just write xg is f kin of sum over i alpha i with t
set to 0.
I just evaluate these this time.
It gives me some constants here.
And I put that through my kinematics.
That's just another nonlinear and a smooth nonlinear function
of the parameters alpha.
So instead of changing q directly,
I'm going to choose the coefficients of my spline.
Those are the standard decision variables in an optimization.
It turns out that people make different choices
about-- the land of polynomials is a rich land.
There's lots of different polynomials.
These piecewise polynomials, which
are representing just t to some power,
they have some expressive power.
They have some numerical properties.
There are different classes of polynomial parameterizations
that have different powers and different numerical properties.
You might have heard of Chebyshev polynomials,
Legendre polynomials, Bazier polynomials.
Bernstein and Bazier are the same thing.
And they all have different properties.
But I think this is a super simple one to understand.
I just forget-- I even forget I-- what if I just said this?
t to the i.
I should have just written that.
That's easier.
Forget about the fact that-- for each segment,
you need to subtract off the interval.
But I'm just saying alpha t to the i.
This would be the simplest piecewise polynomial.
It turns out there are other ways to write.
Instead of just writing the simple polynomials of t
to the i, there are other ways that you might just
say some other polynomial function of t to the i that
might give you different properties.
And they can parameterize similar curves.
The one I chose for this kinematic trajectory
optimization was a Bazier polynomial, a Bazier spline,
in fact.
Not the only choice, but this is my choice,
was a B-spline, which is, again, just a particular form
of a curve like this, where this is still polynomial.
Those ends turn on and off in an annoyingly complicated way.
But the reason I chose Bernstein polynomials and the Bazier
polynomials, this is--
mostly it's Bazier, but I'm pretty sure
it's the same as Bernstein.
Let me not write that in case somebody walks in and says,
what are you talking about?
I'm sure it's Bazier.
And I'm pretty sure it's Bernstein also.
What's that?
[INAUDIBLE]
The Bernstein-- the Bazier basis?
Oh.
Oh, is that right?
Yeah.
OK, that's lame.
He says it stands for basis, not Bazier.
But the basis is a Bazier curve.
Yeah?
Yeah, OK.
I believe you.
The reason that I chose this representation
is it has a couple of nice properties.
The biggest one is it has a property that's
called the convex hull property, which says-- so basically,
the decision variables, the alphas that are in this curve
have a geometric interpretation.
Alpha 0, alpha 1, alpha 2, alpha 3, they are the control points.
The decision variables become the control points.
And I have some guarantee that for each subset of the--
there's a particular order and degree of the polynomial, OK,
but basically that I know that within each segment
of the polynomial, the curve will
be some linear interpolation of the decision variables.
OK, and then I get another region at the next time.
And I know that the curve is going
to be guaranteed to be able to stay inside there.
So because of that, this is a nice property
because if I want to write that q of t
is inside the joint limits, q max, q min, for all t,
then I can say that if just all of the control points
are inside my joint limits, then I
can guarantee that for all time, I will never
exceed a joint limit.
I don't have to sample exhaustively
to guarantee I haven't violated any joint limits.
I can leverage the convex hull property.
It also has the property that the derivatives are still
Bzier splines.
So I can also write for all t velocity min,
the joint velocity constraints are enforced completely
with this parameterization.
That would be hard to guarantee with a piecewise polynomial
represented like this, but it's possible to guarantee
with a Bzier polynomial.
OK, collision avoidance constraints,
I do not have that guarantee.
Once I apply a nonlinear transformation to my q's,
I cannot guarantee that this curve will not
run into a table.
So a common problem would be to say
I've sampled 50 times along my trajectory
to not be in collision, but somewhere between time 37,
which was out of collision, and time 38,
which was out of collision, it went right through.
That happens.
So the more robust solvers, even if it's
going to use this kind of a tool,
will write those constraints, maybe give some margin,
but then after the solution, will subsample densely,
potentially, in order to see if that happened.
The code that we used at TRI would do that.
And if it ever find a violation, it
would add a new constraint, re-solve on the fly,
and you could add layers of robustness
like that in order to try to avoid those possible pitfalls.
But in this formulation, corners happen.
There's no rigorous certification
that you won't clip a corner.
[END PLAYBACK]
So this is actually what we used heavily in the disloading.
That's not completely true.
We used both this and a sample-based method
that I'll show you after.
But this is a nice example where it
had to solve some pretty hard problems.
So the mugs were placed in this video
to show the trajectory optimization.
They were placed in a few different configurations
in the sink.
That one, the mug was sideways, and it
was able to pick a grasp.
And it successfully found a path that
went all the way from the mug in the sink
all the way to the rack.
But when it's top-down, it can't find that solution.
So it had to stop, set down the mug, pick it back up.
And that was because the kinematic trajectory
optimization could not find a solution that
would jointly satisfy the constraints we put on the pickup
and the set down when the mug was in a certain pose.
So it had to do this extra step of rotating
the mug, which was the slowest thing about the disloading
robot.
We actually had people come in, and we
would time the people versus the robots.
And people can do in-hand reorientation,
and it's an unfair advantage.
So we had someone tie their arm behind their back,
and they could still beat our robot because they pick up a mug
and they just turn it around and stick it in.
And we had to go and set it down and then move the arm like this
in order to pick it up.
And that was the best we could do with that hand, I think.
Yes?
So when you're doing the setting down and re-grasping,
is that leaving motion planning and going into task planning
and then coming back to motion planning?
Or is it all in motion planning?
That's great.
So there was an element of task planning there, too.
Absolutely right.
So the task planner would check conditions
based on whether the trajectory optimization could succeed.
There's actually a simple version
of this, which is what we used at the task planning level.
You can actually just solve-- if you forget about this,
there's a shortcut you can solve just
to ask whether you should solve the problem.
So can I find the same grasp on the mug that satisfies
the conditions here and here?
So the only constraint you put between the two
separate solutions is that the relative pose of the mug
compared to the hand is the same.
So that would be-- whereas so far, we've
done grasp selection, where we just looked in the sink
and forgot about what we're going to do
and just said, can I find a grasp?
But if you could say, I have to find a grasp that I'm
going to be able to set down later,
then that puts additional constraints
on how you pick your grasp.
And that's a quick way to verify-- to say,
I should even explore that solution or not even
explore that solution.
A smaller optimization problem.
[INAUDIBLE]
This one, I think, it stopped between.
But we have stronger methods that can go through that.
It's possible to be planned all the way through.
There's some planning time pauses in that one.
The question is, does it take time to plan here,
going all the way through?
Yeah, I think he did plan all the way through.
We'll have to ask Honkai.
Yeah.
So the question about the task planning
is actually a really good one.
I was going to try to make that point, too.
So there's versions of this trajectory optimization problem
that do creep up into trying to solve the task and motion
planning problem.
One of my favorites is from Danny and Mark,
where they're solving this sort of multi-step optimization
problem using trajectory optimization.
They have a trajectory optimization
compatible higher level planner that
turns on and off constraints in a branch and bound kind of way.
And I think we'll-- depending on which boutique lectures
we pick towards the end, we might spend an hour
and a half talking about task and motion planning.
But just to say, this is one of the approaches that
can sort of go at the distance.
Good.
I'll call that a day.
Kinematic trajectory optimization is basically
IK, where you just push a polynomial
through your IK solver.
That's the big message.
OK, see you Thursday.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
I'm happy to answer any project questions
if people have them, too.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
There's probably a good answer for that,
depending on which defects we're talking about.
Yeah.
That's good.
OK.
I'm happy to take that question if someone
wants to send me an email.
Yeah.
Yeah, just give us the context.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
On the YouTube at a certain time or something.
Yeah.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
Yeah, yeah.
It's possible it was flaky.
But as long as it's working.
So I mean, I'm pretty sure it becomes
unlimited number of Meshcat instances
once you go through the NGICs things.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
OK, the time that that happens is when people--
if the output of your notebook was
saved from a previous session, and you don't start Meshcat
again, and you click on that, that's when I sometimes see it.
I thought I had--
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
Just every time you start up the notebook,
you have to start your--