Part two of our motion planning week.
I want to just quickly say a few of the key ideas
from last time to kind of launch us into this time.
So last time we started talking about motion planning.
Wow, that's a bad start.
Last time.
And there were a couple important ideas that came up.
One of them was almost hidden.
I didn't emphasize it particularly.
But one important idea was the idea of just configuration
space.
And we're going to lean on that more today.
So remember that I drew some plots.
One of them, for instance, I used
this example of a simple pendulum with two links
and a ball on the end of the hand that had q1, q2.
And so this picture, when I draw it in sort of the 2D world,
I guess in this case, this is what
we call our task space, or our world space, if you will,
or work space.
But-- and then we drew similar pictures
talking about the geometry in the-- if I drew it instead
of-- this is sort of in our canonical xz world axes, right?
But we also tried to draw the same geometry in our q1, q2
space, right?
And this is our configuration space.
Joint space, if you will, but more generally,
configuration of the robot.
And we drew-- this was-- if you call this, for instance,
a task space obstacle, then we could also draw--
this would be an excellent time to go multicolor, right?
Then we could also draw these regions in task space
in the configuration space.
You remember I had curves that looked a little bit like this,
right?
[DRAWING]
For this region, right?
And so what does this obstacle in configuration space
look like, right?
So if I take a particular set of joint angles, q1 and q2,
and my robot is in collision with this obstacle,
then I'm going to mark that similarly,
you know, for that configuration.
If it's in collision, I'll mark that
as an obstacle in the configuration space, right?
And that geometry is such a strong sort of-- there's
such a strong correlation there that we often
refer to these as configuration space obstacles.
OK?
So this notion of configuration space,
I drew it a handful of times, but I didn't maybe
call it out as important as it really is.
And we're going to use it more again today.
And one of the important things to observe
that this picture was meant to show
was that even geometries that are
sort of simple in the task space-- this is just
a half plane or a wall, right?
It's certainly a convex geometry, if you will,
in the task space.
It got a little curvy, a little bit more complicated
in task space.
Because if you think about it, the conditions
that make this hand run into that wall
depend on the sines and cosines of the kinematics, right?
So those warp my task space obstacles
into configuration space.
OK, so that was one really important idea.
And then we actually started motion planning
by talking about inverse kinematics.
And inverse kinematics is just trying to find one--
especially the type we wrote, the richer form,
was just trying to find some point in my configuration
space that I like, right?
By some objective.
And probably that is not in collision, right?
So we tried to write inverse kinematics as an optimization.
Say, find me some q.
Maybe that's close to my comfortable q.
That's the way I wrote it a bunch.
Maybe I want it to have that the end effector is
in a desired position.
So I put my kinematics as constraints, right?
And maybe I'd say that the minimum distance
to any collisions is greater than something like this,
right?
This is the kind of thing we wrote down
in our optimizations last time.
And then we said that kinematic trajectory optimization--
tradjopped, if you're-- the cool kids call it tradjopped--
then was just finding now, instead of finding one point,
was trying to find a series of points in the configuration
space.
And it may be a trajectory of points
in the configuration space that satisfied some optimization
problem.
So in the optimization view, the way I described it last time,
I said, let's try to find some trajectory.
And I'll parameterize it with parameters alpha.
You could describe your trajectory
as, let's say, a neural network that took t as an input
and put q as the output with weights alpha if you wanted to.
I wouldn't recommend it, probably for this case.
But if you think about things in that space,
this is just a parameterized class of curves.
And the ones that we use the most
are actually just polynomials.
These are polynomial bases.
So we just parameterized some class of curves.
Typically, they're defined well over some finite interval,
maybe some-- that's a nice curve.
It doesn't blow up or something in some finite interval.
And then we just did only a little bit more than this.
We said, let me find-- minimize over the parameters
of my curve.
You can have various interesting objectives, maybe shortest
path, maybe minimum time kind of objectives.
And you put some additional constraints,
like maybe my starting hand position
is where at the beginning of my trajectory.
So let's say q of alpha at 0.
And maybe my goal satisfies the kinematics at time t,
for instance.
And so you could put collision avoidance constraints
and joint limit constraints and all the other things
off the end of this.
I think the one thing-- I got a couple good questions
after lecture.
One thing I wish I had said better last time
was that this looks a lot like this.
If I'm going to hand this to my optimization package,
and it's solving it as a nonlinear optimization,
then it's doing things like taking the gradient,
partial f, partial q, for instance.
And that's how it's doing gradient descent
or sequential quadratic programming
to get to the bottom.
This is not much worse for the optimizer.
This is just saying now f of kin of sum of alpha i and i at time
0, I guess.
I can still take the gradient of this constraint with respect
to just alpha instead of q.
That's just you just use the chain rule
or call it back propagation if you
want to take the gradients of this thing with respect
to alpha instead of with respect to q.
And this is a similar type of constraint
you can hand to the optimizer.
And it can do sequential quadratic programming
or gradient descent or whatever it's
going to do to try to satisfy these constraints
and find the best alpha.
The one we did last time was a little bit fancier.
It also allowed you to search for the time horizon.
You didn't have to specify the time horizon.
So it made that a decision variable too.
And then you could put things like minimize time here.
But that's just a detail on top of that.
So everything we did in that space
was with nonlinear, nonconvex optimization.
In general, this is a nonconvex problem.
All right.
Which means it's subject to local minima.
And local minima sounds like-- I almost
want to call something more dramatic than local minima.
Local minima is not just you always get a solution
and it might not be the best solution.
In this case, local minima could mean
the solver was not able to satisfy all the constraints,
was not able to find a path even if the path exists.
It could just get stuck.
And I think there's two particular ways--
I want to sort of distinguish between the two particular ways
that that nonconvexity comes in because we're
going to try to address that today.
So I think there's-- I mean, they're related.
But there's two big sources.
I think one of them is from the kinematic constraints.
If you tell me that I'd like my q to satisfy some-- my hand
to be in some position, we know that, for instance, there
might be multiple solutions that achieve the same-- again,
my shoulder isn't mobile enough-- but there
might be multiple solutions.
And unfortunately, if you take a straight line between those two
solutions, it's unlikely that they're both
going to be good-- that the set of optimal solutions
is convex when you have complicated nonlinear
kinematics.
So just by the fact that this is a nonlinear function
is the first source.
But there's a second source, which is-- I
think obstacles are sort of a fundamentally different type
of nonconvexity, where you really-- it's
like there's multiple things you might have to try to do.
I might have to be above the table.
I might have to be below the table.
And you have somehow a discrete choice
to make about what are you going to do around that obstacle.
Let me just make that super clear with my little example
here.
So here's my nonlinear trajectory optimization.
I actually-- in this example, I left it going through--
I said all the points are out of collision.
But I was trying to make a point about that the segment--
you have to check the segment, too, to keep it out of collision.
But let me focus on the nonconvexity here.
So this is now a picture in configuration space.
So I just have a point-- call this my start-- another point
that's my goal that I'm trying to find in configuration space.
And there's a configuration space obstacle.
This is way simpler than what a real configuration space
obstacle would look like.
But let me just make the point.
And the solver is doing a good job of finding a path.
The goal here-- the objective is to find the shortest path
from the start to the goal.
And it's doing a pretty good job,
apart from cutting the corner.
And you can solve these in real time.
That's no big deal.
But because it's a local trajectory optimization
approach, it stuck in local minima.
Even if I were to pull the start and the goal over here,
once it starts thinking about going right
around the obstacle, it's not going to change its mind.
Because why is that?
So if I were to make an incremental change
to those points that went into this direction,
then it's going to get worse before it gets better.
Because it's going to get a big penalty for going
into the obstacle.
There's a better place over here.
But it has to get worse before it gets better.
And so the gradient-based methods
aren't going to find it.
OK.
So I can't do that.
So our goal today is to try to get around-- first,
I'm going to emphasize that type of non-convexity.
And we'll think about how we get around this kind
of non-convexity, too.
And the two big approaches we'll talk about--
we'll talk about sampling-based methods and ways
to try to do global optimization,
to try to do more than just look at the gradients.
That's my setup.
Is it clear?
OK, so people have incredibly good solutions to this.
Let me stop that.
And you might have seen some of them.
You've seen robots doing amazing things.
One of my favorites still is my start to the goal, written
as a simple optimization.
And that's what I was solving.
Forgot to use my slides.
But OK, this is a humanoid.
This is a video from James Kupner back in the early 2000s
of a humanoid reaching under-- that's
a lot of degrees of freedom, reaching under
to get a flashlight.
He's solving a big, complicated motion planning problem.
And there's another example here from the same time,
same guy, James Kupner, where he's actually
solving a geometry puzzle, like one of those things
that you find at parties.
And they're challenged to try to figure out
how to separate the two rings, right?
That's the canonical-- well, it's
one of the canonical geometry puzzles for motion planning.
Another one is the piano movers problem.
We're trying to-- if you have an apartment in Back Bay,
and you live on the third floor, and you have a piano,
how do you get it up there?
I think there's no solution.
But-- or it involves taking out windows or something.
But if there was a solution, these
would be the methods you would try to use to find it.
I'm going to put it back to there, just
so the animation stops.
OK, so how are we actually going to do that?
How do we solve these geometry puzzles
when this picture of local minima, I think, is real?
And it's sort of mysterious, maybe,
on the face of it, of how do you actually solve highly
non-convex geometry problems like that?
If I'm talking all about local minima, right?
And the two most famous algorithms,
the variations of this-- many things are-- there's
many, many, many algorithms in this family,
but they're maybe derived from these sources here.
One would be called the probabilistic roadmaps.
PRMs.
And the other is the rapidly exploring random trees.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
How many people know PRM and RRT?
OK.
That's helpful, thank you.
OK, so the big idea here-- I'm going
to actually start with this one.
It's a little bit-- I mean, I know chronologically this
is came first, but I think it's a little simpler
to talk about the RRT.
That's just my preference.
Different people have different preference, OK?
So the idea is simple.
We're going to get around this non-convexity by sampling, OK?
So if I have my configuration space obstacle,
my start and my goal, the basic idea of an RRT
is I'm going to-- don't worry about getting to the goal.
Maybe with some probability I'll try
to get straight to that goal, but I'd fail.
I'm going to pick a point.
I'm going to just define some region safely
around my workspace, OK?
And I'm going to start sampling.
I'll pick a point at random.
I'll take my start, and I'll see if I
can grow my goal to the start, OK?
So in practice, I draw a straight line to that goal.
And since I don't want to sort of teleport all the way
to some distant goal, I'm going to just take a motion
in the direction of that goal.
Now when I sample in configuration space again,
right, this is Q1, Q2, right, configuration space.
If when I sample, I land up in the obstacle, which
I can check quickly by putting my manipulator in those joint
angles, calling my collision detection engine,
and deciding if I'm in collision.
That's an easy check to do, relatively,
given the geometry engines.
But I'll just discard that right off the bat.
I'll say, I sampled there.
That was a bad choice.
Ignore it.
Let's keep going.
And then at some point, I'll sample over here.
I'll grow a little bit over here.
And as the name suggests, I'm going to grow a tree.
The exact version of the algorithm,
every time I pick a sample, I'm going
to look for the closest point in my existing tree
and try to extend from that closest
point in the existing tree towards my sample.
The details I'll put on the slide in a second here.
But the intuition is that I'm solving a non-convex problem
by choosing points at random.
In this case, right, I might grow here.
At some point, I might pick a point that would
cause me to grow into collision.
There's various choices you could do.
You could try to just grow up to the collision,
or you could just discard that sample and keep going.
And at some point, the hope is that I
will have picked enough of these random sub-goals
that my tree will come out, and I'll
have found my way all the way to the goal.
In low dimensions, it seems completely reasonable
that that would solve this problem.
What's surprising is that you can do it with a humanoid,
that it works surprisingly well in high dimensions.
Four problems that have a reasonably large configuration
space region and relatively large tunnels that will get you
from one place to the other.
If you have to thread a needle to try to find it,
then sampling is not a great strategy for that.
OK, so this is the picture from the original RRT paper
where they started there with their initial.
They've grown a tree.
You pick a random sample.
You extend towards that sample, and you add a point.
For those of you that are familiar,
I'm not going to spend that much time on this.
I'm just saying the basics because I
think the intuition is important,
and the details are easy to get.
OK, so I grow towards this tree.
Now, what's important is that that very simple strategy
can solve pretty hard problems.
This is actually a narrow passage kind of problem.
It will solve it eventually.
It just will take potentially a lot of samples.
So I had an initial guess that was in here
and a goal that was out here.
And eventually, if I draw enough samples
and grow a dense enough tree, then this algorithm
will grow these sort of characteristic RRT trees
and find paths if they exist.
This is a good example of a path where if I started here
and I was trying to go here, and my initial guess was trying
to take a straight line there, it
would be very, very hard for a trajectory optimization
approach to get this.
And this, by brute force, will eventually
find its way around it.
That's pretty cool.
OK, so it sounds like an extremely-- so it's actually,
it is an extremely simple algorithm.
But it is not, I would say, a naive algorithm.
There are some very clever things
that make it work, even though it
can be written in three lines and anybody can type it in
and make it work.
For instance, if I take this problem again
and I do a more naive thing, where I just say,
I'm going to take my current tree,
I'll pick a point on the current tree,
and I'll grow it in a random direction.
So just pick a point on the random tree,
grow it in a random direction, add a little edge.
That sounds like a very reasonable search type
strategy.
I'll just pick a random direction, grow.
That doesn't work at all.
That gives you these sort of hairball kind of pictures,
where with high probability, that
would be taking a random walk.
And random walks have this characteristic sort
of Brownian motion kind of picture,
that it would be a random walk that
would stay near the origin.
So there's something very clever about this sub-goal idea,
where I'm going to pick a point randomly in the space
and try to grow towards this distant goal.
That causes it to have this exploration behavior, which
avoids this naive sampling.
In particular, it has something called the Voronoi bias, which
is the best property of this thing.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
You know what the Voronoi regions of a graph
are, or a set of points are?
If I have a set of points in the plane,
then the Voronoi regions are the regions
associated with a point, which are-- if I have all these
points and I make them a little bigger so people in the back
can see.
So I've got some points in my plane.
If I were to draw the regions of all the places in the space
that are closest to this point, then
it's going to be-- there's going to be a line that separates it
from that point.
There's a line that separates it from this point and this point.
And I don't know.
Should have worked out better than it did, but there you go.
Something like this would be like the Voronoi region
associated with this, which is all
of the points in the plane that are closest to this point.
And there's a Voronoi region for this point,
something like that, and a Voronoi region for this one.
So that would be a Voronoi partition of the space,
is this notion of what are the sets that
are associated with the closest distance to each point.
Computing the Voronoi regions explicitly
is a little bit computationally intensive.
The RRT doesn't do that.
The RRT is just the algorithm I said,
just pick a random point, grow towards it.
But it turns out implicitly, because it
does-- when you pick a point, you
try to find the closest point on the tree,
it's acting as if it's trying to take a local evaluation
of the Voronoi region.
And that has this remarkable property
of causing it to explore, not just exploring like-- well,
let me show you.
So if you start growing the tree,
and I draw the Voronoi regions, which is relatively expensive,
the animation is harder than the algorithm,
then it starts at the initial condition.
And because the Voronoi regions of the cells on the outside
are large, with very high probability as it starts--
let me sort of reset a little bit here.
OK, that was a fail.
Let me-- all right, so as it starts,
the Voronoi regions on the outside are big.
So the specific thing that says is
that the chance, the probability of expanding some node
is proportional to the volume, or the size,
of the Voronoi region.
At the beginning of the search, the regions
that are unexplored have the largest Voronoi regions.
So with high probability at the beginning,
it's going to grow out into the free space.
As it continues, the free space gets filled up,
and there's some still large regions in the interior,
and it will start filling those in with probability.
And that sounds incredibly clever,
but it's just because it does this nearest neighbor query.
It's like when you're reading a book in literature,
and they tell you all the things the author meant,
and I'm not sure if the author really meant it.
But it's like endowing it with these incredible properties
post hoc.
But it's beautiful.
So in practice, these things will expand out
into the unexplored regions, and then it
will fill in all the nooks and crannies.
And if there is a region, like this little tunnel in my bug
trap example, then it will eventually sample there,
and it will eventually grow.
So this idea of the Voronoi bias is one important idea.
And the other super important idea
is that it's probabilistically complete,
which means that if there's a path from the start
to the goal, then it will be found with probability 1
as the number of samples goes to infinity.
That last part's a bit of a bummer.
And it's actually not that hard to make an algorithm that
has the probabilistic completeness property.
In fact, even the naive one is technically
probabilistically complete.
It's just going to take a long time
to find this path to the goal.
But that's an interesting class of algorithms,
to say I want to guarantee that eventually I
will find a path if it exists.
There's tons of variations and extensions
that I'm not going to list.
But you can imagine, for instance,
that you might do better by growing a tree from the start
and backwards from the goal at the same time
and just let them connect.
That's extremely effective, used often in practice.
And there's a whole pile of heuristics
that make these things work really well.
Any questions about RRT at the high level here?
Yeah.
OK, so the RRT-- like I said, people plan humanoids.
They will plan on the fly.
You can have a mobile manipulator
that goes into a new environment and will
start planning with RRTs.
But they do spend some amount of-- especially
for hard search problems, they can potentially
do a lot of computation to find a path.
If you're going to do the same-- like in our clutter clearing
example, if you're going to be moving
in the same environment over and over and over again,
it makes sense that you'd want to reuse some of the graph
search, some of this tree that you've built,
to do a multi-query version of this.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
This would often be called multi-query planning.
Then that's where the PRM comes in, the probabilistic roadmap.
The probabilistic roadmap basically
says I'm going to build a graph in the first place.
I'm going to separate my computation into first
the roadmap construction, where I'll go ahead and build
some complicated graph.
I'll show you a couple pictures of it in the first step.
And then when it's time to plan, I'm
just going to try to find the shortest path on the graph.
So imagine building one big network roadmap once
and then planning on it separately.
And this was actually published a few years before the RRT.
In my mind, I like talking about it in this order.
So now I've got my simple configuration space obstacles.
And I'll pick a point at random.
And I'll just look around and try
to connect it to all of its nearest neighbors.
I'll draw an edge to all of its nearest neighbors.
And I'll make this graph.
And the offline phase is just to build up this roadmap
by picking points at random.
There's no start.
There's no goal.
Pick points at random.
Just try to connect it to the neighbors,
make a nice, dense network.
And then at query time, I have an initial--
the robot's in some initial condition.
It's got some true goal.
All I do is try to connect that up
to the closest point on the graph
and do graph search in my graph to try to find the path.
It's very similar to the RRT.
But it makes sense if you're going to do repeated plans.
And you might as well add that node
and add that edge to the graph.
And this thing can have kind of a--
I call it lifelong learning, if you want.
This little thing will continually
sort of fill out the regions of space
that you're actually experiencing.
And it can be very, very efficient.
So for instance, there's a company now
called Real-Time Robotics that does these PRMs on the fly
from in perception by putting all this stuff into the GPU.
PRMs and RRTs are both--
and the collision queries that go along with it
have been highly optimized with GPU implementations
and the like.
This is actually specialized hardware.
I think it's FPGA.
I actually forgot now if it's FPGA or even ASIC or something.
But they're talking and saying that planning doesn't
start until I hit the red button.
And it plans with no pause, no delay.
And this can be made to be very performant to the point
where he's going to come in and shuffle the environment.
People can walk through the environment.
It's doing planning on the fly with highly optimized PRM RRT.
Yes?
So from there on, it's kind of hard
to get the exact pattern because it's temporary.
What kind of process is it for you?
Good.
[INAUDIBLE]
So I have a slide to show--
yeah, so there's something that I think a lot of people--
I tend to call the RRT dance, which
is that if you're trying to find a path from the start
to the goal to pick this up, this strategy,
you might do something like this.
You know?
And that's real.
That happens all the time.
I put a video in the slide somewhere that will show that.
So sample-based planning gives random paths.
There are post-processing algorithms
like you just alluded to.
You could, for instance, take any plan you get out of there
and call a trajectory optimization.
You could call eukinematic trajectory optimization.
That's a great way to do it.
The sample-based community tends to do things like short-cutting.
[WRITING]
So if you found your big, complicated plan that
was visiting more places than it should to get to the goal,
and maybe there was just one obstacle over here,
but it decided to do a little dance,
then the short-cutting type algorithms will, for instance--
they tend to be very probabilistic.
It's kind of the theme here.
And very approximate.
But they'll just say, I'll take my path.
I'll pick a couple points on my path.
If I could draw a straight line to them,
then I'll just remove all the ones that were there.
And now I've added the straight line.
I'll pick two more random points.
If I can do this, then I'll just erase this.
These are kind of a heuristic thing
that's very fast to implement and gives you
pretty good results.
If you have an edge that goes through this--
so people typically-- and this is
one of the things we'll talk a little bit about today--
people typically try to verify this just
by running the collision engine on many samples
along the segment.
But there are more advanced approaches
that can try to guarantee that you don't have any collisions
on the line segment.
[INAUDIBLE]
I think at some point you switch to an optimization
to smooth it out.
But I think you'd be surprised how often people
send piecewise constant curves to their robot.
Almost certainly the controller is
smoothing it out a little bit.
But--
OK, so that's a cool set of ideas.
I mean, a super powerful set of ideas
to use sampling to sort of get around
these hard non-convexities.
They also get around the kinematic non-convexities.
Because when I sample points, I just
have to call the function.
So if I have a sample point in joint space,
I can just call my kinematics on that function
and put my robot into its pose and check constraints
in task space.
I could check whether the real hardware
is running into the obstacle in the original task space.
So by virtue of going to points instead of trajectories
and doing sampling, they're sort of solving
both of those problems.
If you do want to play with more and more of these tools,
the OMPL, the Open Motion Planning Library,
is a fantastic resource that has just
a long library of all the different RRT PRM variants.
It's in ROS that you can connect it
to Drake and collision queries.
It's a great resource for just even seeing
the list of planners, even getting your head
around the sense of different types of planners people
are using.
There's the PRM.
There's different single query planners, the RRT,
expansive space trees.
A lot of the different algorithms that are out there
are available there.
So highly recommend it.
Even if you just look at the website,
it's already super valuable.
We have a bunch of sample-based planners
that have been written at TRI that we're pushing to Drake now,
hopefully, but not quite in time for this lecture, I ask.
So when it's there--
I mean, if anybody needs it, I have
versions that I could share that are just not as polished.
But it has the RRT.
The bi-RRT is going in both directions, bi-directional RRT.
PRMs, we have all the basics in there.
Here's the RRT dance.
And the point was made nicely in a paper by Sertash and others.
This is the RRT applied to the PRM.
I mean, you will really see robots do that sometimes.
It's like, oh.
It's kind of embarrassing.
The other one that's really embarrassing
is when you have a beautiful manipulation robot system,
and it goes, and it acts like it's picked something up,
but it has nothing in its hand.
And it continues through the rest of the motion
as if it's like, oh.
We should never see these things again.
But that's real.
OK.
So I mean, that's just a very quick version of it.
But I think this idea of the RRT,
but I think this idea of sampling
is, I think, easy to communicate and very powerful.
And it opens up a whole class of algorithms
that you can play with.
And people use them in industry all the time.
It's real.
Let me tell you a bit about the optimization
view of being more global.
OK?
I want to tell you--
spend the second half of the lecture
on global optimization-based planning.
This is one that I'm super excited about right now.
We've been working hard on it in my group.
So I'll give you a slightly biased version of this.
But I do think we've made some nice improvements
and to what you can do with motion planning here.
So I want to tell you that story.
Maybe I'll tell it first with code.
So if I go back to this simple example, my red box,
I'll run my--
I'm going to run--
so this is-- the work I'm going to tell you about
is motion planning around obstacles
with convex optimization.
So I just talked about how the problem was clearly non-convex.
I'm going to try to do it with convex optimization.
And that is supposed to be surprising.
So here's the same old example.
And I'm just solving a convex optimization problem.
But now it solves beautifully to global optimality.
So I'll tell you the basics of how that works.
And it's not magic.
It's just putting together some good ideas.
But I think it opens up what we can do with some of our motion
planning approaches.
In particular, the advantage of these optimizing-based planners
is that you avoid RRT dance kind of things.
And if you care about-- like I told you with the DexEye
example the other day, if time is money,
then having the benefits of kinematic trajectory
optimization combined with the globalness of planning
is the dream.
OK, so how did I do that simple example?
And where did I put my chalk?
Jeez, oh, Pete's.
OK.
I said that that was a non-convex problem
and that there's non-convexity everywhere in the motion
planning problem.
So how can we possibly do around obstacles
with convex optimization?
So saying it's non-convex is a little disingenuous.
Any problem can be made convex if you just lift it
to a high enough dimension.
So typically, it's not practical to do so,
but it's theoretically interesting to know
that you could.
So really, I want to dial that in a little bit more.
What I think is important is that we
found a convex formulation that is compact and efficient.
So we didn't have to raise it to some ridiculous dimensionality
that would be impossible to solve,
but we have an efficient convex formulation.
And the way that we did it in that particular way,
that I coded it up in that particular example,
is I have my configuration space obstacle.
And I'm going to first decompose the space.
We'll talk about how to do that in a bit.
I'm going to manually decompose the space
into a couple different regions.
I said that the RRT did this automatically
without doing any explicit decomposition.
I'm going to do the explicit decomposition, but it's OK.
You can do that.
It's not the fastest part of the algorithm,
but it's approachable.
And then for each possible segment,
or region in the optimization problem,
in the configuration space, I'm going
to put a small kinematic trajectory optimization
problem inside it.
So I'm actually going to solve lots
of different kinematic trajectory optimization
problems all at the same time, which sounds bad.
But it can be made very efficient, in particular
because this is the best type of kinematic trajectory
optimization problem, because it only
has to stay-- all of its constraints
are convex, once I've made a convex decomposition
of the space.
Saying that this curve stays inside a convex region
is an easy thing to do.
Staying inside a non-convex region is a hard thing to do.
And then I'm going to build a little graph out
of these regions.
So if I call this region 1 here, I'll make a little graph.
If I call this region 2, region 3, and 4.
Maybe I have 3 and 4.
If those regions touch in the configuration space,
then I'll draw an edge between the two.
It's actually a bidirectional graph in this case.
2 and 3 touch.
3 and 4 touch.
1 and 4 touch.
I could have probably put 4 there.
That would have been a little prettier.
And then I'm going to do the same sort of thing as the PRM.
I'll take my start.
I'll take my goal.
I'll add my start and my goal here.
Add whatever things it's touching.
I'll put an edge to it there.
This was in 4 and 3, I guess.
And I'm going to solve a graph search problem.
But unlike the way that the PRM solves a graph search problem,
I'm going to solve a particular type of graph search that
is actually solving the kinematic trajectory
optimization at the same time as it's finding
the shortest path on the graph.
So let's just understand it at that level.
I'll tell you how that works just a little bit in a second.
But this is like a sampling-based approach.
I'll show you the direct connections
to the sampling-based approach.
But it's more explicitly saying there
is a combinatorial problem in motion planning.
You have to decide, am I going left or right?
And if I write down that combinatorial problem,
then I should use graph search type tools to accommodate it.
And what's nice is that there's actually--
when you think about graph search,
you probably think about A* and Dijkstra's
and these kind of methods.
But you can solve graph search with a linear program
and optimization-based approaches, too.
And so there are ways to jointly solve
the graph search and the kinematic trajectory
optimization at the same time and make that very efficient.
It's not magic.
It's just explicitly writing the combinatorial problem
and the continuous problem down in one formulation
and then doing a lot of work to make
that formulation very efficient.
So I won't go into the math of the optimization.
But if you want to read more, but the basic intuition
is we take the optimization view of the shortest path
on a graph.
I could find just from the start to goal on any ordinary graph.
I can write that down as an optimization problem
in addition to a standard graph search,
kind of the way you think about a standard A* kind of algorithm.
And the mathematical background of this,
we call it the graph of convex sets.
Because there's PRM, there's RRT.
We needed a three-letter acronym.
So ours is GCS.
That's the brand.
And the way to think about how do you
do a continuous optimization at the same time
as a discrete optimization is you basically--
the abstraction we have is that every time you
visit a node on the graph, you pick one element out
of a convex set.
Don't think about this as obstacles or anything
for a minute.
This is just an abstract mathematical framework
where you say, I'm going to do graph search,
but I get to pick one element out of a convex set
every time I visit.
And I'm allowed to put edge costs.
The standard shortest path could have an edge cost on each edge.
Now I'm allowing the edge cost to be
a function of the continuous variables.
And we can put constraints and other things like that too.
We've made a lot of progress on having strong optimization
formulations for that abstract problem.
And that abstract problem is exactly-- this thing
I drew on the board, we just transcribe it.
This is now the motion planning problem,
where our regions are-- the blue regions in the last
are the blue regions here.
But we put and we make a graph based on what is just touching.
And embed in each of those a B-spline,
a kinematic trajectory optimization problem.
You remember I mentioned the B-spline
has that convex hull property?
We leverage that convex hull property.
So it's the parameters of the B-spline
that form the convex set.
You know, the intuition I want to make sure you definitely
get is that we can combine this continuous search
with the graph search.
And when you pick an edge on the shortest path on the graph,
then it implies that some constraints
must be true, which make those curves connect.
And you can make them continuous up to arbitrary degree.
And you can scale time similarly all in the framework.
Yeah?
So the parameters of the spline are the convex set?
It's not the boundaries of the regions?
So that's an awesome question.
So what is the convex set?
So in this picture over here, I have this abstract notion
of the set.
So it lives in some space called big X.
What is big X in this picture?
It is not this region.
So it's the Cartesian product of that region times
the number of control points.
I want to say that one element in that set
means a choice of all of the control points,
and they all must live in that set.
So it's only a little bit different
than the original picture, but it's an important difference.
Thank you for asking.
Is that clear?
Yeah?
OK.
What's cool is that that solves really hard problems
with convex optimization.
So this is like two Iwas playing Twister, where
you have to put a mug on the shelf,
and you've got to reach under the other Iwa.
And that is being solved by jointly solving
the convex optimization on the graph
and the kinematic trajectory optimization.
And this is on the robots upstairs.
And this is actually solving even a richer version
of the problem than I already suggested.
It is choosing what order to pick up the mugs.
And the combinatorial decisions of the task
are also being embedded in this graph, in this big graph.
And it's getting smooth, beautiful motions out.
We have a handful that we put together for the paper
we're writing.
But we want to have smooth, beautiful, time optimal,
if you want, motions coming out of the robot.
That's the opposite of the RRT dance.
That's a little-- that would mean--
my decomposition probably wasn't very good on that one.
But-- yeah?
So is the number of control points
in each convex set fixed?
We choose the number of control points, yeah.
But we allow it to stretch in time.
But it's like how there's a representational power
of the curve in that set.
So how do we choose how many control points
we should get in?
Yeah, so the question was, how do we
choose how many control points?
The more you give it, the more curvy it can be inside the set.
But the more expensive the optimization will be.
So it's a trade-off.
I'll talk about the different gaps.
So what I would like to say is that if an optimal path exists--
if a path exists, we find the optimal path.
We can almost say that.
We can say, if the path exists, we
find the optimal path as parameterized
by the Bzier curves in the decomposition.
So there are a few gaps.
And that is one of them.
In theory, I would need an infinite number of control
points to say any possible curve could live inside the set.
The problem is-- or the interesting part
of the problem is that I talked all about how-- maybe it's--
it's long gone.
But I talked about how convex obstacles in task space
turn into non-convex obstacles in configuration space.
So how did we get those convex regions?
There's an algorithm that we're going to have you explore.
It was released moments ago for your p-set,
which is this approximate convex decomposition algorithm.
And it's related closely to the sampling-based ideas
that we used in PRM and RRT.
But the idea is that when I pick a point at random
in my configuration space, I'm going
to go ahead and do a little extra work, which
is to try to find a big convex region that
is collision-free around that point.
And you'll understand, I think, by the end of the p-set
that it does this by an alternation of finding
half spaces, which separate the sample point
from the obstacles.
And then once you have the half space regions,
you do a maximum inscribed ellipse,
and then you alternate.
The details you'll see closely on the p-set.
We'll work through half of it.
We won't make you do the inscribed ellipse,
but we'll make you do the other part.
So this is an efficient optimization.
It's a large-scale quadratic program
and a really small convex optimization.
And when we did this initially a few years ago,
Robin Dietz was the inventor of this algorithm.
He was trying to do it for Atlas walking around.
And he cared very much about finding big places for Atlas
to step from raw perception.
So he wanted an algorithm, a convex decomposition algorithm
that could scale to raw pixels.
And he accomplished it, enough to work on raw sensor data.
This is a version of that.
But as the robot was walking around,
he was trying to decompose the space into regions
that it could step on or touch.
And we had these convex decomposition type algorithms.
So that was a tool that we had done for walking.
And it turns out then that if you
have convex obstacles in your configuration space,
then the picture is going to look a bit like this.
These are the gaps here, the gaps
that prevent us from saying it's globally optimal.
Because we're going to just do an approximate convex
decomposition.
And if you think about the roadmap generation
phase of the PRM, we're going to do something like that here.
But every time we pick a point, we're
going to grow an iris region.
And we'll end up with an approximate decomposition
of the space.
But then we get to solve a continuous set of curves.
Whereas the PRM was only walking along
the discrete edges in the graph, and therefore
was restricted to the motions of that graph,
here we have enough room for the kinematic trajectory
optimization to do its optimization.
And we get beautiful curves.
Importantly, when you get to things with dynamics,
which we haven't talked about in here,
the kinematic trajectory optimization typically
doesn't include the dynamics of the robot.
But if you have dynamic constraints
and other constraints, optimization-based frameworks
handle that naturally, where sampling-based frameworks
can struggle with those kind of constraints.
OK, so we can't quite say what I want to say.
We say that we're guaranteed to be collision-free because
of this iris algorithm.
We can guarantee that once I'm in the curve in that region,
I won't have a collision.
I don't have to check the line segment
at a bunch of different samples.
I have this nice property.
And then within the convex decomposition
and within the class of curves, we
can be complete and globally optimal.
So this is the-- back when we were doing it
with the big mixed integer problem,
this is Robin's version of it.
So you have your original obstacle-based environment.
And the first step is you compute
these approximate convex decompositions.
This is the iris algorithm that you'll implement.
And then once you have those decompositions,
you can plan optimal motions.
[AUDIO OUT]
That particular environment used to run
as one of our unit tests on an early version of Drake
that was running on the build servers in my office.
And there was a bug for a while that it
would publish its visualization to the LCM channel
across the subnet.
So everybody on the third floor used
to see trees appear randomly and quadrotors flying around.
And they're like, where is this coming from?
And there was a long time where I would just randomly
see that pop up on my screen.
So that brings up fond memories to me.
So that was the case where the obstacles are in task space--
or the obstacles are convex.
And that's the case we'll have you do.
But there's a more sophisticated version
of that, thinking about how do you do it for configuration
space obstacles.
The original algorithm assumed convex.
Now there's new extensions for C space.
And one of them is just using nonlinear optimization.
And it's fast.
And I'll run it right here.
There's another one that gives actual certifications
using sums of squares optimization.
And that's guaranteed to be collision free.
But it's slower.
And I won't run it here.
,
So I was like, how do I visualize
collision free obstacles in a way that you can understand?
So this is a pretty good visualization.
So you've got some weird q1, q2.
There's a weird collision free collision region,
which is these two EOs smacking into each other.
And it makes this very non-convex shape.
And this is a visualization.
As you move around through the C-free,
you can see them not in collision.
Here's the version I put up last night here--
this morning.
Blurs together.
Instead, I made an iris region, which
was seeded with a point inside the shelf.
And I get a convex polytope in the joint space.
And I'm thinking, how do I make you guys understand
what that region looks like?
And I was going to plot it in 3D.
And it's completely uninterpretable in joint space.
My brain does not understand what's happening there.
So this is what I did instead.
Is I just basically-- I wrote a little program that
would basically visit random boundaries of the joint space.
And I just plotted it here.
So basically, this robot is just walking around
inside one of the regions, one of the iris regions.
And you can kind of see that it carves out
a nice large part of the state space.
And it's not in collision.
It'd be nice if it walked a different dimension.
I guess randomness-- oh, yeah, there it goes.
Up and down, right?
So it's got this nice sort of joint space region.
You might wonder, what if a convex decomposition of this--
this is a pretty narrow part of this joint space,
of the configuration space, too, because of the collision
geometry.
But it fills out a nice big region.
And in practice, we found in all those motion planning examples
we did, we only needed a handful of regions.
It's a pretty surprisingly small number of regions.
It's also working with the original collision
geometry of the robot.
So for the kinematic trajectory optimization before,
I had to turn it into a sphere to make
sure it got out of local minima.
None of that here.
It's still the simplified geometry, but it's good.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Good.
So that's exactly the right question.
He says, so the non-convexity that's
coming from the kinematics-- so the way
we're doing this here is we are building
the graph in joint space, not in end-effector space.
But we're certifying that every point in that region
is valid in task space.
So we are addressing your concern.
But we're using Iris to go across that non-linear boundary
of kinematics.
The graph of convex sets cannot go through--
the convex optimization cannot go
through the non-linear transformation,
but the Iris can.
So we have to pre-compute any of the non-linearities away.
[INAUDIBLE]
That's what I tried to do.
Actually, I tried to even walk along the vertices.
But so the way that I've implemented Iris today,
it kicks out a stupid number of vertices, basically.
So it would have been a great video that went--
[LAUGHTER]
So I was like, you know what?
I'm going to just make it go in random directions instead.
You caught me.
That was the first idea.
If the robot is [INAUDIBLE] or it loses a joint,
does the configuration space change in a predictable way?
Or would you have to pre-compute it?
That's an awesome question.
So the question is, what happens--
so your question was removing the gripper,
but even more relevant maybe is picking up an object.
And you suddenly want to not collide
with the object in the sink.
So I think that does change the configuration space.
And we haven't addressed that yet.
This is a hot off the press algorithm.
I think for the case of the clutter clearing,
or the DexEye workflow, or any of the million robots
out there that are moving in a relatively similar environment
all day long--
the multi-query case.
Any case where you can afford to do some pre-computation
and then optimize very quickly, we've dialed that in well.
And I think the next round, which
I'm happy to have you guys think about,
is to think about how to dynamically change
those regions, for instance.
Maybe straight from perception.
Maybe from-- maybe you can crop regions.
There's all kinds of clever things to do.
[INAUDIBLE]
We seed them-- yeah, you can see them in either place.
But they have to be seeds in Q, in the joint space.
But we typically seed them by solving an inverse kinematics
problem, just because that's easier for the human.
[INAUDIBLE]
So that's one to many [INAUDIBLE]
If you seed it in--
like, if doing this kinematics, then
we cover it in [INAUDIBLE]
So you're worried about--
so I think there are sampling-based approaches
that could try to fill out the space
and have a probabilistic completeness kind of guarantee.
But we found, actually, that--
I mean, there's a lot of regions you probably
don't want to visit.
So we found it's more useful to pick the ones
and use IK to sort of filter out some of those crazy regions.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK, yeah, so you can--
right, you can sample directly in Q to grow the regions
if you need to.
That's true.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
That's a great question.
Do humans do graph of convex sets, or RRT, or PRM?
You'll get a different answer from everybody you ask,
I think.
I would guess that they are not doing this.
I would have said that the sample-based things,
like PRMs and RRTs, would be a very weird thing
to think about a human doing.
But I've had conversations with people like Josh Tenenbaum
who say that the cognitive scientists are actually
pretty excited about the RRT kind of view of the world
as a cognitive model.
Still feels weird to me.
I don't know.
I think we are certainly a parallel processing machine.
And maybe we can do a lot of things like that.
If you ask me, I would think that-- and this is speculation.
I think we're probably not solving the geometric puzzles
that we're asking our motion planning to solve.
I'm going to make that point at the very end.
This is a harder problem than humans are probably solving.
This is when you're asked to separate the puzzles out
and stuff like this.
And humans do that rarely and not particularly well.
I think we are much more approximate,
and we're not afraid of bumping into things.
And I think much more simple strategies
can solve a lot of problems.
But apparently some cognitive psychologists like RRT.
It's all good.
I would love to know more about that.
I don't know as much as I would like.
So just to give you-- since I kind of advertised that,
let me just tell you what it can do and what it can't do.
So not every kinematic trajectory optimization
fits in that framework.
I have to restrict ourselves to things that are convex,
costs and objectives.
But it's a pretty large library.
If you use Bzier polynomials and Bzier splines
and all the right tricks and tools,
then you can minimize time.
You can minimize path length.
You can minimize some sense of energy in it.
You can make trajectories smooth up
to arbitrary derivative degree.
You can avoid collisions by being inside the iris
regions of this picture.
And those are guaranteed for all time.
There's no sampling-based concerns, right,
of clipping a corner or something like that,
which is a big deal.
I think lots of people suffer those clipped corners
in practice.
You can put velocity constraints.
I really want the next thing to say acceleration constraints,
but we don't know how to put acceleration constraints on.
That's non-convex so far.
Maybe there's a problem we can crack.
But you can put bounds on the time.
You can give it initial conditions,
final-- those kind of things.
That's a little bit bigger than that,
but that's the main library of costs and constraints
that we can put on here.
But in that regime, we're solving to global optimality
mostly with convex optimization.
And even that, I want to be super clear
that it's actually a mixed integer program where
the convex relaxation is almost always tight.
So it's not guaranteed to solve to optimality
with convex optimization, but in practice, we
find it almost always does.
And we've done a lot of work to try to compare it to PRM.
And this is the shortcutting that [INAUDIBLE]
about.
Take my crazy PRM and try to find the shortcutting.
And how does it compare in terms of time and the message?
This is an unoptimized PRM.
I think people have more optimized PRMs out there.
But it's a good PRM.
It's just not super GPU-enabled and stuff.
We tend to find better paths.
That's what you would expect.
We're using optimization instead of just sampling.
Even then, the shortcutting PRM, we're doing better than that.
And we can often find them in less time than the PRM.
In particular, the one I really like
is that there's some things you can do on the graph.
There's some observations you can
make by just looking at the graph
without even thinking about the continuous variables that
allow you to rule out lots of possibilities very quickly
and kind of pre-process yourself into a very simple problem.
And some problems, if there's not big branching,
can just go solve almost instantly.
So we get all these little examples
of complicated bimanual--
I like the bimanual case because most PRM RRT algorithms
don't scale well.
Sampling scales surprisingly well.
I wouldn't have expected it to work in 10, 12 dimensions.
But when you start getting to 14 dimensions,
or if you put it on a mobile base,
and you've got 17 dimensions, maybe you've got a torso,
you're up to 20, most people don't--
you'll see, actually, most robots,
if you see a bimanual robot, almost always you look for this.
One arm will be fixed.
It'll move the other arm.
And then it'll stop.
And it'll move this arm.
Almost always.
Or they'll be not moving close to each other.
So yeah, just to wrap that up and say it's super clear.
So what I'm advocating here is a change from the PRM,
where you sample and make the roadmap,
to every time you make one of those samples,
you grow a region.
But to some extent, everything you can do with the PRM,
you could do this way.
It's just trying to make those samples into big regions
so that you have room for the continuous optimization
to do its work.
You pay a price.
That's an expensive step at the offline.
Although it's even comparable to building a denser roadmap.
Because we can make 10 iris regions in the time
you'd make 10,000 regions over here.
And that's what people tend to do is make super dense PRMs.
And we get better motions.
All right, sorry for the advertisement.
Having said all that, I actually don't
like collision-free motion planning
as a problem formulation.
This is the point.
So I want to just make sure that I land at the end
that this is kind of a weird problem.
It's probably not the problem humans are solving.
Anybody know this one?
This is from my childhood.
It was a little after people played with sticks and stones.
About a little bit before iPads.
So it's a little game called Operation.
Yeah, thank you.
It's annoying.
It's annoying to have in the house.
But basically, you have to pick out the bones out
of this poor patient.
And if your leads touch the side of the cell,
you kill the patient or something.
It goes, eh.
And mom and dad go, eh.
OK, that's a weird game.
And it's probably not how we move through the world.
So I think a better formulation.
So as we get past the core material of the class,
we're going to enter this boutique lectures.
And I'll ask you guys for feedback.
And we can choose which ones we're
going to cover of the more advanced topics.
But task and motion planning I've mentioned.
Belief space planning was a possibility.
Planning through contact is another possibility
as a more advanced topic.
And it's something that I care a lot about.
But it's, I think, a richer formulation
for these kind of things.
You shouldn't be afraid of bumping into the world
all the time.
There's a bunch of projects.
This is one at TRI.
We're trying to build something kind of like Baymax.
We call it Puno, which is soft and cuddly
in Japanese, I guess.
And we have all kinds of prototypes.
If you were to come over to TRI, you
see all kinds of prototypes of different soft sensors
and soft structures that are instrumented
that try to make it so the robots don't
break when you do rich planning through contact.
And they're safe to interact with humans.
Good.
So that is the second half of the motion planning.
Allows us to think about how to address
the non-convexity of the motion planning problem.
PRM's-- oh, yeah, go ahead.
Yeah, just a general question.
Sorry.
Like, you say, could a free motion planning
be non-convex?
And then you could think about it
from a trajectory organization.
I feel like you can solve the trajectory organization
in the computing space.
But I feel like if you were to think about humans,
that maybe you solve the trajectory organization
problem in the workspace.
But then once you have the gradient,
you just use Jacobian to get back to the Jacobian.
So you go back to the configuration.
Do you feel like that is [INAUDIBLE]??
Good.
So the question is, if the configuration space
is so messy and the task space is so much cleaner,
in general-- we've done the big, boxy objects, right,
where engineers-- until AI designs everything,
we've got nice rectilinear structures.
Why not plan in the task space and then map it back
to the joint space?
I think that is viable.
I think there's, of course-- then the reason it's often
preferred to plan in the joint space
is because the mapping from joint space to workspace
is the good one, is the forward kinematics.
And going backwards is inverse kinematics.
But you're right.
We can do differential, inverse kinematics, and the like.
I do think it would be more-- if I think about how a human
plans-- and I have no reason to have
a strong feeling about this.
But it feels very natural to think
I plan a fairly simple motion of my end effector
and then execute it.
I do think that can be very natural.
[INAUDIBLE]
So the statement was that maybe the gradients in the task space
could be reasonable.
But then the question is, what if I
have to worry about where my elbow is
while I'm reaching through?
Right?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
I think if you were to not think about the arm
and only plan in end effector space,
that's kind of some of the problems
we had with my simple example, where eventually the elbow
would fold in on itself and the like.
So I think you need to think about both jointly in order
to solve the full problem.
If you need-- and I think maybe humans
don't do that very often.
I think most of the time we probably don't do that.
But to solve the full problem as specified,
you would have to solve both of them jointly.
And you can choose to do it with the forward kinematics,
or you could choose to do it with the inverse kinematics.
And I think most people choose the forward kinematics.
But I agree, for more approximate methods that
maybe don't worry about making some collisions,
then it might be very natural to live in the task space.
[INAUDIBLE]
Good?
OK.
See you next time.