th
in the chapter.
And you can and should play with it.
I put that into the systems framework.
And so just to think of it from a systems perspective,
we had this diff_ik system, which
took in a desired spatial velocity of the gripper.
It also had to take in the current q, the EWA positions.
And it output v, the joint velocities,
the EWA joint velocities.
I have to write bigger.
And we'd use the pseudo-inverse in the simple case,
or a quadratic program as the generalization,
in order to implement that differential inverse kinematics
system.
To wire that all up, though, if you remember,
we have the station here, the manipulation station,
which takes in desired positions.
Right?
So to make this all work, there's
actually one more block in the middle, which
is just doing an integration.
You give it some initial conditions,
and it will take these desired velocities out and integrate
them back into desired positions.
The station had an output port for the EWA position, which
has to get wired back up into this.
That's all good.
We have direct access to the EWA position.
And then in the full demonstration,
this came from a trajectory.
We had our initial pose trajectory,
and we took a derivative of that pose trajectory
to get a velocity trajectory, a spatial velocity trajectory.
So this took that spatial velocity,
and then this trajectory system just
plays out as a function of time, the spatial velocities, which
get pulled at every time into this differential IK pseudo
inverse.
And the whole thing went around, and we have a complete demo.
It's actually kind of interesting
that if you were to simulate a little too long,
for instance, then this thing would run out
of interesting things to say.
We've only defined a trajectory up to the final segment
time of our plan.
So your mileage may vary if you try to keep simulating,
because you could just define this more carefully,
but I didn't.
So you could simulate that farther and get a little off.
One other thing just to say about that,
because we're going to build on this this week,
but there's two multi-body plants flying around here,
at least two.
But you can imagine having more.
So inside here is one plant, which
is simulating the physics of the world.
Our physics engine is buried inside this station diagram.
But the diff IK system also needs
to call the kinematics methods of a plant.
So there's another plant that's being used inside here,
and they're not the same.
And that's OK.
So this plant has the robot and the red brick and the bins
and all the details of the world.
It is one mathematical model of the world,
and it has everything inside it.
Diff IK is using a more narrow view of the world.
It has a mathematical model of the world
that only thinks about the arm and ignores everything else.
And this is not unusual.
This is not an artifact of diff IK.
You could think, for any simulation,
your robot might have some internal model of what's
going on, and then there's what the real world is giving you.
So you could think about this as sort of the internal model
that the robot has of what's going on.
And in this case, it's very simple.
It just pretends there's nothing except for the robot arm.
And there's another one out there,
which is this is our simulation of the real world.
So there's cases where we see multiple different plants
flying around, and that's OK.
It's just different models that are used for different pieces.
Does that make sense?
OK, so the big thing that was the assumption last time
is that we assumed that somebody gave me
the position of the red-- the initial position
of the red brick.
And in fact, we did that before this diagram was even
created so that I could-- before I even make this whole system,
I can design this trajectory.
And that's just a fixed thing over time.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: So you're talking about the two
EWA positions are the same thing?
PROFESSOR: Yes, so this is the desired EWA position.
This is commanded.
I forget exactly what I called it in the diagram.
I'll see it in just a second.
This is the commanded, and this is the measured.
And those are joint positions of the EWA.
Yeah, thank you for asking.
[TYPING]
OK, so there was this very artificial assumption
that the robot woke up and knew exactly where the red brick
was, the pose of the red brick in the world.
And the goal of the next few lectures
is to remove that assumption.
In particular, in the manipulation station--
so here, I can answer your question now.
It was called the EWA position on the way in,
and it's EWA position measured on the way out.
And we were also using these--
if we wanted to write this completely,
we were sort of using the cheat ports on the manipulation
station.
We were saying, go ahead and tell me
the exact position in the world of the red brick.
And I put those in the manipulation station simulation
so that they're available, and we can write algorithms
against them.
But you don't have those in the real world.
So in the hardware version of the manipulation station,
those ports are not there.
Nobody's going to tell you exactly where the red brick is.
What you have instead are cameras as sensors.
And we have to now start using those cameras
to infer the position of the red brick,
and of course, much, much more down the line.
So the demonstration, by the time we're done,
is not server-- oh, there we go.
OK, good-- is going to look fairly similar.
I've upgraded from a red brick to a mustard bottle.
So that's good.
That's progress.
You'll also see there's a bunch of cameras around the scene.
That's new.
I had ignored them.
And you'll also see that there's some perception happening here.
So this is a point cloud that we're
going to talk about that is obtained from a perception
system that was looking at the cameras at time 0
and doing some algorithms to try to estimate
the position, the pose of the mustard bottle in the frame.
So the goal of today is to give you that basic algorithm,
and we'll do better and better as we go forward.
But that's our pipeline.
So it's going to look fairly similar,
but there's going to be some initial work where
I look at the camera outputs, extract that pose,
and then create the trajectory.
And when we get even better, we'll
use that in real time feedback.
But today, we're just going to say, look at the world once.
Now design our trajectory, because that's
the pipeline we already have.
[AUDIO OUT]
OK, so here's the thing.
Turns out computer vision is hard.
So looking at your cameras, it's hard.
It's a hard problem.
It's gotten a lot easier now that we've had our machine
learning revolution.
But it's still a hard problem, and you
should understand maybe why computer vision
is a hard problem.
I think it's fairly intuitive, but to say it in a word or two,
why is computer vision hard is if you're
given an image, the red, green, blue values, the RGB values
at a bunch of pixels, then a very small change in the RGB
values can mean a very different--
can have a very different effect on what you're
trying to infer from the scene.
And the flip side is that a very small change in the world
can lead to a very large change in the RGB values.
So the mapping from RGB image to, for instance,
the pose of the red brick, this is a very complicated mapping.
A small change here can lead to a dramatic change here,
and vice versa.
Discontinuous changes, right?
If I have two objects that were to occlude each other,
for instance, it might be a very discontinuous change
in my ability to estimate this or know this and the colors
and color values that come out.
If I change the lighting conditions,
this can change dramatically, even though this changes not
at all.
So this map has traditionally been very, very hard
to reason about, and now we're doing a lot better than that
by trying to learn that map with data-driven methods
in deep learning.
But before that, I would say that we
have had another revolution, not just the machine learning,
deep learning revolution.
Oh, sorry, go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE]
That's a great question, yeah.
And the survey questions, which I totally read,
asked me to repeat the questions better.
So the question is, yeah, has there
worked beyond camera sensors?
It happens, not as much as I would like.
So absolutely, the other big sensors--
so we talk about our joint sensors a lot.
We talk about inertial sensors, maybe an IMU in the robot,
especially if it's a mobile robot.
The other obvious one for manipulation is tactile sensing.
And we are going to talk about that,
but that has been much slower to evolve
than camera-based sensing, partly just because the computer
vision world is enormous, and there's
massive data sets online for computer vision research,
and there's not the same availability of research
for tactile.
So that field is growing more slowly.
But it's an obviously important signal.
Now, you could go beyond that, right?
So I think we use smell.
I think we use sound.
I mean, you can hear things collide and stuff like this.
I was talking to--
I visited the Culinary Institute of America.
They have a very good group of researchers, and they do a lot
of research on the world of smell.
And they have a very good team of researchers.
And they have a very good team of scientists, and they have a
very good team of scientists.
And they have a very good team of scientists.
And actually, this is the sensor that we're going to use for class.
And I happen to have one in my pocket.
Not always, just today.
It looks about like this.
And this is what you saw in the simulation
that was suddenly around the bins
in the manipulation station demo there.
It's an Intel RealSense D415.
This series has been discontinued.
There was a momentary scare where we thought Intel was cancelling the whole line.
But the line has continued.
And these,
the nice thing
about projected texture stereo
as opposed to some of the active
time of flight sensors is that you can put
multiple cameras in the same scene
and they don't interfere.
It used to be as soon as we had some of these time of flight sensors
we would have to really carefully
synchronize the frames of each camera
otherwise they would interfere with each other.
And these that are passive, but they're just
assigning some texture. Any texture is good.
And they don't assume anything about the
particular texture they're putting on.
These now have the ability to sort of work
multiple cameras at the same time.
Yes?
Yeah. Well this is the one that's most relevant
so I'll tell you this one.
So if I do the block matching stereo
this picture
this cartoon I had here
there's a tree in the left, there's a tree in the right
I'm trying to find the same image.
If it really does look like this where most of the image
is white
because I'm looking at a white wall or something
even this chalkboard probably has enough
texture because of my erasing
and stuff. But that's the problem
is that you won't know the depth
if two parts of the image look very similar.
So the trick there
is just in the infrared spectrum
throw some random dots
project texture.
And then, even if they're random
at least when I do my matching
this block will look different than this block
and it's once again able
to extract the depth.
And you see now if you're two different cameras
because I haven't assumed anything
about the specific texture that I projected
the two cameras won't interfere.
They will both just have enough texture.
Okay. So
of course we're going to be able to simulate
these cameras.
Now, let's just think about
what's happening here. So this is a very simple
diagram. I'm going to let it explode
because I know it's too small in this current frame.
But the new thing we've added here
is a RGBD sensor
system. Just
taxon. It listens to the scene graph
and it publishes
color images and depth images
which is RGB
red, green, blue
depth sensor.
Okay.
And its
simplicity in this diagram
hides the massive
complexity behind it, right?
So it's potentially a full game
engine renderer that's happening behind the
scenes there. The one we tend to use
in class here is just a relatively
simpler OpenGL renderer
that doesn't
do photorealistic but it's
very fast and very low computational
overhead and it runs fine on DeepNote and all
these things. But when we're
trying to do things like train a perception
system with deep learning, we will
have a version of that that
renders with photorealistic
rendering.
Okay. So then
what you get out of that
is a color image, the standard thing you'd
like to see.
In this I only put the mustard bottle in the
world. The background
is just whatever
zero in one coordinate
system mapped into the RGB space.
Okay. And you also
get this depth image.
So for every pixel, what these cameras
mostly give you, is for every pixel that
you have a red, green, blue value, you also have
an estimated depth.
Okay. That's the natural
interface that you have
to all these depth based sensors.
Okay. So the system is very
simple. You just go multibody plant scene graph.
I'm going to show you this example
that has both, renders the
ground truth
mustard bottle with
a standard meshcat visualizer.
And then I'm adding the RGBD sensor
which gives me a depth
image, but to
put it, to render it, I'm going to turn it into a
point cloud, which we're going to talk about,
and then hand it out to another visualizer.
And this is what it looks like.
[silence]
There it is.
Okay. So I have a camera right
here. I put my
frame on my camera so you could see,
you know, understand everything in frame
coordinates. Okay. And what you see
mostly here is the ground truth
mustard bottle. But if you go
in and you
turn off the ground truth,
you can see what
the camera sees, which is the rendered
point cloud. Okay.
And I think what's very
important to understand, just from this very simple
example, is that
the camera being where it is,
which I turned off,
yeah,
the camera being where it is,
can only see part of the mustard bottle.
Right? This is going to
have a dramatic effect on the way we think about
these algorithms, right? So occlusions,
partial views,
are part of the problem with perception.
You're only going to see parts of objects
in general. You're rarely going to see
perfect, especially you'll never see the bottom.
Basically, if it's on a table or something
like that, you'll certainly never see the bottom
and you'll probably put multiple cameras
around to get multiple views
when you have the luxury to
do that.
For instance,
when we did the dish-loading
example that I told you about,
these little D415s,
we just took the philosophy, alright, just put them everywhere.
The problem's hard enough.
I don't want to mess too much.
We still have partial views and occlusions
that we have to deal with. I'll define those.
But there's D415s
all over the environment.
This one's trying to look into the dishwasher
when it was there. There's two
on the wrist of the robot.
Okay?
So,
there's interesting operations
we'll think about, about how do you fuse all those
point clouds together and the like.
Yes?
[inaudible]
Yes.
This one was not a mobile robot,
but if you have a mobile robot, then
you quickly need that requirement that you've
actually integrated them directly into the robot.
So, absolutely.
The most common
place, of course, to put them is in the robot head
for no other reason than we like humans,
I guess.
Another natural thing you would think of is
you put it in the hand, and we have
some of the hands I brought down before had cameras
inside them. And those are
useful. I'll show you an example later of them being
useful. But they aren't quite
the tactile sensors that we were talking about a
minute ago, because
one of the problems with these types of sensors
is that they have a minimum
range in addition to a maximum range.
And if you get too close to an object, then
they will become blind again.
So, yes, absolutely.
That's an interesting question about where do you put them on the
robot, and the dream would be that a robot
is only instrumented by itself and can go into
any environment.
Yes?
[inaudible]
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah, so we're not going to talk about psychotic.
The question was about psychotic
eye movements. I showed one example.
So there's
the example I showed you of the super fast
hand that was going like this and catching
a phone. It was actually doing a simple
computer vision algorithm, but it was tracking
really fast.
It didn't have the psychots that
a human does, but it was doing a continuous tracking.
And that can be good
in many applications.
The other thing that's really
popular now is event cameras,
which will try to, at super high rates,
just tell you the pixels that changed.
Maybe we'll get to that
later, but think
slow stationary cameras for today,
just to get us started. Yes?
[inaudible]
Oh, saccade. So it turns out if you were
to have me look, if you
were to have me track my finger
moving across here,
my eye doesn't move as smoothly as you'd like.
It actually jumps.
So you tend to have
a fixed gaze and quick transition
to another gaze.
So eyes, human eyes, tend to
jump in discrete
quick events. The idea
there is, it's even better
if you were to spin around, I see people moving their fingers.
It's even better if you were to spin yourself in a chair,
which I'm glad you don't have rotary chairs,
otherwise I would have lost a few minutes.
But, yeah.
So the idea is that
humans are mostly blind when their eyes are moving.
And so roughly
we do as much as we possibly can to keep our eyes
fixed, and then move very quickly to the next thing.
This is also why
birds, this is going away,
this is also why birds sort of walk like this, right?
Right?
[laughter]
That's a saccade.
That's a saccade, right? That's just,
they don't have the ability to move their eye in their head,
so they move their whole head.
But it's because they're blind
when their eyes are moving, roughly.
Yes, see?
Watch out what you ask, right?
Okay, good.
Moving on.
The other thing to know
about these is that, although I
do think the revolution has
given us beautiful sensors that we didn't
have before, enabling new algorithms,
they're not perfect sensors still, and we
have to think a lot about
the noise in these sensors.
We're going to talk about
clean sensors today, and talk about
noisy sensors in the next lecture.
But if you look at the,
you know, we point this in the lab to a
pile of interesting objects,
if we simulated
those objects, we would get, this is the
depth image I would love to get out of my sensor.
The one you really get looks
more like this. And it's
accurate, it's very accurate
in some places, and it's very inaccurate
in other places. And it depends exactly,
the properties of that
error depends on which technology
you're using, but it's very common
when you see things that are at
sharp angles to the camera,
that your projected texture doesn't do so well.
For instance, and you'll
get, like, the sides of objects tend
to be, have dropouts. These black
frames were the places where it didn't
get a depth return, was unable to estimate.
So it just said, I don't know, there's nothing there.
Right? And that happens a lot on the side
of objects. Also, shiny
objects tend to be defeating
for this, or transparent objects aren't so
good for stereo.
So, a lot of those things
are still challenges with these
sensors. Now, the NERF
type technology, when we get
to it, but some of the
only RGB based technology
can do better in
many of those situations, and that's one of the things
that's exciting about it. But
these sensors, still
very common in robotics,
have artifacts that we have to think about.
This is
the particular sensor that we have here, the D415.
Everybody who talks about it
says it's an awesome sensor,
but it's a little lumpy.
Right?
This is just somebody
having some interesting objects on their desk,
and if you look at it, and you zoom in,
or whatever, it has
consistent artifacts in its
depth estimation. It kind of looks like
there's a little bit more of a wavy field
than you'd expect.
It's interesting that
there's a science of
simulating the noise
that you get from a depth sensor,
and I think
autonomous driving companies are doing that
exceptionally well, even trying to simulate
what happens with the plume
of exhaust coming off a car, how does that
mess up with my sensors?
We haven't done that level of modeling
in Drake yet,
but I think that
field is advancing.
Okay, so
from there,
let me stop that,
okay, from there now
we have a particular
depth image coming out
of the camera, and we need
to think about how we're going to work
with it. And there's various,
a bit
analogous to how there were many
different representations for orientation,
there are many different
representations for geometry.
So,
the
RGBD
image, depth image,
is one,
it's the one that comes out of this camera.
We're going to talk about
converting that to point clouds
in just a minute.
That's what
I drew in the visualizer.
But these are just two
examples, and there's many more.
If you've ever used a CAD program,
you've probably thought about
using triangular meshes,
which tend to represent
the surface of objects with triangles,
right? Or you might,
if you've done more complicated
things, you might have used a tet mesh,
a tetrahedral mesh,
for volume,
which would represent
the entire, you know, you can imagine
triangles for the surface, but if you want to
have the whole volume represented,
you'd use four points
for each piece,
a tetrahedron.
There are
other representations, like signed
distance functions.
So,
this is
a
simplified
representation of
a tetrahedral mesh.
This is
an implicit
representation. We'll get to it, we'll cover it more
soon, and it's the stuff
of deep SDF and
SDF
for short.
And NERF is
grids
or occupancy
maps.
Right, so I might
actually represent
geometry by just saying, I'm going to put a bunch
of cubes in space, and I'm going to put
a one everywhere that there's, I think,
space is filled, and a zero everywhere else.
Right, that would be a voxelized
grid, and it's actually a pretty
common representation.
And there's more, too.
Okay.
And again, a bit analogous
to the rotations,
each of these is going to be useful for
different types of computations.
And for the most part,
you should be, I think,
relatively optimistic of being able to
convert back and forth between them.
There's some cases where
that conversion is lossy,
and you might not be happy
going here and then coming back,
for instance. You might not get the
perfect reconstruction.
But
we get our data in
one particular format, a depth image,
and it makes sense to convert
it into many different formats to make
different algorithms efficient.
Okay.
Let's dive in and actually do a little bit of
perception work.
It's not a coincidence that
we talked about kinematics last
lecture
and differential kinematics and the like,
because
the first step of
perception, really, I think, is thinking about perception
as an inverse kinematics
problem. Okay?
[writing on board]
The way this is going to go, I'm going to make some
silly, simple
objects in 2D
on the board that are supposed to be
visibly asymmetric.
No symmetries to worry
about first. Okay?
So let's say I have an object O.
Okay?
This is my object.
This is a
known object.
The things we're going to talk about first are going to be
are going to work
best if you know, have a model
of the object to start with.
A known object O.
So maybe I've got a
CAD file that somebody gave me,
and I'm going to try to find the object
in the scene, like a mustard bottle
for instance.
Maybe that CAD
file has a triangular mesh.
Okay? But I'm going to
convert it from that format into
a point cloud format
to make the first algorithm work.
So imagine I've chosen
as my representation for this geometry
to be a series of
points on the
surface of the object.
They don't necessarily
need to be beautifully sampled,
evenly sampled.
It's rare that you get that, have that luxury, but
we're going to represent
our object
with just a bunch of points
that are at some position
in space.
We'll call them the model points
in an object
frame. Okay? So this is the
model point
and this is the i-th model point.
And I'm going to write it, I'm going to
denote its position in the
object frame with my standard
you know, mi
is the position in that frame.
My depth camera
gives me
something different, right?
It gives me roughly
what I'll call
scene points.
This is the i-th
scene point in the camera.
And I'm going to call it
the i-th scene point in the camera frame.
To go from the depth image
to the 3D location
of the points, even in the camera frame,
you do have to go through
the geometry
of the camera. There's some perspective
geometry that
you know, the lens for instance
like this, that will help you convert
from the image, the depth
image, into a
bunch of 3D points.
And this, you know, we won't
use points, if the depth camera said the
depth was infinite or the depth was zero,
all those black regions we saw there,
we won't include those in the scene points, we'll just discard
them. But there's a relatively
simple operation that goes from a
depth image into this, which is
what we're calling our point cloud representation.
The list of these points, the point cloud
can have its own, can live in whatever frame.
So these scene points might
hopefully look sort of
as if they were roughly generated
from that shape.
Okay?
Maybe I put it like that.
And there's going to be some points here.
Right? Maybe if I'm
looking at it from this angle, I only have points on
one side, but for now I'll just say I've got points
roughly everywhere around
the object. Okay?
And the next lecture we'll talk a lot more about
partial occlusion, partial views and occlusions.
And I'm going to assume that I
know
I know where the camera is.
So I'll assume I know where
the camera is in the world.
If it's the camera mounted to the hand,
that's just done through forward
kinematics, right?
If it's a camera bolted to the world,
it's just a fixed, constant value.
And my task
is to estimate
the object's pose in the world.
Yes?
Yes, so if
it could be a function of
the joint angles, if you like.
Yeah? And then absolutely
that would be the result of a forward kinematics computation.
But even
in my simple example, they were fixed, and that's
that's fine.
I will in general
throughout the class, when we're talking about estimation,
I will use this hat
notation.
Put a hat over it, okay?
To denote the estimate.
Okay, so x hat is the estimate of x.
Okay, so how do we do it?
It turns out, like I mean, you can tell I'm already
using the language of kinematics
and frames and the like.
So finding the missing transform
is just
a kinematics problem.
Right, if I line up my
if I line up my different
transforms, then it
becomes a simple, a relatively simple
task with one
big assumption.
[writing on board]
I'm going to assume
that
model point mi
corresponds
[writing on board]
to scene
point
i.
We're going to remove that assumption in just
a few minutes, but to start,
let's just say that, you could
imagine if I looked through my camera, if for instance
like every point that I
found had a completely unique and
reliable color, for instance.
So I had no doubt that when I looked at this
that this
point here absolutely goes
with this point over here.
That's a
too strong of an assumption for reality,
but it's going to be the first step of our algorithm, right?
Is to assume that for every one of these
points here, I know
which of the points in my model
it corresponds to.
And that
correspondence is actually
in general
is one way. I'd like to be able to correspond
every point in my scene
to some point in my
model. But it could be that
many points go to one point,
and it could be that not all model points
have a corresponding scene point, but
I want that all scene points
correspond to some model point.
And to begin with, we're just going to assume that
there's a one-to-one mapping, just to
make it very simple, to just avoid
extra notation.
If I do that,
then the problem
is really
just a kinematics problem.
I know that the
position of the
model points in the world should
just be the world to the
object.
I have this.
This is something I've
been given, right?
And it also had better equal
the
position of the camera
for all i.
This is two
different ways to put the
same point into the
world coordinates.
Now, this is
known.
This is unknown.
We need to
estimate this, right?
And we said both of these are
known, right?
This is
measured, and this is known.
So I've got an equation here
where I just need to back out
what is this transform,
given that.
Now just think about, a little bit about
the
properties of this.
For instance,
let's just say that there's no noise whatsoever.
This
is going to have a unique
solution, assuming
I have enough points, right?
If I had just exactly one point,
then there's going to be
multiple solutions to this.
There's some for
a 2D estimation,
there's some number of points required.
For 3D, there's some number of points
required. As long as they're unique points,
whatever, there's very simple conditions.
Basically two points, and then at least
three non-
collinear points, right?
That will mean that this matrix has a unique solution,
given I know these
correspondences.
But,
because this system has noise and other things,
this, I would prefer
to write this not as a "solve
some linear equations perfectly,"
but try to solve this in a
least square sense, just like we did with the
with the differential IK last time.
So it's going to be,
you know, solve this
in a least squares sense.
This, I would say, is an inverse kinematics
problem. Not differential inverse kinematics,
but inverse kinematics,
right? There's no Jacobians involved here.
This is actually trying to estimate
the transform.
So it's a natural question. We talked a lot about
differential inverse kinematics last time.
Why are we doing inverse kinematics this time?
What's different?
Does anybody
have an immediate sort of idea
for why we should jump right to
inverse kinematics this time?
Why aren't we using Jacobians?
Yes?
Perfect. Perfect.
So he says that you don't have an initial ground truth, right?
So in the case of driving
the robot around, I knew what
the initial joint angles were,
so it made sense to ask the question,
"If I made a small change, what happens
to the end effector?"
So the Jacobian, the differential kinematics
and the differential inverse kinematics
became the right object,
or a natural object.
This is a different problem. This is the robot woke up
and it has to find, with no good initial
guess, where the object is.
So we have to solve the harder problem
of solving the complete
inverse kinematics problem. We have to find that entire
transform. This is still
of course easier than when we have joints
in a big robot. This is the one object
case, but this is our first
example of solving the real inverse kinematics
problem.
Kinematics was going from
positions, the
generalized positions, to
poses.
And inverse kinematics is going from poses
back to positions.
I understand it's a little weird the way I've
written here, but I'm trying to back out the positions
of the represented here
as a pose, I admit.
I'm trying to find the
positions description, the generalized positions
of that object
from a series of these chains.
[inaudible]
Yeah, but I would probably address it
before or after. Thank you.
That was probably my one chance.
[laughter]
Right, I probably should have just said
I'll stop everything, let's fix this.
I've tried so hard to get their attention.
So let's write it as an optimization.
So, instead of just saying
I want those to match with equality,
what if I said I want them to match in a least
square sense? So, if I
said that x
w o, whoops,
w o times
p,
I can't even see my own writing up there,
minus
x w c
s i,
I'm going to do the
sum of this over all i,
and I'd like to minimize this
over my decision variable,
which was the object
position of the world.
Okay?
And just to remember,
to be explicit, that
this thing is
a particular
mathematical object that represents
a pose, let me write this down
as saying I'm going to look for this
inside
S E 3,
okay, which is the special
Euclidean group.
It's a fancy way to say a pose, basically.
In three dimensions, okay?
A valid
rigid transform.
Okay, so this is a
sort of a robust way to try to estimate
that pose.
This thing, since both of them are known,
I'll start
just writing p w
s i, or even just p s i,
since the w is implied.
Save me a little bit of writing.
And this
thing we know
from our spatial algebra,
I can write this as
p of O in the world
plus the rotations of
the O in the world times
m i.
Okay?
So I can write this
alternatively as I'm going to minimize
over p O
and r O,
where this is some
potentially abstract
representation of orientation,
but it had better live in
the special orthogonal group, okay,
which is just another way to say
it's a valid rotation matrix.
A valid rotation.
Okay, so this is the problem we want to solve,
and we want to think about the
sort of the geometry of that problem
and how we solve it
robustly.
Does that make sense?
Questions about that? Yes?
Okay.
Yes. So in the case
where we have enough points
and that there's no noise
and there's perfect
correspondences, you could try to
solve that as a bunch of
equalities and find the exact solution.
But even, if you think about,
if you count how many numbers here, for instance,
right,
if I'm going to search for, let's say this is
a rotation matrix, so I have nine
numbers here, a three by three rotation matrix,
and I have three more numbers here, so I have
12 numbers I'm trying to solve for
in general.
And let's say I have
50 points in my
model, then I've got an
over-constrained, you know, they should,
if there's no noise, there should be
a solution, but I still sort of
don't like the idea of
solving a system of
equations that could be, you know,
that is defined
based on some transformation where I have
like 50 equations to solve
for 12 unknowns. That seems
fraught with, like, numerical problems
and stuff like that. So you
could, you know, the no noise case
you could just pick your favorite 12 and,
you know, as long as they were, and do that. But
we're going to just move ahead to the case that's
going to go the distance for us, which is as soon as you have
a noise or whatever, we're going to say
find me the best possible match
that describes this data.
Good question.
Okay.
So let's work with, let's chew on this a little bit.
I need to pick now some
representation for R
to turn this into a mathematical
program.
The state-of-the-art methods
in this world will tend to
either rotation matrix
representation for this or
quaternion representation for this.
Okay. I'll do the
rotation matrix representation.
Yeah.
So it's a, the, so RANSAC
would be a good way to handle
outliers, for instance, if you have
random points that don't correspond with your
object, then RANSAC is a very natural way to
handle that.
Yeah? Yeah, for sure, we're going to get to that.
Okay. So let's choose R as a rotation
matrix, and I'll write exactly the same thing,
but instead of this
relatively abstract saying that my
decision variables live in some special
group, you know, valid rotation,
valid rotations, now I can
write exactly the properties of a rotation
matrix, which are constraints on
the variables in my
decision, right? So now I can say
I'm going to minimize over
P
and R,
now a rotation matrix, okay?
I'll just call that R here.
O, M, I
minus
P, S, I, same thing
squared, okay?
But if I represent this
by 3 by 3 numbers,
then
I need to add constraints
to make it a valid rotation matrix.
So the
important properties
of the rotation matrix is
the most important one is that it's an orthonormal
matrix, right?
So the columns are unit length,
and the
transpose is the identity.
This is an orthonormal
matrix, and the simplest way to
write that would be to say that R, R
transpose is the
identity matrix.
And that's most of what we need.
It turns out there's one more that
you need to be a valid rotation,
is you need the determinant of R
to be a positive
1, okay?
If you allow,
so given this condition,
the determinant will only be positive
1 or negative 1,
but if you don't add
this constraint, then it's possible you could get
something that's a rotation plus a reflection.
It would still be an
orthonormal matrix, okay?
So, I just
meant to make, I was trying to emphasize that,
and I realized it looked like plus or minus.
Okay, so,
if you have a determinant
negative 1,
then that would be
called an improper rotation.
And we want to be, I guess, proper
here, so.
Okay, so
this is interesting now.
This is
almost like the optimization
we wrote last time, where we have,
we still, I see this,
and I see a quadratic objective.
Do you see a quadratic
objective yet? I mean,
the decision variables are here,
right?
In this inside of the equation,
all of the decision variables
enter linearly,
okay?
Because this is known, this is
known.
So the decision variables
enter linearly,
and when I square it,
I will get at most
a quadratic term in the decision variables.
And it's going to be,
because it's this nice, you know,
some quantity squared, that means
my objective is still some nice
quadratic form
in my P and R.
That's good.
We're in the land of
quadratic optimization.
This one, however,
is also quadratic,
right? If I take the
two terms here and multiply
the coefficients of the matrix
together, then I'm going to get terms that are
quadratic in the elements
of R. And I'll do the two-by-two case in just a second.
But this is now
also a quadratic constraint.
So last time we talked about quadratic objectives with linear constraints, and we said there's beautiful solutions. That's the quadratic program.
Quadratic objectives with quadratic constraints are not quite as nice.
These are called
QCQPs,
quadratically constrained quadratic
programs.
And they don't
admit, in some cases they admit
solutions beautifully, but in general
don't admit the same
natural solution techniques.
Okay?
And then this one
is actually a cubic.
Oh no, so it depends on
the thing. At worst it could be a cubic
constraint.
So we're going to tend to,
I'm going to just, full disclosure, we're going to
tend to ignore this.
And I'll justify that
in a little bit.
So let me just do this in a, since that was
a little bit abstract, I can make
it very clear
I think in the two-by-two case.
In a 2D
optimization.
So rotation matrix
in 2D
you probably think of
for instance writing
cosine of theta,
negative sine of theta,
sine theta,
cosine theta.
That's the sort of,
when you think 2D rotation matrix
maybe you think about this.
That is the map that goes from
theta to a rotation matrix.
I'm going to here,
I want to avoid
this non-linearity of cosine
and sine, so I'm just going to
over-parameterize it here. I'm going to call
that AB, negative
BA.
Like this.
So after I solve for A and B
I can back out what theta is.
If I want. But I'm going to parameterize it
like this. And I'm going to take advantage
of the fact that I know that
I could use four numbers
to do it, but I don't have to because
I know that proper
rotation matrices
have this structure.
In 2D.
So if I then write
what is the
RR transpose
equals I constraint.
If I just multiply
this times the transpose of this
then I get two constraints
basically. The four elements
all give me
being one or being zero.
This constraint
converts into just A squared
plus B squared equals
one and
AB minus BA
equals zero.
So when I say this is quadratically constrained
that's exactly, you can see it
multiplied out here.
If I did choose to parameterize
with theta, I
can do that. People do do that. We will
find examples where we do that.
It's still potentially a
reasonable problem, but it becomes a non-linear
optimization problem.
And the language of sort of
unique minima describing
the solution is no longer valid
for us. So that's why
we go from this representation to this representation.
To be linear in our decision
variables.
And then quadratic in our decision variables.
Okay.
So let me consider for a moment
since we've written now this thing
with only two parameters
A and B.
Let's pretend I want to solve the optimization
and I just won't worry about
the positions and I'll just solve for rotations.
What does that
optimization landscape
look like?
Right?
I have a quadratic objective
and I have
this constraint.
I made a plot.
Here we go.
This is what it looks like.
Okay? I'm going to, as I move
the true rotation
around, this is, on the left
is the math
that takes a handful of points
and computes that objective.
The green is the objective
function.
And the red is the constraint.
Okay?
This is A, this is B.
For instance.
A and positive B
over here.
As I move the desired
formula around
then the objective
moves around.
Okay?
And beautifully, in this setting
actually the minimum
always lands on the unit circle.
Okay?
That's because I have no noise.
In that case, it turns out
if I ignored the
constraint completely,
I would get a valid rotation.
That makes sense, right? Because if I
wanted to minimize
this cost
and the true cost
is a valid rotation, right?
Then the thing I get back out should be a valid rotation also.
As soon as you have
noise though, this objective
of trying to reconstruct the points,
if you will, can move away
from the unit circle and having
this constraint that it better, find the best
true rotation matrix
that satisfies the constraints
can be visualized in the optimization
landscape as pulling you back in 2D
just to the unit circle.
Does that picture make sense?
Okay.
Now that's just
for the rotation only case.
But it turns out
the rotation only case is
all we actually need.
There's a very clever trick.
Actually, so
Tom, do you remember
a couple of lectures ago you asked me why
I can go from
we talked about spatial transforms, right?
In our
spatial transforms, we said
BA
expressed in, let me actually
use the same letters I used before.
If I want to change
from PAB expressed in F
to PAB expressed in G,
I claimed I only needed the rotations.
And you asked, "Why don't I have
a position and a rotation?" And I said,
"It's an exercise for the reader, but
you only need rotations."
It's not that hard to see.
This is the relative
distance, the relative position
between two points.
So if I move a frame in translation,
the relative position
between two points doesn't change.
It's only when I
rotate the frame that the relative position
changes.
It turns out
we can exploit this trick
to simplify that
optimization problem. If instead
of trying to write everything relative to
the world frame, we
do it relative to another point
in the same frame,
then the positions
drop, and
I can only optimize for rotation.
Okay?
The relative position
only depends
on rotation.
So the
way that that manifests itself in this
equation is you just
basically pick some canonical point
in the point cloud.
Typically people pick the centroid
of the point cloud.
And you write all of the model points
relative to the centroid.
And if
you do the algebra, this term
disappears.
And then you can always back it out
later after you've estimated the rotation.
So once I get to this relatively simpler
optimization, the same one
I was working on here,
this one
actually has a nice solution.
Although QC, QPs in general don't
have a great solution, this is a
special case, and it has
an excellent solution. And it's
obtained by just calling SVD.
Okay? This is one of the magic
cases where SVD just
solves the problem.
So the problem of minimizing
over R,
the sum over I,
R P0
Mi minus P0
Si squared,
subject to R
transpose equals I,
has a closed form solution.
with the singular value decomposition.
That's amazing, right?
And this becomes a staple
of our perception algorithms.
So what does that mean in practice?
I can do things like this.
I have a
model
and a scene.
Let me make sure I get the right ones
correct. I'm going to move my model
into my scene, okay?
Given this transform.
So the scene is my
salmon color, I think, when I picked it.
And the light blue
is the model.
Let me just say this one thing.
And then I'm going to, I assumed,
I made a huge assumption,
that we knew which point in the scene
corresponded to which point in the model.
That's what these lines indicate.
For every one of those
I knew which point it should correspond to.
And I did it in this example
by just perfectly causing a rotation on that.
And it turns out, in that setting
where I have the known correspondences,
and I only have to
estimate translation
and rotation,
there's effectively a closed form solution
that will snap and find the rotations.
Yes?
[inaudible]
Oh, over here.
So
what I did here was I
moved the
two point clouds,
the scene, salmon colored scene,
and the blue colored model
to be in the same world frame,
or the same frame.
So the fact that it's this brown thing,
that's salmon plus blue.
[inaudible]
I could have moved them
both into
a world frame.
I plotted it, what did I do? I guess
I think I moved the
model into
the scene in this case.
I'm consistent.
The scene I estimated in the world frame.
That's what the salmon is.
I solved for the
rotation and translation that would move
the model into the scene.
And then I applied that
to the blue color.
And the result was that points landed
right on top of each other.
And I got a lovely mud brown
for the geometry.
[inaudible]
So the, um,
I have to remember to repeat the questions.
What is the scene and what is the model?
This is too perfect to get from a real
depth sensor, but the scene is what you get
from your camera.
And right now I've assumed it's perfect and everything.
We're going to remove those assumptions.
The model is the, for the mustard bottle,
I'm going to make a perfect
model in CAD
or something of a mustard bottle.
And I'm going to go through the world, through my
cameras, trying to find that model in the scene.
Right?
And I chose to represent that, instead of
using a mesh, I'm going to represent it
as a point cloud and just do,
this is called point set registration
or point cloud registration, what we're doing here.
Take this point cloud and this point
cloud, find the relative transform so that they
become the same.
(Question from audience)
The
result of the brown thing is complete
success. We've dominated this
problem and the result
was mud brown.
It's the same mud brown that's here, yeah?
(Question from audience)
Good.
So,
let me instead of,
well, let me foreshadow
what's going to happen next time.
Which is that
if you no
longer know the correspondences, and you
have to estimate the correspondences,
then there's a relatively simple algorithm
that I'll do at the beginning of next time, that
will do this for you, and the results look
something like this. It becomes an
iterative algorithm, where you try to guess
the correspondences,
and then you apply this magic
SVD solution,
right? You apply the correspondences,
you apply the magic SVD solution,
and in the good cases,
this works beautifully and can solve the harder
problem. I will also
show you outtakes next time, when it doesn't solve that
perfectly. Right? And that's on
a loop, which is why it's
it gets bad again. It looks like it gets bad again.
Okay?
So, let me just ask a few questions
about
the version we already have here. So,
what happens
if the objects
are perfectly symmetric?
Remember my little...my shapes here were
chosen to be intentionally asymmetric.
So if I just go back to the simpler
case here,
what happens
if the object is perfectly symmetric?
If I just did a square,
or something like that. What changes in this optimization?
[inaudible]
Right. That's the
right question. It says, "Do we still have those
correct correspondences?" If the shape of the
object was symmetric, in this part
of the problem, that is irrelevant.
Because I've already given you perfect
correspondences, so there is no problem
with symmetry.
The next part of the problem, where we have to find
the correspondences, will be susceptible
to symmetries.
Great. Okay. What happens
if I don't have enough data
points?
That's kind of an interesting question. What if I
had...if I'm trying to estimate this and I only
have one data point, for instance?
What's gonna happen?
[inaudible]
There'll be an infinite number of solutions.
And, in practice,
since I'm solving this in this sort of quadratic
form, the solver
will probably find the one that's closest to zero
in these parameters.
Okay? SVD would even do that, I think.
Okay?
So it's not...it
will pick something, but it will be one of the
infinite number of solutions.
[inaudible]
Good.
Let me stop there, and we'll
not try to jam the next
thing into the next five minutes.
I will see you Tuesday.
[inaudible]
How's it going?