And then I'll run a basic simulation
with a couple examples.
So hopefully that'll be useful.
OK, let's do it.
Thank you, as always, for your feedback on the surveys.
Someone actually said they want more jokes.
And if it wasn't an anonymous survey,
I would instantly give an A for that.
But unfortunately, it was anonymous,
and that old person will-- but it made me happy.
Today we're going to do the second half.
Remember, I talked last time about a point finger.
And with the promise that at some point
we'd put the robot back in.
And the goal today is to put the robot back in.
And I'm going to do that in a few steps.
I want to tell you about-- unfortunately,
there's a bit of a zoo of different manipulator control
ideas.
They are all, I think, very related and very simple.
So my task today is to try to keep that organized for you
in your head on the board and try to make it
so it's not confusing.
And I'm going to try to do that by-- I'll put the outline here
and then go back to it a couple times.
So we'll do first just joint space control.
And I want in joint space for you
to just lock in what it would mean to do PD control, what it
means to do stiffness or impedance control, what it
would mean to do inverse dynamics control.
And then we're going to go into Cartesian or end effector
space.
And we'll primarily think about what
it means to be doing stiffness or impedance control there.
OK.
And I'll make sure I talk a little bit at the end
about some limitations and extensions.
OK.
So they're very related ideas, very simple ideas.
I hope that by the end you'll understand
the difference between those and then understand really
the beautiful trick about making the entire robot program
the dynamics at the end effector.
OK.
Now last time we did it on a point finger.
And just partly to review that and to build
into the next one, the interesting thing
about the point finger case is that your joint space
is your Cartesian space.
So we did, in some sense, almost--
we didn't do inverse dynamics, but we did these.
And I'll just write them again.
And we'll launch from there.
OK.
So--
So we thought about our robot as just being
a point with some mass.
OK.
So the configuration of that was really just x, y, z position
of that.
OK.
It turns out that I could have equivalently
said that was the position of the finger,
using my multibody notation, the position of the finger
and the world coordinates.
And since we're going to go back and forth between joint
coordinates and end effector coordinates,
it's a weird thing that in this particular example
they're the same.
OK.
More generally, those are going to be different.
And we're going to want to go back and forth between them.
But I'll highlight here that they're the same
and just show the various components when they're
the same are very simple.
OK.
So the dynamics of this point finger were very simple.
Just had our mass was our gravity vector.
Let me write it in the slightly more general form this time.
This is the gravitational vector,
which for the simple robot is just 0, 0, negative m times
9.81, negative mg, if you will.
OK.
And then we allowed ourselves to have some fictitious forces
being applied.
Our actuator was coming in as a jet pack, basically,
that could apply forces anywhere.
And then I could potentially have some external forces that
were applied at the finger.
And we talked last time about how
to regulate the external forces, either directly or indirectly.
When you see this, by the way, the reason I always
choose to write it like this-- I've said this once before.
I'll say it again because we're going to build on it today here.
But I want you to see this equation.
And the reason I always put some terms on the right hand side,
some terms on the left hand side,
is because I want you to see this as just mass times
acceleration on one side.
And these are all the forces, right?
This is the sum of the forces.
So the gravity is a force, a torque.
My control input is another force
that's being applied on any external forces.
So this is just f equals ma.
And I always try to write it where
I have ma on one side and force on the other side,
unless we start trying to be fancier.
But the original governing equations should be like that.
So in joint space, there's an interesting question, first,
of how do I track a trajectory?
So we talked about force control,
and we'll get back to force control.
But let's forget about interacting with the world.
Let's just say I want to move my finger around.
And I spent some time, maybe, with my kinematic trajectory
optimization, made a beautiful trajectory, q of t.
I've got some beautiful q of t.
I'll call it q desired of t.
Maybe the result of trajectory optimization.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
There's a problem in the manipulator control world,
which would just be trajectory tracking.
If I have some q desired of t, how
do I make it so q of t tries to track,
converges on q desired of t, and maybe
tracks it with high precision?
And for this, I'll say the external forces
are 0 for a minute.
And we'll put those back in.
So what is a good controller for tracking a trajectory
that you might want to run on a robot?
Even in the point finger case, it's just so simple
that I think it's worth writing it here first,
so we can see how those same ideas manifest themselves
in the full case.
We only have a few different cases.
So the one that we've seen a few times--
I feel bad for the people that have a robot directly
in the way, but I guess, of all the things
to be occluded by, robots are good.
OK, so maybe I could do a PD control.
PID control is perfectly good, too,
but I'll just do PD control for now.
So what if I did kp q desired minus q, kd q desired
dot minus q dot?
[INAUDIBLE]
That's one of the systems that we've seen before.
You're right, sorry.
No, it should be plus over here.
Yeah, because I put the desired in, I put a minus here.
Sometimes I do q dot.
It was absolutely an error.
Thank you.
[INAUDIBLE]
Good.
So by the way, this is well-defined.
If I have a trajectory a priori, I
could take the derivative of that trajectory,
and I could have a desired velocity
at every instant in time, too, if I'm tracking some trajectory.
So what happens if I put this controller even
into my little mass system?
Let's say I have a desired trajectory that
was just a sine wave or something like this.
Let's say q desired of time was just, I don't know,
10 times sine of t.
I could certainly figure out-- I could take the derivatives,
of course, right?
q dot t is just 10 cosine of t.
And I could run this controller.
How well will it do at tracking?
What are the good and bad things about that?
Assuming I've chosen pretty good values for, let's say, kp and kd,
how would you expect this to perform?
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Good.
So there's a question about delay,
which we're going to-- that's actually
the second point I want to make.
So yes, there's going to be a little bit of lag here.
What about even if-- what if I just
said the desired trajectory was 0?
What's going to happen?
That's even the simplest case.
What if qd was just 0?
What's this controller going to do?
[INAUDIBLE]
It won't be 90 degrees out of phase.
That's a good question.
I mean, if I've chosen a critically damped thing,
and I say the desired is 0-- so q desired is 0,
q dot desired is 0-- then I will have
a system that has a critically damped response,
assuming I've chosen this.
But the question is, does it get to the desired 0?
And it doesn't necessarily, because there's an offset term
here in the gravity.
And this is fundamentally an error-driven controller.
So if q equals q desired, and q dot equals q desired,
then the torque is 0.
And gravity is going to pull me away.
It requires some error here in order
to resist gravity and balance.
And I made the trivial simulation
just so we could see it.
This is the simple case.
Let's even make-- it's easy to see when I just
set the amplitude to 0.
If my desired trajectory is just a flat line,
and I have a point mass finger, and I have gravity,
and I run a PD controller, then it
will converge to a steady state.
But it's not necessarily going to drive the error
to 0.
A PID controller would drive that to 0
if I put the integral term back in.
But when we start tracking fast trajectories,
the integral term is going to have a more complex effect.
So I'm going to leave it out for now.
There's a different way besides the integral term
that we could take care of that.
And I want you to appreciate that that actually
is what happened when we wrote the stiffness controller
before.
So when we wrote a stiffness controller before,
we wrote almost the same controller.
But we also added in-- actually subtracted off--
the gravity term.
And we called that our stiffness control before.
[WRITING]
And I almost feel silly calling these things different things.
In the point finger case, they're so simple.
But I think this is an important idea.
One thing you can do if you know the mass of your finger
is you can just subtract it off.
And the reason that that intellectually
matches stiffness control is because then I
can say that the resulting closed loop dynamics were
mq double dot plus-- I'll do it like a mass spring damper.
So I'm going to change my sign on that.
Like Leray was looking for.
This is a dot here now.
q desired equals 0, in fact, if there's
no external force.
The PD controller has an extra nagging term from gravity.
The stiffness controller, by virtue
of trying to act like a spring, is actually
canceling that out.
But in the simple case, the only thing
that's different between the stiffness controller and the PD
controller is gravity compensation.
And of course, if I add that gravity compensation
into the simulator, then I get a nice response
that will converge to the desired, when
the desired is 0 at least.
If I do something more interesting,
like have it be the sine wave again,
then this actually will do a fairly OK job at tracking.
This is the orange is the desired.
The blue is the actual.
I started a little bit off the nominal.
And although there's a little bit of lag,
certainly at the beginning here, it actually
does a pretty good job.
I think I'd have to put up the bandwidth to see the phase.
I'd have to increase the frequency
to see any notable lag.
OK.
Turns out you can do better still.
You can get around some of the lag
with just one additional idea.
And guess what?
That additional idea is what happens
in inverse dynamics control.
In the point finger case, it's all extremely simple.
What would you do to try to get around that lag, if you will?
Which is there's an extra piece of information
that we have that we haven't given our tracking controller.
Which is we know arbitrary derivatives of q, right?
Of q desired.
If we tell it where it's going to go and give a feed forward
term that uses q double dot, then we
can get better tracking performance still.
OK.
So there's a couple ways that you could add that in.
The way that it's typically done in inverse dynamics control,
I wish it was exactly the thing you'd expect.
But for an important reason, it's
just a little different than what you'd expect.
But I'm going to say it's q double dot desired.
And I'm going to go ahead and multiply that mass by all
of my terms here.
Flipping my signs.
Let's do it like this.
So this is a feed forward term.
And fundamentally, it's what you need
to do to get around this error driven control.
You want to be able to send it so that if the trajectory is
on-- if your current system is exactly on the trajectory,
it will get the command it needs to stay on the trajectory.
You don't have to wait for error to occur to get back
towards the trajectory.
The way to do that is by giving instantaneous information
about where that trajectory is going to go.
And this is what happens in inverse dynamics control.
OK.
Super simple ideas, especially in the point finger case.
And they're just going to map directly over
to the joint, full joint robot case.
And of course, I will try to convince you here
that if I were to put the feed forward term in,
that things get even better.
That I get beautiful convergence to the nominal trajectory.
And I'll stay on the nominal trajectory.
I won't deviate on every oscillation.
Once I'm there, I'll stay on there.
It's actually easy to see that.
OK.
The reason to do this and have mass actually multiply my--
I'm going to scale my kp and kd also by the mass.
Is because then if I write out the closed loop dynamics,
I can say that I have m q double dot.
I can pull this whole thing on the other side here.
Minus this.
I'll just pull that on the other side.
OK.
I'll put it in spring mass damper form again.
Put my damping equals 0.
OK.
That's the resulting equations of motion.
And if I were to just call this term e,
if I define e to be my error, I'll call it q minus q desired.
Then I could write the same equation.
You'll see this often in the multi-body manipulator control
world.
I could write the same equation as just a first order--
a second order spring mass damper on the error.
OK.
So the error will converge to 0 and stay at 0.
And that's beautiful.
That wasn't true until I put the feedforward accelerations in.
I want to make sure that these ideas are clear.
Because they'll get more--
same ideas, but just with more terms and the like
if we go to the manipulator case.
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE]
Excellent.
Good.
So the question is, what are the requirements for the controller
in terms of knowing the system?
So in this case, I only need to know the gravity terms.
If I have a model of the gravity terms of the robot,
then I can execute this controller.
Here, I applied a controller that
had the mass also inside it--
mass and the gravity term.
OK.
So that does ask me to know more about my system.
But you can ask an interesting question
about if this is approximate, how sensitive is it?
This is actually relatively not terribly sensitive.
You can do an error analysis of what happens if I put m tilde in
like this.
If you have controllers that try to invert mass and stuff
like this, it can get a lot more sensitive.
There's different ways that mass can enter.
This one's not as terrible.
So this controller doesn't need to sense
q double dot on the robot.
It's just if I have a trajectory,
I can differentiate it twice.
That's my motion plan.
I differentiate it twice.
As long as I could do that, that's OK.
So I don't feel that I added a new requirement in terms
of sensing in that.
But there is a new requirement in terms of the model.
Great question.
This controller is actually the one
we've been mostly using in simulation.
It has torques coming out in the Drake systems framework,
whatever.
You'll see this as the estimated state coming in,
the desired state coming in, and then you
can send a feedforward acceleration coming in.
That's the inverse dynamics controller.
You'll see that in the manipulation station stack
that you've been running.
But we actually don't send--
we just leave this disconnected because EWO won't accept it.
And I'll tell you about that at the end, maybe why.
OK.
If I put force back in, then it's not so different.
If I were to put the force back in,
then I'd get a trailing force term.
And it's interesting to think about what happens
if I put the force back in.
Now I have a second order damped oscillator,
but with some driving external force.
So maybe that's still a pretty reasonable thing to do.
Yeah?
OK, sorry.
Thanks.
AUDIENCE: I think we're adding--
what sensor do we use to get q double dot?
Do we use just using the numerical method from position,
or do we have extra sensors?
Again, this is q double dot desired.
Yeah, but like the--
This is--
Oh.
Good, that's a great--
great.
So this is me analyzing the closed loop system.
I don't have to-- this is the controller that I implement.
This is what I have to type in.
The result of combining my controller with physics
is something that uses q double dot,
because physics uses q double dot.
But I don't have to implement that.
What about q dot?
For q dot, it's going to be--
I mean, depending on the sensors,
there's rotary encoders there.
Derivatives-- we typically think of as positions and derivatives
to be pretty clean, and we try to avoid accelerations
as a general rule of thumb.
You don't want to do high bandwidth control
with accelerations.
So EWA-- just something I was going to say later,
but EWA allows you to send q desired,
but it doesn't actually allow you to independently send
q desired and q desired dot.
I believe that's--
I think they made a safety argument with that,
and that somehow--
if you could imagine a bad user sending inconsistent q and q
desired dot, that might break their safety proof,
for instance.
So they instead take a sequence of q desired,
and they add a little bit more delay even,
and they'll take a finite differences to estimate q dot,
and then send that as a command.
But you're only actually allowed to talk to the robot
with q desired over time.
All right, so let's blow this up now.
So we understand in the simple case, PD, stiffness,
and inverse dynamics is just adding one thing at a time.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
For which part?
They shouldn't.
The stiffness control--
[INAUDIBLE]
Tau g.
They should both be minus tau g.
Thank you.
Because, yes, the tau g is on the right-hand side
with the u's, so I have to subtract it out.
Thank you for catching that.
Too many symbols to get right on the board.
OK, same recipe now, but let's do it
on the manipulator equations.
Remember, the dynamics that we were writing
was just mass times acceleration equals
the sum of the forces.
The way that manifests in the manipulator equations
is now my MA is just a little bit more complicated.
It looks like this and this.
These are-- this is now the inertial matrix.
These are the Coriolis terms, but they really go together.
This is-- you should think of this together as MA.
If you were to change the coordinate system,
then they would both change equivalently.
This is MA.
And then we get the sum of the forces,
so you get the gravity forces, which in general
are some function of the configuration.
I'll assume that I've got u's everywhere,
so I'll just say I can command every coordinate.
And then I can have-- I'll write it as a torque now,
a tau external.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
OK, so the first thing I want to ask
is just in joint space, how should I
do trajectory tracking?
If I have a desired qd of t, and now I have these equations,
then what's the analogous thing to do?
And it follows exactly from what we do.
We could do PD control, which actually
looks identical in this case.
It's just now-- it's identical.
I shouldn't even spend my time writing it, maybe.
The stiffness control also looks effectively identical.
It's just canceling out a more interesting gravity term.
Minus tau g, which is a function of q now.
And the resulting dynamics of that
are a more interesting version of what we've done before.
But it's still a-- it's just a more complicated spring mass
damper system.
And it happens in the joint coordinates.
So what does that mean is if I put a resistive force,
if I push on a particular joint, I
expect it to feel like a spring when it's pushing back at me.
OK?
And these terms are the mass of that spring mass damper system.
And they're a more complicated object.
But it should still feel like a-- if I
were to move one joint at a time, for instance,
it would feel like I'm pushing against it.
And we're going to actually do that.
Terry, is it OK to do it now?
Yeah?
Let's do the-- so I want you to at least see me feel the--
we'll do the joint impedance control.
OK?
Now, so EWA does-- it's called joint impedance control.
But like I said before, it actually--
it doesn't shape the mass of the robot.
It only shapes the rotor mass.
So unless you get to the level of modeling the rotor inertia
and the elastic joints, at our level of modeling,
it looks like a stiffness controller.
OK.
Now, let me just say something about safety here.
So this is-- we're only running the very simple controller that
has been actually certified.
And Terry's got his hand on the big red button.
But I don't advise, in general, people running up and touching
powerful robots.
OK?
I'm going to just do this carefully.
So right now, this is in joint impedance control mode.
So that means if I were to apply--
it's got something like a 50 newton meter,
I think, was the gains we put in here.
A 50 newton meter gain on any one of those joints,
it's going to let me move it.
I can kind of move the robot around.
It's going to resist.
It's going to drive itself back to this nominal joint
configuration.
But it's in a complicated space.
The response is a complicated function
of the kinematics of the robot, because every joint
independently is looking like a spring.
OK?
It's pretty beautiful.
And it feels very nice and natural and smooth,
which is a testament to the hardware.
OK?
Good.
We're going to do the other one in just a minute,
if that's OK.
Yeah.
So that's, I think, at our level of modeling,
this is kind of what we should think about EWA as doing.
If you wanted a higher fidelity simulation model,
if the reason your robot was failing to pick up a coffee cup
was because of the dynamics of the elastic joint,
then you have to go dig deeper than this.
But for almost all the manipulation research I've done,
you haven't had to go to that level of modeling power.
OK?
[CLEARS THROAT]
You can do inverse dynamics control, too.
And we often write it down.
It's interesting, though, that EWA doesn't do it.
And I think it does go back to the requirements,
as you say, of what's happening.
The inverse dynamics controller would send in--
I'm going to take a mass times the entire signal here.
I'll send in q double dot desired as my lead,
my feed forward term.
And I'll put inside here my kp plus kd.
Outside here, I'll take my tau gravity.
OK?
And the result is, once again, a beautiful system.
Keep switching my E dots and whatever.
But it looks like this.
The error dynamics in joint space
will converge like a second order spring
with a more complicated mass matrix.
It actually has the Coriolis terms, too.
Like I said, those two go together.
Those are still there.
But it's a more complicated mass spring damper system.
But the error converges to 0.
So this is a nice way to do high-end trajectory tracking
control.
If you had a torque-controlled robot
and you wanted to do extremely accurate trajectories,
then I recommend sending in the q double dot forward.
I think it's only doing first derivative.
It could be taking two finite derivatives, differences
of my q command.
But I don't think the advantage is there when
you've already done a lag.
So I suspect it's not.
OK.
So the interesting differences now
become when we start thinking about how the forces enter
the joint equations, the multibody equations.
Because forces naturally live in Cartesian space.
And everything here is in joint space.
In joint space, it just looks like a more complicated finger,
if you will.
And everything still goes.
But let's see what happens if I add forces in.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
I showed you once before, when we
were talking about friction cones and whatever,
I showed you these equations without fully justifying them.
The way that forces enter the multibody equations,
I wrote this down sort of quickly without justification,
that it looks something like this.
That I have a Jacobian transpose times f,
where this is a Cartesian force.
But these equations live in joint coordinates.
If you have a robot with some joints and some equations
of motion, and you apply a Cartesian force here,
then the question is, how does it affect torques at the links?
Or vice versa, if I were to apply torques to the links,
what sort of force would I be applying
at a point on the world?
And the relationship here, which is there, but more generally,
is that you have this relationship of torque
is the Jacobian transpose times force.
And that one I want you to remember.
That's a good thing to know at parties, I guess.
And it's like-- yes, I think that's core knowledge,
I would say.
How many people know why torque is
Jacobian transpose times force?
Yeah.
OK, I'm going to add to your core knowledge.
It's really simple.
OK, it's just a power argument.
So if you think about the work, actually,
done at the end effector, this is the way we think about it.
So if I have a robot in some configuration,
I want to think about the incremental work done
at this point on the end effector.
Work is force times distance.
This is an argument of virtual work.
It's called.
Work is force times distance.
I'm going to compute the work done at the end
effector in two different ways.
I'll think about a virtual change in x,
and I'll think about a virtual change in q.
These are two different ways, and I
should get the same answer.
So the total work done by the force
should have an equivalent work done by the torques.
So if I say the force-- let me use my correct small f--
dotted with some delta change in x
must equal the torque dotted with some virtual change in q.
So this is a virtual displacement in x.
This is a virtual displacement in joint.
This delta notation, and that's a dot product.
Since we also know that delta x is related to delta q
by the sum of Jacobians, then if you put this together and say
it has to work for all delta q, I have f.
And I'll go ahead and multiply out the transpose.
I'll say f transpose equals Jacobian q.
Delta q is tau transpose delta q.
And this has to work for all delta q.
And it is equivalent to saying tau--
and I'll take a transpose on both sides--
is J transpose f.
So any time you want to go between a force computation
at a particular point and a torque at the joints,
the Jacobian is exactly the mechanism you need.
It's just a Jacobian transpose.
It's just an argument about virtual work.
It's actually-- it was, I think, a major advance
in the rigid body mechanics when people
started thinking about these virtual displacements.
And that's the Lambert's principle
and all the good stuff, all the variational mechanics work.
So there's a lot of depth there.
And the reason for those annoying virtual displacements
is actually really important and the like.
But I think it's mixed for simple algebra.
And you get tau equals Jacobian transpose times force.
OK, so let's think about now trying to live in this space.
Remember, the amazing thing we want
to do if we're thinking about forces
is we want to make the big complicated robot act like a--
be able to control the forces as if it was a point finger.
So given we have this relationship
and we see how it enters the multibody equation,
how do we make that happen?
It turns out this translation between the Cartesian space
and the torque space with the Jacobian transpose
can actually be applied to the entire multibody equations.
And the result of doing that is one
of the most beautiful results on our list
here, which is this idea of writing Cartesian space
dynamics, task space dynamics.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
OK, so now my location of my finger--
I'll call it an end effector more generally here.
So this would be my end effector frame.
We know that that is related to q by the kinematics.
My velocities are related by the Jacobian.
My accelerations also have the relationship,
v dot of e, which we actually have multibody notation for a,
calling that a.
And that gives me-- if I take the derivative,
time derivative one more time, I get
this plus an extra term, j dot q, q dot.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
The tricky step here is if I take the multibody equations,
solve them for q double dot, and insert them
into this equation, then I actually
get a new set of multibody equations.
The derivations in a little bit more detail in the notes.
Certainly all the terms are written out there.
Keep that off just to keep it simple.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
What is this equation?
This is the manipulator dynamics from the point
of view of the end effector.
This is my command input.
I can just achieve this with my Jacobian transpose.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
And I can actually write the dynamics
as it's viewed from the finger, from the end effector.
And since these equations-- so this thing
has the original mass matrix in it.
It has a couple of Jacobians in it.
It has a couple inverses in it.
But it's always well-posed, assuming-- yeah,
it's actually always positive definite.
It has some nice properties.
And all of these are just functions
of the original equations and the Jacobian.
It's basically the Jacobian transpose applied
to all those equations.
But these equations, looking at the dynamics of my robot
through the lens in the coordinate system of the end
effector, look so similar to what we've done before
that I can use the same kind of control.
In fact, I can write a stiffness controller the same way
I did before.
I just will cancel this out.
I'll write the PD terms on this.
And the resulting equations will be an end effector dynamics
that looks like a spring mass damper system.
That's the amazing thing.
So this is Cartesian stiffness.
This is the analysis.
But the controller is simple.
It's still just-- I'm going to do my kp.
I have to modify it into the correct space.
But in this coordinate system, the controller is simple.
I'm going to write it as pe minus pe kd p dot e minus p
dot e, and then minus this f of gravity.
Now you see why I was worried about snilling you
with the details.
So but I hope you see, by the simple analogies,
that this is really just writing the PD controller,
canceling the gravity.
But we're doing it in the coordinate system
of the end effector dynamics.
It's fantastic.
Should we run it, Terry?
Is that good?
I showed you the KUKA folks running this early,
and they looked happy.
So I figured I should try it.
Maybe I'll be happy.
Again, this is just one of the basic certified controllers.
And which one we're doing first, the translational?
So the way to make this interesting
is we put a different translational stiffness in x,
y, and z.
So I think it was 150, 250, and 50, or something like this.
So one of them is going to be really--
that one's a little bit--
that's the 250, and then this is the 50 newton meters.
Yeah?
If you want to go from Cartesian back to the [INAUDIBLE]
OK, there's two parts of that question.
So the controller that I've written here,
I can actually just command Jacobian transpose times
this virtual force.
So I don't have any ugly inverses in the control.
But you're right, there's a null space of that control.
And I should do something-- if I have more degrees of freedom
than the thing I'm commanding, then I
should do something in the null space
to not leave that undefined.
But the actual forward mapping looks good.
There's no inverses in the forward mapping.
So just once more.
So what is also different compared to-- remember,
before I was doing the joint by joint,
and the response in the end effector
was actually pretty complicated, because it
was living in joint space.
The springs were living in joint space.
But now it really does feel obviously different
and obviously kind of linear.
I don't know if I can feel linear.
But in the end effector coordinates.
That's why he was happy.
That's pretty good.
OK, and then we can do the same thing in rotational coordinates.
So all the same things work if you
were to use our spatial vector notation
and say that the thing I'm trying to control
is not the position, but the orientation,
or in general, spatial velocities and frames
in the end effector.
Then you can put a stiffness.
You have to be a little careful at how you write stiffness.
I actually cited your paper, actually,
about maybe an interesting way to write a six degree of freedom
stiffness.
But now, if I wanted to push it sideways,
he made it very stiff in the xyz direction.
So that end effector wants to stay there.
But it's allowed to be soft in the out of plane.
And I've got a smaller moment arm to do the last one.
But yeah, it's math.
Math works.
[INAUDIBLE]
There are different ways to write the stiffness.
How do you parameterize the stiffness in that box?
It's just the-- does it take a--
[INAUDIBLE]
The orientation stiffness, is it a diagonal matrix on RPY?
Yeah, I think it is.
But I actually don't remember.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, they do RPY.
OK, yeah, so don't-- I won't try to get to pi over 2.
Awesome.
Thank you, Terry.
OK, questions about that?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes?
Correct.
[INAUDIBLE]
Good.
That's not a naive question.
That's an advanced question, I would say.
So remember how I said you can mix this
in the hybrid position control?
So EWL will actually also accept a feedforward force.
We normally live in joint-- I know better what it does in
joint.
I assume it could also take a feedforward force in Cartesian.
But actually, I'd have to look to make sure that-- we almost
always use joint space control for a limitation I'll
talk about in just a second.
So yes, if you're in the limit, you
could set kp and kd in the joint space impedance
controller to 0.
You can say, I know everything I should know.
It will still compensate torque for you, the gravity torque.
And it actually does a little bit more.
It compensates friction, too, in a very clever way.
But then you can command forces directly to add in.
Therefore, you could do the acceleration-based stuff
through that.
I think the bandwidth needs to be considered.
So expecting it to track super high through that force
command is to maybe-- there will be limits to what you can do.
Did that answer the question?
Yeah?
Great.
OK.
Yeah, so this is super powerful.
There's only one thing that I don't like about it.
What's the one thing I don't like about it?
I kind of alluded to it in that question.
I mentioned it once before, which
is why it's a fair question.
What's that?
The null space is--
I think that's manageable.
So in fact, I should probably have lectured about that.
Because it's sort of a thing.
It's called operation space control.
And the idea-- so we talked about joint centering
in differential inverse kinematics.
There's a joint centering-- I did put it in the notes.
There's a joint centering sort of version for this.
I can say it off the top of my head here.
How would you do joint centering to take care of that null space?
If you're normally commanding this
with your command that comes from stiffness control,
and you want to take care of the null space,
then the standard thing people would do,
would do-- this is the null space projection.
And then write something like kp q desired minus q.
Lots of symbols.
But the point is, you could write it like a PD controller
and have it in the joint coordinates
and project it into the null space of this.
So that's a really beautiful idea
that says, in some sense-- and the way people talk about this--
this is the first priority task.
The torques you pick should absolutely
create the virtual stiffness that you
want at the end effector.
But in the null space of that Jacobian
and any extra degrees of freedom,
then I'd like the rest of my joints
to act like they're a PD controller going back
to the original.
And this mixing of joint space and end effector space control
was originally-- it's called operational space control.
And operational space control has
grown into a whole rich library of ways
to prioritize different tasks and constraints.
There's humanoid versions of it and the like.
But operational space control was originally just,
let's mix joint and force into the same frame.
Great question.
But that wasn't my biggest concern.
I have exquisite control.
I can write the dynamics beautifully.
But I have to know the point about which
I'm going to write my dynamics.
That's the thing that drives me nuts.
All of this is based so heavily on the Jacobian.
And it's the Jacobian that gets me from robot joint coordinates
to a particular point on my robot.
So if I'm in the factory or something
and I'm applying forces exactly at the end of the orange knob
on the robot, then life is good.
I can act exactly like I want at the end of that orange knob.
It's actually the center of that little orange sphere,
I think, is where the coordinate system is for us today.
All right.
But if the robot bumps into something halfway up its elbow,
then we haven't solved that problem.
We haven't programmed the response
that the robot's going to have if I were to go up--
it's turned off right now.
But if I were to go up and knock it like this,
none of my math has told me what that response should be,
if I programmed the response down here.
And it's for that reason that we tend to live in joint space.
Because if I get a perturbation anywhere,
it might not have a beautiful interpretation
at the end effector.
But it has a logical interpretation
in joint coordinates.
OK?
You would like to say there's a richer problem of trying
to say, how would I program the response for whatever contact
I happen to be experiencing?
That's a rich problem.
And I'll maybe jump ahead and say that, too.
I have-- I didn't even show most of my videos here.
OK?
So there's an interesting problem of contact estimation.
If we know J transpose F equals torque,
then you can ask the question, if I'm feeling torques that I
didn't expect at my robot, where on the robot
could I have been-- did that force come from?
OK?
And you can imagine, if you can estimate
by looking at your joint torque sensors, where
on the robot you made contact, then
you could program the response to interact
at that point with some impedance or some stiffness.
But it turns out that's a really bad problem.
I think this picture was one that Pang
made to try to make that point.
If you are experiencing some joint torques,
and you try to map that back to the possible locations
on the arm, and you admit that there's
a friction cone on the arm, so the location--
the direction is not directly imposed by the location.
It could be-- even if I'm pushing here,
it could be any of these vectors.
And you try to solve the inverse problem.
For a particular torque, there's a bunch
of places on the robot that could have possibly--
this wasn't even the worst one, I think,
now that I'm seeing it.
But there's a lot of different locations
on the robot that could have explained the same torques.
And in general, I think you can make some progress.
The people that have done really nice contact estimation
have done it well enough that you
can stop when you're about to hit something,
but not well enough that you can program the response
at an unexpected location.
That's a hard problem, especially
if I were to allow the fact that there could
be multiple points of contact.
Then it's completely-- it gets very complicated.
People who've been asking about human-robot interaction,
if I bump up against something and it's a wall,
then the thing I should do might be very different than if I
bump up against something and it's a person in both directions.
Because actually, the person might
be trying to command me by pushing me around.
And I should be responsive, submissive, I guess,
to the human.
Or it could be other cases where I should try to get the task
done, even through some--
so it's a very, very hard problem.
I think the world is sort of agreeing
that maybe the way to solve that is with tactile skins.
And that's one of the things we're
excited about with the soft robot project at TRI
is we're trying to build sensing skins.
And I think at some point, you have
to try to estimate the contact location with a richer
set of sensors than just your joint torques.
I think we understand that the joint torques are not
going to get it done, unless you had a lot of links.
So I'd say that's the biggest limitation of this
is the impedance control, stiffness control,
end effector view of the world needs you to know
where the end effector is.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
And that's why-- so if I now go back to this one example
I talked about with key points, it's
kind of exciting to think about maybe combining
some of the tools from perception
with some of the good tools from control.
So the simplest version of this, I would say,
would be that if we're looking at a tool
and we want to apply a force at the end of the tool
instead of the end of the end effector,
if I use my key point estimation pipeline,
if I want to control a stiffness in multiple degrees of freedom,
maybe I'll have an oriented key point or a handful of key
points so that I can get the orientation of the object too.
And then if I assume the object is fixed to the hand,
I just have a slightly different end effector on my robot.
I have a Jacobian that's just slightly different,
but based on the location that came out of the key point
estimator.
And I can suddenly apply impedance or stiffness
control at the end effector of the tool.
And that's what made the examples
I showed of erasing and plugging in and things like this.
This was impedance control plus key points.
There's probably lots of potent combinations
of the different tools.
But you do need to know where the location of the contact
is in order to get that done.
OK.
Yeah.
And so what do we do on the EWA?
We are sending an only queue desired trajectory,
like I said.
And EWA's controller is differentiating.
We don't get to send the feed forward.
We tend to do joint stiffness control.
Despite the elegance of the Cartesian stuff,
the joint stiffness is more robust to unknown contacts,
I think, or more reasonable response.
Principle of least astonishment, if you will,
responses to unknown contacts.
And an important point that I maybe forgot to make,
but the difference between the stiffness control, which
is canceling out gravity, versus just a PD control,
is if I can cancel out gravity with a feed forward gravity
term, then I can choose my stiffnesses to be much softer.
I can choose kp and kd to be much smaller
if they don't have to also fight gravity.
And that's how we got compliant motion for things like opening
up the dishwasher door.
The trajectory of this was, I would say, carefully planned,
but with a highly imperfect model of where the dishwasher
door is, where the hinge on the dishwasher door was.
And we are heavily relying on the ability for that robot,
just like when I pushed it in joint space mode,
to deviate from its planned trajectory
in order to execute that task.
If it didn't, if those gains were too high,
and the robot was pulling down on this,
and it was kinematically bad, the hand could get jammed,
and things would be bad.
You'd blow a fuse.
These things are pretty robust.
Good.
Any other questions about that?
Did that lineup of--
did that organization help with the litany
of different versions?
OK.
Cool.
I don't mind ending a few minutes early.
And I actually have one other thing.
If anybody wants a Drake sticker--
someone gave me Drake stickers, and I
have laptop-sized Drake stickers and cell phone-sized Drake
stickers.
And if you guys come to class, you get to get Drake stickers.
I mean, just take one or two.
OK, see you next time.