[footsteps]
(mumbling)
(footsteps)
(door closing)
(mumbling)
(footsteps)
(door closing)
(mumbling)
(footsteps)
- Okay, let's do it.
This is day two of our mini series
on going from one object in a bin
to a cluttered scene with a lot of the complexity
that goes along with that.
Just to make sure I say that,
I think once we get this far into the course,
I've learned over the years that people,
most people appreciate me just sort of saying,
okay, what have we done, what are we doing,
why are we doing this today?
So I'll try to put these up most of the time
if I remember it, but right, we started with saying,
first in the basic pick and place,
we said we had a single known object
and we even assumed we knew its pose.
Someone told us a priori its pose.
When we did the geometric perception,
we went to a single known object.
We still had the model, but we had to estimate its pose.
And this week we're trying to do many diverse
and unknown objects with unknown poses.
The task is relatively simple though.
It's just gonna be clearing the bin kind of task.
And that looked like this.
You know, it turns out I looked at this afterwards
and actually that's the Spock duck is right there.
That's the one right there.
You'll see it's gonna get picked up in a second here.
There it is, see?
But sometimes it goes, gets thrown.
And actually I wanna watch this
for just a second longer this time
because this video shows actually some of the subtleties.
To get the ones out of the bin,
it has to, you see that out of the corners,
it had to go in and sort of nudge things out of the side
because it wasn't able to find a stable grasp.
And then at some point it tried a few times,
gave up and started switching to the other side.
We actually got to the point
where we'd almost always clear all the bins.
And we'll do a little bit of that with you guys too,
talking about the sort of task level reasoning
and how you'd program that.
But we're gonna be today thinking about the easy picks,
the ones where we can just go in and grab
and don't have to do anything more sophisticated.
So I started this section talking a little bit
about contact mechanics and even contact simulation.
And partly because our tools are very optimized for it,
we're gonna start off by just dumping a bunch of things
in the bin, we'll dump a bunch of red bricks
or cheese boxes or mustard bottles into the bin.
And my preference would be to actually design an algorithm
that would solve a small optimization problem
to find a static equilibrium.
And I have a little bit of comments about that in the notes.
But that actually is a very hard problem to solve.
And it's a much easier problem
to just let the contact simulation engine do its work
and initialize things out of penetration
and just let physics bring you into a nice static equilibrium.
So we talked a little bit about that.
But I use that also as a chance to introduce a few
of the concepts from contact mechanics.
Most notably, normal forces,
the contact frame and the friction cone.
And we're gonna build on that today.
We're gonna use the friction cone idea a lot
'cause we wanna think about what makes a good grasp.
Where should I go in and grasp in the bin?
And there's a few different views of this.
It's changed dramatically over the last 10 years.
But for many, many years, there was a sort
of the classic view.
In fact, I would say a lot of manipulation research
in robotics fell under the umbrella
of sort of grasp analysis or grasp optimization.
If you look in the handbook of robotics under grasping,
you find a couple nice chapters that go through.
I'll give you a sense of what they talk about.
But actually, this isn't as big of a topic anymore
because most of these analyses assumed a lot
about the object.
You assumed a lot of knowledge about the object.
And in practice, when you're getting your information
from a camera, you don't have enough information
maybe to do some of these analyses
that are so clean and so nice,
but maybe not as well-suited to the wild west
of a robot in the home.
And when the deep learning revolution started,
oops, I put that in the wrong place,
but we'll come back to that.
When the deep learning revolution started,
a different approach showed up,
which was we're basically going
to just train a deep net to basically tell me
where's a good place to grasp.
Given a point cloud coming in,
or an image coming in even, tell me where I should grasp.
And there were a handful of approaches
that came out around the same time that did that.
One was by Rob Platt and his students.
There was DexNet.
There's DexNet 4 or 5 by now,
but that was 2.0 was the one that was doing
a lot of these grasp analysis and training grasp methods.
There were a handful of approaches like this.
But they changed the picture,
they changed the landscape
of what we were seeing our robots do
into this sort of, instead of one known object
that you're trying to reason about very carefully,
this was the first time we started seeing videos
that looked more like this,
where the manipulation research was dump a pile of stuff,
random stuff, and start operating on it.
And that was, I think, a really important shift
for the field to make,
was to just go to the sloppy manipulation side of the world.
So this is roughly what I've already shown you,
but this was maybe the first version of that.
These methods took a completely deep learning approach.
They just trained often in simulation
to try to find what was a good grasp
and just, or use some simple heuristics to do it.
You'll also see it in picking sort of versions of this.
This is from Alberto's group
and part of their Amazon picking challenge.
They had very much the same kind of thing.
They had a deep network that was taking RGB images in,
saying these are the places on the image
where these are the hotspots
where you should probably try to pick.
And then a relatively simple algorithm
that would just go down and with suction,
it was very simple to just go down and suck there.
Okay, but this is around the same time,
this is Lucas, who was a student in my group.
We were kind of, we're saying,
do people, do we really,
that's a great problem formulation,
but do you actually need deep learning for that?
I mean, there's pretty simple strategies
that would do pretty much the same thing.
So as almost a thought experiment,
Lucas coded up roughly what we're gonna talk about today,
which is a no deep learning,
just geometric reasoning version of the problem.
And it turns out as things have evolved,
people often combine these two worlds.
So they'll use, for instance, the geometric reasoning
with some perfect point clouds or something in simulation
to give a score for the deep learning system to learn.
But I think you'd be surprised how far you can go
with just the pure geometric version of this.
Okay, so I wanna start digging in
and talk about what makes a good grasp.
What do we learn from our older grasp analysis,
and what can we take into the unknown object case?
And what can we, ultimately, we'll talk about
what do we do, how do we do it with deep learning.
So.
(tapping)
Okay, so the, there's of course layers of thinking
about the complexity of grasping.
The simplest case would be if you have,
just from kinematics alone,
the ability to know that you've got a good grasp.
So let's say a kinematic only analysis.
And the extreme form of this is a notion called form closure.
Okay, so it starts with an object of some interesting shape.
I guess I'm making a Z.
I didn't really know where that was going when I started.
But, okay.
And then, in the case of a dexterous hand,
I might summarize the case of my dexterous hand
holding this Z-like object with the location
of a handful of points, my fingers, okay.
And like we talked about last time,
most of our analysis is actually summarized
through point models of contact.
Okay, so I'll assume I have some fingers here.
In a purely kinematic analysis,
I'm not actually gonna think about forces at all.
I can ask a simple question,
which is have I completely caged the grasp?
Okay, and I'll make it formal in a second.
But the kinematic question would be,
is there any perturbation to the pose of the object
that I could make such that I could move
without causing a violation
of my non-penetration constraints?
If it is the case that no matter what I moved,
what I tried to do to move,
I would always be going into penetration
on one of the fingers, then I've completely caged,
I mean, imagine if I had fingers everywhere,
then it's trivial, but there's like nowhere I could move.
I've completely pegged this thing down.
There's no direction that it can move.
Okay, that would be called a form closure.
Form closure.
So, let me make it more precise.
(fingers tapping)
Yeah, so let me say it this way.
If the fingers are held fixed,
this is all in the object coordinate, right?
Or relative to the object, my fingers are fixed,
then the object cannot move in any direction.
(fingers tapping)
This is a very conservative notion of a successful grasp.
It requires me to have completely enveloped the object,
but this is maybe the simplest to understand.
And the way that you can write those conditions down,
we already have the language for, right?
So if we were to use, for instance,
our sine distance function, which is a function of Q, right?
So this would be, let's say, the sine distance
of the i-th contact.
Then you can actually check the conditions for form closure
by just analyzing the variations of that sine distance,
basically.
So the way it's typically written
in the form closure world would be,
let's distinguish, separate Q into Q object
and Q robot.
We'll split those two in half.
And I'll assume that when Q robot is fixed,
what I'd like to ask is,
if I were to make a change to Q,
so let me write this as Q object and Q robot now.
It's just a more verbose way to write that same thing,
just to make that distinction.
The question is, can I find a Q, a delta Q object
such that for all i, Q object plus delta Q object,
Q robot greater than 0
implies that delta Q 0 must be 0?
That's kind of a funny way to write it.
But the standard thing would be to say,
if my goal is to have non-penetration,
if my sine distances have to be greater than or equal to 0
at all the fingers, and my robot doesn't move,
if I say I'm going to consider all possible delta Qs,
which satisfy this non-penetration constraint,
if basically the only delta Q that satisfies that is 0,
then I've got a form closure.
That's the formal definition.
It's an enveloping bracing contact.
It's actually fun to think about it.
And if you go to the handbook of robotics kind of text,
you'll see all kinds of interesting cases.
So it's written like this.
This suggests that taking the gradients,
would be the right way to look at it,
to look at the gradient of these functions.
And if the gradient is full rank,
you would expect that sort of a condition would hold.
And that's true, but it's actually richer than that,
because you can find some interesting situations.
The classic one is the hourglass here,
where if I have an object that looks like this,
and I have fingers that are here, for instance,
it's possible to have a form closure,
but you only can see that it's a form closure
if you consider the curvature of the surface.
So this is a case where you actually have to take
second derivatives of those constraints
in order to see it.
Okay, so that's the sort of definition.
The definition is less important to me
that you understand than the basic concept
of a completely caged, this thing can't go anywhere
because I put my fingers rock solid, the object can't move.
Okay, but that's not gonna get us
where we wanna be here, right?
'Cause that would require you to somehow
get under the object completely.
That's not what's happening here.
We're coming in from above, we're making a grasp,
and we wanna instead think about a less conservative version
of stable grasping.
So let's loosen up a little bit
and think about static analysis next.
So we're gonna, you could think about this
as basically the limit where I've said
the fingers have to do the work without friction helping.
If the frictionless case,
this thing is still guaranteed to be stable.
But if I go to full statics analysis
and I think about friction cones,
then I can loosen my requirements and just say,
as long as the friction cone is getting the job done,
the contacts with the help of friction,
then I can still call myself a stable grasp, okay?
So we're gonna go from form closure to force closure,
if you guys have heard that,
but let me do it through the path of contact wrenches.
So this is gonna be a statics analysis.
Do you understand when I say that, right?
So there's kinematics, there's dynamics,
which is F equals MA,
and you have large accelerations or whatever.
And there's statics, which is somehow in between,
which you do think about forces,
but you assume your accelerations are zero.
You're looking for static equilibrium kind of conditions.
So we could go to full dynamics.
In fact, we should go to full dynamics,
but we have a nice stepping stone here to go through statics.
Okay, so we're gonna think about,
if I now have point contacts with friction cones,
what can I say about the total stability,
robustness of the grasp I've got myself?
To do that, I wanna go through
the slightly more general form of the friction cone,
which is the contact wrench, okay?
You remember your spatial velocity.
We already talked about one important spatial quantity,
the spatial velocity.
These things in general have components for rotational,
you know, angular momentum, angular velocity in this case,
as well as the translational,
and an algebra that goes with it, right?
Well, today we're gonna use the spatial forces, okay?
So now we have,
and it's notation heavy again,
but this one, I'm tempted to just do this
and say that you're good,
but you don't have forces relative,
you know, in a relative coordinate system.
You do have forces that are applied at a certain point.
So in order to distinguish it from that,
the monogram notation uses this notation,
which I'll spell out here,
which is force on body A
applied at,
applied at P,
and then expressed in C.
(marker tapping)
Okay.
What's important is that it has an algebra,
and it has six components, once again.
It has a torsion, you know, a torque, a moment,
all in the same world,
and it has the translational force.
(marker tapping)
Right, so in 3D, it's a six by one vector.
All of these spatial vectors have similar algebras, right?
So for instance, if I wanna change the expressed in frame,
I can do that with a rotation matrix.
That's the common operator on that.
The way I change the point that it's applied to
is a pretty simple thing,
which I hope is kind of familiar.
So if I had a force being applied to a body here,
and I wanted to instead summarize it
as a force being applied here,
so I wanted to change, if this was P, and this was Q,
and I wanted to change and write F applied to body A at Q,
how can I write that as a function
of the force applied at P?
I don't expect you to answer,
but I give you a minute to think for a second.
(marker tapping)
Probably gonna involve a vector, the vector P to Q, right?
This is P, Q, like that.
The forces, if I apply a force here,
the forces, I could have applied them anywhere,
the X, Y, Z positions, right?
Those are just the same.
So if I break this down in my coordinates here,
the forces that are here are just little f, A, P, yeah.
This is the same.
But if I apply a force here that had zero torque,
for instance, then up here, it looks like a force,
but it also provides a torque.
And that torque is gonna be just the cross product, right?
So the cross product of this with this
is gonna be the torque.
I could summarize the same force as a force plus torque here
as I could summarize it with just a force here.
And that's just our basic cross product force computation.
So just to get it right, I get tau A, P,
plus from Q to P, cross f, A, P, looks like that.
Okay, I think I got my signs right.
That's an important point.
If you don't love statics, that's okay.
But just to say, any force that I'm applying
anywhere on the body, a spatial force,
I can summarize that as if I was,
I can apply exactly the equivalent force on the body
at a different point.
You know, I could have applied it here
with a different torque and force as I applied here,
and it would have exactly the same effect on the body.
Right?
And in particular, when I sum all of them up,
their total contribution, I could summarize
their total contribution of many forces
as a single force and moment at a particular point.
I could just put them into the same coordinate system
and then just add them together.
You can add these forces together.
That's part of the algebra.
Okay, so let's think about how to think
about our friction cone.
Any questions about that?
Let's think about how to reason about different friction
cones and different robustness, now
that we have that basic language of spatial forces,
and we're reminded there's probably a cross product
involved.
By the way, this cross product shows up
in the transformations of spatial velocity, too.
I heard that maybe we didn't get that through on the problem
set, that a lot of people got that one wrong on the problem
set, that people didn't use the cross product thing.
So we'll probably post a little-- that one
was-- we'll post a little summary
of what's the right answer to make sure people get it.
But yeah, these cross products are
standard fare in spatial notations,
whenever you're mixing rotations with translations.
OK, so well, let's even start with a familiar case.
We talked about-- remember that example
where we said the box was on the ramp,
and I had a box with a couple little feet in it,
so that I knew exactly where the contact forces were.
Box with mass m, and we said we had friction cones
that looked like this.
And then we had a mass-- a force of gravity
applied at the center of mass like this.
You guys remember that notation, right?
The normal force was here.
The friction force was being applied possibly
in these directions, and the constraint
from Coulomb friction was that the magnitude of the friction
force is scaled by the magnitude of the normal force.
So the question about whether this thing
can be in static equilibrium could
be written as, can I find such that mg, which I've
written in a spatial force would actually be 0 torque and mg.
This would be applied at the center of mass, for instance.
So I said force applied to A at the center of mass.
We'll call it this.
Can I find an equal and opposite set
of forces at the contacts that would sum up and equal this?
So maybe as an optimization problem, say,
can I find the forces at the contact points
i such that the sum of the contacts i equals mg,
and the torques in general, too?
[WRITING ON BOARD]
I'm trying to find a balance between these things.
And it turns out that the geometry of making
these sums match, that the summing forces is easy.
Summing friction cones also turns out to be easy.
It turns out that if I wanted to find these forces subject
to the F of Ci inside the friction cone-- I
don't know if I said that well enough.
This thing becomes non-zero because
of the coordinate transform.
But if you want to say, is there a force that's
inside the friction cone that will resist this,
you could write that as a very simple optimization problem.
Find me some forces subject to their constraints
so that the sums match.
But I also was trying to say last time,
there's a beautiful geometric picture of this.
We said if that vector lands inside the friction cone,
then there's a static equilibrium.
And if it doesn't land inside the friction cone,
then there's not.
So I want to talk you through the slightly more
general version of that now.
Do people remember that statement?
And do you grok that statement?
Or should we-- if your task is to find a force that
has to live inside this cone, that the sum of these forces
has to be equal and opposite to this,
there's a geometry to that.
So you can add the sum of forces is sort
of the element-wise version of it.
But I can also say the sum of some sets
and ask if the sum of those sets,
if this vector is in the element of the sum of those sets.
OK, that's called the Minkowski sum in this case.
There's something called the Minkowski sum.
[TAPPING]
If you don't know Minkowski sum, it's fine.
I just want you to get the intuition.
But if you knew the Minkowski sum,
it's super useful to know how general this idea is.
There is a notion of, given this friction cone and this friction
cone, their locations in space and the basic operations
of the spatial operators, I can tell you
exactly which forces and moments I can resist at this point.
And the Minkowski sum of these two, if they're in line,
is actually just going to look like a vector like this.
And if the negative of this is not inside that,
then I'm not going to be able to resist it.
[TAPPING]
The Minkowski sum says a vector is in the Minkowski sum.
If I can take one element out of this vector
and add it with any element out of this vector
and get the vector I want.
OK, it's just a notion of set sum.
And the Minkowski sum allows us to summarize the entire friction
cone into a contact wrench set.
So this thing here is a contact wrench cone or set.
And it's a beautiful object.
In particular, because even for very complicated bodies
and very complicated friction interactions,
if you know the points and you know mu friction,
then actually this thing is still a convex set.
Given convex cones for your friction in known positions,
this is still actually a really nice object to work with.
So we've lifted the question of will this block slide
into a bigger question saying, does the force of gravity
live inside the contact wrench set?
OK.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
I feel I didn't say that super well, so please ask questions.
Yeah?
Would it be possible to step through an example of what
it would look like to add those two cones together?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
OK.
So the question is, can I step through an example
of adding those two cones together?
The problem is in 2D on the board,
it's almost always trivial when you have unbounded sets.
But let me try.
Let me try to convince you that it's trivial,
and then maybe I can find a bounded set version of it.
But let's try.
So let's say I had a box, and I had a friction cone here,
and a friction cone-- I'll do the red one over here.
OK.
And let's just ignore rotations for now.
Let's just say ignore rotations.
This is because I'm making an example on the spot,
and I don't know how to draw torques out of the board.
Although the picture is actually really good.
All right, so we're 2D, and we're going to ignore rotations.
Then the question of what is the Minkowski sum--
if I wanted to take in, say, what forces can I resist
with those two frictional contacts?
Then the Minkowski sum of these two sets-- well, first of all,
because the forces just translate,
I could move them to the same coordinate frame
with no extra operations.
I'm just going to move this over,
because the forces didn't depend on the position.
Only the moments depended on the position.
And now if I ask if these two sets-- if I add those two sets
together in the Minkowski sense, meaning for any vector,
can I find a vector that's in-- one vector in this set
and one vector in this set that describes,
let's say, this vector, then the way
to think about the Minkowski sums
is to take any one set and drag the other set along with it.
So you're going to convolve the other sets.
You're going to draw, like, OK, I've got a point here,
but I also have a point here.
Like if I chose this point in the blue set,
I can still choose any of these points in the next set.
OK, so it's the shadow that gets pulled out
when you drag the second set across all points
of the first set.
Those are the forces that are admissible,
given those two friction cones.
And I think it's always trivial in 2D,
because I can get any force.
As long as I have a non-zero friction cone,
even if they're not lined up, I think
I could resist any force.
Because this is because they're infinite.
So basically, you could take your brick
and you could just squeeze the heck out of it
and resist any force.
There's no force you couldn't in this simple analysis.
If you allowed orientation changes,
if then, for instance, this, the way I've drawn it, actually,
if I allowed orientations, this would be susceptible to torques
like this, because both these forces are trying to resist
motion in this direction.
And these forces are trying to resist
motion in the same direction.
If you apply the torque like this,
my fingers wouldn't be able to stop you without moving.
So you'd actually be able to break free of me like this.
And what shape would that be?
What shape would that be?
The result in--
So it turns out-- so because the relationship
with forces in the Cartesian frame,
if I wanted to put them into the frame of the origin,
then I would get-- see?
My forces here for the cross product here
would be resisting things like this.
So that would be the vector either coming out of the board
or into the board.
There's a sign that matters here.
So I have a cross product like that.
But basically, both of these are going to put a vector--
let's call it out of the board.
And if I'm off by a sign, I apologize.
Both of these are going to give me
a cross product that's pointing out of the board.
So the torque that's pointing into the board--
I got it right.
Yeah.
Thank you.
The torque that's pointing into the board,
I would not be able to resist.
Because the Cartesian-- or the Minkowski sum of the two
vectors that are coming out of the board
cannot resist the vector going into the board.
I knew 2D is easier.
Yeah?
But that's a good question.
And I hope I said that OK.
Yes?
This is totally directional.
We're talking about infinite force.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes, great.
So these analysis, when I'm thinking about it as a cone,
so far, we're thinking about unlimited amounts of force
being applied.
Yeah.
There's a more sophisticated version of it,
where you could even have torque limits in your hand.
So that would imply a force limit here.
It would be a bounded cone.
OK.
We can do that with Jacobians and the like.
That's OK.
But there's really this beautiful geometry
of reasoning about all possible forces
that I could get out of a set of frictional contacts.
Now, what makes a good grasp?
Sorry to have taken that a little longer than I meant.
But what makes a good grasp?
What makes a good grasp is that you have a large contact wrench
cone, that when I put all of my frictional contacts together,
you're able to resist all of the possible disturbances
that I might have.
So in general, maybe I don't even know the mass of this.
So no matter what the mass is, I want
to be able to resist the force of gravity.
So that would mean that I'd need to have a contact wrench
cone that could resist arbitrary forces
in the vertical direction.
Maybe I think there's some guy that
comes by every once in a while and applies--
or forces torques in the y-axis.
I've got an adversary that walks into lab every Tuesday at 3
and applies torques around the y-axis.
In which case, I'd want my contact wrench cone
to be robust in that direction.
If your contact wrench cone contains
all possible forces and moments, then you've
achieved force closure.
That's the definition of force closure.
And as you can see from this simple example,
that it is possible.
It's not even that hard.
If you have enough fingers, in six degrees of freedom,
you need a handful of fingers and a lot of friction, maybe.
But force closure, if I can resist arbitrary spatial
forces.
Spatial forces are also called wrenches.
This object that is the staffed torque and force
is a spatial force or a wrench.
OK, so that's a beautiful idea.
Yes, please.
Do you need to go to any possible force
or forces that are behind?
So force closure is conservative.
It says you must be able to resist all possible forces.
If you are not able to achieve such a force closure grasp,
or if you have torque limits or other things on your robot,
then you might not be able to ask for pure force closure.
You might say, let me restrict my attention
to the forces that I think are actually
going to happen in this scenario.
Good.
So I hope that the high level message at least comes through
is that there's this contact wrench object.
And there's actually a beautiful geometry of it.
If you want to get into the optimization of contact forces,
there's a beautiful geometry through the Minkowski sum.
But there's actually also a very important lesson.
Actually, this picture is not so bad for telling that lesson.
One of the strongest lessons from this
is that if you want to be robust, it's pretty effective--
let me make it not a box.
Let me make it a slightly more interesting object--
that if I were to pick places where I could possibly
make contact, all things equal, if you
want to have a big contact wrench,
it's really good to choose points that are collinear
and pointing at each other.
So if I were to pick this set instead of this set,
these are called collinear antipodal points.
Antipodal because the normals associated with those points
are pointing the normal here and the normal here
are pointing like opposite poles.
OK?
And they're lined up.
You can write this analysis in general,
but this analysis tells us that all other things equal,
try to pick your points directly across from each other.
And not in arbitrary-- this is a directly across from each other,
but its normals might be pointing not at each other.
Ideally, you get your friction cones
pointing right at each other.
And that's a very robust grasp if you
get two points of contact, try to pick them like that.
Yes?
What point is that?
Because I thought just now you said
that it would drag across the whole shape,
and so wouldn't it go into the 2D space
or just come into the plane no matter what orientation
they are?
Yes.
So I think it's 2D proved to be too simple.
I mean, because I think even if there's no rotations,
then you're going to resist any translational force.
If you lined up, then you would be
able to also resist any torques.
But in this situation, you were not able to.
So I guess with orientation, it is OK.
This example is enough to see why it's better
to be like this than like this.
And the reason is because when they're like this,
those two are contributing opposite signs in the torque,
whereas this one, they're contributing
the same sign in the torque.
They're both torquing in the same direction around that.
There is some point in the body about which they contribute
the same sign torque.
It doesn't have to be the center of mass.
As long as there's some point on the body
where they contribute the same torque,
then you're susceptible to somebody
coming and applying a torque to you.
OK, so I think a very reasonable thing
to do if you want to pick up Spock the duck,
then is to take this important lesson from grasp analysis.
But that can be applied with very little knowledge
of the object.
If I want to prove that the center of mass
and the gravitational vector is inside a cone,
that requires knowledge of the center of mass.
That requires knowledge of the object in some sense.
But if I don't know that, that as a good heuristic,
I'm going to look for antipodal collinear points.
And what we're going to try to do next
is say if you just look at a point cloud,
you have no notion of what's an object, what's not an object,
how much they weigh.
But you just try to find places on the object
where you can get good antipodal grasps.
And that's a pretty darn good heuristic
for getting a good stable grasp.
And we'll see how far it goes.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, I see your question.
Well, let me make sure I understand.
So you're saying I picked some strange points,
but then I'll kind of turn my hand so that they are lined up?
[INAUDIBLE]
Good.
So this is not about the current force you're exerting.
This is about the normal of the geometry,
which sets limits on what forces you could possibly exert.
So this is the shape of the object.
This is not my current choice of grasping strategy-- of force.
Yeah?
OK, so let's step through-- well,
the next thing I'm going to do is I'm going to step through.
We're going to go from our point cloud.
We're going to figure out how to estimate some normals.
And we're going to apply that to doing grasp selection.
Yeah?
OK.
I've got some-- I've got a demo for this.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
All right.
So it turns out you've already seen normal estimation
a little bit.
You saw plane fitting in your ransack problem.
And we're going to have you do the normal estimation details.
We just gave that as a method in the plane fitting.
But we're going to give you the problem
of doing normal estimation.
I think we picked that as one of the problems.
But this is the basic operation.
So I've got my mustard bottle.
OK?
I've got the point clouds from my mustard bottle
straight out of the camera.
And what I'd like to do is estimate the local geometry
of that frame.
And I think I've got this.
Yeah, OK.
Here's how it works, right?
So try to get it centered here.
Basically, the operation we're going to go through--
first, we have to process the point cloud
into a reasonable form to do these operations.
If it's too noisy, then plane fitting might be not optimal.
You want to do it on the densest possible point cloud.
And you want to do it on all the points from all the cameras.
So we'll step through that sequence.
But the basic operation is, given a point cloud,
I'm going to estimate its normals by fitting a plane
to the n nearest neighbors.
That plane defines the normal vector.
And we'll see it actually also defines
the directions of curvature with the same plane fitting
algorithm.
It's a very useful operation for trying
to decide if you're going to put your finger there or not.
This one is not going to have any photographs,
because it's got no backside.
But we can do it with multiple cameras.
We'll do better.
OK, so let's figure out how that works.
Normal estimation from point clouds.
So we're here.
Actually, the first step is just there's just some processing
that you have to do.
So the processing that I went through
in that particular setup was first
I took the point cloud that was from the cameras
around the bins.
I cropped the point cloud.
That's sort of an easy thing to do based on some xyz location.
Because the first point cloud comes in,
and it has the other cameras in the view.
It has the bins in the view.
This is all pretty confusing.
So I'm going to crop to an xyz bounding box.
Then we do normal estimation.
And the reason you do normal estimation-- let's see.
So let me just say what the other steps are.
Then I'm going to merge the point clouds
from multiple cameras.
And then I'm going to down sample the point cloud in order
to make it more reasonable for my grasp analysis.
But the order of these things is important.
The reason that I do normal estimation
before I merge the point cloud is
because what we're going to find out is-- I mean, you'll see--
is that fitting a plane to these points
will tell me the normal, but won't tell me
which direction is the normal.
So before I get rid of the correspondence
between these points and the camera,
I have to flip the normals towards the camera.
There's a simple little step saying,
you estimated the plane.
I don't know if the normal is this direction
or this direction.
But if the camera was over there,
then I know that the normal is going
to be pointing towards the camera.
So you need to know which points came from which camera
in order to do that.
And you prefer to do the normal estimation on the dense point
cloud.
Then you merge the point clouds into the one big thing.
And then you can down sample and use more efficient algorithms
from then on.
It's kind of crazy to think that we do this all the time.
Compute all of the normals for all of the points
coming in using k nearest neighbor queries
at all of the points.
This was one of those examples when
I started working with point clouds
I don't know how many years ago now.
I was like, no, surely you don't do it for all the points
all the time on every frame.
Yeah, they do.
That's just what you do.
You could do it on a multi-process if you want.
You could put it on a GPU if you want now.
But that is actually a surprisingly lightweight
computation.
And people just do that all the time.
It seems inelegant to me, but that's standard fare.
OK, but once we have our cropped point cloud,
let's just make sure-- the line fitting algorithm
is actually super clean and super nice.
So I want you to think through it with me.
Actually, I guess this is a good stretch time.
You guys want to take a quick stretch as I'm
about to write down the next set of equations?
Quick stretch.
People seem to still like it, the three of you that
are actually commenting on the-- everybody
should write comments.
And when you fill out the survey,
I know you're tired at the end of the problem set.
But I want more comments.
I want to hear what you think.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
All right, let's estimate our normals.
How do we fit a plane to a bunch of points?
It's super simple.
This is like-- I really like how clean this is.
So I'm going to write it as an optimization,
because I always do.
I'm going to say I want to fit a bunch of points centered
around my vector p, and I want to estimate the normal vector.
So how am I going to define that?
I'm going to search for a normal vector.
I'll call my normal vector n.
And I want to find the normal-- I'm
going to define the normal vector is
over all of my nearest neighbor points, i.
I would like to find the vector n such
that the dot product between point i and my nominal p--
this is my point at which I'm evaluating my normal.
And this is my normal.
I want this dotted with the normal to be 0, ideally.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going
to try to minimize the squared sum of the dot products.
The n, which is this close to 0 dot product with all
of my vectors, is the one I want.
And I want to constrain it to be a unit vector.
So what's the picture you should have in your head here?
I've got my point of interest here.
I'll make it blue.
I have a bunch of other points in the scene
that are my nearest neighbors.
Each one of those, the vector pi minus p looks like this.
These are the pi's minus p's.
Again, it's a little rough on the board,
but even in 2D I can sort of do it.
And I want to estimate the normal vector.
These are pi minus p, and this is n.
I want the dot product of these to be 0,
as close to 0 as possible.
And of course, I'm going to get it only up to a symmetry.
This one should be the same equally good answer.
The optimization is really nice, actually, really simple.
The way to see it is to just rewrite this.
I'm going to give you the geometric version of it.
Of course, the answer is, again, singular value decomposition.
But it always is somehow.
I'm going to write this slightly differently.
I'll break that up.
I'll say it's the sum over i.
I've got the dot product is a scalar, right?
A vector dot with a vector, you know, times a vector.
That's a scalar.
A scalar squared.
I could just as well have written that, though,
like this.
This is also the scalar.
And I'm going to multiply that again by this other scalar
here.
This is just playing the trace trick here.
That's exactly the same quantity.
I just unrolled the squared.
One more step here.
Let me write it like this.
N transpose sum over i, P_i.
Same thing.
I just did a little algebraic manipulation there.
And we'll call this-- this is the data matrix of the day
here.
This is our data matrix.
There's no decision variables in there.
That's just what we're getting straight from the point cloud.
And our decision variables-- so our problem here
is just minimize n, n transpose, Wn subject to n equals 1.
Remember what we're doing.
We're just trying to fit a plane by finding the normal vector.
OK.
So let me draw that in 2D here.
I've got n1, n2.
I know that I want my n to be a unit vector.
So this is the n equals 1.
This thing is just a quadratic form,
a positive quadratic form, because it's
the sum of these positive things.
OK.
It's going to have-- so it's going to be a bowl centered
at the origin that's going to have some long axes
and some short axes.
Let me call it the long axis like this.
So this is like the bowl.
Do you see what I'm trying to draw here?
That's supposed to be the origin there.
This is n transpose Wn is some constant.
These are the level sets of that bowl.
Right?
Yes.
AUDIENCE: Is that 3D?
PROFESSOR: I'm trying to do it just as if I was doing it in--
I'm plotting two of the axes of a 3D thing, right?
This bowl would be coming up out of the plane towards you.
Think of that as a bowl where the axis coming out
is the cost.
So what's the optimal n?
The smallest eigenvector.
Is the eigenvector corresponding to the smallest
eigenvalue?
Absolutely.
Right?
So in this picture, it should be more centered.
But it's going to be the place where
the bowl is the most elongated.
Right?
Because the cost is going to go up faster in this direction
and up slowly in that direction, the place where it's elongated.
So there's two optimal answers, n star.
And they're right there as we expected.
We didn't expect to be able to pick this one or this one.
Both of them are optimal answers.
OK?
So it's exactly that n star is the eigenvector corresponding
to smallest eigenvalue of w.
It's the unit eigenvector.
Right?
OK.
So the way to estimate the normal of a point cloud
is just to assemble this little data matrix
and take some eigenvectors and eigenvalues,
and you've got the normal.
You've done your normal estimation.
And you can do this with a KD tree,
doing the data structure for nearest neighbor, for instance.
Pick your 30 nearest neighbors, go
through all the points in the point cloud,
and just compute your normals.
And that's what people do.
Right?
You get these funny looking point clouds
with their normal vectors, yeah?
All over.
Again, the way you pick this one or this one
is you have one extra operation afterwards.
You say my camera is over here, so I
have to pick the normal.
If the normal was pointed-- you could just
pick one of them arbitrarily.
If the normal was pointed on the inside,
just flip it around so it's pointing at the camera,
because you know you can't see behind the objects.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So this is just a more robust way to do this.
So if I had exactly two points, like you said,
I could do that computation.
But now imagine that they're noisy point clouds,
or it's not a perfect plane.
That's a great question.
It's not a perfect plane.
This is saying find the best one that
summarizes in a least square sense over the 30
nearest neighbors.
So it's going to be more robust to small variations
in the pixels, or even maybe there was a little corner
in the real point cloud.
No noise, but there's just a corner.
This is going to be more robust to that.
Great question.
Yeah?
Super interesting thing.
Let me just get one more in.
So if I were to do almost exactly the same optimization,
but I were to say, what if I want to maximize that over n?
I want to maximize my dot product.
So in the picture here, that's going
to look like this, these points over here.
And the exact same computation, the one
that's the maximal dot product is
the one that's the direction of least curvature.
So the maximum, this is the direction of least curvature.
And it's exactly just the eigenvalue
corresponding to the largest eigenvector.
Yeah, what's up?
Yeah, I was wondering if you know
if you'd ransacked this as well, or could you
just do it all?
Yeah, that's a good question.
So we did do the ransack for the plane estimation.
So that was an example where you really
want to get the normal of the table,
the plane estimated of the table.
So it was worth the extra cost of doing ransack
to try to get that right, for instance.
I think in the-- I'm just going to run this
over my whole point cloud.
We typically don't do ransack.
We typically would be-- I think that's just
sort of an arbitrary where the computation falls decision.
I think you're right.
You could do better normal estimation
with ransack in this step two.
Great question.
Yeah?
What do you mean by least curvature?
Least curvature.
So if I were to look at the side of my bunny, my Stanford
bunny or whatever, so I've got some point cloud here.
Look, view from the side.
It has some curvature.
And I've got another direction where
the bunny is kind of more curvy.
So if I were to sum up the-- I had my normal here.
And I have my p vectors like this.
So the vector of least-- and in the other axis
they look like this.
And there's more like this.
So the axis where it aligns the most,
where if I could pick a particular vector that the dot
product is the highest, then that's
going to be the one where the bunny is more flat.
And the one that's left over is going
to be the direction where you're more curvy.
It happens since we know this is a symmetric matrix.
And symmetric matrices have orthonormal, even orthogonal,
in this case orthogonal bases.
We know that even that third axis,
that intermediate eigenvector, has an interpretation
as this last axis.
But I think the math tells us that the dot product that
is maximal is the direction that's the flattest.
If it was completely flat, then you'd expect it.
You would just pick something.
They'd be equivalent eigenvalues.
OK, so let's put this all together
so you can sort of imagine then how I go through this step.
I'm going to look into the bin.
I'm going to crop my point cloud.
I'm going to run this normal estimation over.
I'm going to get my normals, and I'll get my curvature
if I wanted to use it.
I'll pull them all together into merged point clouds.
And then I'm going to downsample.
Downsampling is another one that-- it's
a relatively efficient algorithm.
The way people typically do it, they
would just make a voxel grid over your point cloud
and summarize all of the points that
landed in the same voxel as a single point.
That would be the standard voxelized downsampling.
And you can keep your normals around.
You average your normals, which is kind of weird.
But you just average your normals
of all the points that landed in the same voxel.
But they're standard algorithms.
And there's libraries like Open3D
that are just these lists of-- they
have all mature implementations of all the normal, the best
point cloud algorithms.
Before that, there was PCL.
PCL wasn't maintained for a while.
It looks like it's being maintained again,
but I don't know by whom.
But there are standard point cloud algorithms.
I went through-- we've implemented the simple ones
in Drake, but Drake isn't trying to cover all of these.
Just enough that you guys don't have to install also Open3D.
Because it was a big install that broke all the time.
So now, this is enough for us to do a basic grasp selection
algorithm.
Here's my grasp selection algorithm at work.
I'm going to load up my gripper, load up my scene.
OK.
I'm just hallucinating the gripper
and assuming I can fly around a little bit.
And I'm going to evaluate potential grasps
with no knowledge of the object by doing a little bit of point
cloud math.
So first, I've gone through, I've taken my point cloud,
and I've computed its normals and down sampled
and everything like that.
But now, for any potential nominal grasp,
I'm going to do another little small batch of point cloud
computations.
So first of all, since I want to find antipodal grasps, what
I'm going to do is I'm going to take the place where
my fingers are likely to touch, and I'm
going to crop the point cloud so that the red points are
the ones that are the points of interest.
OK.
And then if I were to have both screens up--
but maybe that's hard right now-- but every time I'm
doing this, it's actually printing a cost.
For every possible candidate like this,
it's computing a sum of the normals
that are in those red points.
Basically, it's saying I'm going to reward normals that
are antipodal and pointing to in the axis of my gripper.
And I'm going to just sum up.
The more normals I have that are pointing right at my gripper
inside those red, the better.
And then I add a little bit more, a few more costs.
These are now just very ad hoc.
But I want to come down from above.
I don't want to pick it up from inside the table.
And I call it infinite cost.
If the gripper collides with the point cloud like this,
that's infinite cost, or if it collides with the bins.
OK.
But the algorithm now is just going to be--
so I'm doing this manually so you could see.
And if you run the GUI yourself, you'll
see in the console it's printing out the costs
and whether it knows it's in collision or not.
And our grasp selection algorithm
for the day, which demands almost nothing
about the objects, is I'm just going
to pick a bunch of-- actually, I'm
going to pick a bunch of points in the point cloud,
put my hand around them, and then just evaluate
the cost.
I'll pick 100 of them, and I'll take the best.
And in this case, I'm going to just take 100 of them
and plot-- I think it runs.
I forgot to run it.
Yeah.
If I generate grasp candidates then, there we go.
I've got random objects falling in the bin.
And I just drew the five best candidates.
And it looks like I didn't simulate it.
I think the things are still falling down.
That was smart.
I let it simulate for a second.
It looks like it didn't quite settle.
And then I said, find some point clouds.
And it does its thing.
And then I just pick the best one.
I go ahead and grasp, wash, rinse, and repeat.
That's a surprisingly effective algorithm.
I'm going to show you by the next time
sort of the full version of this.
I'll maybe give you a preview of it now.
I wrote it very recently.
I hope it runs on this machine.
See how we go.
And I'm going to keep working on it.
But yeah, OK.
So this is basically the end-to-end demo
using exactly that.
And it will go down just using this strategy.
It happened to pick there on the block.
It'll go over using exactly the plans
we did before with my clearance, height, whatever.
It'll go drop it off in the other bin.
Wash, rinse, and repeat.
Just go back.
As soon as it goes down, it takes another new point cloud,
chooses the grasp.
And we'll add more and more logic to it
to know if it fails multiple times,
to give up and go to the other one.
So that is an antipodal grasp.
It's not the one I would have picked
if I had written a better algorithm, right?
There are limitations to the antipodal metric.
Actually, that's a great example.
I want to talk about the limitations
here in the last few minutes.
So why was that a ridiculous grasp?
What do you know that it doesn't know?
What's that?
That the corner is not stable.
So it was evaluating the reds, the red points.
They were arbitrarily close.
It wasn't looking like one step away from the reds, right?
So that's one thing you know, is that there's
a notion of robustness that isn't captured by that metric.
What's another thing?
Torque.
Center of mass, right?
You know you should pick objects around their center of mass
because it'll be able to resist more torque.
This is-- oops.
I ran into the bin.
That'll be fixed by Tuesday.
Yeah.
Yeah, good.
But yeah, so it has no notion of mass.
It doesn't know what the objects are, right?
So it has no concept that can do that.
And it ran into the camera.
All right, let me just call this a work in progress.
Oh, look at that.
That'll be better by Tuesday.
[INAUDIBLE]
Good.
So to what extent-- and this is actually great.
So there's a couple ways that what I've said
was inconsistent with the fact that I just said
you should know where the center of mass is, right?
So one was that-- yes, I think where you pick the object up
is not going to affect the motion of the arm because
of the gearbox thing, right?
So you're absolutely right.
The reflected inertia of the gearboxes
can dominate the mass.
So that robot's going to move mostly the same,
whether it's picked up a red brick, two red bricks,
whatever, OK?
Whether the red brick stays nicely inside the hand
is about whether the gravitational wrench
is inside the friction cone that you've achieved.
Now, there's one more point, which
is that I'm actually commanding that gripper
to have a particular amount of force, of gripping force.
So it's not actually an infinite friction cone.
It has limits on how much force it's going to apply,
partly because I don't want to crush Spock, right?
That's what I was trying to say.
If I don't know anything about an object,
then maybe grabbing it with infinite force
isn't a good idea, and the hand isn't
capable of infinite force.
So that is also a way that the mass
could matter more than the analysis we've done,
the clean analysis would suggest.
Great example.
Great question.
Yeah?
So in the computation that you showed,
there's no distinguishing between objects, right?
Correct.
I understand if two separate point clouds are connected
at all.
Spot on.
So there's no sense in which it knows that two separate point
clouds are connected.
Yeah, and I have an example of that.
Was that your point?
Or-- yeah.
Yes, so what are some limitations
of only using geometry?
And actually, did you see that one right there?
That was exactly your case.
Let me start it over again.
There's two objects there, and they
happen to have their backs kind of close,
and they had antipodal grasps like that.
But it wasn't the same object.
It just got it wrong, and it had no reason to-- it
didn't think about that.
It found antipodal grasps.
They seemed about the right width apart.
It went for the squeeze.
So people call those double picks, for instance,
for exactly that reason.
It also will do things-- like, if you run this long enough
and you throw things in the bin, you'll
see it do what we saw on the red brick,
but you see it in more ridiculous.
You'll pick up a hammer or something by the edge.
It has no concept of center of mass.
It has no concept of object.
So it's not great, but it's surprisingly good.
The other-- I'd say another big limitation of the approach
as I've advertised it here, and I
think a place where the deep learning versions really
do outperform, is on partial views.
So my point cloud is only going to see what my cameras can
immediately see.
If there's a back to the object that was occluded,
or I didn't have a camera over here,
then I've lost my ability to reason
about that antipodal grasp.
If I were to run the algorithm a bunch of times
and just train a network to predict this,
it could in some sense hallucinate
the back of the object.
And so I think these partial views are
one of the big places where the deep learning-based approaches
do outperform this.
But you get pretty far with just a little bit
of geometry processing.
Transparent objects, there's a couple other cases
where I think this doesn't work well.
But it's surprisingly good.
Cool.
Does that make sense?
Any more questions about that?
So the weak part, which is the part I didn't code up yet well,
is the higher level logic.
And that's what we'll talk about on Tuesday.
No, not Tuesday, this Thursday, because we have no class
next Tuesday, which says lots of time for me to fix the demo.
But at some point, when you start writing this higher level
logic of, OK, I picked it three times,
it's time to go try the other bin,
we need more machinery to start dealing with that.
And we'll do it next week.
[BLANK_AUDIO]