[SILENCE]
How are people feeling for their project proposals?
Good shape? Thumbs up? Thumbs down?
Still figuring it out? No idea? Thumbs down?
I'll stick around a little bit after lecture if anybody wants to chat right now,
but just reach out to us and we'll give you any feedback or ideas we can this week.
Okay, well, welcome back everybody.
We're going to talk today about the deep learning version of perception.
And actually, this is one of the harder lectures for me to give
because I think the variance of experience in the room is the highest of all the topics we cover.
I can sort of assume, it might be a few years since you've drawn a free body diagram,
but everybody's drawn free body diagrams at some point.
And here, I think some people have just heard, everybody's heard about it.
Some of you might be training deep networks right now on your laptop while we're in lecture,
some of you haven't dabbled yet, right?
And there are plenty of courses here that can teach you the details of deep learning,
which I would highly recommend. I'm not going to try to do any of that.
Even computer vision, right, there's huge, there's whole courses on computer vision.
I'm not going to try to cover that.
What I'm going to try to do is dial in a few of the key topics,
enough that if you haven't seen it, you can use it effectively.
If you have seen it, I hope to bring some ideas from manipulation
that you maybe haven't thought about the computer vision pipelines from this perspective.
More than any other lecture, I would say, I'm going to be reading you guys
and trying to speed up or slow down based on what you guys are feeling.
Feel free to ask questions, feel free to be like, within reason.
Okay, so I do think that the needs of manipulation for,
you know, put particular pressures on our deep learning pipelines
that are unique and interesting.
Let me just remind you sort of the motivation we talked about
is that we've done a lot of work with geometric perception
and we had a whole pipeline of clearing clutter out of the bins
that didn't use anything from deep learning, right?
And it's surprisingly good.
Like it can just pick up objects all day long,
you can throw any objects in the bin, it'll do its thing.
But it doesn't get done everything that we want, right?
It has flaws, even if your goal is object agnostic,
you don't care what objects are moved,
you might still have problems because it's not just the fact that it doesn't know about objects,
it can make silly decisions about where to put its fingers, right?
It might pick up the hammer from the corner and that's just a bad strategy
because there's a large wrench due to the gravitation
that would cause the grasp to be fragile, right?
So there's a lot, when you go to decide what to do,
where to pick things up, you're bringing a lot of background information
into the picture that geometry alone doesn't tell you.
Even physics alone doesn't tell you,
maybe don't touch the sharp part of the knife, for instance, right?
Okay.
In practice, in the particular tool chain that we gave you,
there are quirks like picking up two objects at once
because you don't even know where the extents of an object are, right?
And so that's a problem that these come in.
The geometric stuff can take its best effort with partial views.
If you have cameras only on one side,
there's a backside of the object that you can't see,
your point cloud reasoning is only going to get you so far.
At some point, inherently, the way to get farther
is to have previous experience which tells you what's on the other side of the object.
A data-driven method becomes a key approach, right?
And it happens that because of our sensors today,
it turns out that some of our geometric reasoning
falls down for transparent objects and other things like that.
But fundamentally, there are tasks that just require you to understand objects.
If you say, "I don't care about the cheese-it box, I don't care about the spam,
I want to move the mustard bottles over because someone just bought a mustard bottle
and I need to put it in the box and ship it," right?
Then that fundamentally requires knowledge of the objects.
Okay.
So, there's been a revolution in deep learning over the last few years.
It was powered mostly by data, right?
Among other things, and compute, and good ideas, and a lot of things.
But everybody talks about the big data.
So, one of the first topics I want to throw in and talk about here is,
how do we get to big data for manipulation?
[Writing on Board]
So, the watershed moments for deep learning for computer vision
ran through the ImageNet dataset and the ImageNet challenge,
where Fei-Fei and her team acquired labels of images, of like 128 million images.
A lot of images. I think it's 1.28 million.
I was off by a couple of orders of magnitude, but it's a big number. That's the point.
So, the go-ahead idea in ImageNet was to crowdsource image labels.
But it took a lot of acquiring images, cleaning images, and then labeling images
to make one big dataset which powered a lot of computer vision.
If I want to pick up mustard bottles, I don't want to start by labeling 1.28 million mustard bottles.
So, what are we to do?
So, I want to just talk that through, and how do we get there for manipulation?
To tell that story, let me just make sure I define our basic concepts.
When you're talking about the standard computer vision tasks in learning,
we have to distinguish between a couple of different categories.
The first one would be image recognition.
I just say, "Is there a sheep in the image? Is there a dog in the image?"
With what confidence would I say that there is a sheep in the image or a dog in the image?
That's the classic first task for computer vision.
That's what ImageNet had a lot of labels for initially.
ImageNet also got labels for object detection, which is to say not only that there is a sheep,
but here's a bounding box around the sheep.
So, the output would be two numbers, for instance, the two sets of four numbers,
the pixel location of the lower left and the pixel location of the upper right, for instance.
We'll talk about exactly how that's done, too.
And then there's two different types of segmentation, which is very common,
which would be the semantic segmentation.
I think the picture tells this very well.
Semantic segmentation says, "Make all of the pixels that are sheep pixels blue
and the dog pixels red," for instance, in this case,
versus instance-level segmentation, which is to say,
"For every different sheep, I want a different label."
So, that's the background for this.
Which of those do we want for our manipulation pipeline?
If we just want to pick the mustard bottles, for instance, out,
which of those is going to be the most useful?
Object detection is going to be super useful, right?
So, at least we could then go in and use our geometric reasoning
on the point cloud inside the bounding box, for instance.
If we can get pixel-wise segmentation, we could do even better, right?
If we can ignore, you know, we've talked about the limitations of ICP,
for instance, with outliers.
If you could really take away all of the points that are not associated
with the mustard bottle, then that's even the dream.
So, instance segmentation is actually the one that's proven to be
the most transferable, I would say, from the computer vision world
directly into manipulation context of this.
We're going to see where I'm going to spend most of the time on Thursday
talking about all of the things that computer vision people normally don't do
that help, that are more specific to manipulation.
But first, we'll try to understand how to get instance segmentation
into our manipulation pipeline.
Okay?
And there's actually two ways. We'll talk about it at the end.
So, I'd say both of our pipelines so far, we could say,
and people do actively use instance segmentation.
So, we'll take an RGB image, we'll pick out the pixels,
and we'll then do, for instance, ICP to find the known location
and then pick up a known, you know, use model-based grasp synthesis.
But you could also use instance segmentation with our
clutter clearing grasp selection.
So, if I just took the point clouds that were left,
the points in the point cloud that were left after a segmentation
and then I did my antipodal grasping, that'll work too.
Both of those are super powerful pipelines.
Okay, so ImageNet was mostly about object detection and image recognition.
Cocoa dataset was the sort of watershed moment for more instance segmentation.
They got many fewer, hundreds of thousands of labels,
but at the pixel-wise level.
Now, imagine going through and labeling every pixel of every image, right,
for a hundred thousand images.
It's a good annotation tools, right, and a lot of people on Amazon Turk at the time, right,
and they got it done, but that's a laborious task, okay.
Some of the first annotation tools came out of CSAIL.
Antonio Torraldo is upstairs.
He's got a lab that's done some of the really defining work in this.
And when this was all starting and he was educating the rest of us
about crowdsourcing image labels and stuff like this,
he said if you look at the quality of the image labels,
you pay people like a penny to do that, right,
it's incredibly good.
He's like if you paid me a penny, I'd be just like, you know,
go to the next one, but somehow people are just really, really meticulous
about getting every single pixel right.
And he said if you look at the statistics and there was an anomaly
of like someone who had labeled way more than anybody else,
and it turned out it was his mom.
He said my mom's an incredibly good labeler, yeah.
Okay, but that was this revolution where people started to get
crowdsourced large-scale datasets for image segmentation.
One of the crazy things, one of the magical things,
if you look at the COCO dataset, for instance,
it's got a bunch of different categories.
You can just go on the website and list them, right.
It's got bicycles, cars, motorcycles, traffic lights,
that's useful for autonomous driving, right.
Birds, cats, dogs, horses, sheep,
those aren't the things that I want to manipulate most of the time.
There's a few manipulation-specific ones.
You know, snowboards and plates, there we go, that's a useful one.
Plates and bottles and cups and forks.
I'd say more than, if you take something that's pre-trained on COCO,
it's going to call most of the things in your bin
a mug or a bottle or a fork or something like that, okay.
So this is super useful, but it's not quite enough
for us to do most of the things we want in manipulation.
One of the biggest ideas, and I don't think anybody really saw it coming,
it's even hard to justify still, given our best theory of deep learning,
but one of the amazing things that happened in deep learning
is the story of transfer learning, right.
So COCO is a hundred thousand image dataset.
ImageNet was 1.28 million images.
The crazy thing is that if you train on ImageNet first,
even though it's only got image detection and object detection labels,
and you take those weights and then you retrain on COCO,
instead of starting from scratch and only using COCO,
then you can actually do better on COCO
because you trained on ImageNet before.
Okay.
So this is the idea of transfer learning or fine-tuning, okay.
[Writing on Board]
Training on one dataset, pre-training, let's say, on one dataset,
almost always ImageNet, for instance,
because it's big and diverse in the right way.
Improves performance on a downstream,
let me just say on COCO here.
It didn't have to be that, right.
Why should you, you know, why would you do better
having trained previously on ImageNet
than just training directly on the objective?
From the optimization point of view, that's a super weird thing to think, right.
If I were to say, if you solve an inverse kinematics problem on a panda,
then you move it over and there you're going to solve
an inverse kinematics problem better on an IWA.
I'd look at you like you're crazy, because that's just a crazy thing to do, okay.
But that is a property that we've seen in the deep network architectures
that people are using day in and day out.
So a standard thing to do, even if you change tasks a little bit
from object detection to instance segmentation,
you can take your original, let's say, ImageNet dataset,
you've got a deep network with many layers, right,
and the last layer of ImageNet is a mapping from some weird,
you know, neural representation to the labels of ImageNet.
You don't have the same labels in your COCO dataset, okay.
So we rip off the last layer and replace it with a fresh last layer,
which has outputs for the labels that you want in the COCO dataset.
And then, you just retrain, but you don't retrain from scratch.
When you're training, I'll talk a little bit about training,
but not too much about training.
But when you're training, you take the weights that you already acquired from ImageNet
and you just fine-tune them for these layers,
and you've trained from scratch the last one
by just running more gradient descent on COCO.
This is the magic of transfer learning.
Yeah?
[inaudible]
That's right, up to the last layers.
Now, what we're going to see, for instance,
is for the instance segmentation,
you actually put a pretty sophisticated last layer that's different,
but still using the front half of the network from ImageNet, for instance,
is enough to do better on the full task.
Now, the intuition might be that you've somehow learned,
you know, ImageNet was big enough,
you learned something about natural images,
you learned some intermediate representations
that captured the diversity of natural images,
and this put you in the right part of the neural network parameter space
that somehow staying near there and finding the best instance segmentation
was better, you leveraged the diversity of the ImageNet dataset
to do better at COCO.
That's too hand-wavy for my taste, but that's the view of it.
Okay, so this fine-tuning is one of the biggest things
that happened in deep learning.
It didn't have to happen.
It's also what provides us the ability to do, you know,
the same things with smaller datasets in manipulation.
So now the prospect is I don't have to label 128,
or 1.28 million images for manipulation.
It turns out in many cases you can label tens of images,
hundreds of images, and do surprisingly well, sometimes zero, right?
But you have to somehow, you know,
at least that output layer needs to be trained with your new dataset.
Okay, so how do we make the instance-level training data for manipulation?
There's a few sort of standard tools that I'd say
almost every manipulation pipeline is using something kind of like this,
you know, that if you want to come up with a lot of labels,
pixel-wise labels of objects that you're going to manipulate,
this is one called Label Fusion.
Let me tell you the steps.
I mentioned it once before when we were talking about ICP,
but now you have more context here, okay?
So you've got a drill in the lab there.
You want to somehow use this to create a training dataset
with pixel-wise labels of the drill, okay?
The steps are pretty simple.
We're going to first just take a lot,
just move the camera around the drill in lots of different ways.
Then we're going to do a dense reconstruction,
which people do, you know, a few years ago,
it was always with point clouds and these fusion algorithms,
which are a lot like ICP, but basically you're going to make
all of these views with RGB data into one big point cloud.
The same way we fused our multiple views of the cameras,
just imagine doing that with a moving camera, right?
Join all the point clouds together.
So that next step is pretty effective at also estimating
the pose of the camera.
We assumed we knew where the pose of the camera was,
but this will just estimate the pose of the camera.
Okay?
Now we said that ICP isn't strong enough to label the drill
if you just give me a huge point cloud,
which we wanted it to be.
It's not, okay?
But it turns out with a good guess,
then ICP is fantastic, right?
So the pipeline is basically make a user interface
so that after taking a whole video of images,
a human clicks like three times to, you know,
they say here's three points on the drill CAD model.
Here's three points in the generated point cloud.
That's an initial guess.
Humans aren't very accurate at that,
but then it just snaps into place with ICP.
Now you know a ground truth, you know,
up to our ICP resolution,
location, pose of the drill.
But we want instance labels out.
Okay?
So given the CAD model and given the videos,
you can just render back the drill
into all of the images you took.
And now suddenly you have a bunch of,
now this isn't, you know,
these are very correlated images,
so it's not as good as having 100,000
completely different images.
But although they're very correlated,
you have perfect labels,
perfect labels of the pixel-wise mask
of that drill.
Okay?
And there's various ways to make that pipeline,
but something like that has been used
over and over and over again
to generate training data
for relevant manipulation items.
What's amazing is that, you know,
relatively small amounts of training data
with a pre-trained instance segmentation network
works incredibly well in practice.
Yeah? Does that make sense?
Okay.
So that's one way that we get
ground truth labels for our manipulation.
The other big way
is synthetic data.
Okay?
Over and over and over again now,
people have been turning their pipelines
to be more towards using
manipulation-based data generation
to train deep learning systems
that are going to work in the real world.
So I motivated our clutter clearing example
by this case,
but if you look at the RGBD sensor
that we've been using the whole time,
right, we've been using the color image out,
the depth image out,
in order to make our point cloud,
but there's another image that comes out,
which is the label image,
which the real camera, of course,
is designed entirely for generating training data.
And this is just a random example
of me dropping the objects in the bin
and then making perfect pixel-wide masks
from the label image.
It's super interesting that,
I mean, this doesn't look very realistic, right?
We can do a better job.
We have better renderers that are slower,
and I would absolutely recommend you use that
if you want your system-trained simulation
to work in reality,
but always, even the best rendering
is going to have some, we call it a domain gap, right?
That most of the time, a human eye
can tell you which one was simulated,
which one was real.
There's a really interesting trade-off
that happens, though.
So you can give me
some amount of hand-labeled data,
maybe using the label fusion kind of pipeline
where a human has annotated it.
It's close, but it's slightly imperfect,
but they're realistic images.
Or you can give me arbitrary gobs
of basically free data
that are perfectly labeled down to the pixel level
with a domain gap.
It turns out that, I think,
the standard recipe now is to use
a lot of simulated data
and a very little bit of real data,
but a lot of times,
the simulated data is actually enough
to outperform the real data.
Having a domain gap,
but absolutely perfect labels
can actually be better
than having the real images
that are imperfectly labeled.
There's a well-known story
that most of the big real data data sets,
even MNIST, which is the number data set
that everybody starts with in deep learning,
they have errors in the labels, right?
There's somehow a ceiling
in what total performance
the learning system probably can get
unless it has to learn the error,
which is probably almost random.
Human labels are imperfect.
Synthetic generation can get around that.
I went through and I made
just exactly from the clutter clearing.
I just dropped 10,000 images.
I just randomized the initial conditions,
picked from the random bin,
dropped it, waited until they settled,
took a picture, rendered both this
and the object labels, the masks,
the object instances,
a handful of metadata,
and I just made a big data set.
You'll use it on your p-set,
and we'll use it in the examples today.
I did 10,000 images,
which was probably way more than I needed,
but I was going for it.
Rather have too many than too few.
We're going to use this to train
our cheese-it box and mustard bottle detector.
Okay, questions about that so far?
Yeah.
[audience member]
The question being,
if the rendering was realistic
on synthetic data,
so you were able to render
completely realistic,
would there be any tradeoff
between the two?
[David]
That's a good question.
If I could render so that there was
really no domain gap,
I think I would probably always pick that.
The domain gap is more subtle
than you might think.
I emphasize the rendering quality.
Oftentimes, the shadows would look
just a little artificial,
or the lighting is a little too spotlight,
and the real image is more,
whatever.
It's almost always the material
that's rendering hard.
But that's not the part that,
I think the bigger part of the domain gap
that you might not think about,
is just that,
is like the random way
that I made these images.
I dropped objects from the sky,
and they rendered in some initial condition.
But if you look at real sinks,
probably people kind of put the plates
down first, and then the mugs.
There's some statistics of the environments
that I probably didn't capture perfectly
in the sink.
But there's probably,
I used 10 objects,
the ones I had 10 CAD files for.
And the real world is open world,
anybody could put anything in the sink.
So I think that's the domain gap
that's a bigger one.
It's more about the art assets,
and the distributions over
initial conditions,
than the render quality these days.
Yeah, sure.
(audience member speaking)
That's an awesome question.
So yeah, what about the noise?
So, I think that's a really good question.
I think that's a really good question.
So I similarly don't want to tell the entire deep learning optimization story,
but I just feel I want to say a few words to connect the type of optimization landscapes we've talked about,
since this is an optimization problem that's being solved, with what's happening here.
OK, so when we talked about nonlinear optimization before, right,
we said we're going to minimize f of x, for instance,
and maybe f of x was this complicated landscape.
One of the ways that you could do that is with just a gradient descent kind of algorithm, right?
So you have some initial guess, and you go downhill, and you land at a minima.
It's not guaranteed to be the global optima, but it would get you somewhere.
For inverse kinematics, this can be a real problem.
We can get stuck in bad local optima.
There might be a good solution for inverse kinematics,
and we don't find it with gradient descent.
Deep learning is very much using gradient descent, right?
It's using a stochastic version of gradient descent.
The standard way that it's stochastic is just by taking, if you have a huge pipe,
I have my 10,000 bucket images.
I'm going to take a small subset of them, 32 of them or something, at a time,
pass them through the network, and I'll pick a random 32 each time.
That gives me a random evaluation of my gradient,
and I'll do stochastic gradient descent to get down.
That's when you hear people talk about SGD, that's stochastic gradient descent.
But for the purposes of our discussion here, it's almost the same.
What can happen, you know, the stochastic version,
in a general optimization problem, you would think that it has a lot of the same properties.
It might walk downhill a little slower, right?
You might kind of take a meandering path down to the optima.
It might also, the stochastic version of it might bounce out of a local minima, by luck, you know.
But it's roughly this same sort of picture.
So, just like fine-tuning and transfer learning was just an amazing thing that happened in deep learning,
something else amazing happened, which meant that my ability to train this with high confidence and good solutions,
despite it solving this nonlinear optimization, it's somehow working.
And that's been one of the mysteries that people are doing a lot of work in deep learning theory to understand why.
Do people know the basic story of that?
Have people heard the basic story of that?
There's a couple big ideas.
One of them is over-parameterization.
The idea is that the pictures I draw here are wrong.
They're not the pictures for deep learning because we have so many parameters,
even compared to our data, that the landscape is so high-dimensional
that even though I have many nooks and crannies,
they're with high probability probably connected in some weird way in the super high-dimensional space.
In particular, I can talk as little as you guys want about this,
and there's people that know much more about it for sure,
but the basic story is,
if you have, let's say, the simplest version of it is this.
If my second to last layer in my network,
imagine I have the last layer here, and it's really big.
Let's say it's a million possible neurons in my second to last layer,
and then I have a function I'm trying to learn from x to y.
Even if this first part of the network is just completely random,
if I have random vectors here in some high-dimensional space,
then I can actually, with just my last layer,
fit most functions almost perfectly.
And this last layer is actually typically a least squares problem,
and I can expect that to work, and I can expect my training error to go to zero.
For big, complicated networks, just because I had a ridiculously large,
even random network to start with.
That idea is called the neural tangent kernel, if you want.
Or ultra-wide networks.
OK, and then the second thing that seems to happen,
seems to happen,
is something that people refer to as implicit regularization
of stochastic gradient descent.
Which is that,
when I'm, let's say after I've gotten my training error to zero,
I've got sort of random vectors here.
Gradient descent seems to do something good
in the null space of the optimization
that makes the weights here
solve the problem not just in an arbitrary way,
but it somehow chooses not random vectors in here
in a way that generalizes incredibly well to new problems
in the fine-tuning sort of story.
And that's been a big object of study in theoretical machine learning,
is trying to understand why and how
the things we're accidentally doing for gradient descent on these data sets
leads to strong generalization.
But there's two points I want you to have from the user perspective.
It is not the case,
some of you might disagree with me on this,
it is not the case that you can put an arbitrary cost function
on the end of these networks and experience success.
This pixel-wise cost that they use in Mask R-CNN,
the particular architecture they used,
leveraged these ideas in a deep way
and was very successful.
You could mess it up very easily.
It can't learn everything arbitrarily.
If it did, then I would be using it for inverse kinematics
and I would probably be mining Bitcoin or something like this, right?
There's things that we've figured out that it does extremely well
and there's things that don't fit in that framework yet.
A good example actually is if you were to do pose estimation.
I mentioned this before, right?
If you trained a network for pose estimation
and you chose rotation,
if you parameterized rotations badly,
the network would have a very hard time learning.
But other pose parameterizations work well
and that's because the landscape,
even in the high-dimensional space,
is more suitable for learning.
So unfortunately, the story's a little bit complicated,
but it is all connected.
There's all one truth here,
which is that I'm trying to do nonlinear optimization
and these neural networks are setting up a rich landscape
that works shockingly well when my kid wants to identify Legos.
That's like from here to there.
Yeah, okay.
Questions?
At that level of detail. Yes?
[inaudible]
We're increasingly understanding, yes,
that these are good things.
And people would argue about what are the most important features,
but I think both of these have got a lot of consensus behind them.
Yeah, the overparameterization story,
there are two different pieces of the puzzle.
The first thing is that for most deep learning problems,
we put ourselves in a regime where we get training error equals zero.
You basically, for your training set,
you expect to basically perfectly recover your desired training set.
And the reason that that is possible is this overparameterization story.
That's the training error equals zero part of the story.
Why does it generalize to new things out of your training set?
That's the implicit regularization story.
This is the generalization part of the story.
Both are amazing and deserve more study.
[inaudible]
Yes?
Great question. Yeah, yeah.
So, okay, you've probably heard of overfitting.
So the concern, the classic picture of overfitting,
would be if I'm trying to regress some points,
maybe the right function is something like this,
and the points had a little bit of noise.
But really I wanted some simple function to come out,
and accept that the data was generated with a little bit of noise.
My overfit solution, if I'm really trying to get the training error
to be almost zero on this, might have, in order to fit the function,
might have done something like this, which is not the solution I was looking for,
but it set the training error to zero.
This is the story of implicit regularization,
is that it tends to somehow find the solutions that are more like this.
That seem to generalize better, and not this.
Okay?
There's very good theory in detail, I mean, the noise story of how does it fit,
how does it do both of those at the same time?
It sounds like that's inconsistent, but it's actually not inconsistent.
People understand that the function it is learning,
even in noise, you know, at least my mental image,
I think this is a continually moving story,
is that it actually learns something like this,
but if you zoom in, it's actually learning like little delta functions
that explain the noise, and it does actually get the training error to zero,
but it learns these beautiful generalizing functions.
Okay?
Theory of deep learning is an awesome topic.
This is a poor representation of it,
but maybe just enough for you to put it in context.
I'm happy to take more, you know, those are useful questions.
Okay.
So, can we play with it for a second?
So this is, I made, you know, I made a,
I actually made three notebooks, okay?
All of them are there.
Now, it's actually, Deep Note is completely awesome in every way,
almost every way.
They give free compute, you know, it's incredible,
it's got a good interface, it's most of the time works.
Their GPU support is not free.
That's the one, you know, it's a buy-in.
If you needed it for your project, honestly,
there's a chance I could ask and get you, you know,
like a special thing for it, because they really are,
they like the class.
It happens that one of them that's high up in the company did robotics,
so it's like, yes, we got an in.
Okay, so, so, so that's great,
but these are the three notebooks that we're going to,
we actually point you to Google's Co-Laboratory instead of Deep Note.
And the reason for that is that Co-Lab is just another online server,
it's from Google, it happens to have a different pay structure
and gives you GPUs.
For training a deep network, you want a GPU.
Okay?
So I'm going to run it locally here, but it runs fine on,
on Co-Lab.
Okay, so, there's three notebooks.
One of them was the data generation notebook,
which I just, you probably don't want to run that ever.
You could look at it and say like,
oh, when you want to use it for your own pipeline, that's great.
It's the thing that runs the clutter clearing for like a while,
generates a huge file on my disk with all the labels and everything like that.
Then there's the training, which runs for a long time,
that will train the neural network,
given pre-trained weights from Cocoa v1,
which was pre-trained from ImageNet.
Okay?
And that works better than if I were to just train from scratch.
The last one is the inference network.
That's what I'm going to run now,
which is just, I'm going to put a new image in.
I'm going to just drop my bins again,
new image in, and render the output.
Okay, and we'll see how it works.
It's interesting.
So this is just in, it's using PyTorch.
If I didn't say it, we were using PyTorch
for these parts of the class.
So, he said, "Make sure you tell them that if you're really running,
you know, training PyTorch is great,
but when you're running it on the robot,
you should use TensorRT or something else
that would compile it into a much faster, you know,
PyTorch is not the fast inference engine.
It's the great training, flexible thing,
but you should compile it down into some more optimized code for runtime."
Okay.
The output of MaskRCNN, if you just say,
"Give me an input, what's the output?"
It has, oh, that's the model, sorry.
If you look at the output,
it gives you this big dictionary, right?
It gives you a dictionary that has, like,
it could do multiple images at a time.
This is, for each image, it tells you a list of boxes
that were possible detections,
a list of labels for those boxes,
which are the numbers I assigned in my training data.
It gives you scores on how confident it is.
It looks like in this one, it was actually very confident,
very confident, very confident,
and then not very confident at all.
So we'll probably see something ridiculous on the last detection,
because it's a 0.05 confidence compared to 0.99 for all the others.
Okay.
And then it gives me the images, which are the masks.
That's a crazy thing to come up--
let's just appreciate for a second that that's absolutely nuts,
that a network would produce all that stuff.
I mean, I remember-- I'm old now.
So, like, we had projects with Jan Lekun, for instance, a while ago, right?
And Jan Lekun used to come to our meetings,
and he would bring a camera around
and, like, train a neural network on the--
a little convolutional neural network on the fly,
and his demos were just always awesome.
But I completely admit that I--
every night, I would go home and be like,
"Okay, but there's just-- that just doesn't scale.
Like, what are you going to have, like,
a million outputs for all the different possible labels on your network?
Like, that's-- no one's ever going to do that."
People do do that, right?
You have, like, cats and dogs and elephants and everything.
He always had three labels that he was training on the fly,
and I thought that was great, but these things are enormous,
massive, millions of parameters, millions of outputs,
and it's all on the GPU and super fast.
I'm running on the CPU now, by the way, so--
This is my image in,
and this is my masks out, okay?
So let's take a look at your image.
Mask number one, amazing, right?
They found a mustard bottle.
Mask number two,
it's probably my Jell-O, right?
The other Jell-O.
Okay, and the last one is ridiculous, right?
Because it was-- it told me it was going to be ridiculous, right?
That one looks weird.
Oh, that's like the occlude-- oh, wow, right?
That's the occluded mustard bottle,
and it just gave the-- it gave a pretty darn good--
look at that, you can actually see the box cut out of it.
That's actually incredibly good, right?
And I didn't change anything.
This is just the default parameters of everything, okay?
Now let's change-- check the object detections.
Okay, that's a bit embarrassing.
Completely missed the Cheez-It box on the side.
That is pretty funny, but--
All right, the rest of them, incredibly good, right?
Incredibly good.
I wonder-- that might be-- I should have changed
my region proposal network parameters, right?
Maybe it didn't have one big enough to--
to get the big flat Cheez-It box.
It's probably dialed in for things that are about
the size of a dog in a picture.
Okay, right? Amazing.
So each one of those gives a bounding box,
which is the pixels, that's what--
the corners of the pixels, and a label,
which I can associate back with my text label.
Okay, so that's--
You can run it a few more times here.
This is-- finds spam cans, finds domino cans,
potted meat, sugar box.
It's incredible, right?
Absolutely incredible.
Amazing, right?
Okay, so that-- like, obviously we should use this
in robotics. It's just so good.
Any questions on that? Anybody-- you know,
we could poke it, if you have, like, something else.
I wanted to see what you try--
I mean, I can't retrain it on my laptop now,
but I could do any inference queries you're curious about.
Or you can-- tonight.
[Audience member] There was one that allowed us--
that allowed us to visualize the region proposal.
Could you go through that quickly?
Yeah, sure.
[Audience member] And see what happens with the Cheez-It box?
So, the-- the-- the--
So, there are--
Okay, I could probably get--
Let me do it so that it has the right image.
The caveat here is there's, like,
order a thousand or more images
proposed, and I didn't visualize all of them.
So, the test you-- I think your test is extremely good,
but-- oh, okay, well, so we did learn here that--
is that the boxes are at least big enough.
So, my concern about them not being big enough is wrong.
But I can't say that it didn't have a box around the Cheez-It.
I would guess it probably did.
There's, like, a thousand-- order a thousand region proposals.
[Audience member] So, do you have another idea
for what could have caused it to not pick up on the Cheez-It box?
It could-- I mean, it could be that I never had
a flat Cheez-It box in my data set.
Could be not a perfect network, you know?
That is the one-- as powerful and amazing as it is,
when it doesn't work, the only recourse we have
is to add more data, really.
I mean, you could change parameters and retrain
and do some hyperparameter sweeps, but--
You know, a lot of the stuff we're talking about in this class,
if it doesn't work, I could-- you know, we could tell you why.
We could tell you how to debug it.
Right now, this one, I can't.
Yes?
[Audience member] Wouldn't it predict, like, something
which is familiar within the image map of Cocoa
if it had, like, cornflakes, cornflakes boxes on there?
So, the question is, why wouldn't it produce cornflakes
or something from the Cocoa data set?
That's a good question.
So, it will never do that, because I've ripped off
the Cocoa head, and the last layer is specific
to my data set, so it will only ever say
the things in my data set.
It might be biased towards things that were
in the Cocoa data set because of its pre-trained layers,
but, you know, it has confidence thresholds
that it will only report that the object was there
if it was above some confidence threshold.
So, it might be that there's a great box
right around the Cheez-It, and it's just
slightly below some confidence threshold.
Good. Okay.
I want to land a few more sort of high-level ideas.
We can take our stretch today, yeah?
Let's take our quick stretch.
That's a good time.
(Pause.)
Okay. So, if you've learned one thing so far,
or, you know, I think the MaskRCNN is going to be
a tool that you will use if you understand
its inputs and outputs. You're already going to have
an incredibly powerful tool at your disposal,
and maybe you picked up a few of the buzzwords
from deep learning theory and the like
that I would encourage you to study further.
But I still think we haven't, I haven't told you
the complete story yet about how to get
big data for robotics, right?
I told you two examples.
The label fusion kind of idea, where we
annotated our lab captured, and then the synthetic data.
Both of those are somewhat limited, because,
for instance, I only have a handful of different
object models that I put in my simulator.
I can generate as many of them as I want,
but I don't have the diversity of the real world, right?
And the same thing, what I can get in lab
is not going to represent the diversity.
If I want to think about open world manipulation,
I want a robot that I got to program,
it leaves, and it's going to manipulate
anything in your house. I haven't given you
an answer for that yet, and I don't have
a complete answer yet, but this is what
people are working on hard now.
How do you have this kind of a tool chain
that could manipulate incredibly large
classes of objects?
There was one more point I was going to make,
but I think you know roughly that you
could go from the mass Garcian end
to the model-based grasp selection,
or the antipodal grasp selection.
Okay.
So, I'll come back to those at the end
to close things, but the big new trend
is that we're going to have a lot more
of this kind of self-supervised learning.
The big new trend is self-supervised
learning. I think many of you will
have heard that also. In particular,
we have this amazing property that if
I've trained on ImageNet, on object
detection for instance, then I could use
those weights to help me do better
on pixel-level segmentation.
I trained on one task on a relevant
layer, but I had a different task.
So, if you open up your mind then and say,
"Well, why did I pick object detection,
which required human labels for my
first task? Why don't I pick something
that doesn't require human labels,
that I can auto-label for my first task?
I just need to pick some surrogate task
that the network, in order to achieve,
learns something relevant in those
first layers to copy over."
So, the new thing is find clever new
tasks that don't require human
supervision, unleash them on the entire
internet, and use those backbones as
pre-training for your run time.
One of the most famous examples is
SimClear, where the idea is very
simple. It's basically, I'm going to
take my original image of my dog, and
I'm going to just start perturbing the
image in lots of different ways.
I'll crop and resize, whatever.
Google basically threw the, this was a
shotgun approach to research, which is
powerful and good, but they're like,
"Let's try every possible perturbation,
and then we'll take the 10 that worked
best, roughly, and we'll call that our
algorithm." But they just absolutely
tried all kinds of crazy stuff.
And then most of these, one of the
dominant ways to do self-supervised
learning is to set up something where
you take the training data, and you
just compare and contrast things that
you know to be true or false. So, this
is a contrastive learning paradigm. The
animation's a little annoying, but
hopefully it gets the point across.
So instead of having labels for the
dog, and labels for the chair, it turns
out to be enough to say, "The dog is
not the chair." If you can say that
this and this are the same image,
because they're just perturbations of
the same image, which you know to be
true, you've constructed that by
construction to be true, you say those
are the same image, and those are not
the same as the perturbations of the
chair, then you don't need any human to
annotate that. And what's amazing, okay,
the general trend is that they,
oftentimes, these don't do quite as well
in peak performance, but for free, you
know, you get so much, you can feed
them with so much data that they do
incredibly well. I mean, at some point
you can actually outperform some of the
original human labels. One more second,
one second. Another example that's a
little closer to robotics, which tends
to be, I think, learning representations
that are more about 3D understanding of
the world, is monocular depth
estimation. This is actually, this is
the one that works the best right now,
or one of the best right now, but the
original idea is even simpler. So,
imagine I have two cameras, and I could
say, from two cameras I can figure out
the depth using a stereo algorithm, and
I want to train to be able to guess
stereo from one camera. Okay, well, I'll
just carry my two cameras around and use
the two cameras to project the computed
stereo to give me the ground truth
answer, but just train the function from
one camera, and you train monocular
depth from an image to predict the
depth. Okay, the newer architectures are
a little bit more complicated. They're
doing reconstruction. They take your
current frame, you take your second
frame, either from in time or alongside,
you try to predict the relative, I mean,
it's more complicated architectures now,
but these work incredibly well, to the
point where people can take just an RGB
camera and move it around as if it's a
depth camera, except, by the way, it still
does well on blank walls, and by the way,
it still does pretty well on invisible,
you know, transparent objects and things
like that. It's incredibly good.
It's incredibly good. Sorry, did you have a question?
[inaudible]
Explain this? The cost function, instead
of saying it is a dog or it is a chair,
is to say, I want to, I'm going to
predict an outcome that says that the
dog and the chair are, the dog is not a
chair, and the pieces of dog that have
been translated are the same. So these
are contrastive learnings. You take
typically two images, you push them
through. The ones that are the same, you
try to make close together in some
representation space, and the ones that
are, you know to be different, you push
them apart.
[inaudible]
I wouldn't ever say you couldn't do
that with a deep learning perception
system. What I would say is you need
more data, maybe, or a bigger network,
right, or more hours of SGD. Yeah, it's
just a matter of levels of accuracy.
Yes?
[inaudible]
Okay, that's a really good point. Good
point. So, yeah, sorry, the point to say
it into the microphone here is that I
could have accidentally picked two
pictures of the same dog in my data set,
and then the contrastive learning is
actually sort of wrong, right, because I
could have had, I could have said this
dog is not the dog. The objective is
basically that that happens rarely
enough in a big data set that it's okay.
Yeah, good point, good point. Yeah,
there's no, there's no label dog, no
label chair anywhere here. It's just raw
images. Good point. Okay, so this is
actually, so Leroy's been playing with
this kind of, the self-supervised
paradigms, and asking about some of the
harder questions about what it means to
have representations for manipulation.
And it's actually super interesting if
you think about, I mean, everybody's on
this quest for finding, you know, the big
data moment in manipulation, right? And
so we've been working with Amazon, who
has big data, and they are doing
manipulation, right? And Leroy started
asking the question, you know, do they
have enough data? How should we process
that data in order to learn
representations that would be
incredibly powerful, okay? And the
interesting thing that happens in a lot
of these real-world applications is
something called distribution shift. So
if you think about, I mean, I took the
same image three times, that was sort of
antithetical to my point, but you can
imagine if you have similar robots
deployed in different warehouses, right,
then they have very similar data coming
in. But there's a big question of, should
you train only, but they're a little
bit different, like the, I'll show you a
couple different specific ways that
they're different, okay? So should the
robot in New Jersey train on the
perception data from Boston? Yes or no,
right? It seems like it's more data, but
the boxes in Boston might be
statistically a little bit different
than the boxes in New Jersey. Or the
boxes at peak season might be more
dense, for instance, on the conveyor
belt than the boxes off peak, right?
They have crazy shifts in distribution.
So there's this question of more data
is not actually, we know that more data
is not always better, that if you have
different data that is different,
from a different distribution, it can
sometimes hurt you. Sometimes it doesn't,
but we know that it can. So there's a
big question, how much should you share
data, how much should you snarf up, how
much should you specialize? And even
more interesting, I won't talk much at
all about this, is that you're doing
this training in a decentralized way. So
you have many different neural networks
potentially living in different places
and different copies of the neural
network, how do you do the gradient
descent update on that? Okay, but the
distribution shift is very real in their
data sets, right? They have different
lighting conditions, different densities,
they have different robots and
upstream handling systems. Things like
the sensors respond differently at
different altitudes and stuff like this.
They have different suction grippers in
different places. So, you know, if you
look at a few different locations, you
might see very different types of
packages or density of packages. This
place does mostly, you know, the envelopes
that you can almost recycle. And then,
you know, this one has more of these,
right, for instance. And sometimes you
have very dense, sometimes you have very
sparse. So it's just an interesting
question of like self-supervised
learning seems to work, but how exactly
do you deploy it at the scale? And is
it, you know, is it going to get us big
data and manipulation? And this is the
takeaway, is that if you just train
directly on doing image segmentation
with supervised learning, for instance,
on your local data, you can actually
overfit. I just, I said overfitting isn't
as big of an issue anymore, but you can
overfit still to your data and have
worse performance if you start applying
that across a distribution shift. You
have limited robustness to distribution
shift. If the, if peak season comes, your
distribution moves, you can have overfit
to your data. And there's a really big
thing that seems to be happening, and
I think you know this, you've seen like
the GPT-3 and DALI and stable diffusion
and all this craziness, right? But
there's something about these self-
supervised objectives that seem to be
learning something more general about
the internet or about the data in the
warehouses. And they tend to be more
robust to distribution shift. And this
is like the big, big question in
supervised learning, self-supervised
learning for manipulation is what's the
right way to learn these
representations using as much data as
possible that work for lots of
downstream tasks? And the
self-supervised objectives seem to be
learning representations that transfer
more generally than the supervised ones.
It's almost like saying that this dog
is not a chair forces me to learn
something general about images and
saying it's a dog, I could have
special-case the dog.
Okay, and the last thing I'll mention
here is all the GPT-3, everything, it's
coming into manipulation in a big way,
which is even if we can't get enough
labeled data or self-supervised data
locally, people are asking the big
questions of how do I take everybody
else's foundation models, right? So the
models that have been trained on huge
language corpuses, huge vision
corpuses, huge text-to-vision
corpuses, and somehow use that
information to augment my small data in
robotics. And CLIP is the one that I
think most roboticists have picked up
of the big models. CLIP is a vision-to-text
model and it's like every
roboticist is like, oh, I could have
taken my image and put it into this
encoding and I could have a sentence, I
could put that into the encoding. And so
people are finding lots of different
ways to use that. And the takeaway is
that compared to the MaskRCNN pipeline
which I talked about, which does
reasonable things on the labels you've
trained, these foundation models are
getting us to the point where out of the
box you now have potential labels from
the entire Internet, like kind of the
captions that everybody has put on the
screen, you could just walk around the
lab and point it at stuff and there's a
chance it will label some, it will give
you a sensible label out of the box in
the open world, right? It's not
perfect, it's not perfect, but it's
mind-blowing. It's mind-blowing. So how
do we use, even for the instance
segmentation problem, how do you
leverage super large data trained with
self-supervised learning, even on a
surrogate task, to make us pick up any
object and manipulate any object? Okay.
Good. So the instance segmentation is
very much a geometry computer vision
task. It is not enough for
manipulation. If I want to know how much
the objects weigh, right, Flickr
doesn't have a data set that where
people, everybody, I mean, actually
probably does. You can probably say how
much does that weigh and it would say,
you know, 2.7 kilograms and it would
probably be like almost right. But I'm
not a data pipeline, right? So if you
want to know like how, what's the
friction, where's a good place to pick
this up, right? That I don't think we
have the answer directly from this.
That's why I tried, I wanted to say in
this lecture, I wanted to give you like
a super fast overview of what computer
vision relative to, you know, the
standard computer vision pipelines for
manipulation can look like. On
Thursday we're going to say that the
computer vision pipelines don't answer
the question. We're going to use more
than computer vision to pick things up.
There's other properties of the
object that we care about rather than
just what it's every pixel label is.
Okay, so we'll talk about that on
Thursday. Any other big questions about
that?
[inaudible]
There's going to be an entire
lecture on it a little bit later.
Yeah, so, but on the control side
learning is having a big impact too
for sure. And the biggest impact is
connecting with vision. So a lot of
our classic pipelines didn't have a way,
they're incredibly good, but they
didn't have a way to talk to cameras
because that's handing a 640 by 480
RGB image into a PID controller
doesn't make sense. So we found,
we're getting new tools for
connecting those wires. Yes, good.
[inaudible]
Yeah, I didn't put it in. He told me I
should put in this. Yeah, I read the
paper. I read the paper, but I...
[inaudible]
There are more than models that do
this much, much better. And it's like you
input the text and like it could, can
find the object really accurately with
fine-grained detections. For example,
like some people say, I put a sticker,
a yellow sticker on my laptop. And now
like I take a photo of a room with all
the laptops and acquire with a laptop
with yellow stickers. In the latest state
of our model can do it pretty well. It
will only give you like a design, the
highest probability to the laptop with
yellow sticker. And I think it's going
to be very, very impactful in
robotics because previously we could
only do like a fixed, a fixed list of
like 20 categories or like a hundred
categories. Now it's just anything
described as soon as you can describe
it with language. Awesome. Yes. Thank
you. So yeah, I think that is a part
of, in my mind, a zoo of ways that
people have found to put these large
language models and connect them to
manipulation. Right. Good. Any other?
I mean, any other big commentaries?
That's good. Okay. I'll hang around
outside. I think we have a lecture
coming in. So I'll hang around outside
if anybody wants to talk about
projects, but I will see you Thursday.
[BLANK_AUDIO]