[ Background Sounds ]
>> Okay. Welcome back.
We're going to do our second round of the deep version
of perception today.
So last time I gave, you know, I'm sorry,
I could have given a whirlwind overview of deep learning.
It's actually, I really want your feedback on that
because my thinking was that I would try to give a version
that people who didn't know much would understand and a version
that called out to some other more advanced topics.
I hope I didn't land in the middle and everybody hated it.
But please, give me, we're going to put a specific question
on that, on the survey about that and help me figure out how
to dial in the first lecture on deep learning.
It's a big ask for me.
Good. Okay.
But today we're going to slow down and we're going to talk
through a couple more specific algorithms, ideas that connect
that pipeline with the things we need from manipulation
that maybe we don't need in a standard computer vision world.
So let me put it in context by thinking about the system
that we sort of built last time.
If I have my block diagram with my manipulation station here
with all my output ports and everything like this, right,
some of those output ports that are most relevant
for today are the RGBD sensors.
And we've got some perception system which is now, let's say,
a deep neural network.
And we're eventually going to get over to our planner,
like we wrote for the clutter clearing example,
and then our controller.
And we ultimately want to send commands back
into the low level of the station.
There's actually even additional layers of control inside here,
right, that are doing joint impedance control.
But we had differential IK, for instance, in this block here.
And the connection between the planner and control,
I guess the example we've talked about the most
so far is sort of well understood.
We said we're going to send gripper trajectories.
We're going to spool them out over time and ask our controller
if this is the DIP IK version to turn those into joint commands
that the manipulation station knows how to execute.
The question really is if we have this immense pipeline
from deep learning and they can work more natively
with RGBD inputs, then how should we go
from here over to the planner, right?
What is the information that we most need for manipulation?
Now, we can be ambitious with our ideas here because,
as we talked quickly about last time,
one of the most amazing things
about these deep learning architectures is
that I can potentially, even if I have a task that's pretty narrow
and specific to my robotics application,
there's a chance I could pre-train
on image classification in ImageNet and then
with a small amount of data,
train a more relevant downstream task, okay?
So the big question is what's the right task?
And let me distinguish this.
Later in the class, there is a version of this that goes
from RGBD through a neural network straight to control
or straight to the manipulation station.
Let me just make it the extreme version,
which would be pixels to torques.
Okay. This is-- we'll do this later.
That's a good idea.
I think there's lots of good things to learn about that idea.
But that's not what I want to do today.
What I want to do today is embrace the fact
that we have a beginning of a pretty powerful tool chain
for these layers, you know, and we're going to have more develop
in that space and there's just this huge power of tools
that we already have in the community.
And we just need to figure out the best way to talk to it,
to get from our rich camera input, our rich environment,
into something that is sufficient
to describe the task and consumable by our planning
and control algorithms.
Okay. So the big question is what are those useful
representations?
And there's not one answer.
There's not a right answer.
There's-- this field is changing every day.
But there's some good ideas that have emerged
and I think even just picking one or two of them and going
through them a little bit carefully, hopefully that will,
you know, encourage you to read more and think more
about even more of them.
So the answer I gave yesterday or from Tuesday was we're going
to take our RGB in, come out with our instance segmentation
and then go through one more step, for instance, maybe ICP,
for instance, and turn that into the estimated object poses,
which I can then send to my planner.
That was sort of version one we talked about,
leaning heavily on instance segmentation.
You know, we also said you could take the same thing
and enable a different planner that maybe in the middle here
if we just do our antipodal grasps.
Right? So maybe if this is still the instance segmentation
here, we could still do this and come
up with some desired grasps and send that to my planner.
OK? So those are two things that we--
if we just use the out of the box computer vision tools,
mask our CNN for this,
then we already have some potential pipelines.
And of course, there's-- for both of these, there are versions
of this where people would recommend
that you just go, you know, all the way here as a neural network,
just try to hop over that, you know,
and-- or maybe go all the way here as a neural network.
Those are certainly possible.
And I'm actually-- I'm going to try to write up a fairly,
you know, succinct but, you know, kind of a summary
of what are people doing in deep pose estimation.
This would be if I did this, that would be the world
of deep pose estimation.
And there's a lot of good ideas in there.
And this would be maybe, let's say, deep grasp selection.
That's my name.
That's not-- there's not really--
there's a bunch of known algorithms for that.
I'm not sure there's one really good overall name but--
OK. Both of those are possible and are good ideas.
But I want to stop and think is this even the right interface?
Is this notion of putting the pose being the summary
of everything that my perception system sees being the right
interface to the planner?
OK. So, remember we get to be aggressive here.
We can train our network on almost anything, right?
Is sending sort of estimated object poses the best signal,
you know, is that the best connection?
And there's a couple of reasons why it seems maybe we can
do better, right?
The first one is I would say this assumes a lot
about a known-- about having known models.
Right? If I have a model then--
and the world is not moving, you know, then telling me the pose
of the object or maybe all the objects
in the scene is everything I should need
to know, right, in some sense.
It is-- well, it's a complete description
of the current state of the world.
That's a slightly different thing.
Maybe in the full glory I would also want, you know,
assuming the world is nicely second order,
maybe I'd also want the spatial velocity of that object.
OK. But if I have known models,
then this is actually a reasonable thing to do.
There are still limitations even in that case.
But we're going to try to overcome
that assumption today a bit.
For the first time, we're going to try
to start doing manipulation of these categories of objects.
OK. The second thing that I don't like about using pose
anymore in this case is that it's actually asking for more
than we can potentially get, right?
It might be asking too much.
[ Writing on Board ]
OK. So for instance, if I have partial views of an object,
maybe it's actually very hard to estimate the perfect pose,
right, especially if there's symmetries for it.
Those would be a classic case
where maybe the pose isn't naturally right description.
And it might be more than I need for manipulation.
[ Writing on Board ]
OK. So I'm going to try to make this case in a story
in just a second, but just to set it
up at the high level here.
And I would say the third thing about it that it seems
like a major limitation of just using pose as our language
from the perception system is that by itself,
just saying that I have a nominal estimate
of what the object's pose is, isn't maybe sufficiently rich
in the sense that it doesn't tell me anything
about the uncertainty from the perception system.
[ Writing on Board ]
OK. And we should try to describe uncertainty, right?
The, you know, I'm going to try to use this as a theme
as we go through, but this pipeline actually,
the MaskRCNN pipeline did talk about uncertainty.
It was a little hidden, right?
But the fact that every classification,
every potential bounding box had a score function that was
between zero and one, right?
And the ones it was confident in was close to one,
and there was one that was ridiculous
and it was close to zero, right?
So it told me something more.
It told me there's, I have some segmentations,
but I've got a limited confidence
about at least one of them.
Right? So maybe we need a language to talk about that
in the language of pose, or maybe we need to just think
about other representations completely.
OK. So let's, let me tell you about this
in the case of an example, right?
So this is, this is the category level manipulation version
of the story, right?
So we want to do some sort of manipulation, but we want
to do it not on known objects, but objects that are all
from the same category.
OK. Is that clear, right?
So it's an interesting question immediately to say, you know,
I know something about mugs.
I could total, I could imagine writing a program
that would work for all mugs,
but if the perception system only told me to pose,
then I don't even know what the pose means for those.
Right? And it's also a good example that I don't need
to know the pose perfectly to accomplish a lot
of interesting tasks with mugs.
OK. OK. This is the category level manipulation problem,
right?
Imagine mugs, it turns out that the field that's working
on category level manipulation have all roughly converged
on mugs or shoes.
Sometimes you get a plate or, you had bowls, right?
I mean, there's a, there's like a really small set of categories
that everybody really likes to talk about.
So you'll see mugs and shoes throughout
from different papers, OK?
And it's an interesting problem because it is a rich class of,
it's like, I think it's like the Goldilocks place between,
I don't want to assume I have known objects, but I don't want
to have to deal with arbitrary objects, right?
So like, tell me it's a mug, the mugs have a handful of,
we can generate arbitrary mugs that are interesting.
You can also find mugs at the Disney store that have, you know,
ears and, or cow udders or something like this.
So you can go as far as you want away from the nominal mug.
But there's a really nice problem
to just say how would I write a manipulation system
that could deal with that level of variation,
not the whole shebang, anything, OK?
I think it's a really nice sort of intermediate.
It's actually pretty cool
that you can have these simulation pipelines
that will just take a few, you know, a few parameters,
kick out a CAD file, there's procedural CAD
as a thing now, right?
You can take a texture map, slap it on your mug, right,
and generate like all kinds of mugs, right, in simulation.
Harder to do with shoes, but mugs are pretty good.
We have done vegetables, procedural potatoes, really.
OK. So how do you do, how do you think about this sort
of pose estimation problem at the category level?
There's a couple, like the first thing that people would think
about in computer vision about how to do this would be maybe,
there's a famous project, a work called NOX, right?
It's this normalized object coordinate space, NOX, all right,
where you take a whole category of objects and you try to come
up with some canonicalization, something that would make it
so that if you tell me the pose of this canonical object,
then I can infer, I can relate
that to the thing I'm seeing right now.
So that pose is still a meaningful quantity.
Because if you don't have some, you know, some notion of how
to go from an arbitrary thing, like what is the center,
what point am I talking about the pose, even though
that point might be in different places on different cameras,
you know, then you don't have a full representation.
So this is an extremely good, you know, way to do it
that has been successful in computer vision.
And there are ways to think about category level.
Pose estimation.
But I want to also talk about this uncertainty, okay?
And I just say like, the challenge, there's still,
there's more challenges that come up if you really want
to use pose and carry it through your entire pipeline, okay?
In particular, like what is the right way
to represent uncertainty in pose?
And I'm sorry that it's become a theme, but once again,
the thing that screws everything
up is the representation of rotations, right?
How do you write uncertainty around rotations?
For positions, you can imagine just using Gaussians,
and that's sort of fine.
You can hire more if you want to, right?
I could say I have a Gaussian uncertainty
around the position of my object.
But for the rotations, you need something more clever.
There is something more clever.
There's a language for this.
It's called the Bingham distribution.
And I just, you know, I want you to know that it is possible,
and it has, there's a sort of, there's a natural Gaussian
in the space of rotations.
And it's done by taking a Gaussian
in the higher dimensional space and then projecting it,
and then intersecting it, I'm sorry, onto the unit disk.
So this is the 2D version where it's easy to visualize.
I've got just a Gaussian there, and I have the intersection
with the S1 here.
But the place where we want to use for 3D orientations is
to think about how do I put a distribution
over possible unit quaternions on a four dimensional sphere?
OK. And it looks like this.
This is an, I just want to just open your mind to the fact
that these kind of things can't exist.
That actually a Gaussian on a quaternion sort of makes sense.
It's just called the Bingham distribution.
OK. You can write the intersection of a Gaussian
with the four dimensional sphere,
and you get beautiful representations.
This is kind of the right way to do Gaussian like things
on the quaternion space.
OK. Where small distributions would be,
you just have the antipodal pairs show up, right?
And then as you widen it,
you remember the quaternions are always antipodal,
so it's going to be symmetric along that antipodal axis there,
and you can get full rings of uncertainty and the like.
And I think you need to do this.
If you want to use pose everywhere in your system,
and you want your perception system to be able
to say it's uncertain about things, you need to do that.
I mean, mugs are actually a great motivator for that.
If I see a mug in the kitchen sink, right,
and if I can see its handle, I might be able
to give you the pose with a very small uncertainty estimate.
But what if the handle's on the backside?
It would be just wrong to give me any, to choose any one
of the possible orientations without, you know,
without somehow saying it could be any of these, right?
So having distributions over pose is a thing you can do,
but it gets hard fast.
It gets very hard fast to carry that all the way through.
And the types of distributions you get with partial views
and conclusions are probably non-bingham pretty quickly.
There's a pipeline you can exercise,
but I don't think it's the best one.
It's not the one that I would fully advertise.
Okay. So here's a different,
just to give you a version that's a different answer
to this, what if instead of using pose, we just talk
about a handful of points attached to the body
or in the coordinate frame relative to the body?
This is our first, you know, proposal
for an alternative representation at that level.
[ Background Sounds ]
Let's think about key points.
Okay. And the key points I'm going to talk about now,
if you're familiar with the key point literature, this would be,
I'm talking about the semantic version of key points first.
Okay. So roughly speaking, what if my RGB or RGBDIN goes
through some sort of perception module and output
at a list of X, Y, Z positions for key point one.
[ Background Sounds ]
My claim is that that, I'm going to try to argue
over the next few examples here,
that that actually is a pretty natural way to talk about a lot
of the category level problems we have.
It assumes less about the known models, right?
It does surprisingly well thinking about partial views
and symmetries, we'll talk about that.
And it has a nice connection to uncertainty.
Even more, it turns out it's actually really pretty useful
when you hand that to the planning.
It's a pretty natural representation to think
about writing a planner around.
Okay. So this is just the first example
of a different representation we could use as the output
of our perception system.
Okay. Right.
So it comes from, key points are a thing in computer vision.
They started off with these open pose kind of, you know,
people dancing, you want to track the dancing people, right?
And so the way they do it is they put key points on the hands
and the elbows and the shoulders and make a skeleton out of that
and track it, it's incredibly impressive.
Okay. It works really well like on novel videos
and things like this now.
So the proposal here is let's take our mugs and instead
of trying to represent a canonical pose
for all possible mugs, let's pick a few canonical points,
just a few of them maybe, right?
Maybe the bottom of the mug where it's on the table,
maybe something that says what's the top of the mug,
just so I have a sense of maybe the bottom should be
below the top, you know, that's useful.
And then depending on what you want to do,
maybe you can put a key point in the handle if you want to pick
up the mug and in this case hang it on the rack.
That's another favorite, yeah?
Hang the mug on the rack, okay?
Then in order to do that, you know, we'll work through it,
but you can actually write that task pretty nicely
as a planning problem where you just know what the location
of the yellow dot is, right?
You don't actually have to know the absolute pose of the object
and we'll argue, like I said, it fits more naturally
into this framework.
Okay, so here's the basic idea of how it's going to fit
into that planar framework, okay?
So imagine that the output of this,
I should even use my multibody notation.
So what I'm going to imagine is that this outputs the position
of key point one in the world frame here and key point I,
you know, for all I.
There's a pretty simple assumption we could try
to make, the first assumption just saying I'm going
to reach over, I'm going to grab it.
Once I've grabbed it, I'm going to assume that those key points,
because if I've sufficiently grabbed the object,
are going to move with my hand, rigidly with my hand.
And then when I release, they'll stay in the world, right?
And we should pick manipulation actions for which that's true
if I tried to grab over here, that's not going to be true.
But with a little bit of a few assumptions about,
you know, pretty reasonable assumptions,
you can imagine that the dynamics
of these key points could be such that when my hand is open,
then those key points aren't moving.
And when my gripper is closed, then I'll
just assume that the position of the key point
relative to the gripper frame is constant.
That's the only difference, right?
And if I do that, then I can imagine coming up
with a sequence of these plus the open and close
that could schedule me to move my key points around
in the world.
I'll plan to go over and pick it up, close,
and then I'll start the key points moving along with my hand,
and I'll drop it off, off we go.
So it turns out, actually, it's a pretty rich specification
language.
It's even more rich, especially--
so the versions we've talked about so far
have been I had a desired pose exactly of my hand at the end
or my key points at the end.
You won't be surprised that when we get to motion planning,
we're going to loosen that up and be
able to write objectives and constraints
on the potential key point locations.
OK.
OK, so to execute that, the key points
are almost of what you need, but they're not quite enough.
The key points will let me write my planner for the most part,
but I do need to have some notion of where to grasp.
So different people address this in different ways.
So Anthony's got a version where he's
got key points for the grasping, too,
and dense enough key points that he
can find a grasp that will-- in the language of the key points,
roughly, in his neural descriptor fields.
But you could also, in a simpler case,
maybe just use the raw point cloud
and do your antipodal grasping in the vicinity
of the key points.
So just if I have the top center,
maybe I have the ability to segment,
because I've got my Mascar-CNN, then you
can imagine, choose your grasp on that object,
but then plan the motion once I'm
in that grasp in order to move the key points around.
And that works incredibly well.
There's a few things that I think it's worth saying about
how you make these tools work.
People have questions at that level?
Yes?
How many people know key point type algorithms?
Used them?
OK, good.
I can see both.
And in the middle.
That's good.
There's a few important things to know about them.
And knowing them will help us understand, for instance,
how you think about uncertainty in the language of key points.
There's a few famous architectures,
neural architectures.
I won't dwell on them.
There's a convolutional pose machines is one of the first.
I'll link to them in the text.
The one we've tended to use is the integral pose machines,
or the integral version of that.
Just a small change on the original architecture.
But there's a key feature that both of these
have that you should understand, which is that I take my RGB in,
and I don't actually directly regress the key points.
What I put out here first from the neural network
is a heat map.
For instance, in the simple case,
let's just take RGB and have a 2D heat map come up.
And I've got a figure for this in a second.
And then afterwards, I'll find most often the highest value,
the peaks in my heat map in order to put out my--
it's an interesting idea.
It's one of these things that makes
things more differentiable.
And it tends to be a more robust metric for neural networks.
So the key points are probably impossibly small to see,
but there's little red dots here.
I didn't think about the screen resolution
when I took this particular image.
There's little red dots on the faces that are picking
nominal key points on a face.
People do this for face tracking, by the way.
They'd actually have pretty dense--
they have a key point for every part of your face,
for your lips, for your eyes.
And it's kind of spooky to see the points being plotted
around.
This one's just plotting five of them.
One for the left ear, I think, is this one
in each of those pictures.
And the heat map is the ground truth heat map
that people would use, would say that if I
know the key point is in a particular location,
here for the left ear, then I'm going
to draw just a Gaussian bump centered at the known heat
point location.
That's the standard thing.
And have it basically effectively
zero for most of the image, but just
have this narrow Gaussian bump.
And your goal is actually for every point
you're trying to estimate to predict
an entire image which has the peak at that value.
So this is the heat map representation.
Now, you can see quickly how that could encode uncertainty
in a nice way.
So if I was confused about which was the left or the right ear,
maybe I'd have a second small hill over there
in my output of my network.
And that allows you to then, if you
wanted to do more robust things down the line,
reasoning about the uncertainty, you
could leverage that richer representation.
The fact that it's a Gaussian of known kernel,
that bugs the snot out of me.
It's total hack.
People just, I think, do kernel hacking on that.
It doesn't seem particularly principled to me,
but it works well in practice.
So just admit that.
But this is a nice representation.
How do you train that?
Well, you can, of course, click on key points,
have humans label key points in a lot of different images.
And then for every click, you make
a little Gaussian desired image, and you train your network.
Yeah?
There are, of course, better ways in the manipulation
workflow.
We can play the same kind of trick we played
to label our segmentations.
You could take an object that you don't even
have a model of, you could spin your camera around it,
make your nerve for somehow your dense reconstruction of it,
and then click once for each key point
on the reconstructed model, and back project
to have labels for all of the possible images that came in.
That's a really fast way to generate a lot of label data
for key points.
And that works pretty well.
So this is the way that we then-- this
is the shoes example, right?
But if you want to sort of manipulate any possible shoe--
this was a great demo.
I remember we had this running one day during visit day
when the new grad students came to the lab,
and then they were coming into our lab space to eat lunch.
And so we basically asked everybody
to take their shoe off, which was maybe not the best hosting
I could have done.
But we got a huge variety of shoes to test that day.
And it picked up almost everyone.
It was incredibly good.
It was just, boom, put the shoe on the rack,
put the shoe on the rack.
And then Daniela, our lab director, Daniela Rus,
came in, and she had these ridiculously shiny black
Italian shoes, and we couldn't do it.
And I was terrified of hurting her shoes, by the way.
So that was the one we failed on.
Gretchen actually also had some high heels
that we had never seen before.
But it's all good.
We added them to the training set, and now we can do it.
Now we can do those high heels.
So it's a surprisingly powerful and simple sort of pipeline.
You can, of course, also generate key points
synthetically.
If you have a distribution of objects,
if you have your parametric mugs,
and you want to just generate a bunch of different labeled key
points, then you can generate synthetic images.
And that's a super powerful pipeline.
So we did a quick example of it on boxes,
because this was when Greg was during the pandemic,
and he was walking past the lobby of one of the dorms
and seeing piles of boxes.
He's like, that's a pretty good data set.
So he just started collecting images
of the front lobby of the dorm and generated a whole category
level of boxes.
But he also did this amazing job of using blender rendering
to set up the procedural models.
So it's not too hard to generate boxes of different size,
but it's a little hard to see.
But it's incredibly close to photorealistic.
He took a handful of texture maps of different boxes
that he saw in the front lobby and generated just
these huge data sets of perfectly labeled boxes
that looked pretty realistic.
You can get the ground truth instance level
pixel-wise segmentations, but you also
get to see the ground truth key points.
It's super relevant and interesting
to know that you could train your key point
detector to predict--
you don't have to pick only visible key points.
You could choose to predict key points that are occluded.
If I look at that image on a brighter screen,
I could hallucinate for myself and give you
an estimate of what the back corner looks like,
even though I can't see it.
And if I can generate training data that
puts a mark in the back corner, which both of those two
pipelines I suggested couldn't do,
then you can still ask the perception system
to predict even occluded key points.
So that's pretty powerful.
Almost always, this was a little too simple.
Almost always, people will run it
through a segmentation pipeline first
so that the key point network has to only work
on the segmented point clouds, maybe the bounding box that
comes out of Mascar-CNN.
I assume you could do it on the big image, and it would be OK.
But it tends to work better if you give it
the scaled and cropped version, zoomed-in version.
And then this is the detections on his raw data in the lobby,
his predicted key points, where you
can see the heat maps and various levels of uncertainty.
The fact that those are spread out and not as peaky
is important information.
It's sort of frustrating that, although it's obviously
important and good, the back half of our tools--
a lot of the algorithms we'll talk about in class
don't actually know how to reason about that uncertainty.
It's an advanced topic to reason about uncertainty
in your planner and your controller and the like.
We'll mention it-- I think we'll have at least one lecture on it
towards the end.
But there's no question we should
be asking our perception system for it.
I think there's work to do in how to consume it.
So that's pretty good, and those are the ground truth key points
that were labeled.
Questions about the key point pipeline?
[INAUDIBLE]
Did I make the point of how it works for a whole category
sufficiently well?
It's easy to label the toe of any shoe, the heel of any shoe,
the top of any shoe.
But it's harder to talk about a canonical pose of every shoe.
There are people that really don't like key points
as a representation.
I'm not trying to say this is the end all be all,
but it's surprisingly simple to think about and good.
And we did demonstrations back then
of understanding how many trained objects
and finding every mug we could buy on Amazon,
and it's pretty darn robust.
There's also nice additions to it.
So if you think about what that pipeline couldn't
do right out of the box--
so if I just used the initial point cloud
to decide where I'm going to grasp,
and then I just think about where those key points are
going to move in space, the fact that the key points are not
a complete representation of the geometry,
we had to be fairly conservative so that we didn't, like,
crack mugs on the table as we went around.
We had to pick fairly conservative trajectories
for our key points.
But you can put this together with other deep learning tools.
For instance, if you just imagine
the missing part of the point cloud
and have a completed shape of your object,
then you could put the entire geometry moving through
as a constraint in your planning system.
And that added some richness to what we could do.
We could do more realistic collision avoidance constraints.
Now, this one's pretty cool.
People also talk about learning-oriented key points,
where you have not just the x, y, z location,
but maybe the axes, the three-dimensional coordinate
system.
If you do that and you just know,
what is the key point and axis on the object I'm manipulating,
that turns out to be enough to do interesting control with.
So if you wanted to regulate the force at the end effector
of a screw or an eraser or whatever,
then you can write a controller making the same assumption
that the object becomes rigidly attached to my hand
when my hand's closed on it.
I can start regulating my forces of my hand
at the point defined by the key point
and with the orientation defined by the key point.
And that's enough with that pretty simple pipeline
to do some pretty cool stuff.
So Wei was able to pick up various LEGO blocks,
insert various USB keys, do mating.
All of those are sort of force-sensitive type tasks,
putting LEGO blocks together or putting USB in.
And you could do that with very little knowledge of the object
by just assuming, just understanding its geometry
in the level of a key point and applying these tools.
Seems only-- there we go.
So you get any possible eraser.
You want to be able to apply a wiping motion on the screen.
And the controllers that we'll talk about more soon
are enough to regulate the forces pretty well.
Yes, please.
[INAUDIBLE]
Awesome.
So what are we assuming here?
So we are assuming that key point 1 versus key point 2
is fixed given the initial observation,
but it's not fixed to some canonical model.
So my model does not assume that I know this a priori.
But we assume that they are rigidly attached.
They rigidly move through space.
[INAUDIBLE]
That's right.
Exactly right.
Yeah.
Perfect.
There's versions of this that people have done.
I mean, that David Held's lab, for instance,
has done that use key points or other particle level
representations that do this for deformable objects,
for instance.
There are definitely extensions like that.
But the simplest version is just assume
they're going to move rigidly.
Good.
Other questions?
Yeah.
It's a surprisingly powerful pipeline, I'd say.
One thing that people don't like about the key points--
I remember when we did those demos, for instance,
the thing that every single person asked,
they're like, OK, but you hand labeled the key points, right?
You're going to learn them next, right?
Learn the key points, right?
And I took offense because I actually think at some point,
the human has to say something about the task.
And I think this is-- in my mind,
the key point is like a minimal amount of information
to ask the human that defines the task.
And I think that's true.
I think there's a role where you have to have semantic key
points, where the human applied some amount
of semantic information to the-- this is the handle.
I want you to pick it up here, right?
But there are also ways that you can use key points where
the semantics aren't important, and they're really just
a summary of the geometry.
And in that case, I think people have done beautiful work
on learning key points.
And so you can, for instance, self-supervise and try
to find ways to label key points.
One of the best examples, I think, of that
is this Keto work of learning the key points that
were relevant for some forceful manipulation type tasks.
So learning key points is absolutely a thing.
But I think if you do learn them,
you don't get to call them a label.
You don't have the human-informed knowledge
attached to them.
You don't have the semantics attached.
But it's absolutely a thing.
So you can actually take that idea even farther
and think, why am I just doing-- this
is sort of like the sparse key point story.
There's really no reason to make them sparse.
You can go ahead and try to learn dense key points that
cover all over the entire geometry.
And if they're consistent, then they
take on a different sort of notion here.
So there's another representation
that's called dense object nets.
I'll tell you some of the details of this one too.
This was very enabling for us.
So when I show you these pictures,
this is what I hope you see.
So in the left, we have a canonical image of the object.
And the task, the object in this case being a MIT hat.
We have someone holding their mouse
over the object at a particular point
and maybe moving it around to make
the demonstration interesting.
And now we're seeing a different playback.
And the goal here is to find the associated key point,
if you will, in the hat in the other frames.
So this is also called dense correspondences.
Why is-- I mean, it's exactly the same
as we meant by correspondences in the ICP pipeline.
And it makes total sense to try to learn correspondences.
Remember in the ICP loop, once we knew the correspondences,
extracting the pose was easy, if that's our choice,
or maybe we don't want to do it.
So it makes total sense that if you
try to solve the hard combinatorial part
of the problem by learning from trial and error
and then allow additional tools to work from there.
So asking now as a different representation
now, not just sparse key points, but dense key points,
is I think really powerful.
Is that image clear?
I'm going to show a bunch of them so I hope it's clear.
So you can see the uncertainty there.
But the big thing that changed is this is not
n sparse key points here.
We could put this over anywhere on the hat.
And for any possible place on the hat,
we'll show you a distribution of possible correspondences.
So let me tell you a little bit about how
a standard correspondence network would work.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
Now, when we're going from every pixel in the original image
to every pixel on the final image,
we're not going to use for every possible key point
its own heat map.
That would be the logical extension of this.
But it gets pretty expensive.
So we're going to do a slightly different representation here
based on some of the ideas from self-supervised learning.
So we're going to take RGB in, put it
through our neural network.
And the thing that we want out is a dense descriptor image.
Whereas if this thing was a RGB, it
has some width by height by three channels.
So I've got-- see what I'm saying?
It's width by height by three.
It's a tensor, but each color channel
is an image of width and height.
And then there's three of them, RGB.
And then this one I'm going to put out
a different image that is colorized, roughly,
in this arbitrary extra dimension of descriptors.
So I'm going to map every pixel in my original image
to some descriptor space.
I don't know what that space is going to look like exactly,
but I'm going to ask it to have certain properties.
In particular, that it gives correspondences.
If I have two images where I know
I have the same point on the object,
then they should arrive at the same place
in dense descriptor space.
So D, when I draw those pictures like that,
we chose D to be three so that we could render it
as an RGB image.
But you can choose D to be higher, for instance.
It doesn't have to be just three.
And then this is trained Siamese style
with self-supervised learning.
So we take two images that we know
have the same points in them.
I'll show you the pipeline in a second,
but we're going to do that same dense reconstruction trick
and know from two different images
that there's a point on the geometry
that if I back project, it should be the same point in both
of those images.
And then there's a bunch of points on the object that
should be different points.
So I'm going to put two images through my neural networks.
My dense descriptor net.
Get my other image.
And I basically give positive reward for matches
in descriptor space.
And I also have some negative examples.
I do some hard negative mining to say this is a non-match.
So start off by making the robot move around.
You come up with a dense reconstruction.
And then for each point on this image,
for each point on the caterpillar in this case,
this is a plush toy that we got.
It has lots of interesting buckles.
And so we thought it'd be good for learning manipulation.
But we ended up just using it for perception.
Everybody wonders why we have this strange caterpillar
in the lab.
But we take all those images.
And this time it's deformable.
There's no rigidity assumption here.
And then we say this point here, which
I know to be in a different frame, the same point,
that should arrive in the same place in descriptor space.
So we get right loss functions like this for matches.
We say that we want some average of the neural network
output from image A at a known location A minus the neural
network in image B at the known correspondence B,
where UA is known to correspond match with UB.
I minimize that loss.
I normalize it over the total number of matches.
And then I take a bunch of non-matches too
and just play a little trick.
It looks like the opposite of this roughly.
It says I want points that should not
be the same to have a large distance in this space,
up to some threshold.
And you sum those two together.
And you get your pixel-wise contrastive loss.
[TAPPING]
There's a bunch of tricks that people do to make this work
better.
For instance, normalizing so your descriptors
are on the unit sphere, that seems to be a good idea.
Data augmentation is absolutely a good idea.
People do background domain randomization
as a particular form of data augmentation.
All those tricks that people do in similar pipelines
are applied here also.
And then what you get out here is you take your caterpillar.
Even though it was stationary when we scanned it,
there's nothing in the network that requires it to be rigid.
And what you want to see here is that the colors, which
is our 3D-- when we choose D to be 3,
and we draw them as an image, that as you move the caterpillar
around, you want the same points in the caterpillar
to roughly come up with the same colors in all the frames.
And it's surprisingly good.
We have a Baymax doll in lab.
We had various-- this is now the same demo again,
where the mouse is over this.
And this is the old version.
This was the new version, where we got much tighter predictions
by playing some of those extra games
about normalizing the descriptors and things
like that.
And it's surprisingly good.
You can go down left leg, right leg,
and it gives you a distribution of possible key points.
If you wanted to extract a particular key point out,
you can, of course, say there's a descriptor here.
What is the peak value of my uncertainty
map in the other image?
That's an operation that's natural to do,
and can be done differentiably, for instance.
But it turns out that this is something
that we didn't actually have any reason to expect.
But if you train it on a bunch of different hats,
then somehow we also found that the dense descriptors--
I mean, I would say this is a limitation.
It worked, and we exploited it, but we
don't understand it well enough for it to be a reliable thing
at the time.
But it turns out that it somehow learned a category level
descriptor.
We trained on a bunch of different hats independently,
and then we could put it on one hat.
And it tells us the correspondences on all the hats.
Something about the fact that the way
it fits things in d-dimensional space somehow made this happen.
If you want to learn different hats independently, you can.
That's what this other side was doing.
You just have to train with all the hats in the image
at the same time.
And if you're specifically saying,
don't match the point on this hat with this hat,
then it will learn not to.
But without that pressure, it somehow
seems to pick points that are somehow geometrically related
across different objects in a category.
So think of that as a dense, self-supervised key point.
There was no human labels anywhere in that pipeline.
We scanned the object, and it did its thing from there.
And that alone, depending on what your pipeline needs
to be after the fact, that's actually
a loan to do some interesting things.
So if you just say, I want to pick up the object,
I want to pick up the caterpillar from its ear,
from its tail in this case, and we put it down
in all kinds of different places,
it'll pick up the caterpillar by its tail.
You can deform it.
You can change it.
It'll pick it up by its tail just
by having a correspondence function.
Pick up from its ear.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
OK.
Pretty good.
Let's take a quick stretch.
Seventh inning stretch.
That's what it should be called, right?
The seventh inning.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
,
All right.
So you should ask high level questions
or low level questions.
But is that landing?
These are different representations.
They're fundamentally not just summarizing
the state of the world as its pose.
And they're sufficient for control,
but they required us to think about control
a little differently down the pipeline.
Yes?
So it seemed like those correspondences
were on the surface of the object.
Yes?
Has there been work done where it's like volumetric?
So I know this point is the volume,
and then if it's like clay and I reshape it,
I know where that particle is in this new, kneaded shape.
That's a neat question.
So I'll repeat it for the people watching at home.
But yes, so the question is, if these are always--
all of the points we're registering
are on the surface.
In fact, when we make the 3D image,
we're actually using the depth image
to project our colorized--
this is-- the output of the network
is an image in this case.
And we are actually projecting it on the point cloud
and spinning our camera around to make that image.
And you say, could we do a volumetric version of this,
where you actually correspond into the body?
I don't see why you-- as long as you can--
you trust your reconstruction enough
to talk about a penetrated point being the same in both cases,
I don't see why you couldn't do that.
I haven't seen it done.
Have you guys seen it done?
Did you do it?
[INAUDIBLE]
Is that what the-- do you consider
that to be in the neural descriptor?
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
All right.
Good, good.
Yes.
Are dense correspondences the way?
Or what are the pros and cons versus the key points
that you were doing with the categorical mode?
Yeah, awesome question.
So are dense descriptors the way?
I actually have seen people use them over and over again
in lots of different applications.
So there's a particular-- I mean, the correspondence,
they do pretty well.
And I have seen that be successful.
They don't have any semantic information.
I was going to talk at the very end about just some
of the things that are not here.
So there's still-- the notion of object
is sort of still missing here.
The notion of dynamics is missing here.
So you could potentially train one per object, for instance,
and have correspondences have a type of object.
We did call it an object representation.
But certainly, the dynamics of the object are missing.
We don't know-- and it doesn't tell you anything about the mass.
It's not going to help you crack an egg.
It doesn't tell you how things are going to evolve.
That's missing from the key points also.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
Both-- I think-- I mean, for both of these examples,
it's absolutely missing from those.
But for moving nearly rigid or possibly deformable,
slightly deformable things around,
it's a pretty powerful pipeline.
I don't know that we've finished thinking
about how to plan and control with it either.
So there's work to do even just thinking
about the right way to consume that information, uncertainty
in that information.
[INAUDIBLE]
I think it would--
let's see.
I've seen enough people use it, both of them.
I mean, in various forms, people have implemented it
in various capacities that I would trust that it would work.
I wouldn't be afraid of saying you could grab the repository,
grab some of your own data, and expect it to work.
That's not the case of every tool we've played with,
but this one seems pretty robust.
OK.
Yeah, so this is a class of--
just two examples of a big class that I think is super powerful.
I mean, I guess I forgot to show.
This is the dense descriptors on that box pipeline
I talked about before.
It's interesting that it need not be--
I mean, if there's symmetries, it
could learn correspondence functions that
are good up to the symmetries.
You wouldn't expect it to be able to do better than that.
But that's a super valuable representation of the object
to go ahead and manipulate things.
That's Greg, and that's our messy lab.
This is Anthony's extension of it,
which I hadn't thought about as a volumetric thing,
but there you go.
So neural descriptor fields, you should check it out.
The emphasis in the title is about the SE3 equivariance,
right, to be able to do relative coordinates, for instance.
The video actually very nicely describes the pipeline.
Still mugs on racks.
It's the thing.
It's pervasive in the field.
, OK, so here's the-- let me pause that before I run it
here, but-- yeah, here's the thing.
So let's compare it.
Remember I said that at the beginning
that we're not yet going to talk about--
we're trying to do representations
for the rest of our existing pipeline.
And that is putting some sort of a constraint
on our representation space, right?
So what I'm basically saying is that we're
taking RGB or RGBD or some combination
in to our neural network.
We've asked this question, and we
said we're going to do it like a human-designed pipeline here.
[TAPPING]
And humans are pretty creative, but somehow I
think that it's putting pressure on this to be interpretable
in some ways.
And the big thing that is, of course, happening
is people are asking bigger questions now about,
what if I remove that assumption and use a learning back end,
right?
And you could ask-- you could just say,
I'm going to train end-to-end from my neural network
right through my learning control.
And the thing that's exciting about that
is that really does remove this requirement, right?
That if it needs to represent uncertainty,
then it will represent uncertainty
in order to get the job done.
If it doesn't need to-- if it has-- if it needs to represent
something specific, only specific to a task,
maybe it'll do that, only capture
some relevant parts of the scene in order to capture the task.
But the design strategies we have for these components
are much, much weaker, right?
So you end up using reinforcement learning
or imitation learning.
We'll talk about both of them.
And they're not as generalizable,
and they consume massive amounts of compute,
as these kind of planners.
So I think there's a--
I think to some extent, this is a slightly artificial
distinction.
But what the field has done in the last few years
is more and more people are just saying,
I don't like this constraint.
I don't know what the representation should be.
It should be whatever the learning does.
And therefore, I must use learning control.
And I think there's a lot more to do
where you can have rich, possibly
uninterpretable representations here,
and still do really good control over here.
So that's a personal agenda for me,
is to embrace learning control when it makes sense,
but also remind people maybe that it's not the only way.
So we'll talk a lot more about some of the general approaches
to control up here that could consume richer, possibly
not just kinematic models of the state.
And there's a big topic of learning state representations.
So I would think, in answer to your question, David,
I think these examples are some impoverished state
representation that are sufficient for some kinematic
tasks.
But they're an impoverished notion
of what the state of the world really is.
Like I said, cracking an egg is just an extreme example,
but-- or boiling-- I don't know.
You can imagine a bunch of things
which have a lot more state than just its current positions
as specified through the correspondences.
So thinking about how to find those richer representations
and learning or writing controllers around them
is a big agenda.
[LAUGHTER]
OK, so when we do do imitation learning,
we found in our lab that using these dense descriptors
as a pre-processing step in order
to then train a neural network policy
does work incredibly well.
So this is just taking those same examples
where we're using the dense correspondences.
For instance, on the hat--
I'll tell you more about this when
we talk about imitation learning.
But it turns out that if you just sort of give
to your learned policy a handful of key points on the hat trained
through dense descriptors and ask it to then put hats
on the rack or learn controllers that can move plates around
and do more dynamic tasks, it's been surprisingly good.
So we'll talk about that in the imitation learning section.
And I really think this is just two examples
of a big class of approaches that
are thinking about novel representations
for the geometry.
One that I like from Andy Zhang and company
is they do this transporter nets where roughly they're saying--
I mean, there's a lot of interesting things
happening in the paper.
But maybe at the high level, what they're saying
is that my assumption about the dynamics
is when I grab these pixels, those pixels
are all going to move together.
And that allows them, with a rich pipeline,
to sort of do incredibly general and useful tasks
for picking random unknown objects
and putting them into bins and things like that.
Just from looking at the raw perception,
having a model that if I pick here,
those things are going to transform
through a standard rigid transform into the new place
allows me to do a lot of rich tasks.
So the deep perception world is alive and well.
It's moving super fast.
And I think you will find many things
that will change the way we should program our robots.
Good.
I'll end a few minutes early, I guess.
And I'm happy to stick around and answer
questions for projects.
[BLANK_AUDIO]