But having read your pre-proposals, which I thoroughly enjoyed, there was a
surprising number of projects, not surprising, it's great, but a
surprising number of projects that wanted to throw things or hit things or
smash things or somehow do very dynamic things with the arm. And having just
talked about motion planning and now seeing a lot of people that probably
want to have fairly sophisticated motion planning in their project and
possibly something with dynamics, I just want to take a minute to sort of
make sure people realize what we were talking about, how it might relate to
breaking stuff or throwing stuff or skipping stuff or... there was a
definite theme there. I actually want to know why, I mean, but I know a bunch of
you read the tossing bot paper, you know, that's a good, maybe that was a
motivation, but it just, it was surprising. For me, see, I teach
the two classes, I teach underactuated, I teach manipulation, and underactuated for
me is about the dynamics, right, and manipulation for me is about perception
and things are relatively static or quasi-static, you know, but you do
perception, you do high-level planning, you do all the other stuff, but I think
the worlds collide inevitably. Maybe it's even my own bias creeping in somehow, but
let me just distinguish between kinematic versus dynamic trajectory
optimization, because I think probably a lot of you said maybe I'll do some
motion planning with trajectory optimization to catch something or
throw something. So, you know, this is what we talked about last week, I would
just say last week here. The dynamic version of that is actually a big topic
in my underactuated class, but we didn't actually talk about it here, and maybe
you guys, I think a lot of those projects don't need it, but let me just make sure
you understand when, maybe when you'll need it or when you don't need it.
Okay, so what we talked about last week was parameterizing some curve, you know,
this is just a curve in space or a trajectory in space. And in fact, so the,
you know, I told you I was going to finish pushing that kinematic trajectory
optimization into Drake, it's there now. If you look at the constructor, just as a,
you know, if you look at the constructor of the kinematic trajectory
optimization class, it doesn't even take a plant. It has no notion of
dynamics by default. The default is just, this is just some curve in space. You can
associate it with a plant by adding kinematic constraints to it or add other
constraints to it, but by default this is just some, you know, it's just some curve
parameterized by a handful of numbers, that's it. And then you can, if you want
to say, I want this to be a certain place, I wanted this to be associated with the
kinematics of the arm, you can add costs and constraints that make that true. Okay,
that is in contrast to some of the, if you look at some of the other trajectory
optimization methods, like direct collocation for instance, takes the
system directly in the constructor, right? And so does direct transcription and so
does some of the other, multiple shooting, you know, these are, these are more
fundamentally about dynamics. This is fundamentally starts with this, the
construct of a dynamical system, continuous or discrete depending on
which transcription it is, and the decision variables are all set up to
basically, to basically solve the numerical integration of this, these
differential equations, right? So the different, the decision variables encode
the numerical integration. And actually the different transcriptions that you
see, like the direct transcription versus the direct collocation, those correspond
to sort of different numerical integrators. They're kind of, but that's
the way you think about it. Okay, so you can of course put derivative constraints
on this. You can say that Q double dot at some point has to equal something. This
would be a constraint you could add in kinematic trajectory optimization. So you
can start putting dynamic constraints onto your curve. And in full generality
you could implement a numerical integration scheme as constraints on
this curve. But the, you know, these methods were built for it. These methods
you'd have to build them yourself. Okay, so I think most of you are probably
going to be okay with this, but I want you to be aware of that sensitivity. So
when would you go from this to this? It's when the dynamics matter, you
know, in a way. So I can say for instance that I want my robot to execute
some joint trajectory, and I could say it's got velocity limits, it's got
acceleration limits. But if you suddenly have the robot and a ball, for instance,
and you want the evolution of this curve to be, to represent both the robot's
joints and the ball's joints, and that those are only coupled through the
equations of motion, then that's where you start getting into the, you know, where
you probably want to live in this space. I think a lot of the cases of catching,
throwing, smashing, or whatever, are probably okay thinking about just the
robot, and just making sure that once you're at the end and you're actually
connecting with the robot, with the ball, or whatever it is, that you do so with a
velocity to send the ball off into some ballistic trajectory. And, you know,
you can compute some very simple dynamics of the ball here, and just make
sure the robot gets there. And that coupling might be simple enough that you
don't need this machinery. I think that, you know, or catch, or smash, or whatever,
okay, I think most of you are in this regime. But I want to just make sure that
that's clear. There's another set of tools. If you find yourself that the,
basically, I would say start here. If you find yourself trying to write more and
more dynamics constraints, the curve of the robot depends on the motion of the
ball, of the objects, then you might look at that API, or even the notes in
underactuated. Okay? Good. All right, so today is mostly about force control. And
I have a bad joke ready, so I'm going to do an example of force control here. I
know I have many bad jokes, but. Thank you. You got it, right? If you missed it, here's
another example of force control. That's a pretty good example, too, right?
Probably, when I was writing those letters that are erasing the board, I was
in a force control mode in my arm, right? I mean, exactly what is my brain doing? I'm
not trying to make any statements about that. But this is a kind of task that if
you wanted to program a robot to write on the board, you might consider doing
force control. Why? Because if I were, let's say I was executing a position
trajectory, right? You missed my joke. If I was executing a position
trajectory and just going through the letters example, you know, in joint
space, and I was just a little bit off in my estimation, let's say I was in the
perfect position to write my example, okay? But now I, you know, someone came and
just like, I put the second robot down that's supposed to write and I just put
it off two degrees to the side. And I start writing, I'm going to air ball a
little bit, and then I'm going to break the chalk as I go into the board, right?
If there's any uncertainty about where the board is, then following rigidly a
joint trajectory could be a bad choice. Now in practice, since we're typically
controlling our EWA through a joint impedance control mode, which we'll come
to understand this week, there's going to be some flexibility in that. Even if you
command, you know, just an end effector trajectory, it will comply to some extent.
And that's because actually, but underneath it, it's doing some force
control, okay? So, but if you were to just take a rigid, you know, factory position
control only arm and try to do writing, you'd be sad, right? Unless you're super
calibrated and dialed in to the location of the robot relative to the thing it's
trying to put force on. In fact, that's one of the classical examples that
people originally moated force control, motivated force control, was things like
following a wall or painting or welding or something like this, where the robot
had to follow some continuous curve in space, not based on, you know, open loop
trajectories, but based on actually, you know, sensing the force on the robot and
executing a path due to that force. Okay, so that's what we're going to talk about
today and understand how to work with it, how to think about it. I'm going to
break it up into into two pieces. I find there's a lot of notation, I would
say there's even a lot of philosophy about that comes in when people talk
about force control. People will say it's, you know, it's morally better to do force
control, you know, or, you know, the world can only do this or... I'm gonna, I think I
can keep it pretty simple, but I think it's helpful to distinguish first the
case of just thinking about forces. I'm gonna assume the robot is a point, okay?
I'm gonna start by just assuming that the robot is a point. There's a joke
about assuming a spherical cow. I'm doing worse. I'm gonna assume it's a point.
It's not even a sphere with any radius. I'm gonna just take a point robot, okay?
Then we'll figure out how to make that force happen when we put the arm back in
as a second pass, and we'll talk about the manipulator control, impedance
control, and the like there. And we'll get basically the same things to happen, but
we'll throw in some Jacobian transpose kind of logic there. So let's start by
thinking about, you know, what is force control. So I'm gonna start with...
Let me start with a little bit more motivation besides the writing, okay?
So if you look at the images that I generated by generating lots of
training data for the segmentation pipeline, this is one I actually had to
take the cheez-it boxes out of the end-to-end clutter demonstration, because
I can't get an antipodal grasp from the top that would have picked that up.
Right? The cheez-it box is just too big for the hand. I actually asked my
daughter. I said, "Okay." I gave her a two-fingered gripper, and I asked her to try
to pick up a big box, and she did it really well. Not surprisingly, she's a
human. And, you know, but we don't have... We haven't developed that capability yet,
right? And so if you want to do more dexterous things in order to get those
big boxes out of the bin, then we're gonna be in this regime.
Now she's also got a dexterous hand, which is just not even fair, right? And
she can even stretch her hand out to do that. So this is too advanced, but you get
the point, okay? So we're gonna work towards that type of a demonstration
right in our clutter clearing kind of example. And here's another good example
that we'll talk about, and you'll even do a problem set about. So this is now...
I'm gonna push the... We're gonna push the book to the side of the table, and you
have to think about this for a second, but why does that work? Okay, we've
thought a bit about friction cones and the like, but how is it that the robot is
able to push the book to the side of the table? This is a clever way to pick up a
big book.
Okay, but even in this first part, right there,
why does that work, right? So a couple things possibly could have happened,
right? It could be that the robot went to do its thing and there was so much
friction that the robot doesn't move. That didn't happen, okay? It could have
been that the fingers slid on the book. That didn't happen either. This was a
nice regime where the fingers stayed attached to the book, but the book slid
on the table. So think about how that has to happen, right? There has to be some
sort of difference in friction in order for that to happen. Our normal forces are
similar, so somehow there's a difference in the friction cone. If you look
really carefully, you'll see that there's some tape modifications on the end of
that finger to just make sure it's nice and sticky. I mean, okay, it's not
adhesive, but it was a textured tape that we put on onto the finger.
Okay, so we'll understand that, but thinking about that, you have
to put yourself in the regime where the forces you exert on the
table and on the book are such that the friction cone allows you to slide the
book, but if you push too hard, then nothing's moving. If you push too
soft, you're going to slide on the book, but there's an intermediate regime which
only exists if there's a difference in friction cones, at friction coefficients,
but if you have that regime and you can control a force that
puts you into that regime, then you can slide the book. Okay, so this is what I
want to do. I'm going to flip up the Cheez-It box like my daughter,
but I'm going to take even just a point finger example. Okay, so we're
going to try to regulate the forces on the boxes by thinking
through a point finger, and the reason to do this is just that everything is super
simple and I can write the equations of motion in a heartbeat, so in this case
I'm going to say q of the finger is just the xz position. I'll even stay in the
plane. Okay, the dynamics of this, f equals ma, is going to be--ma, right, is on the
other side I've got mg, where mg is going to be--is my vector notation, g is 0 and
negative 9.8. Okay, I'm going to assume that I have the ability to just command
the forces like it's a little jetpack on there, but I'm allowed to produce
generalized forces directly on the finger. Again, we're going to add the
robot back in at the end. Okay, and then I also have any contact forces that are
coming from the finger interacting with the box or the wall or whatever, and now
the spatial vector notation that I introduced before, we're going to lean on
it heavily today, okay, because it's all about getting the forces in the
right frames and everything like this. So this notation, remember, means that this
is a force on body--force on the finger at point or frame C, which is my contact
point. And you can imagine, for instance, if I--this is what my dynamics are trivial
here--you can imagine maybe that this is something I could even have a force
sensor for. There's various ways in the space of force control to try to
regulate your force. You could try to measure your accelerations. You could
assume accelerations are small. Let's just assume for a minute that I could
actually, as I'm executing in the world, I can measure that force. Okay.
Or, you know, or I can assume that x double dot, z double dot is small.
Actually, maybe I'll do that one first. Let's just do this--let's do this one
first, okay. If x double dot and z double dot are small, I'm not accelerating my
finger rapidly, right. Then, if I want to control that force, then I could just
choose a u. Let's take the position where I'm already in contact with the
wall, okay. So I've got a point finger I'm pushing on the wall. What should I
choose u to be to make that force be whatever I want? The accelerations are
zero because I'm stuck on the wall. I can just choose u to be exactly what I need
to make this--the equations--this would be zero here. I just want to choose u so
that the force is the desired force, okay. So I can just say u equals negative mg
minus f fc. I'll call it desired. I'll use little f since I'm talking about
Cartesian forces so far. Okay, so if I have a desired force and I apply this
thing, I should first just take out gravity, but otherwise I'm just going to
apply the force I want. And by assertion that these are--this is small, that
equation will just give me that the measured force equals the desired force.
That's just logic, but I just want to make sure that the algebra is there. What
happens if you're not in contact with the wall and I apply this controller,
assuming that you are in contact with the wall? This is an extremely important
point and it's one of the best things about force control. What's going to
happen if, in fact, the real contact force is zero and I apply this
controller? I'll get mg minus mg, those terms go to zero, and then I get minus
my fc desired, and this thing is--I'm saying is zero. So I'm going to
accelerate, right? In particular, I'm going to accelerate into the wall. This is a
beautiful thing, okay? So the signs are a little bit hard to think through, but in
general, this is the property that if I--I think intuitively it makes a lot of
sense. So if I'm close to contact, I think I'm in contact, and I ask myself to get
positive contact force off the board, the control I would execute to try to ramp
up the contact force that I'm not getting will have the effect of driving
me into the board. This is a hugely important thing, right? So this is
why, for instance, in walking robots people like to use force control in
their legs, okay? Well, it's more subtle than that. Typically, when you're swinging
your leg through, you would typically try to do a position control and try to make
sure you know where your foot's going to land and control that. But when you
actually go to land, and when you're maybe when you're in stance, when this
leg's in stance, you'll switch to a force control mode. And in particular, for that
moment where you're about to put your foot down, where you may not know exactly
where the terrain is, rather than have to perfectly estimate the shape of the
terrain, you just push down. And you say, "I want some amount of force to be
coming off my, maybe I've got some force sensors on my feet. I would like to push
down until I feel the forces on my feet be the desired forces." Typically,
roughly the opposite of the weight of the robot, right? And if I'm asked to
have that force be large and my foot's in the air, then it tends to go down, okay?
And this adds a lot of robustness. And this is why, when I'm writing on the
board and I'm off by a few degrees, we're gonna get to that completely,
completely, but that's why I can get some extra robustness if I'm thinking in the
space of forces and not in the space of positions. Okay, so unsurprisingly, I have
a couple notebook examples that I want to play. So let's think about the
simplest version of this. I'm actually gonna draw the Cheez-It box a bunch in
these examples with, you know, just like that, like it was on the screen here. So
this is my bin that I was in with the wall that would have blocked my view, cut
away, okay? And I actually, just to keep it simple, I make the Cheez-It box so it
can only rotate in the plane. So I just took away the extra degrees. It won't
spin around or whatever. The point fingers aligned, I'm just living in
the plane, okay? But let's say I just come, I put my finger in some known position
and I ask for a force to be exerted on the finger. I'd like the FFC, FFC
desired, is that I want to be feeling a force that's pushing me that way. If I'm
not feeling it, I'm gonna push harder this way to try to get it and it'll put
me into contact. So the first notebook I'll just run here is what happens if I
just apply a constant desired force and I start the finger here. Think about it
for yourself for a second. If I just command a desired force and, you know, and
start the robot here, the block here, the Cheez-It box here, and the finger there,
what's gonna happen? I'm just gonna run a fixed duration simulation with a handful
of different commanded forces. Commanding a constant force. What's gonna happen?
Tell me what's gonna happen. It's gonna push the box into the wall, if there's
enough force. But there's other cases, right? At the other extreme, it could just
go up and do nothing. The box will stop it if you're not pushing hard enough
because the friction on the floor. And then there's actually a super
interesting regime where it slides, you know, different amounts
it could slide depending on how hard you're pushing, right? So this is the
different rollouts, if you will, where in one extreme, so the box is like right
around 0.1, okay? The finger comes into the box. It comes in more slowly if you
accelerate more slowly. The blue line is the one extreme with the smallest force
and then it just hits the box and the box just, you know, stops it basically. It
actually goes a little bit into penetration because that's what the
contact model we're using is. It allows it to penetrate just a little bit, okay?
The other extreme, it hits the box, it barely slows down whatsoever and starts
pushing the box until the box jams into the far wall, you know? Okay, and in
between you get all these other different possible behaviors, including
this one pushed it for a while and then stopped because there was a collision
event that started it moving, but the continuous, it could actually be under
the friction cone. So there's lots of interesting different things that can
happen. Okay, my claim is that there are some things, if you want to regulate the
box, there's some things that are more natural. I mean, already we get some
robustness by not knowing the geometry of the box and we can shove it around.
Like the first thing my daughter did was shoved it to the side, right? She didn't
need to know the geometry for that. She could just say, "I expect to feel forces,"
and boom, he pushed it to the side. But we're gonna do something fancier here,
which is what that other, that picture was. This is something that would be very
hard to do. My daughter didn't do it, actually, in the video, I don't
think. She could, I'm sure she could have, but this is a little fancier. This is, if
you're really thinking about forces and regulating the forces, you can do pretty
cool stuff. So I'm gonna see if we can take the finger, put it in a regime where
it's actually rotating the box up right in the middle of the bin. How? We're gonna,
we're gonna, there's, we're gonna be in a regime pretty quickly as soon as it
takes off where there's two primary points of contact in the plane, right?
There's more out of the plane, but you've got a friction force resisting the
sliding in that corner. You've got the pushing you're doing there. Depending on
the friction cones, if they're large enough, there's actually a place where
you can start lifting it up. You get enough friction on the finger that you're,
that you can provide a torque, okay? But you're not producing so much force that
you're sliding. And you can put yourself in this regime where you can, you can
lift up the box. That would be extremely hard. I hope it's clear that, I like this
example because I think that would be extremely hard to do in position control
mode. That's really a force kind of action. And if you, even if you don't have
the perfect model, but if certainly if you do have the perfect model, then you
can just do it. Okay, so here's my mesh cat cheese it box, right? The fingers off
and in contact there, okay? It's come into contact because I commanded some non-zero
force. The controller we're gonna write now, and I want to step through it on the
board and be a little bit careful. I actually, that was the one feedback I got
from your, what you guys said about the deep perception network is the lectures,
which I really liked that level of feedback. People said, you maybe step
through a few more examples a little bit more slowly. Happy to do it. I'll try to
do that today and, and you tell me. Okay, so I've got, I've got, I'm gonna write a
controller that controls basically the orientation of the box by controlling
the force on the finger. That's our goal. And to convince you that it works, I just
have a little, I'm only controlling through the finger, but I can basically
regulate the orientation of the box. This is the full physics engine, right? Running
and it's not sliding at the bottom corner. It is, and it's providing the
forces only through the finger, through force control mode. Okay, it's actually
worth going through the exercise of doing that, I think. Now let me do
something a little crazy. So watch what happens to the finger if I go like this.
That was actually pretty good.
Darn it. I switched to the SAP solver, which is great, and I recommend it, because
I recommend it to everybody. But now the finger, normally the finger was flying
off at the end, and I guess it doesn't go flying off. Okay, my controller is better
than I wanted it to be. Imagine that the finger happened to slide to the edge of
the box, but it's still commanding a force, right? I made a strong, I'm making a
strong assumption in this controller, which is that the finger is pushing on
the side of the box. If you're regulating force and your finger is suddenly in
free space, then what's it gonna do? It's gonna rocket itself down until it
collides with the ground. Or, depending on the angle, it might rocket itself off into
free, you know, off the box. And there you get into your throwing and smashing
regime. Okay. Oh, I'm a little bummed that I, I think probably this is the right
answer, but the other one was allowing a little bit of numerical errors. Okay, good.
So let's, let's actually work that out a bit. How can you write a controller that
does that? The hardest part about it, I think, is getting the notation right. And
maybe there's some tricks of kind of how to write it in a way that doesn't, doesn't,
isn't too susceptible to model errors and the like, like, okay. So let me draw my
free body diagram. I'm in the middle of the bin. I'll exaggerate here and put it
in some relatively large angle. Okay. I'm gonna have a bunch of frames that matter.
This is my body frame, the X, Z. Okay. I'm gonna call this frame, since I've got B
and I'm gonna have a contact frame C, I went ahead and used my imagination and
called this one A.
So that's frame A, where this is X and Z. And I'll have a contact frame over where
my finger is touching the wall. And I'll put that frame, remember the normal
forces always go in the Z axis in our contact frames, right. So this is frame C
and this is Z and this is X, to keep with my right-hand rule. Now, when we were
talking about the point of view of the robot, we were trying to command the
force that the robot felt, you know, the force at C applied to the finger F. But
for the free body analysis, I actually want to think about the equal and
opposite force, which is the force that the finger is applying at C on the body
B. So that force, which is gonna use all my colors here, so probably, and you could
see it in my simulation, which I should probably stop just so I don't like run
out of battery or something silly, probably I'm gonna have a force that's
in this direction here. And that's gonna be, that force I'm gonna call the force
on body B at A, see, oh my god, named ground, okay. And I can express it in
various frames, but let's express it in the A frame, okay. And I have another
force, which is probably gonna be pushing me, it's gonna stay inside the friction
cone, okay, but if I wanted to tip up, it's gonna be, it's gonna have a component
like this, right. This, by default, is gonna be on body B applied at C of the
finger, that's my name for it, this is the finger, and it's most natural to express
it in frame C, well, we know our transforms to go back and forth between
them. And then, of course, I have a gravity force here, which, if we want to keep our
notation consistent here, this is the force applied at body B, normally you can
just write B for that, but I'll just be explicit from gravity, and I can write it
in the B, actually it's most natural to express that in the world
frame, because then it's just 0, negative, M times 9.8, whatever.
Okay, what do we know about these different forces? We know, I'll stick
with the color codes here to try to keep it clear, we can, let's assume for a
minute we know the friction cones, we'll assume we know the mass, we'll assume we
know the geometry, but I promise that the controller I give you is gonna actually
be pretty good about that, not having to know them very perfectly. So, if I know
the friction coefficient at the contact point, then by my notation, right, what I
know is that the force of the finger, the Z component, well first of all, it's only,
it can't pull on the box, okay, and then the X component, magnitude, is less than
the friction coefficient times the Z component. In the frame of C, this is a
simple thing to write, okay. The implications of that, of course, in the
world frame, for instance, depend on transforming the frames into the world
frame, but it's really just that simple, you'd call it the simple ice cream cone
in that case, where it's just along the Z axis. Same thing for the
bottom, for the ground, okay, right, we could say the same thing for the ground.
I won't write it all out here, but the force B at A of the ground applied at A,
can I just say that's in the friction cone at A? That's kind of a notational
shorthand for that, yeah, and that would depend on mu A, of course, which I think I
said to both of them, both would just be one in this case. It doesn't have to be,
in the book case, they have to be different. This one, it's not clear
to me that it has to be different. It depends on the geometries and other
things. Okay, the force of the finger, if you think about that as a three-element
force, we're going to be commanding that effectively, right, we're going to be
regulating that. Our controller gets to, in some sense, set the force of the finger
as an input. What do we, how do we think about the force on the ground?
This is saying it's inside, this gives me a whole range of possible forces,
but how do we know which force is going to happen? Which one's Newton going to
give us, or God, or something?
Cool.
Good, right, it's the, it's whichever one's going to keep the point
from moving, right, it's whatever force is necessary to set the velocity, to
keep the velocity at zero. If we're in the stiction regime, so if no sliding,
then if we comply in all these forces into the frame of A, this is the important
way to say what you just said here, if we put all the forces into the frame of A,
that they're in equilibrium at A. There's no acceleration at A. Okay,
so the force of the finger, I can map that to point A, and I express it in A,
plus the force of the ground, expressed in A, applied at A, plus the force of
gravity at A, EA, that equals zero, because that's what friction does.
Basically, given this and this, it will set this to make that zero. The causality
is not something I'm trying to make a statement about, but in practice, since
we're controlling this, we're going to be able to understand what the
ground is going to be. So this is the important equation, the no-stick,
or the stick no sliding condition at the ground, which helps me solve for the
ground forces. But inside that, I can choose different forces to apply at that
ground, as long as they are able to satisfy this equation by staying in the
friction cone, then I have room to possibly push up, and try to torque this
thing up. So the last important thing that we have to think about is the torque
applied to the body, expressed at, let's say, the total torque in the frame of A,
for instance. I want this, which is also going to be the same sum, you know,
finger plus ground plus gravity in the torque components. The torque of the
ground at the ground is zero, because its moment arm is zero, but I can
control the-- I can choose this torque at the finger to try to make a torque around
this bottom point. So by reasoning about the forces and the friction
cones, I can lift up my objective to say I basically want a pure torque around
there, subject to the constraints that the forces doesn't slide-- that the ground
doesn't slide. So we just need a control strategy for choosing that,
you know, this torque that's now, you know, abstracted-- we've abstracted away, we can
sort of think about what torque do I want. And there's lots of possible
answers. I could choose-- I could use my perfect model of the cracker box and my
perfect sense of the geometry, but I don't want to do that. I want to show
that force control is a little general and doesn't work-- doesn't require perfect
knowledge. So let's just say I want the-- even the finger here, that's the one I
have direct control of-- the finger to come out of a PID controller. How about
that? And I'm going to have a-- I'm going to call it-- let me just see if I can write
that. So I'd like to think of the torque as being-- you guys know PID control? I've
said it a few times, but never perfectly defined it, right? The proportional
integral derivative control. Why would I want to choose that? Well, let's say I
don't know the force of gravity, the torque due to gravity, because I don't
know the mass perfectly of the Chezyt box. I don't know that-- maybe I don't
know the gain of my-- you know, if I don't know the position of the finger
perfectly relative to the position of the ground, because I don't know how big
the box is, then I might have some slop in any model-based control here. But if I
do just a simple linear feedback, if the angle isn't as high as I expect it to be,
I'll pull more, okay? I'll put more torque in. If it's too low, I'll
push less, and I'll even have an integral term that could compensate for that mass.
This is a very simple-- since it's a one degree of freedom problem, I can just do
a very simple controller that'll use feedback that says if the angle's not
where I want it, pull a little harder. If it's too far, pull a little back, okay?
And that'll just change the torque of the finger. Is that clear?
Unfortunately, this is a competing objective. It's not clear that
I can choose any torque of the finger, because there's other constraints coming
from the friction cone. So I'm going to pull up my optimization playbook, and why
don't I say this is my goal, so why don't I write a minimization over the--
ultimately, it's going to be on the force of the finger that I can pick, which
I'll write it directly in the B of the contact-- I could pick any of them,
though, really-- of the finger. These are my decision variables, okay? And I want it
to be that my torque of my finger is approximately my PID controller. This is
kind of my objective. This is my estimated angle of the-- I'll make that a
quadratic objective, and I'll solve for it subject to my friction cone
constraints, and the force balance constraint.
And everything we wrote here, it turns out, is a linear constraint. Even though
we're changing coordinate systems with our spatial algebra between frames A and
frame C, it's a cross product that happens, but of a cross product
with a known position, and the decision variables only enter linearly. So this is
still a quadratic objective, and these are linear constraints. So this is the
good case. It's a quadratic program, and you can solve your little quadratic
program, and apparently never let the finger slip off the box. Okay, that's all
I'm running right here. Is that level of detail useful? A little slow? Okay, send it
to me on the survey or something. I will continue to try to dial it in.
But so there's, you know, the particular instantiation of it as a quadratic
program is cool, but I guess the essential element is that I can choose
commands for my point finger that if I didn't think about forces, there's just
like no hope. I could rotate that thing up and think, you know, the
exact force that I'm applying, no matter what the angle is, is hugely dependent
on my friction cones and things like that. And it's only with that that I can
get this sort of rock-solid demo where I can move the box up and down.
Actually, I thought about bringing a Cheez-It box down, but I didn't want to
embarrass myself, because that's actually really hard to do that. I was also going
to then have to bring like a rubber mat or something like that, and then it gets
less cool. Dryad at home, homework. Flip up a Cheez-It box without using the
wall. OK? Questions?
That's a narrow example of something that I would-- we'll call direct force
control.
Even though I have two controllers in some sense happening here, I have this
higher level controller, the command I'm sending to my robot is trying to
directly command a force. And it'll make that happen in the-- point finger case,
it's trivial to make it happen. In the robot case, maybe you have a force sensor
or something to make that happen. OK? Guess what we're going to do? Indirect
force control next. OK? But I guess I-- everybody still says they like the
break, the stretch break. So let me stretch for a second, and then we'll do
the indirect force control.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
[END PLAYBACK]
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, good.
Good, good, good. So if I'm writing this in the code, I have to somehow relate
tau finger A with the decision variables here. So this is really a function which
does my spatial algebra, that does the coordinate change. But this is a linear
function of this, given I know the position-- if I know the position of C in
body B relative to A, for instance, then I have that cross, is what gives me this.
But this is just a constant matrix times my decision variables. There's also,
because I changed expressed in frames, I would have a rotation matrix also on top
of that. But those are just-- that's a great question, thank you for asking it.
Those are just linear functions of this. And you can play with it if you want. So
if I didn't know this exactly, but I just estimated it, it's still going to work
pretty well. In fact, the first version I did, I just assumed I knew the width of
the box and I didn't even put in the term relative to the height of the box, and it
was fine. In fact, I think I updated it. I can't remember which version I pushed to
git. But yeah, so it's pretty robust to that.
Okay, so I think this is a beautiful solution-- oh, please, go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE]
Okay.
Yeah. So he says, what if we have a springy material? How would that change
things? Yeah, let me think where you're coming from here on that. So I mean, in
general, I would still be applying a force. So far I've said, let's say you
can measure the force on the finger and regulate it. So it might be that by-- in
order to regulate the force, it might push into whatever surface is a
little bit springy. And it could change the equations that I'm trying to balance
in order to, you know, reason about the far corner. So it might change the free
body diagram. But I think the formulation will still work. I think that the basic
concept of regulating-- just reasoning about the forces should be
intact. And even, I think, linear springs, which is a pretty good model of those
kind of contacts, should go through without even changing the complexity of
the task. If you had a very nonlinear, you know, response curve or something in the
spring, then it gets harder.
[INAUDIBLE]
I see. Okay. I see. So humans are-- so he says, what if it's a human arm?
Right. So humans are annoying. I'm sorry. That's a bad way to go through life. Hard
to model. Humans are hard to model, both physically and their intelligence is also
hard to model. They're squishy, but we're kind of like full of water. And so we
tend to not build high-fidelity models of their skin. And oftentimes fairly
simple models of softness are sufficient. You're also not supposed to
push on people, I think. Not with big robots. So be careful with that.
Disclaimer, nothing-- if you push a person with this controller, I'm not to
blame. It's all good. That's a great question. That's a great question. Okay.
There's only one thing that I really think this controller is very
sensitive to. I claimed it as a good thing that, you know, when you're close
to contact and you're not in contact, you command a force. At least locally, it does
the right thing. Okay. But if you're just a little bit off and you command a force,
it could do an exceptionally wrong thing. Okay. So it is making a big
assumption that you're in contact or nearly in contact. And applying
that force is in contact. And it does require, you know, maybe, you know, it does
require some free body diagram kind of modeling. It turns out there's a version
of force control, an indirect version of force control, that can be a lot more
natural. It can mix objectives about position and force and give you, you know,
another programming language. Think of these as programming languages to
control the end effector of your robot. Okay. Position was our first control, our
programming language. Force, pure force was the next one. And we're going to go
into kind of a mixed position and force, if you will. Indirect force control. In
particular, let's start with stiffness control. So here's the paradigm, right? So
let's say I am doing this dangerous thing of walking up to my robot and, you
know, pushing on the end effector. But I'm going to push it. And the force I want,
what if I wanted, even though it's a big robot and it's complicated, what if I
want it to be, when I push on it, it acts just like a linear spring. That I want
whatever force, you know, when I'm not pushing out at all, it should just sit
still. When I push on it a little bit, I want it to push back proportional to how
far I've pushed it from that. Right? It turns out we can make our whole big
complicated robot act like a spring at that point. Okay? And that's sort
of the second big idea. And again, if we write down our simple dynamics in the
point finger world, it's simple to accomplish that and to even say more
carefully what I mean. What I would like is to pick a u so that my effective
dynamics look like this. On the wrong side.
That would be the equations of a spring with a resting point at the desired
location. Okay? So now, this is in some sense programming indirectly the forces,
but it's programming the interaction that the robot is going to
have with the world. If the world applies this, it's going to respond with some
motion. Similarly, if the robot is at a motion, you know it's pushing back with a
certain force. So it's defining that relationship. That turns out to be a
really nice paradigm. Okay? Let me play with it. Okay? To do this, though, I needed
to make the box in see-through. So let's see if I can make this clear. Okay, so the
same box, it's just less, I've removed the market branding. Okay? And I've got two
fingers because one is the virtual finger, which is my X desired and Z
desired, and the other finger is getting pulled there with a spring. Okay? So as I
move around in the free space, my finger, the actual finger tracks the desired
finger. Okay? But if I push into here, now I'm applying more force depending on how
big that spring is being pulled, and at some point I can move the box by moving
my virtual finger. So I'm, there's this natural interaction of kind of, I can
still think about forces, but I'm thinking about it through the set
points of a spring. What's good about that is if I were to suddenly move up,
for instance, it doesn't go totally crazy. Right? I've defined a more robust law, but
you also saw, I kind of gave a hint there, right? It's actually not a bad way to
flip up a box. Check this out. I'm leaning on the corner there. Okay? Let me reset
and I can do it better.
Okay, so now what if I just put the set point of the spring somewhere over here?
We're gonna think about what the physics of that is, but it's actually a beautiful,
beautiful idea. I want this suddenly to have forces applied to the box such that
it's, there's like a spring rubber banding me to the wall right around
that pivot point. Okay? What happens? Whoop! That's pretty good, right? Just in case I
couldn't do it myself, I made an open-loop script that does the same
thing, right? It's actually so, I would have had to be pretty, pretty bad to not
get it to work. But this is now open-loop, if you will. It's just executing an
open-loop script, no feedback required, except at the level of regular, of making
this law happen. It's a beautiful way to program the interaction. Okay? You can
imagine that, so stiffness control would be if you made it act like it had a
particular stiffness. Okay? Damping control would be if you programmed the
damping. Impedance control would be if you programmed all three of them. You
could even change the effective mass. Okay? Those of you in Neville's lab can
weigh in, but, right? So, impedance control is the most general name of it.
You can program m, v, and k, for instance. It's kind of weird that you could apply
forces, so I could push on my robot and have it act like it's a different mass
robot than it is. Right? It turns out it's hard to do that, and I think a lot of
people will do this and this, and I think it's less common to do mass. In the
EWA specifically, it's called, it is an impedance controller, but they're not
actually regulating the mass of the robot. They're regulating the mass of the
rotor. So, at the rotor level, there's doing some amount of impedance
regulation of mass matrix. Inertial shaping is what they might call it.
Okay? But maybe not at the full. Make the robot, like, making a heavy robot act like
it's very light requires typically high bandwidth, maybe either good force or
acceleration sensing, those kind of things that are strong requirements
for a control system. Okay. So, that's pretty good, right? So, and you saw what
happened, right? Was that we took a different strategy to flip up the box. We
made a virtual pivot point here, and we made effectively a spring that was here,
that was applying forces just based on that spring, and then as I moved this up,
the spring force caused it to not only flip over, but also push down, right? Once
I got here, and it started pushing up and over, the forces changed direction from
here to being here, and it actually did exactly what I wanted the whole sequence
through by thinking of it not as programming the force directly, but by
programming the interaction.
Yes?
[inaudible]
I mean, normally it's, let me think about, so I think normally the task sort of
provides that, right? So, in most cases I think there is a natural answer, but it
comes from the task definition. Like, for, you know, for pushing books or
something, then maybe books will have some natural stiffness that they'll want
to be interacting with or whatever. I worry you're asking a deeper
question than I'm answering. Can you give me an example of a situation where it
would be hard to pick those?
[inaudible]
I see. Excellent. Okay, so the great, so great. So, even in this
controller specifically, how did I pick kp and kd? Perfect. That I can answer. I
think I set them to one. So, the point is, I think in this example it was
pretty, I mean, maybe ten or something, you know, actually almost always I'll pick
this to be, you know, square root of g more than this so that it's critically
damped or something like that, okay? But, so that, there are basic heuristics like
that. But, if I had picked a smaller or bigger gain, then I would have just moved
the finger more into penetration or less into penetration, and I think the same
phenomenon would have worked over a large range of gains. It's just a matter
of how, you know, where that critical point for the virtual finger
would have been, I think. I think this particular demo would have been very
robust to that. The box is experiencing different forces, right? But, what's
essential here is that there's a pivot point about which those forces are
rotating, which is somehow inside the box. And I think that's true for basically
all k's.
[inaudible]
For any given task, right? So, this is, in some sense, this is what's
happening when you're commanding the EWA now, right? It's happening in joint space.
We're going to talk about the rest of the robot on Thursday, but, you know, so
far you've been thinking about commanding positions. In fact, what it's
doing is it's setting a virtual position and it's putting a small spring between
your command and the actual. And that's why when you take the dishwasher door,
and you might not know exactly where the dishwasher door is, but you command some
trajectory that's close, it will actually deform. The true, you know, finger
will track, but with some error, the commanded cues in that position. So,
oftentimes the programming paradigm is command what you want. Maybe you go
a little bit more into penetration than you would have otherwise, or
something like that. But you command what you want and the robot will get it done
in a soft way.
I did that for emphasis, you know, so if I made the stiffness higher, then it
would have been pretty, it wouldn't be as far. There are interesting
cases, maybe I should even jump to that, but I'll come back to the hybrid version
in a second here. But let me actually make this point of the best case, the
most interesting case of doing this. Maybe you guys know, do you know the
remote centered compliance story? This is like so clever. It's really kind of what
we just did. There's something called RCC, remote centered compliance. It's one of
the most clever things, I think, in force control, because it's done in hardware.
There's no software, okay? It was done in 1977 at MIT by a guy named Drake. I thought
that was so cool. I didn't know that. That's great. Okay, so this was
about, this was originally motivated by peg and hole tasks. It turns out it's
more generally useful for assembly tasks, okay? So if you think about sticking a
peg in a hole, then a lot of interesting things happen, okay? Certainly you can get
a little bit out of line, right? And things could go bad if you're coming
down with a peg and you're just out of alignment. That could be bad.
But you can play some tricks like chamfering the edges to help a little
bit with that. And people actually have changed the strategies
where you often come down a little bit at an angle, so you have a little bit
more robustness to the exact arrival. But the really nasty thing that can happen
with the peg and hole task is you can be partially inserted but out of alignment.
Let me see if I can draw it with a different color here. And you can get
yourself jammed. Like actually the forces here and the forces here could be large
enough that you can't really even pull yourself out, okay? So this is a really,
this is nasty business. And this is such an important operation for assembly, you
know, for factory robots that it got a lot of attention, you know, in 70s.
Actually it motivated some of the early work in motion planning too. So if you
know Tomas Lozano Perez's early work on configuration space, which is kind of a
core idea, a lot of those initial papers were actually done in the
context of peg and hole insertion, okay? So it motivated AI stuff too. But the one
I'm telling you about here today is let's think about how would you program
a response that you'd want to do here. What's the analogy of that box flip up
for this, okay? It turns out that what you want to do is have a center of
compliance that's somewhere down here instead of somewhere up here, okay? So I
don't know how to make that super clear except maybe I'll use my eraser,
okay? I'd probably get all chalky in the process. So if I've got a some sort of
stiffness in my hand and I'm holding it at the top, which is where the robots
going to be holding it for peg insertion, and I come down at a little angle but
I'm a little bit out of alignment, then what happens? Right, this is me just
trying to move my hand straight down, right? Things go pretty bad. Okay, let's
say I had the center of compliance at the bottom. A little awkward that my hand
would have to be in the hole, okay? But let's say I could do it for a second. I'm
coming in at the same angle going straight down. It lines up beautifully. It
lined up even better with the lighter eraser I had in my office when I was
playing before. Let me try with a lighter eraser. Alright, so if I go straight down
from this, not so good. If I come down straight down like this, it just actually
lines perfectly up, okay? So the stiffness you want is like a torsional stiffness
but not where the hand is. You want to have an effective stiffness down here.
But your hands up here, you really can't put your hand in the hole, that would
just not be good. It turns out there's this super clever mechanism that looks
like that. Oh my god, there's a few of them, right? That was one of the
original ones, which has cantilevered springs up here. See, it looks, it has
these springs up here, the point of the tool comes in here, and this, it
basically is this elaborate spring mechanism that makes the effective
center of compliance. This is the instance center side of beam
deflections and the center of compliance ends up down here. It gives a remote
center of compliance. So this is far in the regime of, you know, I said most of
the time you're just doing virtual things that are small. This is far
in the regime of being very clever with where you put that virtual force, and so
there are cases where you can do that. And this means that I go in and I jam
my pin down, it's a slightly wrong location, and the mechanism with
effectively infinite bandwidth, you don't have to, people tried to do this in
software, you could try to do this in software, but the software is going to be
running on a control system which reads the sensors at some rate, the
actuators can only move at some rate. If you do it with physical springs, it's
effectively, you know, arbitrarily fast. Physics is doing the work for you, and it
can adjust itself and snap itself into place. And people really do
this, like when you're jamming parts together, this is a physical one. This is
mating, so there's some pins on the bottom and there's some holes on
this top, and they have to align it, and the robot is not doing super detailed
visual servoing, it's just kind of jamming it down, and the remote center
compliance is doing the work. It's such a clever idea, so good, put it in hardware.
Okay, so that's on the extreme of being very clever with it.
All right, so but overall, the message of the lecture, I hope, is that you
realize that sometimes it's more natural to talk to your robot through
the language of forces than through the language of positions. That's true, by the
way, if you care about reinforcement learning or supervised learning, you know,
behavior cloning kind of learning, there are some tasks that you would want
your neural network to output forces instead of outputting positions, right?
This is a general concept, and people, you know, there's papers like, oh, I
switched to impedance control mode on the output and it learns four times
faster. Depends on the task, but that can happen.
Okay, so the stiffness control, the impedance control, is one way to
just say I'm not going to command forces directly, I'm going to switch to
commanding virtual stiffness, but you don't have to, you can mix and mash these
different ideas. So the book example was actually hybrid force control, where I
cared about regulating the forces directly. I actually commanded force in
the vertical position, because I wanted to be in that friction cone sweet spot,
okay? But then for sliding, I wanted to have position control mode, because I
wanted to control where the hand was going to go. And you'll do that, you'll
work through that example on the homework. Okay, but instead, just to give
you a couple different ways that you could do hybrid force or stiffness
control, it's called-- it's often called force position control, but let's stick
with the theme here. So what if I did in my-- this is my xy components here-- what
if my x-axis, I wanted to do position control? So I'll program the stiffness in
this. It's on this side, it's got to be like this, x desired minus x plus kd, x
dot desired minus x dot, for instance. And on the x-axis, I'll go ahead and
command the force desired in just-- sorry, in the z-axis. And if I want to
command it like this, then I put a minus inside, okay? So that's roughly what
happens in some of these hybrid, where you want to-- in one axis, you're going to
act like a position source, and the other axis you'll act like a force controller.
Okay? Now you don't have to choose world X and world Y, you could do this in any
frame you want, multiply it by a rotation matrix in front, do your spatial algebra,
and achieve forces that are, for instance, if you are welding that--
following the wall, for instance, maybe you want to always in the
normal direction, your current normal direction, you want to act like a force
and in the horizontal, you know, tangential direction, you could act like
a position, for instance. Those are these kind of things. Okay, so that's a general
recipe. It's also not the only recipe. You can also mix them, sort of-- oftentimes
you'll actually just mix them all together, right? So you could also do u
equals negative mg plus-- maybe if I'm not using scalars anymore, I'll make it a
capital-- Okay, so you can have a little bit of this and a little bit of that, and
if you turn up kp-- if you turn kp down to zero, then you could be almost
completely in, you know, if these two coefficients, these gains, are zero, you
can be acting like a force source, and if they're turned up, then you can act more
like a position source, and you keep that command small. That's another way to mix
them. In fact, this is what-- this is a common interface for the
panda or for the iwa, and this would be called-- typically called like a
feed-forward torque or force. An extra command to send down, but you, you know,
often primarily interact through the stiffness controller. Okay, so this is--
this is actually great in some applications, but this is just maybe the
most-- the most general way to write it, if you will. Certainly I could produce
this with this with the proper choices of kp and kd and f. Yeah? Okay, so next time
we'll tell you about-- we're gonna stop assuming a point robot, but that's a
pretty good stopping point. Okay, see you Thursday.
Hi.
Sure, sure, sure.
do the picking up with other.