[BLANK_AUDIO]
>> It's on now.
I'll keep talking for a second here for you.
Yeah.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
>> Okay, let's get started.
So last time we started our work on perception, right?
And I had intended to get through iterative closest point.
We didn't quite get through it, so I'll finish that off today.
And the goal for today, last time we sort of assumed perfect point clouds.
We assumed that our sensors were giving us the best possible information that
they could given the projection through the lens.
But there was no noise, there was no outliers, there were nothing like this.
So today we're gonna think about what happens when those point clouds get messy,
because real point clouds are very messy.
And think about ways we're gonna sort of modify our basic computational framework
to make this more robust.
And I think there's a couple particular algorithms I'll try to show you.
And I think they kind of represent a nice way to understand the problem,
understand what you can do with it.
There are many different variants out there, but
I think there's a few that you can get a taste for what's possible.
So just to set that up again, remember that our goal for today, for
this week I guess, is to do the same thing we did before.
But we've added these D415 cameras, and now we are reasoning about where
in the scene, I hid my point cloud there, but
we're actually using those cameras to find the mustard bottle.
First by taking pictures, then by turning those pictures,
those depth return, RGBD images into a point cloud.
This is actually the result of after filtering the point cloud,
getting it down to just the mustard that's left there, and
removing the bins and all the distractors and stuff like this.
And then what we'll see is we run ICP on this mustard bottle in order to
then accomplish the task.
Okay.
So we started last time with a really important component of the algorithm
that started us thinking about sort of connections between the kinematics
problems we've talked about and the perception problems we're starting to
talk about.
So we started off by saying we were given a few things.
We were given a model in the form of a point cloud, so our model points,
where we wrote them as a bunch of points, model i, and
we had this canonical model frame in the object frame, right?
I'll write bigger, I remembered.
Okay.
And then we also had scene points.
This is what we got from the camera with a little bit of processing to put it
into a point cloud format.
And this was originally, we obtained some scene points in the camera
coordinates, and then we assumed we had the camera pose.
So this is the camera.
Right?
And then the biggest assumption we made last time
was that point mi corresponded with scene point si.
Right?
So we somehow could look through our camera and know that there was a
particular point in the point cloud, and that should be associated with a
particular point in our model.
Okay?
If we have this setup, then it's incredibly useful to know that given
that setup, we can write an objective like this, minimize over the unknown
pose, which would be the pose of the object in the world.
And when I'm writing it as an optimization, I want to be clear, our
notation sort of makes it clear, but I want to be super clear that as an
argument to a mathematical program, that this is an object that is the poses.
So especially you put it in group three.
Okay?
And the objective is that for all of the eyes, I'd like that if I take both
the model points and the scene points into the world frame, then their
distance is small.
And I tried to show you the landscape of this.
This is a quadratic objective.
Right?
When I plotted it with just two decision variables, which I could do in 2D
with just rotations, right, then it looks like just this quadratic bowl.
And then this constraint here, the fact that these are not arbitrary
rotation matrices inside here, meant that there was an extra constraint,
which was that unit disk.
We'll see that picture again.
But this was sort of a nice optimization problem, and it has a closed form.
It's numerical, but an algorithm that's almost as good as closed form
solution via SVD, singular value decomposition.
That's where we were last time.
Right?
I want to just point out again, point out quickly here, because we're
going to play with different formulations of this today, and different ways
that are going to be good optimizations, ugly optimizations, that are going
to give certain robustness properties.
Maybe there's a point to plane version of this, where you can try to
correspond points to whole faces of a mesh, for instance.
There's a bunch of versions of this, but we're going to be doing
manipulations on these basic equations.
OK?
So the first one, just to observe right off the bat, is that if I had
written instead, if I wanted to transform the scene points into the
object frame, for instance, if I had done-- what do I want?
I want the transform from the world, let's say, into object frame,
should be the inverse of this transform.
And I'd written this optimization with this guy.
OK?
That's solving for a different transform.
This is trying to put the points together, everything in the object
frame.
OK?
But from the point of view of an optimization problem, this looks
identical, and can also be solved with SVD.
Right?
This is still linear in the decision variables here, plus some
constraints that are solved by SVD.
OK?
So you can go back and forth, and we're going to move these
things around, and we'll understand where it breaks and where it
works.
OK, but I want to address this big assumption, because really, how
could you possibly know which point in the model-- if I get a
point cloud of a mustard bottle, how am I possibly going to know
which one goes to the top, which one goes to the bottom?
That's maybe the hardest part of perception, is to make that leap.
OK, so I think a picture-- well, actually, the picture on the
screen is a pretty useful one.
So this is-- remember, my blue is my model.
My salmon-colored is my scene.
Right?
The brown is what I get when they overlap, and it wasn't
artistically chosen, clearly.
OK?
And the green here, the green lines, are the correspondences.
I just drew in, saying, if I said that this point corresponds
to this point, I'll just draw a line.
OK, so let's say I didn't have those correspondences, but I had
this initial frame of the model points and these initial scene
points.
You can imagine-- and the algorithm's name is a pretty
good indication of what the first thing we're going to try
is-- a fairly good heuristic would be to say, let's just
guess that the points that are-- the correspondences are the
points that are closest in space.
I'll have an initial guess of the object, and I'll have the
actual scene points.
And let's just start by saying the ones that are closest in
Euclidean distance are the ones that correspond.
OK?
It's interesting.
Right here, you'd see that this one on the first guess
might get it wrong, that this point would correspond to this
point, probably.
But if enough of the points correspond to the right points--
I'll make this precise in a second here-- then we can have
an algorithm that can be, I think, actually very effective.
So this is the iterative closest point algorithm, which
is doing exactly this.
And I'll write the equations down to make that precise in
just a second.
And what you can see is, even if the first guess is wrong,
and then you solve for a new pose, given this singular value
decomposition, it puts you in a new condition where you can
try to make your correspondences again.
And as long as that alternation converges, you can get
global solutions to this.
Now, we're going to-- this is also susceptible to local
minima.
You'll see the bad cases in a minute, too.
But this is the basic algorithm I want to understand next.
So the iterative closest point algorithm
is going to try to solve for the correspondences.
So we need a notation for our correspondences.
We're going to have an initial guess for the object.
I'll stick with the original one.
We're moving the model into the scene points.
When I'm going to do an estimate,
I'm going to try to use this hat notation to say,
this is my guess at the true x.
So given this, I want to find correspondences.
So step one.
And I'm going to write the correspondences
in a correspondence vector.
OK, so let's just write it like this.
I'll call it the vector c here, where I'll say c-- let me do--
ci, the i-th element of this vector c.
I'll choose as my heuristic to take the point that
is the minimum distance.
I'll make sure this notation's clear in just a second.
Given my initial estimate x hat, argument over j.
I'll search over all of the j's, psi x squared.
And since this is just going to be
a guess at the correspondences, I'll put a hat there too.
OK, so what is this?
This is saying that I'll take each point--
for every scene point i, I want to find a corresponding model
point j.
So I'm going to loop through all of the possible j's,
try all the possible model points,
and compute the distance between that model point
j and my scene point i that I'm considering.
And whichever one minimizes it-- so min
would be the value of the optimization,
and arg min is the element j which
causes this to be smallest.
That's the difference between min versus arg min, yeah?
So this is returning the element j,
and I'll tuck that into the vector c.
Is that notation clear?
So this is a vector of integers.
So how would you compute this in general?
So we talked about quadratic optimization over there.
This is now an integer optimization,
but it's just a list of numbers.
So you can just compute-- worst case,
you can compute all of the distances
and just take the smallest one.
There's a finite number of things to compute.
Just take the smallest one.
In practice, we don't do that.
In practice, there's efficient data structure
for nearest neighbor queries, so we're going to use those.
So kdtrees, there's public libraries
that make these very fast, approximate nearest neighbor
queries and the like.
So in practice, you can make this computation
use your best nearest neighbor data structures.
And then step two, the reason I chose this notation
is that I can just say my new x hat is
the result of that optimization with just the correspondence
is written in here.
So I've got model point ci hat in here minus psi.
See what I did?
I've got to sum all these up over i.
So I used to just have mi here, assume that I knew
one-to-one correspondence.
Now I'm going to say I'm going to take whichever model point
corresponds to that scene point.
And I'll sum over all the scene points,
and I can still-- it's, from the optimization perspective,
the same as that optimization.
So I can use my SVD.
Is the algorithm clear?
It's the simplest.
It's like the bread and butter point cloud algorithm.
You'll see it used in lots of places.
Yes?
I thought the question was still like,
what if the dimensions don't match?
Good.
Yeah, so the question was, what if the dimensions don't match?
So I made a choice here with my notation
to say that I'd like to say for every scene point,
I'll try to find a model that corresponds.
We're going to talk about that.
So that has implications.
So in the case of partial views, for instance,
that makes a lot of sense.
I'll say this very carefully in a minute.
But I made a choice so far to say that all I'm requiring
is that every scene point, it corresponds
with one model point.
You could have many model points for ones
that are used by the same-- sorry,
one model point that's used by many scene points.
You could have some model points that
are used by no scene points.
But this notation says that for all the scene points,
I'll do this.
Good question.
Yes?
Is this honoring Merck if you don't go around all
of the top [INAUDIBLE]
That's a great question.
So the question is, what happens if you
don't take all of the correspondences,
but you take a few of them?
And I think we're going to have to do that at some point
to address some messiness.
So we're going to think about the right way to do that.
So at some point, we're going to have to deal with that.
And let me give you an example right away that sort of, I
think, makes that point.
Imagine if I had my object of interest here.
And this is the ghost of the-- I'll
use my reddish color for my scene points.
You get the idea?
And what happens if, I don't know,
there was a reflection or something,
and I got a couple scene points way over here?
And I have my model that started off with some initial guess.
So this is nicely getting pulled in this direction.
But I said so far that every scene point corresponds
to at least one model point.
So these points are still going to pick some point on the model.
And they're going to pull this in this direction.
They're trying to minimize the distance
between the corresponding points.
See, I've got all the colors here.
I can say, if I've got some green correspondences here--
I guess that would be the shortest one would be a straight
line, like this.
And then even if I have a lot of good correspondences here
that's pulling me this way, I can
have even a very small number of correspondences
that are far off.
But because that distance is large,
they can have overwhelming effect
on the quality of the algorithm.
So that's a reason maybe that it feels unnatural
to say that every scene point has
to match with at least one model point.
That makes you susceptible to outliers.
But the reason I chose that was because there's
another direction, too, which is that what if I only
have partial views?
So I've got a camera.
I'll use white for my camera here.
I've got my camera over here.
And it's looking down.
And I can see this part of the object.
But I'm not seeing any points over here.
OK.
So if I said, for instance, that every model point
has to correspond with one scene point,
that would be the opposite choice
if I had made the opposite choice over there.
Then again, I've got some model points here
which don't have a correspondence here.
And they will cause big artifacts potentially here.
So you can choose either to correspond scene to model
or model to scene.
One of them, the scene to model, I think,
makes you susceptible to outliers.
And the model to scene makes you susceptible to partial views.
OK.
And that's kind of the point of the lecture
is that we're going to have to do a little bit better
than both of those.
I would say that these are the dominant problems,
the important ways that real point clouds are messy.
I would say messy is a silly term.
But noise is taken.
I would say I want to reserve noise for something
like I'll say in a minute.
So what would noise be in the context of a perception system
like this?
Maybe I measure the true scene point,
but plus or minus some Gaussian noise, for instance.
So every one of those points is just
perturbed with some Gaussian.
I shouldn't say this.
That's what all the theorists pick
when they try to prove something about perception
or something like this.
They always assume Gaussian noise.
But that's not what real cameras do.
In fact, I would say that it's the easiest thing to analyze.
But it's not a property.
I'd say that the real cameras are actually
very low in terms of noise.
And this kind of noise is relatively easy
to be robust to.
In fact, we've already got relatively good robustness
to noise just by writing it in this least squares objective.
To some extent, if you've got Gaussian noise added in here,
then you'd expect this least squares objective
to be the right metric for rejecting that noise.
So by virtue of not asking David Urest
the last time about whether we should make this a quality
and what that looks like, by asking for it to be softer,
this gives us nice robustness to that Gaussian noise.
But I think partial views are a very big one.
You're never going to see the bottom of your object that's
sitting on the table until you pick it up.
No amount of looking around or whatever is going to get you
to see the bottom.
So you're going to have partial views.
Another way that you get partial views is from occlusions.
Partly it's just by having a camera looking from one angle,
but also when you get more cluttered scenes,
you'll have occlusions.
Something will block your view of an object.
And I think the last big one is-- it's a type of noise,
maybe, but the outliers are-- let's define them
as spurious random points added to the image
in arbitrary locations.
A reasonable model, I think, of this
would be just choose uniformly over the viewing window points
at random.
If you can be robust to that kind of outliers,
that's a first order sort of robustness.
More interesting outliers are where you have other objects.
For instance, maybe you have a mustard bottle,
but you have a ketchup bottle nearby,
and it's kind of got some of the same shapes,
but clearly your perception system
should be able to disambiguate them.
But maybe these kind of algorithms
might get pulled towards the ketchup bottle
and never break free if they're similar enough.
So those outliers can be pretty complicated.
I think there's at least one more type
that you have to worry about with real cameras, which
are dropouts.
You remember the picture I showed
of some of the real cameras?
Yeah, like this.
This is what real things look like.
You'll just have no returns from the side or shiny parts
of the images.
So we want to be robust to that.
But given this basic algorithm, I
guess I got ahead of myself a little bit.
This is a very powerful basic algorithm.
This is just the ICP, and this is the Stanford bunny,
which you basically-- if you were ever to write an ICP
paper, it seems you must use-- a condition for acceptance
is that you ran your system on the Stanford bunny data set.
And you will do this on your problem set,
so you can join the ranks.
That bunny shows up everywhere.
But this is ICP in actions.
If you remember the dish loading robot from Toyota Research
Institute, did you see what happened there?
So there are two perceptions at work in that video.
Let me show it again.
There's an initial one that's actually using mostly
deep learning to try to find where the mug is in the sink
roughly.
But then when it gets close, you see this little realignment?
That was an ICP-based algorithm that
was using the local camera on the hand,
comparing it to the expected mug,
and dialing it in and going in for the grab.
And that's a pretty common pipeline.
That was it again right there.
Right there.
A little refinement and then go.
Can the camera see it that close?
Yeah, right here you can see it.
Once it gets too close, it becomes blind.
Right here.
Right there it can still see it, yeah.
You're right.
They do have minimum depth.
And it gets blind pretty quick.
And let me give you one more sort
of high-level motivation for the ICP class of algorithms.
This is actually when deep learning
started approaching some of these perception problems.
And everybody was trying to train their first deep networks
to try to estimate the pose of objects, which
is an extremely powerful pipeline now.
But the first versions of these algorithms
all required you to label the ground truth
pose in real data sets.
So this was a tool that was very useful for--
and still is useful.
We would take real data in the lab.
That's the messy lab upstairs.
And we had a model of the drill.
And we would just have a user interface,
which after collecting a video stream of data,
would just click-- you'd click two or three times
in the interface.
Let me stop that.
And you click two or three times just
to give ICP an initial guess.
It would fit the point cloud into this really noisy point
cloud, this big complicated one.
And then all of the images that you
had from all the different interactions
were suddenly perfectly labeled, or labeled by ICP.
And then you use that to train a higher level perception system.
Yes?
In the dishwasher example, do you have models of the cups?
In that case, yes.
So in the dishwasher example, we had a model of the cup,
the plates, the spoons.
In fact, that's why we chose dish loading,
was because you can sort of imagine going into a restaurant
and having a finite number of things.
It's a pretty good case for the known model assumption.
And we tried to take that as far as possible.
And then anything we didn't have a model for,
that we couldn't register to one of the known models,
we'd throw in the trash.
Yeah.
Every once in a while, we'd throw something important
in the trash.
OK.
So partial views, I think-- partial views,
it makes sense to do scene to model correspondences.
For outliers-- I'm sorry, did I say that right?
You'd like everything in the scene
to correspond to at least one model.
But for outliers, you'd like the opposite.
And at some point, we have to do better
than these hard correspondences of trying
to correspond all the points to all the points.
And we need some sort of mechanism
to do something better than that.
We're going to talk about soft correspondences.
And we're going to talk about outlier robust correspondence
rejection, basically.
OK.
Is that the sun changing?
The lighting's just changed a lot.
OK.
Let's talk about soft correspondences first.
Well, let me just-- I had a couple animations here, too.
This is ICP running in the partial view case.
It can do pretty well, but it can really mess things up.
OK.
And this is what happens with a few outliers,
chosen how I did, where I just picked some random points
in the world.
And those points, even as it tries to converge,
are going to have potentially an overwhelming effect
on the convergence of the algorithm.
So that's what we're trying to fight.
OK.
The first way we're going to try to fight it
is by taking these hard correspondences
and softening them.
OK.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
So let me write the same thing we're doing here.
I used this notation right here.
I used this-- I'm going to sum over all seen points
and look into the index of my correspondence.
I'm going to write the same equation,
but I'm going to write it a little differently.
And it's going to lead to another algorithm here.
So I'll take my min over x0 in SE3.
I want to keep my x0, p0.
But now I'm going to do mj minus psi.
And I'm going to hit this up front with a correspondence
matrix, Cij.
And I'm going to sum over j and sum over i.
This is now a correspondence matrix.
And Cij is going to be 1 if i corresponds to j and 0
otherwise.
So this is just-- I'm taking my original single sum
with an index.
I'm going to write it as a double sum.
And basically, every time I sum through this,
if I wanted to get exactly the same correspondences,
I just set a lot of the terms of the sum to 0.
But out of the box, I'm going to say there's a chance
that any of the model points can correspond
to any of the seen points or any combination thereof.
That's why it's a generalization.
Now, if I wanted to impose something like every seen
point must correspond to some model point, or vice versa,
I could put a constraint on the rows or columns of this
if I wanted to.
But let's not.
Let's leave it as a slightly more general case.
This could have a row that's all 0's.
It could have a row that has multiple 1's
if there's multiple correspondences.
Is that clear?
No?
So minimizing this is actually-- since this is just
a constant-- if I use this as a constant matrix,
if someone gives me this coefficient matrix,
this is still something I can solve with SVD.
It's got more terms, but it can still
be solved in the same way.
The trick is that this has to be fixed.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
I would love to optimize c and x simultaneously
to be able to leave this as a decision variable.
But in this problem, the correspondences
are given in a slightly more general way,
and I'm still just finding x.
And the interesting case, then, the soft case--
this so far is the same as what I've written before.
I can make these soft now if I change and allow cij is just
between 0 and 1, for instance, instead of saying
it must be 0 or 1.
I'm allowed to correspond a little bit
with some of the points.
Right?
Does that make sense in the equations?
It turns out that's exactly what's
happening in one of the famous softer correspondence
approaches called CPD-- coherent point drift.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
This is just another coherent point drift CPD.
It's one of the famous alternatives, if you will,
to ICP.
But you can really just think of it as a soft version of ICP.
The CPD paper, actually, is all written
in terms of the language of probabilities
and trying to say I've got an estimator and the like.
But the math is the same.
You're still-- there's a probabilistic interpretation
of what I'm writing, but it's just a Gaussian,
and the math is the same.
So in the CPD paper, basically, they just
say on each iteration of the algorithm,
I'm going to still initial guess x hat o.
And then I'm going to set cij to be basically
like a soft version of the distance,
like a Gaussian kernel around the points.
Right?
I'm going to take one of my points
here and score the-- if I just have one dimension here.
If this is my scene point here and my model point is here,
then I'm just going to score in some Gaussian kernel
the distance from the points.
So there's a normalization term.
And there's some parameters of that Gaussian,
but roughly it's the distance we know.
That's our estimated distance, right?
Over some variance here.
And I'm just going to use this as my distance function,
my correspondence function.
And there's a beautiful Bayesian interpretation of that,
but you can think of it just as a distance function that's
giving you these correspondences.
And then on step two, you solve SPD, and then you repeat.
The word on the street is that this is much more robust than--
it tends to be more expensive because you're
summing over a quadratic number of points
instead of a linear number of points.
And so some people actually choose
not to use the algorithm because of that quadratic cost.
When point clouds get big, that can be expensive.
But it tends to be-- just the word on the street
is it's more robust.
I think I have the snapshot of the Stanford bunny from the--
oh, this is the CPD one.
But this is roughly what you see in every paper.
I could have put CPD on the bottom,
and it would have been a similar picture where
you see the Stanford bunny, and you see it
with some noise and stuff in it.
And then you see my algorithm is better than their algorithm.
I thought I had the CPD one in here, too.
Hey, here's CPD.
You see they corrupted it with Gaussian noise.
It's all good.
OK?
But in practice, people do like CPD apart from its speed.
Yes?
In the SYNC robot--
Yes.
--is that ICP because of the quadratic [INAUDIBLE]??
That's a good question.
So the ICP in the SYNC-- why did we use ICP and not
CPD in the original one?
There are many variants of ICP also,
and sometimes more mature implementations.
I think probably if that had been
a pain point in our pipeline, we would have explored CPD.
But I think the off-the-shelf ICP implementations
were good enough for that job, and we worried more about--
yeah, it was about the computational cost.
In fact, because ICP is local--
I can tell you specifically-- because ICP is a local
algorithm, it can run into minima.
We would actually take a handful of initial guesses
for the pose of the mug, given our original perception system,
and we would be in parallel, run multiple versions of ICP,
and take the one that fit the best.
Go, and we optimized that pipeline,
maybe before we fully thought about whether we should use a CPD
or not.
Yeah.
We did explore, actually, a CPD-like version, too,
and I think that was also viable.
Yes?
What did it address [INAUDIBLE]??
In this algorithm?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yep.
So we still need the initial guess
to come up with some initial correspondences.
The notion of distance, which sets my initial correspondences--
before, we were just using it to down-select which thing
to correspond with at all.
Now we're setting the soft correspondence with it.
But it should not be x hat?
I should use x hat in this.
Yes.
Thank you.
And soft [INAUDIBLE]
I'd like one of those to be j.
I wrote that whole term too quickly, clearly.
Thank you.
And this is also a function of i and j.
I think that's right.
Good catch.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
To CPD?
I think I would guess that there's
somebody who's put RGB into CPD.
But I don't see any reason why you wouldn't.
I just wouldn't think that any Euclidean distance in RGB space
is going to be only good very locally.
People do it for ICP also.
There's an RGB version of ICP, where
you put your distance across the RGB values in addition
to the xyz values.
I've always thought it was a little weird.
There's things you can do that use descriptors, more
general descriptors, to do the point matching and stuff
like this.
And that makes more sense to me than RGB.
Great.
OK, so this tends to be-- so how does this handle outliers,
for instance?
Compared to the ICP algorithm, what
is this doing with outliers?
If I had the picture I drew initially,
where I had a perfect point cloud here with two points way
over here, what happens?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Exactly, right?
So this one, unlike the original one, which is even
at convergence is getting pulled by those outliers,
depending on which direction you put your correspondences,
this one is effectively ignoring points
that are a long distance away.
So it handles outliers in a soft way.
It also means that if you're too far away in your initial guess,
you have no hope of converging.
But this is intentionally introducing
some notion of locality in our distance function,
which is good.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
These days, you use deep learning
to get an initial guess.
And then maybe you use ICP, or there's
even deep versions of the refinement
that can work very well.
But I think that's a very natural pipeline.
Use a data-driven thing to take an initial shot,
and then refine it with ICP.
There are versions of this that we will cover--
I'll mention, at least, at the end, in our last variance--
that try to solve the global point correspondence problem.
And they don't work great.
There are some algorithms that will
solve a global optimal problem, but it will take, potentially,
to the age of the universe to solve.
And there are other ones that are close to global,
but in practice, people don't consider
global point correspondence in noisy point clouds
to be a solved problem.
There's two important versions to think about
when you're thinking about this initial guess.
How do you think about this initial guess?
If you have a point cloud that looks like this--
it's a bunny, but it's a little furry--
then, actually, it's not too hard to get an initial guess.
It's not too hard to solve ICP.
If you're in this setting, for instance,
where there is a drill in there, for sure,
but there's also every other tool and a bunch of, probably,
student lunch or something like this.
There's all kinds of other stuff in the point cloud,
and you have to find the needle in the haystack.
That's a much harder problem for initializing ICP,
and we don't have strong point registration algorithms that
will solve that global problem.
In fact, when we did this project to try to just label,
we figured, who cares if it's slow?
Let's take a global point correspondence algorithm
to just generate the labels.
It's offline.
We'll just generate a big data set, no big deal.
But we couldn't get a global point correspondence method
to be robust enough to do the job.
So it required having a human click.
But those are two very different cases.
It would be the needle in the haystack versus a fuzzy bunny.
So this is a soft version of rejecting outliers.
But let's try to work-- let's think about how
we could work a little bit more towards the rigorous sort
of outlier rejection case.
The problem with this is that I still
had to come up with that kernel function.
I chose some parameters of a Gaussian,
which was sort of arbitrary.
Nothing about my data told me really
what those coefficients should be.
I picked some kernel.
I tried it.
I maybe tweaked the knobs until I got
something I was happy with.
But really, if I could solve this jointly,
saying that both c and x are decision variables,
find me the best fit among any correspondences,
that would be the dream.
That would solve the global ICP problem.
We can't do that.
But we're going to do something a little bit closer.
So let's talk about rejecting outliers.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
Basically, removing spurious correspondences.
And I think there really are two cases.
There's the easy case.
I guess I called that the fuzzy bunny.
Let's just stick with that.
That's not what I called it here,
but that's what I'll call it for today.
The fuzzy bunny case, where we have almost our model
in the data, but it's just been corrupted
by a handful of outliers.
So really, I guess maybe to make that more formal,
you could talk about the rate, the percentage of outliers
in your data set.
So if you have 1,000 points in my point cloud, and 990 of them
are bunny-like, and 10 of them are just spurious points,
then that's sort of an easier setting.
And then there's the, I've got a drill
in that 100 of my points are associated with the drill,
but there's another 900 associated
with other things that are interesting.
That would be the hard case.
The easy case, there's a bunch of heuristics
that I should acknowledge, but I don't want to dwell on.
You can imagine heuristics, which
are-- and you could sort of call this CPD approach heuristic.
Or you could just say, let's say, I'll truncate distances.
If I have my ICP loop, and any distance that's greater than 5,
I'll just put a threshold on distance, for instance.
I'll just remove those from the correspondence list,
and that's fine.
Right?
Other thresholds that sometimes people will put in,
they'll say, I'm going to look for 100 best correspondences.
I'll just put an upper limit on the number of correspondences
to consider, and I can just put in sort of a threshold on that.
And there's a bunch of algorithms like that,
which are useful.
The hard case has more interesting algorithms,
in my opinion.
And I'll list a few.
So one of them-- actually, David, you said RANSAC last time.
Right?
RANSAC is random sample consensus.
We're going to ask you to play with that one on the homework,
because it's a pretty simple algorithm to understand.
In a few words, it is, I'm going to take my 1,000 points
in my point cloud, and I'll try to pick 100 of them at random,
and start using ICP from those 100.
And maybe I can combine it with a few of these thresholds
on distance, or whatever, to bring in other point clouds
that are fitting.
But then I'll stop, and I'll pick a different 100
initial point clouds.
And I'll do that a bunch of times.
And when I've happened to pick-- if I do that enough times,
then I will hopefully, luckily pick
some subset of the point cloud where those initial subset
gives me a good initial guess, and I can go from there.
So it optimizes on random subsets, roughly.
I'd say initialize with random subsets.
[WRITING]
RANSAC is useful more generally in ML kind of problems
and the like.
I hope the problem set will step you through that,
and you'll get a basic understanding of that.
I want to spend my time here talking about one
that I think is much more clever.
It leverages some of the geometry
in the problem, which is using pairwise distances.
OK, what are pairwise distances, and why is that a useful idea?
So here's an observation.
You remember how I said that the relative distances
between points depends on the rotation?
The relative positions between points
depends on the position, but not the translation.
We use this trick.
I have a bunch of points on my point cloud.
Then the relative positions, this vector here,
I take any two points, right?
If I do P of, let's say, mi, I'll
just do m2 versus m1 in some frame,
this depends on the rotation, but not translation.
That's what we used to justify-- that's
how we designed, actually, our SVD algorithm,
because we said we actually only have to worry about rotations.
Because that vector, if I slide this thing around on the board,
that relative position is invariant to translation.
OK, the pairwise distance-- this is the pairwise distance.
--is invariant to rotations and translations.
OK, so if I put this object in some completely different
configuration here, the distances between these points
here is the same, even though it's
been under any rigid transform.
If I just look at the length of the pairs, does that make sense?
So if I were to go through my original model
and compute all possible pairwise distances,
and now I go through my scene and I
compute all possible pairwise distances,
if my scene has a point whose pairwise distance isn't
in the model up to some noise, then one of those two points
had better be an outlier.
Did I say that well enough?
Right?
If the scene-- I'll write it like this-- s1, s2 distance
is not a pairwise distance in the model,
then 1 or 2 is an outlier.
Now that's a little bit weird, OK?
Because-- so I think that that analogy is perfect
if I take an initial point cloud, if I have my model,
and I think the real data is just
a perfect translation of that, and then
some extra things thrown in.
The mustard bottle, right?
In practice, I made some point cloud representation
of my mustard bottle once, and I've
got a different set of points that
are all on the surface of the mustard bottle later.
So you have to put some margins on this.
You can't say that with exact equality
these distances have to match.
But in practice, there's a distribution
of expected pairwise distances that
represent your object, which you can look for in the data
without having solved any pose estimation problem.
If you can find a clump of points in your data,
then you can actually reject a lot of outliers.
So there's a nice algorithm called Teaser,
which is from an MIT group.
Luca Carlone and Hank was the lead author.
Teaser actually had a bunch of different components of it,
but one of the pieces that I'm highlighting here
is this outlier rejection step.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
Hank wrote a bunch of papers, and I'm sure that the piece--
I think he had a different name for every piece
of the algorithm, so there's a better name for just this piece,
but it's all under the Teaser umbrella.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
OK, so you're worried about reflections.
So that's true.
If you had a perfectly mirrored object,
you wouldn't be able to distinguish it,
I think, with the pairwise distance computation.
I completely agree.
I think that's-- I mean, in practice,
if I accidentally found the mirrored mustard,
I guess maybe that's not the biggest problem.
But you're right.
It's exacerbated, I think, in 2D on the board.
It looks like the mirror operation is very natural.
But if you think about objects of interest
going through any rigid transformation,
the case you're worried about, I think,
would be a reflection, where you're really
going through some axis.
And you're right, this would not distinguish that.
But at the very least, it could reject a lot of outliers,
maybe not all.
Good question.
So this Teaser algorithm by Hank and Luca
made a really clever idea.
They said, we've got this cluster of-- there's
some distribution of possible pairwise distances.
And they said, make a graph where the edges--
I'm going to put the picture up that'll help.
You make a graph connecting all the matching pairwise
distances.
And that actually, if you can find the maximal clique
in the graph, that is likely your object
of interest in the data.
So let me show you the picture that I
used to think about this algorithm.
So there's maximum clique in correspondence graphs.
And this is actually-- they showed it
in very complicated settings, big point clouds and the like.
I was like, Hank, just explain this to me.
I have a triangle.
It has the sides 3, 4, and 5.
Let's just work out that case first.
And I liked his answer so much that it's not in the notes.
So hopefully, this will help you guys too.
So this is the setting.
I have my same model blue and salmon scene.
And the setting I was worried about
was what if I have the object of interest, my model, my blue,
if it appears in the scene perfectly--
and a bit like what your reflections question here--
if it appears in the scene perfectly,
but there's enough similar distances that
appeared also in the scene.
So I said, imagine you have the exact triangle, the 3, 4, 5
triangle, but you also had a prism or a pyramid
there that had 3, 4, 4, 4, 3.
Right?
You see what I was trying to do?
Was make a lot of similar distances.
The distance 4 shows in my data.
The distance 4 shows more on the object on the right
than on the left, even though the left is the right answer,
correct answer.
Similarly, the number 3 shows up a lot on the right.
By counting, there's more correspondence,
pairwise distance matches on the right.
But the correct answer is on the left.
The way their algorithm works is like this.
So we're going to make a node here.
If A in the model, point A here, corresponds to A over there.
If A corresponds to B over here.
Each of these circles, each of these nodes in the graph
is one possible correspondence from model to scene.
An edge in the graph happens if the pairwise distances match.
Yes?
So if A to A and B to B here is the same distance,
then I'll put an edge in the graph.
Otherwise, I won't put an edge in the graph.
OK, so that gives you this graph structure
of possible pairwise distance correspondences.
And the claim in their paper was that the maximum clique is
likely the object of interest.
And indeed, this object here on the left
has a bigger clique of 3 than any of the pairwise comparisons
on the right.
So they defeated my counter example and won me over.
That's a very clever idea, isn't it?
That you can use this invariance without even
knowing the pose of your object at all,
the rotation nor the translation.
You can compute this quantity.
And you can look for the statistics of your object
roughly in the data.
I think it gets a lot harder when you have noise in the data
and you expect those to be almost pairwise distances.
Then you'll have probably many more edges in your graph.
And it's not as clear what the maximal clique looks like.
But it's a very clever idea.
Questions about that?
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes, that's a great question.
So first of all, never do that with a robot.
I'm kidding.
So I actually think this is a very, very good question.
So Tom's asking, he says, what if my object is long and flat?
And I'm looking at it like this.
First of all, especially on your iPad,
you're going to get no returns on the side.
So that's just dead in the water probably.
But even, I would say, long, flat objects on tables
are a good example of how the ICP objective that we've
been writing all day is actually probably not
the right objective.
Because I could get a lot of good matches
in terms of distance, even if this is shifted by a lot.
If I'm looking at this object on the table,
I'm probably weighting the edges a lot.
Those are where all the information is.
But the density of points I'm going to get
is mostly on the top.
So my ICP objective, I think, is deficient in that case.
And you shouldn't think of this as definitely
the right objective.
That's the point I always try to make at the end,
is that it's not clear that ICP is the right objective.
And I think long, flat objects on tables, or books on tables,
is a great-- or iPads on tables is a great example of that.
OK, people understand the pairwise distance?
I mean, roughly understand?
I think you should think through that example.
It's in the notes, obviously.
And it's worth thinking through.
That one was very impressive to me.
OK.
OK, last version that I'll try to do today here,
for being robust, is trying to solve jointly
for the correspondences and the poses.
So let's try to take the slightly more interesting
version of the algorithm.
And I'm going to do that first with just a small modification
of the original algorithm.
I'll do the point-to-plane ICP.
It's going to be a window into, I think, a bigger idea here.
So the idea here is I want my model
is a triangle mesh, a triangular mesh,
instead of a bunch of points.
And I'm going to do my example here just in 2D.
OK, so let's just say I have my model looks like this,
whatever.
OK.
Rather than represent the model only as a series of points,
I'm going to model my-- in 2D, I'm
going to model it as a line segment.
These line segments are the models.
And I want to correspond points in the scene,
not necessarily just to the vertices,
but to the closest point on the face.
In 3D, this is point-to-plane.
Is that clear?
I'd like to measure not the distance from point to point,
but the distance from point to plane
and allow it to match anywhere on the plane.
OK, so how would I write this?
How do I represent these meshes, these triangular meshes?
OK.
So typically, you have a list of vertices
plus a list of faces, which are-- these are points in x, y,
z.
And these are vertex indices, i, j, k.
So this would have vertices-- I don't know-- 1, negative 1.
It's going to have another one, 1, 2.
It's going to have all these vertices listed.
And then it's going to have a face saying that vertex 1
and vertex 2 are connected.
In 3D, it would have three numbers.
But in 2D, it's got two numbers.
It's got another one that says vertex 2 and vertex 3
are connected.
This is my list of faces.
This is a perfectly reasonable on-disk--
you'll find CAD formats that are basically just this.
OBJs are basically just this.
OK, so I would like to now take a scene point
and somehow correspond it to this face.
So I want to correspond to the face
and then have the math be the closest distance
point to plane.
There's a bunch of different ways to do that.
You probably know the equation of the distance
between a point and a plane.
You can absolutely write that into your algorithm
and work from there.
I'm going to show you an optimization version of it,
which I like a little better.
So let's try this.
Before I even write the full optimization,
I'll make one point here.
Instead of saying that my point is-- I
could compute the point to plane, the normal distance.
I can write this equation for the point to plane distance.
But let me instead say I'm going to correspond this point,
this red point, with an equation that
describes all possible points on that line segment.
So let me say that carefully.
If a point on a face is the sum over alpha i of the vertices--
I've got a notation that I liked here--
bi in face f, subject to all of my alpha i's
being greater than 0 and the sum of my alpha i's equaling 1,
then a perfectly good way to describe
all points in this set, in this vertex face representation,
would be as a linear combination of the points on the vertex
that sums to 1.
That's a way to parameterize the set based on the boundary.
Did I write that clearly enough?
So if alpha is 0, it might be all on this point.
If alpha 1 is 1 and the rest are 0's,
it might be at this point.
If alpha 2 is 1 and the rest are 0's,
And if I go between them, I'll get alpha 0.5, 0.5,
somewhere in the middle.
That's a standard sort of parameterization
of any convex set.
And it works for a plane, for sure.
OK, so now let's try to write minimize
over x0 in SE3.
Going to minimize over my scene points.
This time I'm going to use the x transform the other way.
So I'm going to modify my scene points into my model
coordinates so that I can write sum over i alpha ij p vertex j
in face i squared.
OK, there's one big point you have to get here.
The details are less important to me.
The big point here is that-- so if you contrast this
to the CPD, where I had a coefficient
matrix off to the front, which was a hard optimization
because I was multiplying c times my other decision
variables.
This is a clever trick where this term on the inside
is linear in these decision variables,
and it's also linear in these decision variables.
So I'm optimizing over this, and I'm optimizing over alpha.
That's very nice.
It looks very nice.
I have to still say alpha ij for all ij alpha ij greater than 0
and sum of alpha ij over-- which one did I do it over?
Over i over the face equals 1.
That's something to work with.
Now, remember that this optimization,
if I didn't have these constraints,
this optimization still has a solution via SPD.
Unfortunately, once I put these constraints in, it does not.
So we have to open up an optimization playbook
that I've only given a few tools towards, but not
the full playbook.
But this is another form of optimization,
a more complicated form of optimization
that you can use to try to solve this harder joint problem.
OK.
It turns out-- so remember, there's also
these hard constraints hiding in here.
The RR transpose equals identity,
and the determinant of R equals positive 1.
It turns out that I don't know how
to solve this big problem well.
But if you're willing to relax this constraint to a softer
version of this constraint, then we
have nice solutions for this.
And this is actually the crux of a lot of the point cloud
algorithms that are trying to use heavy optimization
to solve this kind of problem.
And the picture, actually, I think, is very intuitive.
OK.
You remember this picture, which is my ICP objective?
The quadratic bowl is a beautiful object
for optimization, and it's still present here.
This is still a quadratic objective.
The red circle is a horrible object for optimization.
It just happened that we had a special case
that we could solve with SVD.
If I start adding other constraints on top of this
that might look like lines through this or something
else, then I don't have a solution with SVD.
The things we know how to do with optimization
are typically about convex sets.
So the standard relaxation that people
do for this sort of a constraint in the 2D case
is precisely you're changing the circle to a disk.
OK.
I'm only intending to give you the fringe.
I've got a few furrowed brows.
But the geometry of this is that the relaxation
of this hard optimization problem
turns that circle constraint into a disk.
And so when you hear people talking
about semi-definite programming relaxations of point cloud
algorithms, that's what's happening.
It's happening in high dimensions.
It's hard to think about.
But it's just turning the circle into a disk.
And I think if you're willing to say--
so remember what happened before is
I have some rotation matrices that describe my data as well
as possible.
In the simple case, they ended up just landing--
in the noise-free case, they landed directly on the circle.
OK.
With noise, they might move away from the circle a little bit.
The circle pulls them back.
If you change the circle into a disk,
then there's one type of noise you reject very well.
If you're going outside the disk,
then your relaxation is tight.
If you're inside the disk, you're
going to possibly get things wrong.
You're going to come up with rotation matrices that are not
proper rotation matrices.
The orthonormal vectors are a little too short, roughly.
OK.
So I know I haven't equipped everybody with that.
But I wanted to just make those connections.
That this picture I gave you before,
which I hope you did understand when it first came up,
actually is the lens by which you
can look at much more complicated versions
of the algorithm, where you can do things like attempt
to find correspondences at the same time as poses.
And they typically fall under the heading
of semi-definite programming type relaxations.
OK.
Of point cloud-- of point registration algorithms.
And the theory will say that they're
tight in some settings.
And that's typically the noise-free setting.
They're tight.
OK.
And when you get noise, they become loose.
So I think like 10% of you are happy with me for that.
Maybe in a couple years, you'll be like,
oh, it was worth him saying that.
But OK.
Good.
I said that.
All right.
So I think we did a pretty good job with our agenda.
Yeah?
So you guys know what ICP is?
Have some intuition about when it works, when it doesn't?
Some of the biggest sources of noise in our point clouds--
dropouts, partial views, outliers, and then
a little bit of noise.
But that's, I think, a small factor.
Hopefully, soft correspondences landed.
That was a pretty smooth transition, I guess.
And then there was a bunch of different algorithms.
The pairwise distance was a good one.
And this SDP relaxation is another powerful one.
OK.
I'll see you next time.
Good job.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
(crowd murmuring)
[BLANK_AUDIO]