Today we're going to start talking about reinforcement learning.
It's funny how the pendulum swings, but I was just saying that last year I felt bad
about waiting until lecture 18 to talk about reinforcement learning, and this year I'm
not sure if anybody cares.
And who knows what next year is going to be, right?
But I think some people are incredibly excited.
I think it's an incredibly exciting topic.
Let me try to do what I do on good days, I think, which is to bring back the last ideas
from the last lecture and kind of fade into the ideas from today.
So last time we talked about the visual motor policies, right?
For me, I think it is now clear that I want policies that-- I will no longer be happy
if my policies don't read from the cameras and make decisions at high rate.
I think we've seen something good happen there, and we should continue to try to do that.
So the way that looks in our world here is maybe I have the manipulation station here.
It has a bunch of output ports.
It has the EWA state, the WSG state, but it also has some cameras.
And then we put that broadly into a visual motor policy here.
And that's what's going to send ultimately back into my EWA commands input port, my WSG
command input port.
The idea is we want to build controllers that can go from pixels all the way to-- well,
these positions, maybe not torques.
That would be crazy.
There's reasons why you might want to do torques, but in a lot of our cases, positions are going
to be good.
And we talked about the various ways you could think about what's inside this box, including
maybe everything we've done in class so far sort of fits inside this box.
But the huge promise of trying to get these with tools that are more based on machine
learning was-- the huge promise-- let me just write as I say it-- of ML in here is that
maybe I don't have to do anything in the middle of that that assumes a state representation.
For me, that's the biggest deal is using learned state representations.
That I don't know how to write the state of the peanut butter on the toast.
So with a lot of the classical tools, I would have to impose some representation of what's
happening in the world in the middle of this.
And maybe with some of the tools we're talking about in the last lecture and in these upcoming
lectures, I don't want to do that.
I don't have to do that.
So we could say that, like I said, everything we've done in class so far where I maybe have
a state estimator and a motion planner and a low-level controller, that could all be
inside.
I would call that a visual motor policy.
But I only would be happy calling it a visual motor policy if it was really making decisions
based on that camera at high rate.
Last time we said a simple way to start thinking about what visual motor policies can do was
via behavior cloning, where we really just took in, for instance, the EWA state and the
cameras, WSG and the cameras.
And we put it into a big neural net.
And we output the EWA command from that.
And we talked about the sort of characteristic architecture of that, as you maybe have an
enormous network to deal with the camera input, because it's a very complicated input.
And maybe pre-training on image net makes sense.
And for all the reasons, we might have an architecture that has a big network to deal
with the images, but then you bring in your EWA state, your WSG state, where you have
sensors on them directly.
You shouldn't have to only get that from cameras.
Those are easy sensors to add in.
And then maybe a relatively smaller policy.
In BC, we would collect an output of this directly.
In human demonstrations, let's say.
And so if we really just have a bunch of samples of the data here and the data here, then I
have a standard supervised learning problem where I just want to find a function, or potentially
a recurrent network, if I want to think of it as a sequence.
I want to find a function that predicts the EWA command given the inputs that I'm seeing.
That was last time.
And I think there's a lot of promise in that.
We're seeing some of the best demos in the manipulation world today are using that pipeline.
But we also have-- these are some of the ones from our group.
But we also know that there are limitations to that.
So it's a big open question about how far that takes us in the grand scheme of things.
How much is imitation learning going to be part of the final answer?
That's maybe one question.
And maybe a slightly different question is, do we only need behavior cloning to get to
the broad manipulation systems that we are looking for?
And maybe if we get cool enough haptic interfaces, then all this stuff starts to work.
We don't know.
OK, so that was the backdrop.
Now enter reinforcement learning.
How does reinforcement learning compare to that?
So this was a large requirement to say the burden of these demos, of doing a great behavior
cloning demo, starts with collecting lots of human data, collected on the day of your
demonstration, collected with experts.
This is a high cost.
Just like in supervised learning, there was a high cost initially of having somebody label
every pixel in your data set.
The cost of labeling or the cost of demonstrating becomes very high.
And if we can't generalize broadly beyond our demonstrations, then there's limits to
how valuable that can be.
So a harder version, but a super interesting version, is to try to describe what we want
out of the system, not with specific input/output pairs, but by saying just what we want the
robot to do over the long term.
And that's what reinforcement learning is doing.
In fact, that picture up there is the classic picture you always see in RL.
You see-- they don't always call it the plant, but I'm going to keep calling it the plant.
Maybe it's the world or the environment.
So my visual motor policy is my policy.
My manipulation station is my plant.
I have my observations coming out here.
I like to call observations y.
You could call them o if you're more CS inclined maybe, but these are my observations.
Over here is u for me, which is actions.
And we also have one other thing involved, which is a reward, r, which you'd like r to
be some function.
This is the-- I'm going to even say it clearly.
This is the one step reward function.
It's a scalar function of the current observations and the current actions.
So a richer way to describe what we want the robot to do would be to write it as an optimization
problem.
Let's say I have some policy.
We'll call it pi.
And maybe it's got parameters theta, the weights and biases of my neural network, for instance.
Then the optimization problem I want to think about is how do I maximize over my policy
parameters theta the sum of the long term rewards, given that those rewards were generated
by interacting with the plant.
So this is not maybe what you'll always see in-- the way you'll always see in RL, but
I'm going to write it this way because I think it's consistent.
So we're going to define yn to be my output function of my dynamical system that I've
defined carefully.
And xn plus 1 is just the forward dynamics of that system.
And I have to somehow specify the initial conditions to start that up.
So if I was actually going to implement this in Drake, for instance, then I have some--
potentially a whole diagram.
It has a context which has its state described.
It has its forward dynamics that the simulator knows how to evolve.
It has its output functions.
The diagram has outputs that are pulled from system outputs that evaluates things like
the image or the state of the EWA.
And subject to this dynamical system generating y's and u's that are consistent, I want to
maximize the long term reward.
I think I did it.
I was worried that I would get here and I'd write min.
And I was going to write cost over here.
It's my habit.
But I didn't change u and y, but I did change to r.
So that's a little compromise.
As I've written it here, this is not just an RL problem.
This is an optimal control problem, broadly.
And we haven't spent the many lectures it takes to build up the total toolbox of optimal
control here.
I could still, I think, give you some useful insights about RL today.
So the other class I teach, underactuated, we spent a lot of time thinking about the
optimal control problem more broadly and all the ways to think about using this dynamical
system to solve these problems.
But long before RL existed, there was optimal control.
And I would say reinforcement learning is a subset of optimal control, which has a particular
characteristic, particular emphasis.
Can I say RL is a subset of optimal control?
I mean, some people might want to write it that way.
Some people might write it-- I'm just going to say that.
I'm going to stick with that.
And it puts particular emphasis on a few things.
In the library of optimal control tools, the RL methods emphasize, first of all, black
box optimization.
So unlike most tools in optimal control, the RL algorithms, I think people know, are
not going to assume necessarily that we know f, the function f, or the function g, or even
the function r, only that we can get samples from it.
So we don't need to know the structure or the governing equations.
I just need a simulator that will tell me the output, or a real robot that will tell
me the output.
And the other thing that it emphasizes strongly, partly because it wants to connect to the
real world and to data, is the stochastic aspects, stochasticity.
So stochastic optimal control would be if I wanted to maximize over theta, for instance,
the expected value of my rewards.
And I think there's lots of ways I could discount this, or do average rewards and stuff.
I'm just going to keep it at the high level for now.
And it's interesting to think, OK, so this-- I haven't written anything that has probabilities
yet.
So here are my equations.
So my output functions can take random variables.
And my dynamics functions can take random variables.
And we've already done this a little bit, actually.
This is also a random variable.
And I can start my initial conditions, in general, from some probability distribution.
And once I pull-- I mean, any one of these would be enough.
Once I make the initial conditions come out of a random variable, then suddenly the future
state is a random variable, and the future observations are a random variable.
And it makes sense, then, the reward is not a random variable.
And if I want to maximize a scale or function of a random variable, I need to take some
measure of that random variable.
And the most common one for lots of important reasons is to take an expected value.
So this is, I think, the way to connect the modeling that we-- oh, yeah, please.
Yes.
Oh, no, it's not.
It's just too many symbols coming out of the typewriter.
Yep, thank you.
Yeah.
So this is, I think, a very nice match to the modeling power we've been talking about
in Drake's systems framework, for instance, and the way we've been writing simulations,
and the way you would generate this.
There's one thing that is missing, actually.
There's another way to add randomness besides just the initial conditions and
sort of noise.
That's a really rich specification.
Even if I were to restrict myself to Gaussian noise coming in, once I have a
nonlinear f, I can do anything.
Sorry about that.
How many of you here are professors?
We're from MIT.
They can't hear you on the lecture capture.
Check on your mic.
Thank you very much.
We stopped using that.
We just record ourselves.
I apologize.
OK, cool.
Thank you.
Yep.
So even if this is just Gaussian random variables, since I'm multiplying it by an
arbitrary f, I can do really rich things with that.
But there's one thing that I think is missing in that standard math.
Anybody know the thing I think is missing?
We'll see it in the code in just a minute.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK, there's definitely a reward.
That's in here.
Oh, OK.
You might say the thing that I'm missing, constraints.
But you can make reward up-- in reinforcement learning or any of the
unconstrained optimization, you would take the constraints you might have in a
normal optimization, and you would shove them up into the objective as a
penalty function.
So maybe that's-- yeah.
But I would tuck that inside here.
But as rich as I let R be, as rich as I let G be, f, and this probability
distribution, there's still something that this model of the world doesn't
quite capture.
Yeah.
Unknown model.
I mean, depending on how rich your unknown model is, that could fit-- this
is a pretty rich specification, right?
The policy can be stochastic.
That's true.
I didn't actually even write the-- I should have written the policy.
I missed my u of n is policy of y of n.
And this could be-- that was an omission, not a philosophical miss.
You're totally right.
You called me on it.
And this could be stochastic or deterministic.
You're totally right.
But that one I just forgot to write.
There's a more fundamental thing that this doesn't capture.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
It's discrete.
But I would say if I make my discrete to continuous math,
I could make discrete step small enough that it can capture most--
that's not the fundamental one I'm missing.
People do it in RL all the time.
But we didn't do it enough, I think, in classical control.
[INAUDIBLE]
A particular type of randomization, I think,
has happened in RL that didn't happen in optimal control.
If I made a random number of objects appear in my world,
then even the definition of x is different.
The number of state variables is different.
And so I don't quite know how to write that here.
There's a distribution over the size of x.
And that kind of breaks my otherwise beautiful state-space view
of the world.
You can still accommodate that in the tools we'll build today.
But this is almost perfect.
But there is something that it's missing, which is that I really
could have, in random draws of my simulator,
a completely different state, a completely different number
of objects in the world.
That's the only thing I find unsatisfying now
about writing it that way.
But you can't always make your y fixed.
You might have to alter the rate.
I think it must-- apart from clever network parameterizations
and stuff like this, but I do want y to be roughly fixed.
I think it's x that gets bigger or smaller.
If y is a camera, if y is my camera input and my robot data,
then that doesn't change, even if I have different numbers of objects
in the scene.
But x would be a different size.
So the generating equation--
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
OK, so maybe you say that this-- if I was thinking of this
as a general data structure, then everything's fine.
If I'm thinking about this as a vector space and a difference
equation on a vector space, then it's impoverished.
But if this is like a dictionary in Python, then I'm good again.
And that's maybe a good way to think about it.
I need to go from my comfortable vector space world
to a dictionary in Python world.
And that kind of messes with me.
But it's important.
It's an important change.
OK, so let's just take a second to appreciate
that this is harder than BC.
So behavior cloning is here.
I collected directly input/output data.
But this is a harder problem than BC for a subtle reason.
Because BC can do sequence learning.
If I'm going to train a LSTM policy for my cloning,
then that's actually got some temporal components to it too.
But RL is harder than BC.
This is supervised.
[TYPING]
Learning.
Even possibly sequence learning.
[TYPING]
But BC doesn't have to think at all.
By having the data before and after my policy curated for me,
it doesn't have to think at all about all the stuff that
happens inside my plant.
It just completely avoids the plant.
And a lot of messy stuff can happen in the plant.
Inside our manipulation station, we have the physics engine.
We have the geometry engine.
We have the contact.
We have the renderer.
That's a lot of messy stuff that our algorithm's
going to have to go through now.
And BC just skips all that.
The classic way that people would talk about RL
being harder than supervised learning
is the delayed reward problem.
That you have long-term consequences of your actions.
The sequence learning has some of that.
[TYPING]
So I de-emphasized that here.
But there's another.
The fact that my reward depends on-- even my reward,
my instantaneous reward at time 23
depends on all of the actions I've taken from time 0 to 23.
Whereas in behavior cloning, certainly
in the simple versions of behavior cloning
or feedforward network, it just depends
on the instantaneous input.
But this is such a powerful general framework,
this optimal control framework, the RL framework,
that people are-- and it's had some incredible success.
So AlphaGo, for instance.
There's just so many--
StarCraft, you name it.
There's incredible successes of RL.
And we've seen some in manipulation, too.
So the one that everybody talks about
was the initial one by OpenAI.
But now it's been recreated in a lot less time.
And it's super compelling to say the recipe
to make an advanced robot manipulation system
is you just make the simulator.
And people have simulators, where you just
write the cost function, and then you do deep RL.
And people say things like, ah, it's so nice
we don't have to do control anymore.
Control is hard, and I just don't
have to do that anymore.
But it's not completely all done.
And like I said, the pendulum swings around.
And people seem-- even though RL is incredibly powerful,
I would say this year people are a little less excited.
I'm sure next year they're going to be super excited again.
But there are shifting winds, and people are--
there's various levels of excitement in RL.
I actually-- I started--
I did my thesis in RL.
I don't know if you guys know that.
I had a little walking robot.
I couldn't afford a full piece of rubber.
So I had to cut out--
I had to use a other piece of rubber one day,
and I never had a new one.
So I just had to--
I had very humble beginnings, I guess.
This was a CD rack that was holding up my ramp.
And then so that was a-- that's just a mechanical toy that
would walk down a ramp.
And then my thesis, dating myself now,
was a robot that learned how to walk
because it was close to walking by falling down a ramp.
And I-- actually, I have a secret.
The only reason I put this in here
is because Bojan's about to throw away
my treadmill that's been sitting in the lab corner.
And I was like, I just want to show it one last time
for nostalgic reasons.
No, no, it's good.
It's good.
This is the thing.
Like, so if you're doing an RL thesis, right?
So for me, I was like writing my thesis here, right?
And there was a treadmill here.
And all day long, you just kind of hear this--
[TAPPING]
You know, it's like, oh my god, I'm going to--
every once in a while, you hear--
[TAPPING]
And then you'd hear it go--
[MAKES EXPLOSION NOISE]
You know, as it was--
the treadmill shoved it up against the wall, right?
But that was my beginnings, I guess.
And I don't use RL a lot in my--
to make robots move today.
But that's not because I don't think it's powerful.
I think it's a pretty subtle--
there's a pretty subtle reason.
And maybe we can come back to it later.
But I just don't enjoy the state of it right now in that way.
But I don't want to tune cost functions and stuff.
I'll say that more carefully as we go.
We are doing RL theory, because I think
there's some beautiful things that have happened in RL that
need to be understood more rigorously.
So the group is actually doing a lot of RL.
But just maybe when we want the robot to do something,
that's not the tool I turn to today.
Sorry, someone's-- yeah, Rob.
Can you talk a little bit about the runtime
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, yeah.
OK, good.
So I think people have the impression,
like, the open AI was massive amounts of compute.
It simulated millions of years of finger twiddling
in order to do that.
And people have gotten that down.
NVIDIA has a version now that's doing a very similar task
and dramatically less, at least, wall time.
I think a lot of compute still.
Optimal control isn't immune to that.
It depends which versions of optimal control.
So linear optical control is immune to that.
Nonlinear optimal control, there's
many different approaches, which I think RL is one of them.
And they enjoy different levels of generality,
like how many different problems you can embrace with that
and how strong is the algorithm.
So RL is all the way on the side of you
can optimize any plant and any cost function,
but it might take a long time.
And if you say, I don't want to do any,
I'll carve out a smaller set of problems
that I want to focus on, then you
can write narrower, more efficient algorithms.
And the big question, the big money question
is, where is manipulation in that space?
Is manipulation so complicated that you
have to treat it with the anything algorithm?
Or is there enough structure in the manipulation problem
that more targeted algorithms should be used?
OK, so my plan for today is to talk basically--
I don't have all of the optimal control background
that we've developed, but I could still
talk about some RL examples, including
the sort of software, how do you write these things.
And then I want to talk a little bit about RL
from the optimization perspective,
because we've been going back to optimization,
using a variety of optimization tools,
and I think we can connect to that.
And I've got as much as we have time to say about that.
Let me start by thinking a little bit about the software.
So how many people know OpenAI Gym?
It's a great thing.
So everybody agreed that there's a relatively simple requirement
to define an RL problem.
You just have to define your observations,
define your actions, define your reward.
And the community finally got behind a particular interface.
Someone agreed that these are the function names in Python
that we should all write our code behind.
That way, anybody who's writing simulators or problem instances
on one side can present this interface,
and everybody's writing RL algorithms on the other side
can act on that interface.
And the OpenAI Gym is the interface that won.
It's maybe transitioning to gymnasium.
We'll see.
OpenAI did a mic drop on it, said,
we're not going to do that anymore.
And someone else is like, that's still important.
And we'll see if the world moves to gymnasium.
But I think it's got so much momentum
that we're not going to lose it.
So the software interface to this optimal control problem
is just you have an initialization
of your gym environment.
You step.
That's my f of x.
You can reset if you need to.
You can render.
The step also actually takes the action,
and it outputs both the observations and the reward,
maybe a close.
All of those have a direct mapping
to what we've been doing all term.
So your init is just your build your simulator.
The step is just an advanced two in your simulator.
And then evaluate your observation
and evaluate your reward, for instance.
And reset might just be resetting
the context in our setting.
So everything-- this is just--
and anything, any simulator can easily present this interface.
That's the point of it.
It could be an Atari game.
It could be Go.
It could be a manipulation station.
Render might be-- is like the Meshcat publish kind of idea.
To make it easier to go from that diagram
and get it all correct, the actions and observations
and rewards, we have a thing in--
currently in manipulation repo, it's
slowly moving to main Drake, which is just the Drake gym
end, where you can hand it a simulator.
You can tell it which ports are the action ports you
care about, which ones are the observation ports, which
ones the reward port.
Or you can write a function for the reward
if you don't want to use ports.
And it'll wire that up and make that for you.
So it just makes that easy to make that interface.
And then-- so that's the OpenAI gym.
And a lot of people knew that.
But maybe I could have written it more carefully.
, So this is my step reset whatever.
And then on one side of this are the simulators, for instance,
or a real robot if you so choose.
And on the other side of this are the algorithms.
Only one simulator will be discussed today, unfortunately.
But there are other choices that are perfectly good.
On the algorithm side, similarly, I'm
just going to pick one because I don't want
to talk about all of them.
These days we mostly use stable baselines three,
which is a nice implementation from DLR, I think,
and that has a lot of the-- kind of like OMPL
had a whole list of motion planning algorithms.
Stable baselines has a nice list of reinforcement learning
algorithms.
And this one is written in PyTorch.
A surprising number of our libraries
never made the leap to PyTorch.
So it's a perfectly good implementation.
It's the one we use.
It's interesting that the algorithm that most people use
or that we'll talk about the most today is PPO.
Maybe, what did you say?
SAC.
Right, so let's distinguish.
So in terms of the algorithms in manipulation, for instance,
there tends to be a breakdown between--
if you're using simulators, then PPO is often a go-to.
SAC maybe.
But if you're using real robots that people
tend to do Q-learning kind of things,
I think really the distinction is this is-- with a simulator,
you worry less about data starvation.
You just-- you run your simulator fast enough,
and you don't curate your data carefully,
and you do online RL.
And with real robots, data is precious,
and you don't want to have to run 100 million trials,
so you do offline RL a lot more, which
is more compatible with Q-learning type approaches.
So you store every piece of data.
You reuse the data to update your policies,
even after it's not the same policy that's running.
I'll get a little bit into that distinction later.
But PPO seems to be a fairly dominant entry now.
PPO has become the default. See, I backed it up.
Reinforcement learning at OpenAI,
and just a lot of people do.
In fact, it's not just PPO.
It's like there's a particular commit
in a particular repository that has a particular set
of parameters for PPO.
And you should only use that one,
because people have done studies of saying, we took PPO.
We did huge parameter sweeps, and we
got all kinds of different answers.
And then we did git bisect on the original PPO repository.
And we found out that this is the commit
that everybody should use.
And then another paper found roughly the same thing.
So it's like the world just tried to implement exactly
the policy parameters, the optimization parameters,
from this one commit.
Don't mess with it.
You're going to spend a lot more time optimizing.
But that actually is nice.
Kind of weird way that's nice, because then you know if--
there's just one version of PPO that you should care about.
So if I wanted to slip in PPO and just be happy,
as long as I use the parameters from that one commit,
I should be good.
I should have the same performances as other people.
And stable baselines is to use that commit, for instance.
OK, so let me do a little example.
I think it helps to put the stuff in context.
So remember the box flip up.
I thought that was just such a compelling example
for force control before.
So let me just even remind you of our existing example
for that.
This is the old notebook where I'm
going to run the stiffness control version of that.
Not force-based, I'll do the stiffness control-based.
And I'll just do the version that was scripted.
So we had a virtual finger.
We programmed the remote center of compliance, if you will,
and got this just beautifully simple high-level control.
Just says move it towards the wall, start lifting it up.
The center of compliance goes here.
The box will flip up.
And it'll pull itself back down.
That was just a really nice way to flip up a box, I guess,
if your finger was a point.
OK, so I did that again in RL.
This morning I just thought I'll code the exact same environment
and I'll put it in my Drake gem and then I'll run PPO on it.
And I did.
So let's see what happens.
Restart that so I can use the same Meshcat instance.
So I'm going to just use the pre-trained model.
It doesn't take long to train this one, a few minutes.
But I'll just use the--
mostly so I don't run out of batteries here,
I'll use the pre-trained one.
OK, so it flips up the box very well.
And then it smashes its head against the side.
So I'm going to just use the pre-trained model.
And I'll just use the pre-trained model.
And then it smashes its head against the side
for the rest of time.
It'll get random resets.
OK, it flips up the box.
And then it smashes its head against the wall.
And I got to the point I was like, oh, I could tune that away.
But it kind of makes a point.
Like, it's pretty good, but it's annoying that way too, right?
So I mean, I didn't tell it to smash its head against the wall.
I'll show you the cost function.
OK, that keeps going.
All right, so yeah, I recorded it just in case.
All right, so let me just sort of step through what that looked like.
And you can ask as many questions as you like.
But so what was the network in that?
OK, first of all, maybe I should have started with the action space.
So I wanted it to have the advantage of stiffness control.
I didn't want to deprive it of stiffness control.
So the input was actually-- because if you remember,
if your finger's a point, the difference between stiffness control
and inverse dynamics is non-existent.
It was just a 1 over mass.
So I basically gave it the-- that should be export input.
Inverse dynamics desired position was the action space.
So that's like the virtual finger in the stiffness control.
The observations was direct state output.
So I'm not even doing visual motor yet.
I'm just giving it access to the true state
and asking it to learn from that.
And then I just used stable baselines default MLP policy
to go directly from state to actions.
Now, we should expect that to be enough,
because the optimal control for that problem
should be just a function of state.
I didn't have to use an RL-- I didn't have
to use a recurrent network here.
I think just a multi-layer perceptron policy feedforward
network is enough.
And if you look at the default MLP policy, which is actually--
like all the examples use the default policy.
It's kind of a weird thing in RL for control.
If people basically-- there's like maybe this one and maybe
one with 255 units in the middle.
And they almost all use these same network parameters.
And people really don't change those very much.
My instinct would be to start mucking
with the size of the network a lot,
but the people really don't.
So the default network architecture
from stable baselines is just that.
So that means the policy network has 64 hidden units.
So it has the observations, which in this case
was the state, mapped into 64 hidden units, 64 hidden units,
and to the output, the action.
The value function was basically the same size.
So PPO, I will get to it as I go into it a little bit.
PPO is actually an actor-critic algorithm.
So it has both policy parameterization and a value
function parameterization.
And then I told you that the way that you make that in the Drake
GMM is you just have-- I just have my plant.
It's a little smaller than I would have liked here, sorry.
And I have an inverse dynamics controller.
I made a super small function for my reward,
and I piped that to the reward output.
I took my state, I put that to the observations output.
And the actions were almost just directly the inverse dynamics
controller, but my inverse dynamics controller
wanted a desired state.
And I only wanted to give it a desired position,
so those little boxes just put 0 for the desired velocity.
But it's really just like, make your little diagram,
pick the input that you want as your actions,
pick the output that you want as your observations output
or a function to be the reward.
The cost function is kind of fun and interesting.
I really didn't do any-- I mean, there's
one thing I did to do cost function tuning, I would say,
which is this last line.
But I'm allergic to cost function tuning.
I don't want to do much of that.
I did it before, and I don't ever want to do it again.
It's basically the box angle.
I wrap it around because sometimes it
did play tiddlywinks with the box,
and it would do multiple spins and land upright.
So I'm OK with that.
I'll take that as a success.
So the box angle modded into pi.
And most of the cost is just saying
that I want my angle from vertical to be small.
I do think about the world in terms of cost, not reward.
And I put a minus sign when I'm handing it
to my RL algorithms.
That's just how I roll.
So I penalized angle from vertical.
I penalized box velocity.
I penalized the effort, which is the difference
between the virtual finger and the actual finger.
I penalized the finger velocity because I
don't want it to be going like that.
But it still did.
And then the 10 is the one thing I was like,
I didn't type it in the first time, and I had to put that in.
And you can see the comment, why.
So if I only had negative rewards only,
and the Drake-Jim-Env will terminate
if the simulation crashes.
It'll terminate early.
If every time step can at best be a negative reward,
then it wanted to crash the simulator.
It was learning to break multi-body plant.
So I had to add 10 so that every time step was positive.
And then it would be rewarded for running a long simulation
and not rewarded for crashing my simulator.
How do you crash the simulator?
You cause ridiculous penetrations
at high velocities and stuff like that.
And it was learning to do that.
That's cool, but it's annoying.
But that was the one thing I was like, OK,
I have to go back in and add a 10.
Everything else was like, I don't
know why I picked 2 and 0.1, but it wasn't 2.
That was just me thinking that was 20 times as important
as that.
Yeah?
What was the effort?
The effort-- in the stiffness control,
I chose effort to be the distance
between the desired finger and the actual finger.
So that's like the stretch of the spring.
Yeah?
Why 10?
Why did you do 100?
I just looked at the rollouts and saw
what the largest cost I could get with those other things.
My one-step costs tended to be between 0 and negative 5
or something like that.
I just added something that was safely
bigger than the smallest reward I had gotten,
just to shift that up to be in the positive space.
[INAUDIBLE]
So the comment there, just to say back
for people watching remotely and the like,
is that stable baselines certainly recommend strongly
that you normalize your action space,
you normalize your observation-- maybe less about even
observations-- or normalize your reward.
And it does some amount of automatic things,
depending on if you turn that on or off.
So the question was, does it even
matter if I had picked 100?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, normalization wouldn't fix it
wanting to crash the simulator.
Right.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Good.
Any other questions about that?
I definitely could have made that better.
It was a teaching moment for--
I just thought, if I leave that, it's kind of like--
because that's real.
I mean, you'll do that.
You'll see robots smacking their head against the wall
and stuff like that until you tell them not to.
And I want to think about--
I mean, that's like--
well, let me distinguish between two different types
of that kind of behavior.
Some of it is power, in the sense
that it can find very strange solutions.
And some of it is bad behavior by the optimizer, I would say.
So when it comes to tuning-- so if I wanted to make that better,
that basic framework is probably OK.
I could maybe make the 2's and the 0.1's different.
And I could dial that in and get a behavior that was less--
right, if I'd really penalized action,
then maybe it wouldn't do that.
But let me distinguish between two types of tuning.
I won't write the word distinguish.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
I was only going to write reward training, but I wrote cost.
I'll just go with it.
I would say the first one is whether you fully
specified the task.
OK?
[WRITING ON BOARD]
And I'll contrast that with reward shaping.
And these are slippery slope.
OK?
So let me distinguish what I mean here.
It's actually hard to write a cost function whose
optimal solution has the behavior you really want.
I gave an example of that before when
we were talking about loading the dishwasher, right?
I didn't tell the robot, don't throw dishes across the room.
Right?
And if I didn't tell it that, if it
could throw the dishes into the dishwasher,
it probably should.
Right?
That would optimize the objective.
So I would say that's my fault. I
didn't specify the optimization function whose optimal value
had the solution I want.
And it's not because I'm a bad person.
It's because it's really hard to write good optimization
landscapes.
Right?
And in general, I think a lot of the behaviors
that we do as manipulators, as humans that do manipulation,
is due to a lot of common sense understanding about the world.
Like, dishes shouldn't be smashed into the plate,
into the ground.
You don't have to-- having to tell all of these-- Leslie
Kelbing likes to call it background utility functions--
into a robot is very, very hard.
And I think it's really interesting and hard
to think about how do you give the programmer the vocabulary
to specify the super rich semantics.
And I'm all for that.
I like that a lot.
I think that's an interesting problem.
And I think-- and so natural language
can help with that, large language models, foundation
models.
These are things that are going to help
us make progress on that.
There's a second thing which happens,
which is just you're helping the optimizer.
[WRITING]
Which is that the optimizer got stuck in a local minima.
And if I write the cost function a little differently,
then maybe it'll do better and it'll
get down to the right solution.
And this one, I choose to do less of this
and try to work on better optimizers instead.
That's just my preference.
But so this one I have less excitement about.
This one I think is fundamental and good.
So for instance, like which one--
if I were to start tuning that example, my box flip example,
which one do you think is more the problem there?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
There's probably both.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Nice.
Yeah, so I didn't actually say don't smash yourself
into the side of the bin repetitively.
That's my bad.
I could have said, I don't want you to smash yourself.
My bin is important or something.
But there's also-- I mean, I did tell it.
All other things equal, use less energy or use less effort
and keep your finger velocity small.
And it still chose to go like this.
So I'm pretty sure there's a solution that
would have flipped it up just as well that didn't go like this.
And so, yeah, in that case, I think
the optimizer has done a good enough job to get the job done.
But it hasn't found the optimal solution.
And just so you see the world through my eyes a little bit
more, if you-- let me take the opposite extreme of that.
Right?
So when we talked about the graph of convex sets motion
planning, the cost functions there of like this--
the bimanual thing doing complicated,
it was there's a start, there's a goal,
I want the shortest path.
Subject to velocity limits, acceleration limits on there.
The optimizer solves the global optimality,
or it says there's no solution.
Right?
That's just-- I mean, it's hard--
there's only a limited class of problems
that we know how to write that have a strong solution
like that.
But the joy of working with that system
is more for me than when you have to do this.
Right?
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, that's a great question.
I suspect it would continue to get better, yeah.
The question would be like how long and what.
But you're right.
I think I could probably just let this go.
I did that fairly long for once, and it didn't change a lot,
but in that particular example.
But I do agree.
I think you could-- I mean, fundamental to RL
is a little bit of exploration.
And as long as it's still exploring,
it could eventually hop itself out and keep getting better.
Great question.
I mean, to some extent what we're doing is we're
lifting up the programmer from-- so like,
I can make a robot do anything using GCC or Clang.
I just have to write C++ code, and if I write good C++ code,
I can make the robot do anything.
And that's true of RL, too.
If I can write a good enough cost function,
I can make the robot do anything.
But in C++, the compiler is deterministic, and it's fast,
and the error messages are clear.
And I think RL will get there, but right now RL
is such that you try your cost function,
and then you wait a while, and it's
more frustrating to work on.
But that's just an intermediate state.
And actually, I think those of you that are working on RL,
I think you should work on that, because that's super--
there's just better things that will happen as the field
continues to work on it.
And the fact that it's solving problems
that nobody could program-- well, that's hard to say,
but people have not written GCC programs
to do some of the amazing things RL is doing.
So it's lifted our abilities.
I would put kinematic trajectory optimization somewhere
in the middle between those two.
So you're going to have to do some amount of tuning
with kinematic trajectory optimization.
A lot of times, you can do it with an initial guess,
or add a constraint to say, oh, I
didn't want you to do this crazy thing that you chose to do.
Put a constraint on there, and then you
could shape it in that way.
And I similarly find that very annoying,
and wish that we could just have stronger optimizers.
So there's a whole spectrum, I think, of these algorithms.
OK, quick stretch.
I wrote to myself, don't forget to tell people to stretch.
[LAUGHTER]
OK, so let's talk a little bit more about at least
the optimization view of the PPO class,
or maybe even simpler than PPO view of optimization.
So--
, we've talked a bunch about optimization.
We've talked about nonlinear optimization.
We've talked about some convex optimization.
In general, let me say if I've got some parameters,
and I'm going to just call it f for my parameters here,
and I've got some complicated landscape, right?
And I want to try to find-- I'm going to stick with minimum,
because I'll screw it up all day long if I don't.
I'm trying to find the minimum of some non-convex objective
function.
And really, in the discussion today,
we're going to have this be unconstrained optimization.
We're not going to add additional constraints, OK?
If we did have additional constraints,
we would push them up into our cost function
with a penalty method, like an augmented Lagrangian
or something like that.
We've talked about various ways you can optimize this.
Maybe you find an initial guess, and you start moving downhill
based on the gradient, right?
So we've talked about gradient descent.
Now, gradient descent, as we've talked about it so far,
is off limits.
It's not allowed today, because it required us
to be able to evaluate the gradient of that function.
And that means I needed to know something about this.
This is not allowed in the black box view of the world,
right?
Because if I'm going to play Atari or Go,
or let's say StarCraft or something like this,
I don't have gradients coming out of that simulation,
that game engine.
We talked about sequential quadratic programming.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
That's what SNOPT is doing when we're solving IK problems,
or even kinematic trajectory optimization problems.
It similarly is using partial f, partial theta.
You would think, since it's doing quadratic programming,
that it would also be using the second derivative.
But actually, it's making an approximation
of the second derivative and only asking for the first one.
Sometimes to its detriment, but also requires that.
The question is, how do you do optimization
if you're not allowed to get the gradient?
And RL has a-- I mean, black box optimization in general
has a bunch of interesting solutions to that.
And RL has particular versions of black box optimizations
that are very well suited to the RL domain.
So what do I mean by black box?
That means I have-- let's call it f of theta here.
I have access-- if I give it a theta,
I'm allowed to evaluate f.
I get the value of f.
But I don't get to know anything more about f.
I don't know if there's sines and cosines in there.
I don't know anything.
As far as I'm concerned, theta goes in.
I can't see behind the curtain.
The f of theta comes out.
And I have to write an algorithm around that.
You would contrast that with-- people
call it white box optimization or glass box,
maybe makes more sense-- glass box optimization,
where you can see everything.
I mean, this is-- so the reason--
I think it's obvious that you can make Drake look
like an open AI gym.
It makes me a little sad to do that,
because the whole point of Drake is to look inside f.
Drake is a differentiable simulator.
It can give you partial f, partial theta,
even if you run a whole simulation.
It's not just the dynamics of multi-body plant,
but you can take gradients through simulator advanced,
too.
You can put a gradient in, get a gradient out, right?
So all of those things are available.
And we're going to throw them away
when we're doing things today.
And it turns out I haven't yet been able to do much better
with gradients.
Maybe I'll have to get to that next time.
So that's the game, black box optimization.
So how do you do black box optimization?
It sounds like, ah, how could I do anything without a gradient?
But then if I tell you how they do it, it's like, of course.
So let me give you the simplest black box optimization.
I'll take theta times 0.
This will be my optimization step.
So every time I'm going to run a simulation or something,
I'll increment my theta estimate by 1.
So here's a simple algorithm.
I'll evaluate f of theta i plus some random noise.
And then maybe I'll also, for good measure,
I'll evaluate this.
Turns out you don't have to.
But I'll evaluate this.
And if the random vector I chose was better, I'll keep it.
And if it was worse, I could keep this.
Turns out there's even funnier things you can do.
So not a huge brainstorm algorithm here.
It's just I'm going to say I've got an initial guess.
I'm somewhere in the landscape.
I'll evaluate it here.
If that was better, I'll keep it and I'll move down to here.
If it was worse, I'll stick with this one.
More generally, if I were to say theta i plus 1 is-- let's say,
I'll write it in the discrete logic,
but we can do it more directly in a second here.
If f of theta i plus w-- this is my experiment.
I'm doing minimization because that's how I roll--
is less than-- if I got better, then why don't I
update this to be plus w?
Now, for reasons we'll understand
as we get to the stochastic case,
we tend to actually put in a learning rate here.
[WRITING]
Some small positive number.
So I don't go all the way to the guess.
So why is that?
So if I were to go all the way here,
oh, it looked better on this one particular simulation.
But when someone else puts a different mug in the scene,
maybe that was a little too aggressive.
So I'm going to say, if I did one experiment
and it looked better, I'm going to take that as a suggestion
to move in that direction.
But I'm not going to go full tilt into that one observation.
And there's a stochastic interpretation
of what happens with this version of the algorithm, which
plays out beautifully.
And then otherwise, I'll go in the opposite direction,
but again, I'll put a learning rate in there.
That's supposed to be eta.
It's looking a little more curly than I meant it to,
but that's an eta.
And there's simple versions of this
that instead of writing a plus or minus here,
if I just multiply it by the difference of this,
I get a version of that too, which will always
go in the direction-- I can get rid of my if else
and just write this as a single line
by putting the difference here in here.
And that would basically set my sign and actually
my amplitude of my update.
But the basic idea is take a random guess.
If it looked better, let's go that way.
Now, that's actually a pretty powerful algorithm.
And PPO is doing a very smart version of that,
but it's not that different than that.
So what would you expect that to do compared to a gradient
descent type algorithm?
Gradient descent would take a sort of direct path,
in this case, here.
It'll get stuck in local minima here.
This one will take maybe a more meandering or slow path
to get to the minimum, but we'll have similar behavior.
Take some more trials.
It could also get stuck here.
If we start adding the randomness,
it could potentially jump out of here.
So it becomes a stochastic gradient descent
instead of a deterministic gradient descent.
So that's-- Don was saying, if I ran it longer,
it might have hopped out of here and come and found
a better solution if I ran it long enough.
So I think that is a pretty decent first order
model of what you should think about the R algorithms are
doing.
They're doing much more behind there,
but just as a very first glimpse of how does that compare
with the more model-based methods, which
are taking exact gradients, for instance,
this is doing random gradients.
And we're going to have you look at a version of this called
reinforce in some detail on the problem set.
Some of you already started.
And reinforce is sort of the predecessor to PPO.
So the picture you should have in your head
is that you're going to go downhill.
You're still doing a gradient descent-based algorithm.
You're just going to take a random walk downhill
that's biased towards in the direction of the true gradient.
And that's actually something that can be made precise,
is that with most of these updates,
you can say that the expected value of the update
is in the direction of the true gradient.
And the variance, you'd like to be small,
but the variance tends to be big.
And we do a lot of work in RL to try
to make the variance of the update smaller.
So that's kind of like the black box equivalent
of gradient descent.
But you can also think of black box equivalents of SQP, too.
You could take multiple samples.
And like CMAES is called-- it's covariant matrix adaptation
with something sampling.
It's the-- what's the ES?
Evolutionary strategy.
Thank you.
Yes.
So imagine taking lots of random points on your landscape
and fitting a quadratic approximation to it,
and then taking a second order update.
These things can be made to work.
The picture is clean if the function is deterministic.
It's more beautiful, but a little bit more complicated
when you get noisy evaluations of your function.
Someone could have put a different number of objects
in front of me.
Every time I run the robot, I get a slightly different answer.
And I'm trying to optimize the expected reward.
But the background is the same.
And some of these algorithms enjoy more robustness to that.
You can think of it a lot-- for those of you
that do a lot of supervised learning,
you could think of it about how does your SGD come out
of mini-batch.
And some of the optimizers are a little better
at handling mini-batch.
Adam seems to be really good at it.
And these are the same kind of things.
So we get the comparable algorithms here,
which some of them enjoy more robustness to the mini-batch.
It really is very similar to mini-batch.
But every time I do 10 rollouts and I get 10 slightly different
evaluations from a potentially infinite number of evaluations,
it's very much like a mini-batch kind of update.
OK, so I said before that we do a little bit of work.
I'd say we're leaning into the group in various forms
of thinking about what RL is doing well,
what it's not doing well, how I can combine it
with some of the model-based control that we do.
So maybe I'll spend a few minutes
at the end telling you one of our recent research
stories about that, because I think it fits
this picture fairly well.
So let's just think, is this a good idea?
So I told you that I had-- the whole point of Drake
is to make it so you can look inside F if you want to.
Is there any reason why you shouldn't take gradients
if you have them?
It's a super interesting question,
because here's the mystery, right?
RL started to show robots doing things with their hands
and stuff that we haven't seen from people
who are using gradients before.
But with that picture, you'd say gradients
should only be better, right?
If I have a gradient, why wouldn't you use it?
OK, well, there's a couple reasons why it gets subtle.
The first one, I think, is very easy to see,
which is that if I'm doing visual motor policies,
it's hard to take gradients through a renderer.
So if I go from my equations of motion of my plant,
and my output function is render a camera into pixels
with a game engine style renderer,
and then do a neural network to go back to my actions,
the neural network's super differentiable.
That's great.
It's built for that.
But the renderer's not.
And there's been a lot of interesting work
on differentiable renderers.
But renderers aren't different.
If you move to the next pixel, you
could have an object whose pixel value is-- that pixel 14 by 28
hits the object.
And 13 by 28 misses the object.
True renderers actually do a little bit of smoothing
around the pixels and stuff like that.
But if you give me a gradient of how pixel 14 by 28
changes with respect to my parameters,
that doesn't do as much as you'd want.
So differentiable renders have been great,
but not the panacea, maybe.
Value metric rendering, like NERF,
seems to be a much better way to talk about that.
And that's been paying off.
But if you just wanted to take gradients,
if I just had the ability to take gradients
through Drake's renderer and back,
it's not clear that that's going to solve my problems.
But if you look at the OpenAI example,
they didn't even have a renderer in there.
They were just doing state feedback.
And they still did something that
surprised those of us that have been working on control
through contact for a long time.
So what is up with that?
And we spent some time thinking about it, actually.
Terry and Max and Kai-Ching spent some time
thinking about it.
And I can tell you the story in like five minutes.
It's a great 30-minute version, but I'll
tell you the five-minute version.
So you take the OpenAI example.
If I give myself observations, or state observations,
then the major complexity that remains, actually,
is the contact mechanics.
And somehow, they seem to have done an optimization that
was beyond what we had been doing
and other people had been doing through the contact.
So was there anything happening there?
And I think the story that has been emerging
is that we knew for a long time that contact dynamics leads
to discontinuous landscapes.
And I'll say that in the short version of that here.
And it seems like the random sampling, the way
that people are doing messy gradient descent,
is actually smoothing out some of the discontinuities that
comes from contact.
And that it was a good idea, and we should have been doing it
the whole time.
So actually, taking random samples
could be better than taking analytical gradients.
It's more subtle than that.
But we talked about some of the discontinuities of contact.
It doesn't happen everywhere, but it
does happen if a small change in my initial conditions,
for instance, causes me to hit a different face of the robot,
of the environment, for instance.
And that leads to these simulations that could have--
so you could imagine if I change the initial conditions
and I now look at the final conditions,
I could have a very different final condition
if I moved the initial conditions along here.
I'd get a very different final condition.
I'll end up on one side or the other.
So I can get a very different reward
if I went one side or the other.
So that would be a very discontinuous--
it's not this picture.
It's this picture with just immediate jumps.
Can happen if I have contact.
You also have these weird artifacts from simulators.
Remember I talked about how you can be going inside one--
the simulator is pushing you back towards one face,
and then you're all of a sudden pushing you
back towards the other face?
I think this one we should just resolve,
but this one causes some problems too.
And if you look at how people in optimization theory--
forget about RL-- optimization theory
think about how to do non-smooth optimization,
they have known for a long time that, first of all,
non-smooth optimization landscapes
could screw up gradient descent.
It could screw up even otherwise convex optimization.
And a natural idea would then be to smooth the objective.
So if you could take this and draw--
if you could somehow take your cost function
and just average over it and get a nice smooth version
of the cost function, wouldn't that be nice?
Wouldn't that make things better?
It turns out there's an interpretation
that the way people are sampling in RL
is doing that to our cost functions.
A bit.
It can move the minima.
I mean, there's a lot to think about in this world.
It changes the optimization landscape.
In some ways, that might be better for finding a solution,
but might not find the optimal solution.
So you could take these things that we get out
of actual contact problems and see
that they get smoothed out with RL type sampling.
Those are actual mechanical examples.
And I'll skip a little bit here.
So then the question is, if you have the analytical gradients,
should you use them?
And it's actually very subtle, because there's
times in your landscape where you're in smooth sailing,
and you should definitely use a gradient if you have it.
There's times where you're very close to a discontinuity,
and you prefer the first-- the black box methods.
So we've been thinking about ways
to take the best of both worlds.
And you can actually-- if you compute
both the empirical gradient from an RL side
and the analytical gradient, you can actually
do a little numerical test to see if they agree,
and know if you should trust your analytical gradient or not.
There's games like that that are actually super interesting.
One last point I'll make, because I know I'm out of time.
The coolest thing, though, is that once we
realized that was helping the optimization landscape,
you could stop and think, OK, well,
did you actually need to be random to get that effect?
And no, you can actually just change your contact model.
It means a little bit of force at a distance.
It means a little bit more penetration.
But you can soften your contact model
in a way that has a similar effect,
like almost an equivalence.
For any noise sampling model in RL,
we could find a contact model, but they
might be weirdly shaped.
Is stochasticity essential?
And it turns out you can do deterministic smoothing.
And you can put that into an RRT kind of planner
for contact, which never worked through contact before.
Motion cones are good.
There's a couple examples, but RRTs
have not had the success you might
think in planning through contact before.
But they work a lot better if you just smooth out
some contacts.
It makes the distance functions work better.
I could tell you more or less of the details.
But this lights me up.
This is like something amazing happened in RL, empirical RL.
And now I think the theorists are coming in and understanding
it a little bit better.
And sometimes the answer will be not just RL,
but a mixture of RL and true gradients and models.
And I would put my money on that being the future.
Because Go maybe has some structure,
but it doesn't have an obviously interpretable structure to me.
If I take a picture of a Go board and I move one piece,
the rollouts could be completely different in ways
that I don't have enough Go skills to understand.
But if you take my robot and my environment
and you move me by a centimeter, it's
going to be pretty similar.
It better be, otherwise I'm in trouble.
So I just think the structure in those problems has to matter.
All right, that concludes RL day one.
We'll talk a little bit more about maybe model-based RL.
And we're actually surveying you on this p-set
about what you want to see in the next few lectures.
So tell us, and we'll dial it in.
[BLANK_AUDIO]