[ Background noise ]
>> I actually don't know why it's not projecting.
>> It was up a second ago.
[ Background noise ]
>> Take the cable.
>> The actual camera setup.
[ Background noise ]
>> Very.
>> One more.
[ Background noise ]
>> You can bring the whole laptop up there.
>> Can you still see okay?
I'm not occluding you with that?
[ Background noise ]
>> Put your mic right there.
>> What's that?
>> Mic.
>> Thank you.
Yeah.
[ Background noise ]
>> I don't -- when I see you smiling like that,
Bojan, I'm worried because --
[ Background noise ]
>> Oh, yeah.
>> He deep faked me in his final project last term,
so I'm a little wary.
[ Background noise ]
>> Okay. Welcome back, everybody.
Let's get started.
We have a double recording technology going here,
so I'm mic'd like six times, and I've got --
I'm plugged in over here, and hopefully one of the two
of them is going to look great.
Thank you to the TAs who are working hard to make this good.
Okay. So I want to pick up where we left off.
We did a lot of stuff last week.
Yeah. And -- but we didn't complete the story, right?
We had this basic idea that I'm going to put a red brick
in front of you, we're going to design a complete stack
to go pick up the brick, move it to the next --
you know, from one bin to the next.
And today I want to complete that story for you, right?
So this was our task, basically red brick,
EWA with a WSG gripper.
We're just going to pick it up, move it to the other side.
And if you remember, the sketch for how we were going
to do that had a few steps.
The first step, we had to learn a bit about kinematic frames,
how to work with them, the spatial algebra of reasoning
about frames, rotations, and translations.
Then we made a sketch in the end effector coordinates.
So we decided that, okay, if I know the initial pose,
given a particular -- in the world frame, for instance,
of the object, then I can figure out what I want my gripper
frame to be relative to the object frame.
I can project that into world coordinates.
And I can go through and make a bunch of key frames
for where I'd like that gripper to eventually go.
And then I can connect those key frames with a trajectory.
We talked a little bit about how to interpolate carefully
on the trajectory.
But the last big step is to turn that end effector trajectory
now into joint trajectories, because that's what we have
to send to the robot.
And we started that, too.
We started talking about the forward kinematics, right?
If you have the joint angles of the robot,
how would you figure out what's the pose of the end effector?
That's the forward kinematics problem.
And at the very end, I mentioned that we're going
to try to use differential kinematics to decide
our joint angles.
And so today, we're going to try to finish that story.
And I love the questions I got last time.
Please keep them coming.
I'm prepared to speed up or slow down, depending
on what you guys need and want.
So let's just make sure, when I write this down,
that we're super clear.
Remember, one time in answering one of those questions,
I said positions.
And I'm like, well, no, the other positions, right?
I just want to be super clear that we
do use the word position to mean a three-element vector
in space.
We also use it to mean the notion of generalized positions
is the Q that we talk about, which is the-- in the IWA case,
it's just a series of joint angles.
But more generally, it's whatever coordinate system
we need as a sufficient description
of the complete configuration of the robot and the object.
It's everything in the multi-body plant.
So generalized positions we call Q.
So when you say plant.getPositions or setPositions,
it's talking about this generalized positions.
And then this is the pose, right?
We talked about representing that as a transform or a pose.
And this is of the body or frame B. B typically meaning the body.
Right?
And this, without the extra superlatives,
would mean it's in the world frame, expressed in the world
frame and relative to the world frame.
Good.
So we sort of figured out how to do that,
that we could go through a series of our spatial algebra
relations and go from end effector to the second to last
end effector all the way up to the base
and figure out the transform from the gripper in the world.
The thing that you guys asked a bunch about that I tried
to sweep under the rug was this notion
of different representations for 3D rotation.
I still want to mostly sweep it under the rug.
Posted on Piazza earlier too, but I
did try to write some more notes about that,
just so you have references.
And I'll just say a bit about it now
because it actually will play out
in the differential kinematics story too.
And it's important to think about-- just
to understand that there are different rotation
representations and all of the complexity of what
we're going to talk about today sort of comes down to this,
I would say.
So the fundamental problem is-- so in 2D space,
having an angle is enough to tell me what a rotation is.
Right?
If I'm in the plane and I want to just rotate a vector,
I can do that with just an angle.
In 3D, you would think that you'd
use three angles to do that.
And you can, but there's a problem.
If you only use three numbers, like the roll, pitch, and yaw
would be a standard thing, then you can run into singularities
basically because roll, pitch, and yaw all
live on the sphere, on a circle.
And when each of them are pi in the wrong place,
you can end up with a singularity.
And it's well understood that you cannot completely,
without singularities, represent rotations in 3D
with just three numbers.
You need one more number.
And because of that, there's a handful
of different choices of which numbers you might do.
So the ones that I called out here,
you can use three by three rotation matrices, which
have the property that you can think of this as the x-axis,
the y-axis, and the z-axis unit vectors stacked up.
And that's a total of nine numbers, way more than three,
right?
But great on a GPU, or great on a processor.
You can often do a lot of computations
nicely with the rotation matrix.
The more minimal representation, you would think,
would be the Euler angles.
In particular, the one we use in Drake is roll, pitch, yaw.
OK.
So roll is a rotation around x, the x-axis.
Pitch is a rotation around the y-axis.
Yaw is a rotation around the z-axis.
OK.
This is three numbers.
It's convenient to think about.
I can sort of intuit roll, pitch, and yaw.
But it has singularities.
OK.
So we use roll, pitch, and yaw a lot when the human's involved.
Like if you're in a description file
and you want to just position something,
it's often easier to type in roll, pitch, and yaw.
Like the universal robot description format,
the scene description format, all the standard formats
will take in a roll, pitch, yaw description of the orientation.
And that's fine if you are specifying it in one direction,
but it has singularities.
There are a few more that you might know or might have heard
of.
The axis angle representation, where
you can specify any rotation in 3D
by a vector and a scalar rotation around that vector.
That vector may not be axis aligned,
almost certainly isn't for interesting rotations.
But you can always pick a vector and then
think about a scalar rotation around that vector.
And that's four numbers again, but a complete description
that's useful for some things.
I used it for interpolating between two rotations
last time.
And then there's the famous unit quaternions.
Again, four numbers.
And you can actually think of unit quaternions
a lot like the axis angles if you
want geometric interpretations of it.
A scalar cleverly scaled to be on the unit
circle in four dimensions.
They do have an interpretation like that.
And there's a lot of things to know about quaternions.
So I want you to recognize these.
But the most important thing, like I said last time,
is knowing that they all exist.
You can go back and forth between them,
except for a few cases of singularities,
you can go perfectly back and forth between them.
And they're good for different computations.
So having a unit quaternion, just four numbers,
is, for instance, the choice we make
when we're populating our configuration in a vector q.
So the generalized positions we choose
when we want to represent an orientation
is we use the unit quaternion.
But when we're doing kinematics queries,
we often use the 3 by 3 rotation matrices, for instance.
Does that make sense?
Questions about that?
Yeah?
Can you give a quick example of the singularity
for that one-way?
Yeah.
So it's famously known as gimbal lock.
So basically, if you rotate pi this way and pi this way,
then you can't come out.
There's a singularity in trying to understand
what's going to happen.
I mean, there's even-- you can't rotate.
There's directions where it's like you can't rotate.
There's a singularity in this map.
It always happens.
You can try to place it.
You can choose your coordinate system
and the singularity is in a reasonable place.
But it always happens at this pi-pi case.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, it's just a limitation of using only three numbers
to represent this topological space.
You actually-- this space wants to live in four dimensions.
So trying to-- we're going to give
a really good example of the singularities in a few minutes.
But yeah, it's a well-known sort of-- it's frustrating,
but well-known that you can't do it.
So just to make that super clear,
so if you think of a single free body--
so I took in pseudocode here.
I took a plant.
I just added the brick, only the brick.
That's it.
It's not welded.
It's just floating around.
So it's a free body.
And I've got a context for it.
I didn't mean for that to be there already.
But what is q?
If I say plant.getPositions, what is q in this case?
Positions and orientations, how big is it?
It's in seven, which is a coincidence that IWA has seven.
But this is three positions and then four numbers
in a quaternion stacked in a vector to make up the vector q.
What is the pose?
If I were to call plant.evaluateBodyPose in world,
what is that thing?
So the output of this is a rigid transform.
The representation it uses in memory
is actually the rotation matrix plus the translation matrix,
plus three numbers plus the 3 by 3 rotation.
So it's a 3 by 4 matrix.
So when you go from, in this case, where the q vector
perfectly represents the position of the object,
that's its only job in this setting.
I've got a single free body.
The only job of q is to tell me where the body is in the world.
And I'm asking the question of the kinematics engine,
where is the body in the world?
It's kind of funny, but this kinematics function,
which in the robot case does lots of work, what it's doing
here is really just changing coordinates from quaternions
to rotation matrices.
Right?
It's still doing some work, but it's just
doing the change of representation.
Is that clear?
Because we're going to take derivatives of this in a second.
So you want to make sure it's clear.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: I'm sorry.
So you were saying, in the case of an identity transform,
it's still doing work.
Is that what you're saying?
PROFESSOR: Let me say it carefully.
You might think it's the identity transform.
The same information is present here and here.
But it is not just an identity transform,
because the way that the orientations are represented
in the q vector are different than the 3 by 3 matrix.
It has to convert from quaternions
into rotation matrices in this transformation.
This function, as I've written it,
is not the identity matrix.
Or the identity.
[INAUDIBLE]
If you were to put xB on the object?
Tell me what you mean.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
This is just-- both of these contain the information,
which is, where is that object in the world?
Yeah?
No, that's good.
I appreciate the questions.
OK.
So we're going to take different gradients of this thing now.
And there was good questions about,
when is the inverse kinematics well-defined?
When are there many solutions?
So we're going to get into that in some detail here.
But we're going to see it through the lens first
of differential kinematics.
So if I have this function, which in the case of the EWA,
q is a bunch of joint angles, not quaternions.
But if I had the EWA and a red brick,
I might have the seven joints from EWA and the seven numbers
for the quaternion plus position of the brick.
Now, if I ask a question, given those configuration q,
what is the position of some body?
That's my function there.
What I want to think about is, what is the gradient
of that function?
So I want to say, if I make a small change in my q,
what does it look like as a small change in the pose?
And that's just a partial derivative of that function.
So the kinematics function, partial derivative.
And I think partial derivatives are basically
always called Jacobians.
But in robotics, we don't even say kinematic Jacobian.
We just say Jacobian, and everybody
knows we're talking about this particular Jacobian,
if there's no other context.
So we're going to try to study this object today,
understand when it's full rank, when it loses rank,
think about how to work with it to make a controller.
So I just did this as a sort of variation here on q.
But if I were to take dt, if I were to take a q dot here,
d dt of q, I get d dt on this side.
The derivative of this pose, d dt,
is the spatial velocity, so the change in pose over time.
And it's interesting to ask, this
was a-- we decided it was a 3 by 4 matrix.
That's how we choose to represent it for computations.
What's the right way to represent
a spatial velocity, the derivatives?
It turns out we're going to think of it
as a three element angular velocity and a three element
translational velocity.
So not the full 12 numbers.
We're back down to six numbers.
And the first point I want to make sure I land for you
is why that is, at least to some extent I want to land that.
But there's a lot of v's flying around here.
So let me just note the type setting.
So there was the LaTeX times Roman v,
which is my generalized velocities.
This v is translational velocities.
There's a lot of velocities, and they're all v.
And this is the spatial velocity, the capital.
I try to be super careful about that notation.
It's almost always clear from the context.
Sorry, not the context, but from when you're reading,
it should almost always be clear.
It's very rare that we have them all in one equation.
But nevertheless, I try to be really clear
with that notation.
So now the big question is, 3D rotations
were this weird thing that we needed
a bunch of different possible options to represent.
How do you represent angular velocity?
It's derivative of rotational orientation.
It turns out everything's good again.
Three numbers are sufficient.
The fundamental reason why that is-- so all the problems
with the coordinates is because when you wrap around a 2 pi,
you want to get the same number again.
The topology of that space wraps around
on 2 pi in each of the different coordinates.
Angular velocities don't have to wrap.
You can have an angular velocity greater than 2 pi.
There's nothing-- you can have an angular velocity
of a million in some direction.
There's no getting bigger, getting bigger,
and then I came back around.
The space is easier when you're in angular velocities.
And so it turns out that three numbers are sufficient.
You could pick various versions of three numbers.
You could pick the derivatives of roll pitch yaw
if you wanted to.
But the canonical one that has really nice properties
for our spatial algebra is this angular velocity vector,
which means something in particular.
It's basically the-- it's a three element vector.
It's three numbers.
We call them wx, wy, wz.
And if you think about the direction of those three
numbers, it's kind of the instantaneous axis of rotation.
And the magnitude of those three numbers
is the rate of rotation.
You may never need to know that.
But what's important to know is that three numbers are all
you need and you don't-- and we're going to-- they are
sufficient and efficient in all of our computations.
So we don't have a bunch of them flying around.
We just always use this one.
OK?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes, it is.
Thank you.
That would be a lot more reasonable.
x, y, z.
Yes, thank you.
OK.
They have the same sort of rules of algebra
apply to spatial velocities.
And I won't write them up slowly on the board.
But basically, they add.
And you can use rotation matrices to change coordinates.
All the same rules apply.
OK?
It's less common that you will have
to manipulate the velocities.
The dynamics engine is going to do
a lot of manipulating of those velocities for you.
It's less common for you to have to know these rules.
But I find myself going back and just saying, OK, if I need them,
then I can look here.
OK?
And that's kind of the level I want you to have, too.
OK.
So let's just think this one through again.
Again, the simple case of a free body.
Right?
What is q?
What is v?
Well, let's do it carefully here.
So q, in the case of the single free body, we agreed,
was a seven element vector.
Three positions and four quaternions.
If I say plant.getVelocities, this
is the generalized velocities.
For the EWA, it would be joint velocities,
the rotations of each of those joints.
But for the free body, it's this v. OK?
What is v?
How big is it?
This time it's six elements.
OK?
So this is a six element vector.
Which is a little funny, because that
means the derivative of q is not necessarily v. Right?
In some cases it is, but in general,
there's some transformation that you
have to use to go back and forth between v and q dot.
OK.
Ask questions.
Is that clear?
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
This is the generalized velocities.
[INAUDIBLE]
That's translational velocity.
And then the capital is spatial velocity.
Yeah.
That's great.
OK.
This n is useful to know.
There's map q dot to velocity, map velocity to q dot.
You can go back and forth between them.
The transformation is a function of q.
So you pass in the context to get it.
This is like saying q times q dot and vice versa.
n is invertible.
Sorry.
OK.
So now the question is, so we sort of understand,
I think, a little bit more maybe some of the subtleties
of the representation.
But when I write now the derivative
of the forward kinematics, the output I get
is always going to be represented
as a spatial velocity of a body.
Six numbers.
I could take the derivative with respect to q dot
or with respect to v. Both of these are valid,
and both of those are available in the code.
But the Jacobian is going to always output spatial velocity.
All right.
So now let's step back and think about how
am I going to use that in the code?
Why is that the thing I want in order to move my robot?
So we said this on the board last time.
That's why the stuff I'm putting on the slides
is partly because people can see the slides better,
but also some of this is fleshing out
what we did last time.
OK.
So there's the different kinematics problems
we talked about.
We're the forward kinematics, which
goes from joint positions, generalized positions,
to pose.
We talked about inverse kinematics,
which goes from pose back to joint positions.
I put an asterisk there because I actually--
when we really cover inverse kinematics,
I'm going to try to give you a much richer, I think, picture
of inverse kinematics than just pose.
You might want to say, find me the closest pose,
but try to minimize something else
and try to stay inside joint limits and whatever.
There's a much richer way to specify inverse kinematics.
But the vanilla inverse kinematics
says, you've got an end effector.
Tell me what the joint positions are.
And this is where, when you were asking last time about,
are there multiple solutions, this problem absolutely
can have multiple solutions.
You could say the same end effector,
and there might be many joint angles that
would get the same end--
I'm trying to keep that still--
same end effector.
So that makes it a hard problem.
It's also a very nonlinear problem in general.
So it might be that some of my solvers--
OK, if you have exactly six degrees of freedom
in your robot, a serial chain robot,
there's closed form solutions for this.
And we know exactly where the solutions are.
As soon as you have seven degrees of freedom,
you have to do something more.
And when you have a humanoid, you definitely
have to do something more.
And there's not-- I mean, this is still
a hard problem in some ways.
OK.
How does differential kinematics fit in?
Differential kinematics goes from joint positions
and velocities to spatial velocity.
Jacobian was a function of q.
And it multiplied the joint velocities
to get to spatial velocity.
Differential inverse kinematics is going the other way.
It's going to use the Jacobian again,
something like the inverse of the Jacobian,
to try to go the other way.
So it's actually a function of spatial velocity
and joint positions.
I'll make this super clear.
Don't worry.
But roughly, it's going from spatial velocity
to joint velocity.
You know where you currently are.
So the map from spatial velocity to joint velocity
is a function of joint angles.
In our notation, it looks like this.
Basically, I'm going from q.
Inverse kinematics goes from q to pose.
Inverse kinematics, roughly, from pose back to q.
Differential kinematics is a configuration-dependent map
from generalized velocities to spatial velocities.
And inverse kinematics is trying to go from-- it's, again,
configuration-dependent map from spatial velocities
back to velocity.
My claim is inverse kinematics is hard.
Differential inverse kinematics, it
can still have multiple solutions and the like.
But it's all easy, because it's a linearization
of the hard problem.
And we're going to have good solutions for it
and be able to understand it completely.
And people use it on the robots all the time.
Yes?
When we talk about spatial velocity,
that's the velocity of the end effector, right?
Like the gripper.
Yep.
Exactly.
So the most common one we'll use is the spatial velocity
of the gripper frame.
So like what we're saying, like on the previous slide,
we're saying velocity to q dot.
Yep.
That would be the spatial velocity
to the joint angle velocity.
I'm glad you asked.
It's not that.
It's the little v. This is going from the generalized
velocities.
The generalized velocities may not
be the time derivative of the generalized positions,
but they're related.
So this is not necessarily a square matrix
that transforms little v, not spatial v,
to the time derivatives of the joint angles.
I don't know how to say that better.
But so this is a map.
I mean, this is really-- in the case of joint angles,
this is the identity map.
It does no work.
The only time it does work is when
you have a different representation
for the velocities than you do as the derivative
of the positions.
And that happens when you're doing these orientation things.
So if you had a quaternion in q, then you
don't use the time derivative of the quaternion.
You use the angular velocity vector.
So there's a change of variables that has to happen.
I'll ask later.
Yeah, yeah, it's good.
It's good.
I know when I've failed.
All right.
So we're going to now-- let me, before I put that up.
So here's the straw man proposal for how
we're going to start moving the end effector.
If I have-- and in the case, let's
think of this as a body.
Let's use the gripper frame.
I'll go ahead and, like you said,
that's the most common frame we're
going to use is the gripper frame.
So I'll make this gripper.
Although I wrote everything in-- if I read B later,
that's my-- this was a bad choice.
But OK.
So in this case, if I-- let's forget
the brick exists for a minute.
Let's just think about moving the EWA around.
So in that case, if it's just the EWA,
then this is seven joint velocities.
Because there happens to be seven degrees of freedom
on that robot.
This is my six element spatial velocity.
Now, what we had from last time was we had a bunch of grippers.
We had gripper at time equals 0.
We had gripper at time equals pre-pick.
Remember how we had the whole trajectory, right?
We actually turned that into a function
that was defined for all t in my interval.
0 to t final.
OK?
I'll try to write bigger, but I'm
hoping the video is better today.
And there's software that helps you represent that, right?
With piecewise polynomials, piecewise linear interpolation
of the positions.
You remember that we had to do that slurp for the quaternion.
But we had a nice representation of this
that defined it for all t.
You can take a derivative of that representation,
and it will give you another trajectory that's
the time derivative of the spatial velocity
as a function of time.
So my proposal is if I had my plan,
and it basically tells me what my end effect
or my gripper velocity should be at all times, spatial velocity,
then can I use this to decide what my joint angles should be?
And the proposal is something like I
want v of t to be the inverse of this.
Right?
This relationship is a nonlinear function of q,
but it's a linear function-- a linear relationship
between the-- it's just that gradients are always
a linear relationship, right?
But it's a linear relationship between the joint velocities
and the spatial velocities.
Since I know q, this is just a matrix.
And I can try to take its inverse
to try to go the other way.
That tells me, given I want to go in some direction,
what should my change in my joint angles be?
Now, if I write this, the natural question
is, can you take that inverse?
Does that work?
OK.
Can I take that inverse?
Does it work ever in this case?
What's the size of the matrix J?
6 by 7, which is not square.
So I shouldn't write that.
I kind of don't want that on the board, but I shouldn't.
I shouldn't take an inverse.
I can't take an inverse of a non-square matrix.
There are generalizations of the inverse
that can work for non-square matrices,
and we'll use them now, right?
So Jg of q is a 6 by 7 matrix.
Doesn't have an inverse, but the generalization
is the pseudo-inverse.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
How many people know the pseudo-inverse?
OK.
So everybody has their own favorite symbol for it, right?
I wrote this before as a minus 1, as the inverse.
People use music symbols and whatever.
I just use plus, OK?
Plus is my pseudo-inverse.
OK, and the question is now not does the inverse exist,
but the pseudo-inverse will always return something.
The question is, is it any good?
OK?
And we'll dig into exactly how you compute
the pseudo-inverse in a minute.
But first, just know that you could call P in the MATLAB.
It's a linear algebra operation, or a numpy,
and you can ask for the pseudo-inverse of a matrix.
And the question is, when does it work?
So in particular, what do I want?
If I put a desired VB in, and I use the pseudo-inverse here
to get a joint velocity, if I were to put that back through
and think about what was the resulting VB actual,
when does this equal this?
Did that make sense what I did?
I went from end-effector velocities
into joint velocities with a questionable pseudo-inverse.
And then I went from joint velocities
back to end-effector.
This one is always well-defined.
And the question is, when does that
become the identity matrix?
When does this work?
It can work even when it's a non-square matrix.
In fact, this is the good case in some sense,
because being 6 by 7 is the good case.
We have six things we're trying to do,
and seven joints with which to try to do them.
So you'd like to be optimistic about this,
that that transformation should work.
People know?
Do you know the property for that?
Yeah.
So full rank, which in this case would be at most the row
rank.
The rank of the non-square matrix
will be determined by the number-- the smaller
of the rows or columns.
So works when jq is full row rank.
Here, rank j equals 6.
Now that's a math answer, which is the right answer.
I mean, that's the question I asked.
But when you go to put it on the robot,
there's a-- rank is like true or false.
Is the rank 6?
It's a true or false question.
But what really matters is somehow
the condition of the matrix.
If you look at the singular values of j,
and the smallest singular value gets very close to 0,
then that means the matrix is getting numerically close
to being non-invertible in this sense.
And you start having problems.
Even if it strictly has rank, but the condition is very bad,
when the smallest singular value is small, close to 0,
that means that I might-- if I wanted
to make small movements in velocity here,
it might take ridiculously large joint velocities
to accomplish something small here,
if those eigenvalues, the singular values,
get very close to 0.
So what we really want to look at is the smallest
singular value.
It should be not-- when it gets close to 0
is when you have issues.
So luckily for our IWA, most of the time that's good.
Most of the time this is full row rank.
And I did some little animations,
which are in the notebook, so you can run them.
Start with this Jacobian one here.
,
So what I have here is an unfortunate choice of screen
layout.
I have here a little notebook that just prints the Jacobian
when I move this thing around.
So I can move this around, and it's
going to print out the Jacobian, JG, the gripper Jacobian,
in a font that's probably not useful.
Make it a little bigger here.
And it also is just printing out the smallest singular value
of that Jacobian.
And the game is move this around,
convince yourself that in most configurations of this robot,
it's fine.
It's really pretty good.
How can I make it not good?
Yeah, right?
If I put it at the end of its-- if I put it like straight out,
right?
Like if I straight it out, now I've
got a smallest singular value of negative e to the negative 16.
Why is that?
The map saying I want to command an instantaneous velocity
in the end effector would require ridiculously large joint
angles.
I mean, this is just-- that's numerical nonsense.
That's zero.
It's saying that I would need infinite velocity
at the joints to achieve some desired force at the end
effector.
If you tried to go straight down, it's not going to work.
It would require-- if you wanted to move down
at a certain velocity, it would require infinite joint
velocities.
That's a funny thing, right?
Maybe you should have a problem with that.
That seems broken.
It seems like maybe we've just written the problem down
wrong, right?
Because clearly the robot can move back down.
How do I justify that?
Like, are singularities real, or is it just my math's bad?
The second derivative is non-zero.
So here's a super simple example to make that work out.
So this is just a two-link robot.
Each link is the same length.
So I can write the kinematics very simply.
And I'm going to just make it move
through the straight position like this.
So that's going through the singularity and back.
I can loop it.
I think I need to reflect it.
That'll be cool.
OK, so do you understand what's happening here?
Two-link pendulum, they just happen
to have exactly the same length that
makes the kinematics trivial.
It means I can write down the Jacobian.
It's a two by two matrix.
It's super simple.
And that Jacobian loses rank when
q's are zero like this, when it's straight out.
And I'm just telling the robot to go through q
as a sine wave, basically.
q1 and q2 are sine waves of scaled magnitude
so that they stay perfectly in that line.
OK, it's clearly going out and coming back.
It's not like it can't come back.
So what happens?
We already got an answer, right?
So at that instant of being completely out straight,
it is true that the Jacobian is singular.
If I wanted to instantaneously command a velocity back here,
I would fail.
But I can accelerate back in that direction.
The derivative is OK.
I can accelerate in that direction
and get myself out of the singularity
and eventually get back and everything's good again.
So it is absolutely true that the map that
goes from joint velocities to end-effector velocities
has a problem.
You cannot invert that map at this configuration.
It does not mean your robot is stuck there
for the rest of time.
I mean, with some controllers, it is.
So we're not going to handle that case beautifully
with a pseudo-inverse controller.
We're not going to try to.
We'll handle it in a different way.
But in the case where we're close to full rank,
we'd expect this sort of pseudo-inverse to work well.
The scary thing is when you get close to singularity
and then you start commanding very large velocities.
Those are the kind of things that we definitely
do want to address.
Questions?
You see one?
OK, there.
Yes.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Down here.
I'll get you next.
I'm sorry.
So this is for not being able to move within our range of motion.
Can we capture not being able to move outside of our range
of motion, outside of our range of motion as well?
I see.
So I think the question is, what math
tells me that I can't go out there,
beyond the reach of the robot?
I mean, differentially, this is still telling me,
also if I commanded in this direction, it will fail.
And similarly, if I'm at the edge of some workspace
and I'm trying to go-- this is what happens, actually,
is you command yourself to go farther than you should.
Your arm goes straight and the robot goes crazy.
So the math does tell you that in both directions.
And it's very much a differential quantity.
So it's only telling you, as a function of this,
which directions can I move.
It's not an absolute workspace analysis.
It's just instantaneously, can I move in that direction?
Sorry.
So if we say that in that position
we can't have [INAUDIBLE] velocity,
then is it that we tell the robot
hard to have an acceleration?
And what would that mean?
Great question.
Yeah, so if I was writing a really good controller
and I found myself in this position,
I would start commanding an acceleration.
Or I could forget about trying to command an end effect
or I could just command-- this controller is just--
it makes a Q trajectory.
It says, forget about the end effect for a minute.
I'm just going to move the joint angles through some simple
function.
But somehow, in that situation, you
have to give up on commanding via the velocity of the end
effector.
Great.
Yes.
I'm not able to distinguish my intuition
between this motion, which is the side wave,
and let's say we had the same end effector motion,
but just going half the distance.
So you go out there.
And somehow that would be within the range of motion
and would be controllable.
But the motion is the same.
I'm not able to picture why at any point
here you can't have immediately a velocity and only
an acceleration.
Great.
So I mean, I can't flip in that case.
But let's say I was just going like this and back.
This is your example.
But not going to full extension.
That at any one of those configurations,
if I wanted to command a particular xy position--
velocity, sorry-- of the end effector,
I could do so with a reasonable velocity in the joint angles.
So that's the big difference.
In all of those configurations here,
I still have the ability to command a velocity
in the end effector.
It's only when my Jacobian becomes close to singular
that I-- and when it's close to singular,
it just requires ridiculously large velocities.
And then when it's singular, there is no velocity.
That's the critical difference is
that it's really because these things line up.
And so think about the effect that moving this angle has
on the end effector velocity.
It moves in both x and y here.
But when I'm here, it only moves in y.
If I had a multi-jointed elbow.
So the ability to command an x with respect to this is gone.
And similarly, the ability to command
an x that direction in this joint angle is gone.
And the rank of that matrix is what tells you that's true.
It's really just the trigonometry
of what a small delta in that angle
is going to produce at the end effector.
So yeah, sure.
Yeah.
Does [INAUDIBLE] always happen at the edge of the world?
No.
You could have it similarly if I were to-- you guys,
I need to do some yoga or something.
But if I were to go like this, right?
And if I folded back in on myself, for instance,
that could be on the inside of-- it's still maybe,
you could call it the edge of a configuration space,
workspace.
[INAUDIBLE]
That's right.
Yeah, OK, so is there ever an example?
I think with more complicated mechanisms,
you could say if you had a four-bar linkage or something,
you could probably get yourself in trouble, even
in the comfort of the middle of your workspace.
But it's certainly common that you would be--
it's at the end of the workspace.
Yes?
So I guess, say you were sitting in your lab
and you're running a robot, what would happen?
And what would make this happen in terms
of what you get close to singular?
In practice, could you break your robot?
Robots have broken because some people
used simple Jacobian controllers and got
too close to singularities, yeah.
And in the '80s in particular, there
was a series of papers about what's the right way
to do this sort of control.
And they worried very much about not blowing up
during the singularities.
Absolutely, yeah.
What physically happens?
Yeah, so typically nowadays, the controllers,
that big box underneath the robot,
says you've asked for a big velocity, and it turns off.
If you've made your own robot and you didn't put that safety
protection in, then I did throw a robot across the room once.
Yeah, that can happen.
And there's big red buttons next to the big robots
in case that starts to happen.
But it can really--
that math is bad.
You shouldn't apply that joint velocity command.
OK, so I want to spend the rest of the lecture thinking
about maybe a generalized version of that pseudo-inverse,
the different view on that pseudo-inverse.
And it's going to at least help us
think about putting some of the guardrails
on so that it doesn't throw the robot across the room
or fault the controller that's trying to keep you safe.
And I'm going to do that by first just making
us think about the optimization view of what
the pseudo-inverse is doing.
So I like optimization.
That's a thing.
And there's a lot of the tools from class
that will use the language of optimization.
And really, the code, the equations
that are giving us the pseudo-inverse, I think,
are best understood as the solution
to an optimization problem.
And once we think about it that way,
then it becomes natural to put on a few extra protections
and write a slightly different optimization problem that
can say, try to do that, but don't blow up, for instance.
So let's think about pseudo-inverse
as an optimization.
So what I want to say is it's something--
what I'm writing here is really something
that looks kind of like this.
Find me joint velocities such that the end-effector velocity
is approximately equal to the desired spatial velocity.
I wrote it by taking that-- the pseudo-inverse
is sort of the solution to try to do that.
But think about it in its sort of primal form.
I'm trying to solve for a v such that this map comes
close to my desired.
Since q is given in this case, we
know where our robot is at any moment in time.
So really, this just looks like-- I could write this.
If I abstract away from the robot a little bit,
this is just like saying, find me an x such that Ax is
approximately equal to b.
This is just a 6-vector.
I'll call it b this time.
And this is Jacobian.
In the language of linear algebra,
this is really just Ax equals b.
And you can call it slash and map
by-- to solve that, that's one of the ways
to call a pseudo-inverse, for instance.
Now, a way to write this as an optimization
is instead to say, let's try to minimize some error term.
So I'm going to minimize the penalty, the difference
between Ax and b.
So I've got some distance function, some cost function
that says, basically, I'm going to penalize.
And in this case, I've chosen in what directions--
I've chosen the cost function, so it
says what my values are in terms of what kind of deviations
I like and what I don't like.
But this is sort of a standard way
to say, try to find me an x such that Ax is approximately
equal to b.
If the error goes to 0, then I've solved the problem.
And I would expect that to be true
when j has these properties.
But this problem makes sense even when j can't get you to--
when a is such that I can't drive this error directly
to 0.
So you see how that's kind of a more robust specification
of the problem.
So this is where I give a-- I'm going
to start using some of the language of optimization.
But it'll be, I think, a gentle introduction to that.
Let's even do it in the scalar case.
So think about what does the geometry of that problem
look like.
So if I said-- just like that, right?
No vector norms, nothing.
This is just a squared of a scalar.
a is a scalar, b is a scalar of the data.
I'm trying to find the smallest x.
I think the geometry of that problem
is easy to think about.
Right?
This looks like a quadratic form.
This is my ax minus b squared.
This is x.
And somewhere, there's a happy place
where I'm at the minimum of that.
And I'll call this the solution x star.
And for this particular problem, we
can find x star very easily by just taking
the gradient of that function, asking when
the gradient is equal to 0.
And that's going to tell us, since I know that in the case
where this curve is pointed up, it's
a positive definite function.
It's a convex function.
Then the minimum is going to give me the solution.
The place where the gradient equals 0.
So I take the gradient with respect to x of ax minus b
squared, set it equal to 0.
And this tells me that the solution to that, just worked
out, is just b over a.
Right?
So does that always have a solution?
I'm just sort of asking sort of an almost trivial question,
I guess.
a better not be 0.
Right?
So what happens when a is very small?
That's kind of what's happening as we get close to our singularity.
When a is very small, this thing starts
getting more and more elongated.
This cost function, as I get small, it goes like this.
And then maybe it goes like this.
Right?
And it's going to move out.
And the optimal solution is going to move out this way.
That's the geometry of what's happening here,
is that my cost function, as I change a and make a very small,
it's going to move the solution more and more towards infinity.
Right?
That's just saying when a gets close to 0,
x star is going to go to infinity.
And the objective function follows suit, as it should.
OK.
So that's bad.
Right?
You don't want x star to go to infinity.
And that's exactly what happens.
That's what's in danger of happening when the Jacobian loses
rank.
OK, so the matrix form of that-- are there
questions about that?
The matrix form requires more linear algebra, of course,
but is really exactly the same math.
OK?
So if I want to say minimize over x, now ax minus b,
I can multiply this out if I wanted to.
This is going to give me a transpose ax plus--
if I multiply it out, I guess it's minus 2b transpose ax
plus b squared.
It's just another quadratic equation.
Right?
And in two dimensions, if I had x1 and x2,
it's still going to just look like a quadratic function.
Right?
And it's going to have some optimum at the bottom.
Everything holds in the matrix case.
I can do the same thing.
I can take the gradient of that function with respect to x.
Now I do a little bit of gradient math.
And I set that equal to 0.
And I find out that the slight generalization of what
I did there is just b transpose a inverse.
And guess what?
This thing here is what you get when
you call the pseudo-inverse.
Right?
There's a left and a right pseudo-inverse,
and this is the one we're using today.
OK, I could write this as b transpose--
it's the transpose of the pseudo-inverse.
I've got a transpose here somewhere, but--
OK.
So actually, the pseudo-inverse, which I said
was just a generalization of the inverse-- that's
how I introduced it before, maybe
how you've seen it before-- it actually
is doing something very clever.
Right?
It's taking this slightly richer specification of the problem,
and it's not necessarily guaranteeing
that it's going to get a cost of 0,
but it's going to give you the best cost it can.
That's why the pseudo-inverse will always
give you something back.
OK?
And that something is exactly this.
So that's the picture I want you to have in your head.
The shape of that bowl, by the way,
is just governed by A transpose A.
The eigenvectors and eigenvalues of that matrix
will change the shape of that bowl.
I know that's a lot of equations or whatever,
but I want you to have the intuition.
Right?
So what happens when j starts to lose rank?
Think about what happened here.
The same thing happens in the vector case.
This bowl starts getting flatter, maybe in one axis,
maybe in multiple axes.
But if it's one eigenvalue goes to 0,
it will get very elongated to the point
where it can be a trough if the eigenvalue is exactly 0.
And the worst thing is that the minimum of that trough
is going to move off to infinity.
OK, so that's what happens.
That's what goes wrong when you call a pseudo-inverse.
It's not that it's solving a beautiful problem for you.
It's just that you're asking it to do the wrong thing.
You're not telling it to be reasonable.
You're just telling it to get as close as possible.
Questions about that?
OK.
Now here's the win.
OK?
The language of optimization is way richer
than just calling pseudo-inverses.
I can-- this is an objective, but I could also
add constraints.
So what I'm going to do, for instance, is say,
get as close as possible, but don't pick a velocity greater
than like 10.
I don't want my robot moving-- it's
got-- because the controller isn't going
to set a velocity limit, right?
So a perfectly good question, which looks simple in this case,
is what if I did minimum of x ax minus b squared,
but I'm going to do subject to, OK?
Let's say I want x to be less than or equal to 2,
something like that.
OK?
Then the picture is still like what I've got here,
but maybe I've got 2 here.
So it's going to say, go down as far as possible,
but don't cross this line.
If you get there, then I want the best solution
to be right on the rail.
OK?
That's another way to write a mathematical program.
And since we're going to be doing it a lot,
let me just stop and say, in this language,
this is the decision variables.
This is the cost or objective.
And these are constraints.
I can do exactly the same thing in this problem.
I could say, I'd like the vector 2 to be less than norm 2,
or something like this.
Or I could say the i-th element of the vector,
maybe every joint velocity has a limit.
So I could put, let's say, x0 less than 2, maybe x1 less than
3.
I've got a different load around that second joint,
so I could use a different joint velocity limit.
OK?
The language of optimization is super general,
but we're playing in a very nice version of the optimization
landscape, where this objective we wrote down.
OK?
This is a quadratic objective.
And it's a positive quadratic objective.
It can never be negative.
Right?
Really, the generalization is that it's positive definite,
or at least semi-definite.
So let's just say positive definite,
meaning the matrix which gets inside here, this A transpose
A. And I should say semi-definite,
because we're talking about when it can drop rank.
So I'll say semi-definite here.
Because the matrix A transpose A, the eigenvalues of this
are all greater than or equal to 0.
So my function is always going up, and it's always quadratic.
So it's a convex function, and it has a unique minimum.
And if I restrict myself to any constraints that
are of the form of linear equations,
the absolute value can be written
as just two linear equations.
I could have written that as x less than 2
and x greater than negative 2.
So these are linear constraints.
This is the domain of quadratic programming.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
You'll hear people talk about QPs.
So now, when I run my controller,
instead of calling pseudo-inverse every time
I want to-- every time step I want
to decide what positions to send to the controller,
I'll solve a small quadratic program.
The geometry of it, I made it look deceptively simple in 1D.
It is simple in 1D, but in higher dimensions,
you have a quadr-- it still can only do that, roughly.
But the geometry of these constraints can be interesting,
and you want to solve it efficiently.
So there are strong solvers, strong numerical codes
that will take the specification of the problem
in this kind of language.
They're called QP solvers, for instance.
And they'll solve this problem for even very large matrices
very fast.
And it's entirely practical to run them in a control loop.
Now, this-- I tried to visualize the geometry of this.
OK?
I made a nice little animation here
that writes a small mathematical program that just--
I'll tell you about that in a minute, maybe more next time.
But-- OK.
And here's what it looks like.
This is my two-link KUKA.
OK, so I basically-- I took the KUKA,
and I just froze all the two links,
because I can only plot 2D stuff.
If I have two decisions-- two velocities to move,
and I'm just trying to move in the plane or whatever,
I can plot that.
If you get higher dimensional, I can't plot it.
Now, this green is the quadratic form in those two planes.
That's just the objective.
And the red is the constraints.
Don't go outside those constraints.
As you move through the singularity--
see if I can make that visible enough-- what happens?
That quadratic form flattens out.
And the solution is trying to move off to infinity.
That's the bad case.
But the QP says, don't go past the limits.
Yeah?
So now I can just play with it a little bit.
OK?
So as I go close to the singularity,
you can see that that becomes a trough instead of a bowl.
It's actually-- until it's exactly 0,
it's still got a minimum.
At some point, it's just off at infinity.
And when it's exactly 0, it's infinity.
But the QP can move right through there pretty well.
It'll always come back with a solution for you.
OK, so the quadratic program is a nice generalization
of the pseudo-inverse controller.
OK, I did have another notebook that just showed it actually
moving the end effector.
But just for the sake of time, trust me,
it moves the end effector.
If I just command a velocity like this, it goes--
[MAKES NOISE]
It works.
You can run it.
So there's a language-- so Drake sort of
has three big components.
You've seen the plant, multi-body plant.
You've seen a bit of the diagrams, right,
and context and all the stuff you love.
And then there's the third sort of big piece of Drake
is the mathematical program interface.
Because I believe that the language
that you want to talk to your multi-body plant
is the language of optimization.
And so you could find these pieces in different toolboxes.
But having them in the one toolbox,
I can easily say, make me a cost or constraint
based on that robot.
And I can do things that I wouldn't be able to do
if they were separate.
OK, so the code looks pretty simple.
You say, like, make a new mathematical program.
I want to have two decision variables.
I'm going to add a constraint.
Like, this is x0 plus x1 equals 1.
That's a linear constraint.
x0 less than x1, that's also a linear constraint.
I can write them both in the form of that.
I can add a cost, like x0 squared plus x1 squared, solve.
OK?
And behind the scenes, what it does
is it examines the costs and constraints
that you've given it and tries to call the best solver.
It has a bunch of commercial solvers
that are back behind it.
If you're at MIT, most of those commercial solvers
are free with an academic license.
If you're not in education, they're really expensive.
It's kind of like, you learn how to use them,
and then you go off in industry.
And it's like, oh my gosh, those are costing a lot of money.
OK?
But that's the language that we use.
And I guess I have just one minute.
The code is pretty unintimidating, I think.
But our simple pseudo-inverse controller-- I
forgot to close the other one.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
You can write a little pseudo-inverse controller,
and then you can write a QP controller.
The one that just uses the pseudo-inverse
can still move through.
I just said a desired velocity.
It just moves through.
And then the differential IK, solved as a quadratic program,
can do all that.
But it can be robust to singularities and the like.
OK.
There's a bunch of other things that you
can do once you have this language of Jacobian control
as a mathematical program.
I'll list them.
And the details are in the notes.
But it's sort of nice to think about it.
So the linear constraints we talked about here
were just velocity constraints.
The decision variables in my pseudo-inverse-like controller,
my Jacobian controller, were the velocities.
And the objective was based on the Jacobian.
But you can actually add some amount of position constraints.
If you take a linear interpolation of your Jacobian
and try to say, what's my next position's going to be,
and you want them to not go past some linearization
of a collision constraint, you can do that, actually.
And similarly, you can take a derivative, a first derivative,
and put acceleration constraints.
So this becomes a super useful sort of language
to start adding richer and richer specifications of what
you want the controller to do, always locally.
But saying, given I want to follow this,
maybe I don't want to run into a wall,
and I don't want to exceed some accelerations.
That can all fit in the language.
And there's sort of right ways to write it,
so that it always has a solution.
You want to make sure you don't write constraints
that can potentially not have a solution.
And that's an important thing.
But mostly, that's packaged up.
And you can just call the differential IK system
and use that controller.
You actually used it if you played with that first chapter
notebook that half of you tried, and the rest of you
made me cry.
But if you did, you might have gone to the limit.
And then the IK solver said, you've got no solution.
That's because it was a simple form of the IK.
But the full form actually is robust to that.
OK, good.
See you Thursday.
Yeah?
Just when you were showing us the green thing,
so the green thing is you're saying it's a plus function.
and the class/objective is the velocity.