This is a quick trick that I just mentioned here.
But do you know, this is not a Drake specific thing.
This is just a GitHub thing.
And I guess Microsoft, I think, bought GitHub.
I'm not wrong about that.
But if you have any GitHub URL, you
have just GitHub open in your browser,
and you want to search the code, browse the code,
just replace the GitHub with GitHub 1S,
and it'll pull up a Visual Studio client in your browser.
And you can just quickly search and whatever.
So if you want to quickly poke around in the source code
for Drake, even if you're not super comfortable in C++,
there's often use cases of all the different methods
are all searchable inside there.
And even the C++ and Python syntax is not very different,
possibly to a fault. Good.
OK, so today I want to launch into the bigger conversation
about control for manipulation.
We started it by talking about manipulator control last time.
But I want to go from manipulator control last time
to the more full discussion of feedback
control for manipulation.
And let me make sure that distinction is clear,
because it looks kind of the same words.
Let me just make sure my intent is clear,
even if you might recommend some better words for it.
But when we were talking about manipulator control,
this was only controlling the robot.
And that was important.
That made a lot of things a lot easier.
Remember, we were using-- the reason
I call it manipulator control is it
leans so heavily on the manipulator equations, which
was just my mass times acceleration equals
the sum of the forces, which looked like mq v dot.
It has a particular form in the manipulator equations,
but something like this.
Or this was the mass times acceleration terms.
This is gravity force.
This was maybe damping or friction or other things.
Importantly, this was my torque input.
These were maybe my contact forces
or other applied forces that were
described in a Cartesian frame.
OK, and we worked with those equations a bunch last time.
You could also-- I mean, so I hope
you see that as mass times acceleration
is the sum of the forces.
You could also see this as just a differential equation, which
looks like f of xu, where my x is q and v.
And so this is just the equation for x dot.
This is half of the equation for x dot.
So you could say I would write this as-- that equation
is similarly v dot is f of qvu.
The other one that I need is that q dot is just v.
And that together is my upside down x dot.
OK, but there's a bunch of things
that this distinction of only control the robot
was baked into what we did there.
So in particular, the way I've written it here,
I had that the dimension of q equals the dimension of v,
at least for my revolute joint robots,
equals the dimension of u.
And even more than that, just the way I wrote in u
is it entered linearly like this.
Well, it always enters linearly, but there's
no modifiers there.
So it just came in.
And you can use any u to directly control v, v dot.
So that-- I teach a whole class on the difference
between fully actuated and underactuated,
but that makes these equations a fully actuated system.
And it's a particularly easy one to control in that form.
For instance, we saw that PD control worked.
We saw inverse dynamics control, stiffness control.
We saw a bunch of things that worked pretty easily, in part
because I had u that had direct control on v dot.
Also, this was one important point.
A second important point is that MQ and all these other terms
were known, or at least estimated, pretty well.
Let's say estimated well.
OK.
In practice, we have good system identification tools
that if I have an EWA or a Frank or some other robot,
I can move it around a little bit.
I can get very accurate estimates of M.
And in fact, KUKA has done that for us.
And they are doing the low level control that's
canceling that out for us.
OK, there are things that can make that control a little
easier, like torque limits and-- sorry,
a little more interesting, like torque limits or other bits.
But out of the box, that was a class of control problems
that we know a lot about and we have very good solutions for.
We can command fast trajectories and track them very accurately.
We can control contact forces pretty accurately.
But that is not representative of the bigger problem
of feedback control for manipulation.
So the bigger problem is to not just control
the state of the robot, but to control
the state of the robot and, more importantly,
the state of the world.
And a lot of those assumptions that
were fundamental in the way we wrote our controllers
become no longer true.
And I want to spend a little time talking about the ways
that those are not true and the ways that those complicate
control.
OK, so whereas before we had x.
Was-- let me just say q robot, maybe,
and v robot was our state before.
Now we're going to at least something
that has, in that example, the state of the brick
in the state space.
But unfortunately, our u is still just u robot.
I picked up more degrees of freedom
that I'm trying to control, but I didn't actually
pick up more actuators by which to control it.
OK, so that is now another differential equation,
which I could write as my same sort of v dot is f of q v u.
It's still a differential equation in all of those,
but the dimension of q is now greater, strictly greater,
than the dimension of u.
And that makes control a lot more interesting, a lot harder.
So that's where you come into underactuated systems.
OK, but that's not the only way that the problem
got a lot more interesting, if we start controlling--
trying to control the world.
There's a bunch more, and I just kind of want to talk through them
and make sure we appreciate those.
So even if we assume perfect perception--
so let's ignore the perception problem for a second.
So let's say that I have a perception system that's
reading my cameras or whatever, my perception system that's
outputting some estimate of my state.
And perfect perception for me means that x hat is just outputting x directly.
In simulation, we could just be using the cheat port
and going-- asking multibody, what is the true state?
OK, so still the problem is rich because it's underactuated,
but also because the only way-- if you look at the equations,
u on the robot is what you get to control.
Your goal is to control, let's say, q brick.
If you look at the way those equations come together,
the only way that u gets over to control q
is through the contact forces.
The equations of motion are, in some sense, decoupled.
They're only coupled through the contact forces.
So you have to do the control through the contact forces.
OK, so if I were to-- when I do write the equations of motion
for that robot plus brick system, it actually
still looks like the manipulator equations.
Those equations are still valid.
But there's an extra set of equations.
Let me put a little b underneath all of these.
There's a new set of equations for the brick variables.
You can write force equals mass times acceleration for this,
too.
You have the gravity of the brick.
B is for brick.
OK.
I also have the robot ones.
And the whole thing together is one big set of equations
that I simulate with my integration methods.
They are beautifully decoupled.
Like, as a structure you'd want in your equations
to make your math better and stuff like this,
it's beautiful that these equations actually
don't depend on the robot.
And these equations don't depend on the brick,
except for the one extra thing, which
is that the forces here on the robot at C
have to be equal and opposite of the forces on the brick.
There's one extra constraint that couples them together,
which is that those two are equal and opposite.
But if you think now, as the job--
like, before what we were doing, right,
when we were working with those equations,
is we would choose a u that would cancel out some dynamics,
put in some spring-like dynamics to make
it feel like an impedance or a stiffness.
Or there was a bunch of tricks we did.
Those are not readily available now,
because the only place that my u came in
was in the robot equations, my control input.
And the only way that those u's get through to the other side
is through the forces.
Is that clear?
And those forces are fickle.
They're subject to a friction cone constraint.
They turn off if you're not actually touching things.
That's kind of annoying.
You can push, but you can't pull unless you
got a suction gripper.
So this is not as direct of a way
to control those variables as just having a torque directly
on the motor.
And that complicates.
That means if I want to start having any effect on the brick,
I have to touch the brick.
I mean, that's obvious in the physical interpretation.
And it's visible here in the equations of motion
by seeing that the only way that that happens
is if these forces become non-zero.
And that's how it goes across.
The fact that those are not only intermittent,
it makes things non-smooth because they
go from sticking to sliding, or you weren't touching
and then you are touching.
There's all kinds of interesting stuff
that happens with that interface.
So those are two big ones.
We're suddenly going, if we want to control the world
and think about it as a feedback control problem,
then we have to think about it being under-actuated
and we have to think about the control through contact.
But wait, there's more.
It's still harder.
So I'm going to spend a little time making
you see how hard it is, and then we're
going to try to hopefully make it look easy again.
But that way, hopefully we appreciate
at the end why the thing that makes it look easy
is surprising, I would say.
Unfortunately, perception is not perfect.
So if I think about the role of my perception system that's
taking, let's say, cameras in perception,
even if I'm trying to estimate the state of both
the robot and the brick, the way that the perception system
makes errors is pretty non-trivial.
And you've seen that already.
You've seen, for instance, ICP works spectacularly well,
and then it doesn't.
And it's not that this is a little bit off,
but it would just give you complete garbage on one frame
if it loses track, for instance.
And that's true of many camera-based perception
systems.
They can often work spectacularly well,
but then fail catastrophically.
So a lot of our traditional controls,
you might try to say that this variable maybe
has Gaussian noise on it or something like that.
And you could think about this as part of a Kalman filter
framework.
You know that.
But perception systems make very non-Gaussian types of errors.
In particular, if you have a linear Gaussian system,
if my equations happens to be linear
and my noise happened to be Gaussian,
those are not linear equations.
Those are non-linear equations.
And hidden inside there, there's sines and cosines and the like.
They're not linear.
And the system was Gaussian, then I
could say that if x hat was just sort of the expected
value of x already, we're in pretty good shape.
And maybe I have to also-- I want
the variance for linear Gaussian.
You don't actually need even the variance.
But maybe the variance of x can be a useful thing
to estimate, too.
And even though those equations are not linear Gaussian,
if you're just controlling the robot but not the object,
then we saw cases where we could use feedback
to make the equations look very linear.
And in fact, these linear Gaussian tools
that have grown up in control theory
work really pretty well for a robot.
It's pretty reasonable to think about estimating
just the mean of the joint positions and velocities
and possibly having a covariance of the joints and joint
velocities.
But once you add in the brick, all bets are off.
Because suddenly you're going-- your only sensors measuring
the brick, unless you're in a strangely instrumented
environment, are like your cameras, maybe your contact
sensors and the like.
And those are not sensors that give you sort of nice Gaussian
noise properties.
And you remember that, right?
So we talked about, for instance,
when we were talking about perception,
the types of uncertainty you might have of a perception.
I was going to bring a coffee mug down.
I forgot.
But if you can see the handle of the mug,
then maybe you have pretty small uncertainty.
But even if your sensors were perfect
and your perception system was doing as best as it possibly
could, if the handle of the mug is not visible to you,
then you cannot estimate the orientation of the mug
with absolute certainty.
You have to somehow communicate that I only
know the orientation of the mug up to some uncertainty
ellipses.
Partial observability also causes non-Gaussian uncertainty.
How many people know what a POMDP is?
A partially observable Markov decision process.
If you like POMDPs, you could just say it's a POMDP, right?
I'm not advertising this as a path of happiness.
So if you don't know what a POMDP is, you're all good.
It's useful to-- I mean, I do think
the language of POMDPs is very powerful
and helps us understand the problem.
But I'm not going to give a whole lecture on it right now.
OK, right.
But more generally, if I think of my system as a POMDP--
I'll give you the language.
It's a partially observable Markov decision process.
It's a fancy way to say that I have a dynamical system that
has some stochasticity, and I don't get to see all
of the states directly.
OK.
But for those of you that do know what a POMDP is,
I want to connect to that real quick.
And I think in general, in the general POMDP case,
what we should say is that the output of our perception system
should be not just x, but a whole probability
distribution over x.
And that's the kind of thing that COSNET tries to output,
and a lot of perception systems these days will try to output.
This would be like a probability distribution or a belief
distribution over x.
From the mathematics of partially observable Markov
decision processes, we know that that is a reasonable answer.
That's a complete answer.
If I can put out an entire probability distribution,
and if I can write a controller that
can consume that entire distribution
and make good decisions, then we know
that is sufficient for making optimal decisions,
even in a partially observable setting.
But this requirement of outputting
an entire probability distribution
is a large requirement.
And in particular, designing a controller
that can reason about that is very hard.
OK.
It's also sort of interesting that it's not--
I'm going to say it, I guess, later.
But having a perception system that
gives me the complete output of all the possible states
of the world is sufficient to make optimal decisions.
But over and over and over again,
we've seen people write great controllers,
like spot opening the door, or I call them the robot whisperers,
write incredible controllers that do not
use this as an input, but use a much smaller
amount of information from the observations as input.
So even though this is sufficient to be optimal,
it's probably a lot more than you need.
And that's an important big theme.
So this is a mathematically powerful tool chain,
but it's probably more than we really need or want.
I would say, though, that even the POMDP language,
as I've written it there, can be insufficient for the manipulation
problem, because it made one particular-- there's
one place where it has a weakness.
Everything is a POMDP, I give you that.
But it's a POMDP in some state space.
And if I've chosen some representation of my state, x,
and written a probability distribution over x,
I may or may not have gotten the right state.
So even P of x might not capture the true state.
and this is a-- I actually mean this
in a deep and important way.
I'm not trying to be flippant about it.
I think most of the control theory that we've done
or sort of in life is assumed that we know at least what
the state representation is.
That you know that, for instance, the joint angles
of my robot, the joint velocities of my robot,
the quaternion plus translation that specifies
the pose of the brick plus its spatial velocities,
that that is the right state.
And if I write a distribution over state,
then I can solve that.
Then I've somehow solved the problem.
But that broke down when we started
thinking about category level manipulation.
As soon as you say you have uncertainty
about the geometry of the object,
then again, suddenly, where does the uncertainty
about the geometry fit in x if I just
had x being the positions and velocities?
So x somehow needs to encode uncertainty about geometry.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
Maybe even uncertainty about the mass.
Not for that particular type of task.
You didn't need to know the mass.
You just needed to know the geometry, really.
But certainly there is tasks like the force control tasks
we talked about where the mass estimates are
important and the like.
And this is, I think, maybe one of the biggest things
that we've done.
We've railroaded ourselves a little bit
in the sort of classic control.
For robots, we say, OK, we're going
to estimate a distribution over the possible joint positions
and velocities, world positions and velocities.
And we haven't sort of naturally encoded geometry and mass
uncertainty and the like.
So people are really excited these days about,
let's say, well, maybe I've got an implicit representation
of geometry.
And maybe if I have a nerf or a sine distance function
or something like this, and I can
use that in my state representation,
then I can somehow write controllers
that work for many geometries.
And that's a huge, big topic that's hugely important.
But even that can fail.
So even if I had a beautiful way to write x with positions,
velocities of the robot, and the brick,
and then I have the geometry included and the mass included,
there's still-- I have only a handful of examples
that I always use.
But now, what if I'm just doing this?
OK, I could write positions and velocities of all the pieces,
but the number of pieces is breaking.
And the contact mechanics, that's hard stuff.
That's kind of like, if I start writing that down and asking
about the dynamics, how they evolve,
and the state space evolves and stuff,
that just kind of breaks down.
The way we would write that control problem breaks down.
Makes my multi-body head explode.
This one does too, right?
I mean, if I want to do--
I consider this like a pinnacle of manipulation.
We all do it a couple times a day.
But that's incredible.
But what is the state of the shoelace?
Yes?
Do you have the answer?
That would be amazing.
I'm sorry, Rob.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK, great.
Awesome.
So let me come back to that.
I'll just do my three things, then I'll
come back and try to answer that.
So when you get to deformable objects,
then suddenly the state representation question
gets really rich again too.
So we use methods from finite elements and stuff.
There's ways to represent the state in order
to simulate it, of course.
But is that the right state to build a controller?
I always talk about spreading peanut butter on toast.
There's a few of them I feel I kind of capture
most of the things.
What is the state of the peanut butter?
That's ridiculous, right?
But that task should be very easy.
The way we've typically written down feedback control
makes it seem extremely hard.
And people clearly have these strategies
where you can kind of feel when the peanut butter clumps up.
And there's a lot of, I think, tactile feedback
in there, visual feedback that's happening.
Probably there's not a finite element or granular media
model of the peanut butter in my head.
And the last one I always talk about is buttoning my shirt.
So this is a how-to button your shirt.
But if you think about what is required for control,
we button our shirts all the time.
But probably the first step of buttoning my shirt
should not be to completely estimate
the entire state of my shirt.
I have probably a very nice local policy
that works with feedback on my fingers or whatever.
It's not very visual, I don't think.
OK, so there's something that the mature view of control
isn't doing.
And that's what I want to talk about today.
So Robby, to your question, why is it-- did I say it's a POMDP
instead of an MDP?
I think there are versions of the manipulation problem
that-- and maybe when I put the red brick with cameras
all around, I think an MDP would probably
describe that very well.
But if I were to take my coffee mug and occlude it,
put it behind here, then suddenly
partial observability has a very physical manifestation.
And it happens all the time in manipulation.
If I have a hand and I go to pick something up,
the hand almost always occludes my head-mounted sensors.
It's really annoying.
It's like the time where you want the information the most,
you've occluded yourself.
And so people say, oh, I'll put a camera on my hand.
But then cameras get blind when you put them
too close to an object.
So partial observability, even if the world
didn't start with occlusions and the like,
it's a real problem in manipulation.
So I think POMDP is the more general framework for that.
Thank you for asking.
It's good.
OK, so maybe you get my point.
It's a hard control problem, even
if you knew the state space.
You probably have to think about uncertainty
over that state space.
And guess what?
We don't know the state space.
It's a lot of interesting problems.
And even trying to know the state space
seems like a tall ask.
OK, so what do we do about it?
The hope is that some of these tools for machine learning
are going to help out.
And they've done incredible things
over the last few years.
And they've kind of come in from the other end.
So this is maybe coming from the multibody equations
up and adding all the complexity.
And there's another set of tools that have come from--
let's start with just images and start working back
towards control.
And I would say the field is kind of working this way
and working this way.
And we haven't quite met in the middle yet.
But I'm optimistic.
We're pointing at each other and coming more and more together.
So if I'm going to do machine learning for it,
what's the machine learning problem that I need to solve?
So if I think about the multibody case again,
let's just distinguish a couple of the different control
approaches.
So if I have my plant here, I'll do it
in block diagram language.
And I have y here.
These are my cameras, for instance, my sensors.
More generally, cameras.
The way I've always talked about this
is that I have some internal state inside my system.
You have some inputs.
You have some outputs.
That's exactly what Drake makes you say.
I've got some state dynamics.
I've got an output.
I've got an input.
The output of the, let's say, the manipulation station
is like the cameras.
And you typically don't have direct access to x.
And that's what I'm doing with my perception system.
And maybe I'm outputting something like x hat.
This is my planning and control.
But I'll just write control for now.
That goes to u and around.
So I would call this state estimation
plus full state feedback architecture,
where this is my state estimate and this is my full state
feedback here, which takes x hat as an input.
The POMDP belief space planning in the language
of the diagrams here is a superset of that.
But if I think about my perception
outputting an entire probability distribution over x,
then I have to write some controller that
knows how to take that, do something more than just assume
I have x given to me, but I've got an entire distribution
over x.
This is what I get in my sort of POMDP belief space
architecture.
Belief space is just another name
for my estimate over x, my probability distribution.
And in both of these settings, the perception system
maybe could be a Bayes filter, if you know about filters.
Or a Kalman filter is a simple version of a Bayes filter,
just to connect those words, if those are
something you've thought about.
But like I said, this is more than you need for control.
And I remind us of the controller
that was written for this is extremely robust.
It sort of has a sense that someone could push me
with a hockey stick implicitly.
And it's an incredibly good controller.
I don't know that it's optimal in any way,
but it's highly functional.
And it is not trying to estimate a full belief
over the possible environments.
It's not trying to estimate with high accuracy
the angle of the door handle or the door.
Using a much smaller summary, Andy and colleagues--
I know it's very distracting-- wrote a beautiful controller
that used the sensors more directly.
They didn't try to estimate the full state of the world.
And it works really well.
So there's some sense, I think, which
is that that picture makes the problem look too hard.
So the way we want to think about it today,
to sort of launch into our further discussion
about control, is to go to the other extreme
and appreciate that there's another extreme here, which
is, what if I just take my plant--
I have my observations coming out y--
and I'm going to go directly from y to u,
even if these are cameras.
And I'll call this output feedback.
It's not my name.
It's an output feedback control, as opposed to the state
feedback control.
When y are pixels, or camera images, let's say, u are torques.
People like to call it pixels to torques.
It's a really funny-- a lot of people say pixels to torques.
Some people say it like, it's awesome, pixels to torques.
And some people are like, pixels to torques
would be the thing no one should ever do.
So it's a highly volatile term.
But pixels to torques for self-driving
sounds kind of scary.
But it's a very powerful possible framework.
And in particular, if this is a kind of a high rate--
if this controller updates frequently,
then I would also call it a visual motor policy.
In the manipulation space, we'll call these visual motor
policies.
And that's kind of a weird caveat
that I'm putting in there.
But I just want to distinguish it from--
you could make a diagram that looks a little bit like that,
that would be a little bit more of a sense, plan, act,
classical architecture.
And the type of policies I want to think about today
are ones that are looking at the camera all the time
and constantly making decisions.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
So this, of course, should just encompass those.
I could take both of those, write a diagram around it,
and call it an output feedback.
And that's true.
But I think this version of the picture
opens up the door to different architectures that
don't impose that structure.
So that's the big question is, what
is the right architecture for that kind of-- how should we
write that down?
How should we describe that output feedback policy?
And then how do we find its parameters?
Once we choose a class of possible output feedback
policies, how do we find those parameters?
Is that setup clear?
[WRITING ON BOARD]
The exciting thing, of course, would
be if we can go from y to u without ever having
to pick an x.
As soon as a human picks an x to represent
our intermediate computation in, we've
assumed something about the state,
and it's not going to spread peanut butter and toast.
And that-- I don't actually like peanut butter and toast.
But there's something similar to that
that I would like a robot to do.
OK, here's my opening bid.
What if we just say I want my output
to be a direct mapping from-- whoops.
You could have told me.
How about that?
A direct mapping from camera images, let's say,
directly to torques.
And that seems like the architectures
that know how to take camera images as input
tend to be neural.
So I'll go ahead and say that's a neural network.
Probably a deep net, convolutional,
or whatever architecture you like.
OK.
This architecture, if we were to just write
a function of a feedforward network that
goes from an image in to a control torque out,
the control theorists would call that a static output feedback.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
Like for a linear system, it would
look like instead of negative kx,
if you thought about this, it's something
that looks like this.
Would be a direct linear mapping from observations to inputs.
And it turns out, although control theory
knows a lot about the static output feedback problem,
most of what they know is that it's hard.
That even finding this for a linear optimal control problem,
finding that k is actually an NP-hard problem.
So that's not a good sign.
But there is a lot known about it.
But let's ignore for a minute the fact
that maybe finding the optimal parameters are hard.
We'll come back to that.
But let's just say, what is this class of policies
capable of doing?
Let's say I had an oracle that would just tell me,
these are the weights that are the best
controller in this class.
You've chosen a number of layers,
a number of activation units, and stuff like that.
And then I'm just going to tell you what the weights
and biases should be.
The best possible.
What can that do?
And what can't it do?
What can it do?
What can't it do?
[INAUDIBLE]
It can't deal with occlusion.
So if you had a frame that-- if you said,
reach for the red brick, and I put the red brick, let's say,
behind my laptop screen, then that
would be uncertainty or something,
control through contact.
If I had the red brick behind my laptop screen,
I said, go ahead and pick it up, then that kind of controller
doesn't have any mechanism to sort of reason about what
should it do to pick that up.
If you were to watch me take the red brick
and put it down there, then you would
know there's a red brick there.
But if your controller is only able to look
at the most recent image in order to make its decisions,
it doesn't have that power that you have.
It has no memory, no history.
So despite the incredible power of deep networks,
a deep network-- there's a bunch of things
that this isn't going to be able to do.
Occlusions is a good one.
What's another one?
Even if there's no occlusions, there's
some things this can't do.
Let's say, why is an image?
Almost all of you are throwing things, or catching things,
or smashing things.
You can't get mass.
So that's right.
I mean, so really, any dynamics.
So you could argue that you could get a mass
from a statics point of view.
You could know from a static equilibrium type analysis
something about mass.
But you can't know velocity, for instance.
So if I show you a single frame of a ball,
and I show you another frame of a ball,
and you're only thinking about that,
the fact that it's coming towards me or away from me
is completely-- I'm oblivious.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Perfect, yes.
So there's a natural-- that's a great question.
So Jenny says, what if I have a history?
So this would be my second bid.
Would be, what if I said that u at time n
is a function of the image at time n,
but maybe a image at time n minus 1, maybe some n minus m,
or something like that?
So that you could do.
You could even also do some occlusions.
Although, if I take the red brick, and I show it to you,
and I put it behind here, you better
pick it up in less than m steps.
Otherwise, you're going to forget.
So but certainly, 2 should be enough,
depending on how noisy things are, to estimate a velocity.
And more than 2 maybe would allow
you to estimate a velocity more robustly,
because you'd have enough to estimate covariances
and the like.
OK.
So this is great.
So this is also something that we
know a lot about from more general systems theory.
This would be a finite impulse response model.
There's different names for it, but if it was a linear system,
it would be a finite impulse response model, FIR.
People remember FIR filters and the like from-- you
take signals and systems?
Yeah?
Right, you could call it a moving average filter,
or something like that.
OK?
And we know what it can do and what it can't do.
In particular, it's got a finite impulse.
It won't remember things more than capital M,
and you have to make an M. When Y is an image,
that could get expensive if M gets too big.
So for long horizon tasks, this might not be a good choice.
But for short horizon tasks, it's a perfectly good way
to take and give some limited form of memory
to a neural network, feedforward neural network
architecture.
But I also really like this, because even though you might
not think of it this way, when I start thinking about it
this way-- and maybe not if I called it a neural network
with an image in and whatever-- but when I write it this way,
and I think of it as an impulse response filter,
then you realize that this is actually just an opening--
even this one is true.
This is a dynamical system.
What I want you to start thinking about
is that the control policy should
be a dynamical system, right?
It's a dynamical system that takes
a time series of Y's in, outputs a time series of U's.
And U equals pi of Y is one form.
This is another form.
But more generally, you could make an IR filter,
an infinite impulse response filter.
You can do a state space model.
And that's exactly what's happening in the neural network
world too.
And I just want to make sure you see it that way.
Because we know a lot about what each of those models
can and can't do.
And sometimes that gets a little bit
hidden in the weights of the neural network, for instance.
So you could do an IIR filter, like a simple change that's
an infinite impulse response filter.
Or more generally, be called an autoregressive moving
average with exogenous inputs.
Oh my god, I'm not going to write that.
But RMAX, people say, that's like a cool thing
to say at parties, right?
This would be like an RMAX system
that would say, if I wanted to say that U of n--
if you want something to have an infinite impulse response,
you want it to have arbitrary history.
It turns out you don't have to do much more than that.
Jenny's proposal was good.
And I can just change it just a little bit.
And maybe she even meant this.
But if I also put in U of n minus 1,
and then Y of n minus 1, U of n minus 2,
if I just cycle back my outputs, then that system--
it depends, of course, on the weights, whatever--
that system can have an infinite impulse response.
That's a neural architecture you could pick
that would have more representational power
than that, from finite to infinite.
And the linear systems equivalent of that
is super well understood.
More generally, you could write a state space model.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
Where you could say that U of neural network is--
let me call it that U of n is a function of X of n.
And X of pi n plus 1 is some other function of pi n
with Y coming in.
I could have a neural network that has an internal state.
And I could allow that state to evolve
with another neural network, for instance.
And then I could just have my output
be a function of that state.
That would be a state space model.
Linear state space models are AX plus BU stuff, standard fair.
And that's just what a recurrent neural network is doing.
For instance, if you know what LSTMs are,
long short-term memory.
Yeah?
That's just another representation
of a dynamical system.
And it has representational power.
It similarly has infinite impulse responses.
And it can have a long history.
That's most notable here is if I compare this versus this,
this has the representational power
to remember things for arbitrary durations.
So if I take that red brick and I put it behind my laptop,
then you could just say, I'm going to devote one of the Xs
to remember that guy put a red brick behind the laptop.
And a year later, you come back and say,
I remember where that red brick is.
Because you've given yourself that power of memory.
This is a scratch pad for memory.
And it can evolve in beautiful continuous equations.
It can be a less beautiful neural network,
but still exceptionally powerful.
But those are standard things.
The Kalman filter state estimation
that I talked about here fits into this model.
If I said that x hat, I'd call it x pi here.
That is certainly similar.
But it's way cooler if x pi doesn't have any presupposition
that x pi should be an estimate of the original state.
If no human said what x hat is, but the learning system
decided to use x however it needed
to reproduce the input/output of the system.
So this suddenly, if we ask how do you
find the parameters of this input/output system,
whether it's static, FIR, IIR, or state space,
then that becomes a second question.
And a good answer to this would be one
where you don't have to say what x hat is, or what x pi is.
OK?
The simplest form of this would be an imitation learning form.
In particular, I would say imitation learning,
broadly speaking, slightly oversimplification.
But I'd say there's two big classes of imitation learning.
One is inverse optimal control.
And that's not what I'm going to talk about now.
But I don't want to pretend that I'm talking about all of-- oops.
That was pretty funny.
Revealed my biases, I guess.
[LAUGHS]
And the other one I'll call behavior cloning.
OK?
Just to say that-- I mean, imitation learning also
is called learning from demonstrations.
There's a bunch of buzzwords, but they're all the same thing.
Roughly.
Sometimes you'll just see LFB.
OK?
But let's think about the behavior cloning
version of the problem.
Behavior cloning is actually an old idea that-- I went back
and looked where it started.
I found '95.
You know, it's an old idea.
It's cool now.
But it's an old idea of a 1995 paper, just behavior cloning.
And really, this is a simple approach where you say,
I'm going to treat control design as basically
a system identification or a simple supervised learning
problem.
,
So if I have a human, let's say, that's
trying to control my system, and I have a policy here
that I'm trying to fit.
It's a dynamic output feedback policy.
If I watch the human operate the task,
and I record the y's and the u's,
you know, the actions that the human took
and the observations that they had available,
then I can try to do supervised learning to make
the policy do the same thing.
When it's a recurrent network policy,
it's a slightly more interesting supervised learning problem,
but we know a lot about how to train recurrent networks
for sequence learning like this.
So I don't think many people would
say this is a final answer, but this is a really interesting
way to start looking at the problem.
And in particular, I think it lets us sort out
a lot of the architectural questions of how should we
represent our policy?
How valuable is it to use cameras at 10 hertz
versus 1/10 of a hertz?
Yeah, every 10 seconds, right?
And asks a lot of those questions.
But a natural question for this, before I
get into the details of how we do that,
is how do you even get that input, right?
So for robots and mobile manipulation and manipulation,
as deep learning started getting good,
people started coming up with more and more clever ways
to capture humans doing the task where
you didn't want to watch-- if I watched a human doing this,
like on YouTube, if I want to watch a human rolling dough,
that is a hard problem still to map from a human's control
torques and a human's real observations
into a robot actions.
It's much easier if you can get a human to operate the robot.
And then you watch directly the torques
that are being applied from the human's controller.
And maybe if you give the human exactly the inputs
that the robot's getting, then now you
have exactly the input/output data that goes to the human.
And you can try to just turn that into a supervised learning
problem.
The people have been making cooler and cooler versions
of this.
How many people know that the X-Prize, the Avatar X-Prize
happened this weekend?
Yeah?
Right?
How cool is that?
So just this weekend-- so the X-Prize
is like they make these grand challenges about improving
the world.
And they picked a robot example this year.
And it just happened on Friday and Saturday.
I won't play the whole thing.
But it happens that the way it worked
was they had roboticists that were the judges.
This is my friend Jerry Pratt, who's driving.
This is the winning company.
He was the best driver, apparently,
and had the system that won by Sven Benke and company.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- --and will involve a lot of operator skills to complete.
- OK, so there's this whole mock setup
where he had to drive up.
He was only given even the context of the task
by talking to somebody who told him
what the rules of the game were.
He says, you're going to have to go over here.
You're going to have to pick up the cylinder.
And only one of the cylinders is heavy
and should be placed on this other spot.
So you have to actually use your force feedback
through the avatar in order to know how to complete the task.
There was another one, he says, where
you're going to pick up some moon rocks or something.
And one of them has a particular texture.
And you have to put the one with a particular texture over here.
And there was a series of pretty complicated things.
And-- I'll forward a bit.
He talked for a long time, I guess.
- If you haven't noticed, it's pretty quick on the commute.
That was the HOV lane.
So they've got right through--
- I'll try to turn that guy off.
Yeah.
Yeah, so this is the one where he had to pick up something
that was a particular weight.
And he's strapped into a series of-- that was too light,
so he threw it away.
OK.
Now he picks up the next one.
But he's driving-- these are actually just two panda robots
that are in kind of like gravity comp mode.
So they can be used like this, like a teach mode.
And he's got an exoskeleton hand.
And he's driving this thing around and doing
super complicated tasks, right, with force feedback,
haptic feedback.
And he completed the entire course.
I don't think they were sure that anybody
was going to complete the entire course.
But he did, and they did, and they did extremely well.
So you should go back and watch the long version of that.
One of them that I really like, there
was actually an entry by Northeastern that came in third.
That-- Northeastern, just across the river.
They had this awesome setup with a dexterous hand here.
And this is in their lab, but they did very well
in the competition too.
Similar things.
Pick up the heavy thermos.
He's able to do all kinds of stuff.
He like shakes hands.
OK, he shakes hands.
And off to the side, this is what it looks like, right?
He's seeing through the robot eyes
and wearing this cool exoskeleton.
[INAUDIBLE]
It's awesome, right?
I want one of those in my lab.
They're super cool.
If we have time at the end, I'll show you my version.
Not as cool, but you can use it on DeepNote.
It's a crowdsourced teleoperation,
which is a thing, by the way.
People have started companies saying,
we're just going to crowdsource tele-op
and learn how to control your factories, for instance.
I think that's a super interesting business model.
OK, so let me tell you a little bit
about maybe how you would architect that visual motor
policy and how you do some of this behavior cloning.
So there's a kind of a canonical architecture for these things.
You tend to have two components.
You have your image coming in, and you
have some big, deep network, like a ResNet, whatever,
something that's trained on ImageNet,
pre-trained on ImageNet, for instance,
and is good at going from pixels through millions of units
into some other representation.
And there's a lot of different choices
for how you pick the output representation.
We've talked a bit about the rise
of self-supervised learning as a way
to maybe train a feature representation z.
You could just look at objects from two different angles
and label them to be the same.
And somehow, that can self-supervise a network
to represent something important about the scene.
But your choice of z, that's where
all the interesting work is.
People are asking, what is the right z for manipulation?
But it's interesting that because
of the computational burden of training a perception system
and because of the wealth of just purely perceptual training
data, people typically separate out
that massive perception system from a relatively much smaller
policy representation.
So the neural network that goes from z
and maybe my joint encoders of my robot into my torques
tends to be like a three-layer network with 255 units.
So I kind of joke when people talk about deep reinforcement
learning or whatever, but then they only use three layers.
It drives me crazy.
But that's a very standard architecture.
In fact, I would say--
I've talked to people, and I said,
how many hidden layers do you use?
How big is your-- what's your architecture or whatever?
And they're like, well, jeez, we started using three layers
and 255 units like six years ago, and we never changed it.
It's just kind of baked in.
All the papers use exactly the same architecture.
OK, that is the architecture that did the kind of stuff
I showed you early on.
This was an imitation learning pipeline
that made super rich visual motor policies for doing things
like putting hats on a rack, picking up the plates,
switching sugar boxes, or whatever.
And compared to the previous-- this
was the first one we had done.
Other people had been doing visual motor stuff,
but this is the one that really convinced me.
I had to do it ourselves, right?
But the robustness that you get out of a demo like that,
compared to things that are estimating
the location of the sugar box, which tends to happen only
when you don't have conclusions, and then maybe you
make a long-term plan and you execute,
this is using high-rate feedback from the cameras,
trained with imitation learning, which everybody, I would say,
thinks that's an initial startup thing, but not a-- well,
some people would say it's a long-term answer.
But when you're in the lab and you're pushing the shoe
and it's pushing back, and it's so compelling.
It is so much more compelling than the things we've done
before, right?
Where if someone came up and moved the shoe,
the robot would be like, still pick up
where the shoe used to be.
And then it would go through the entire task
and drop off the shoe.
And everybody's there like, the shoe is still on the table.
The airball robot videos are less with this.
Less.
Yes?
Why is it that everyone is using such small networks,
whether it's simple science?
They seem to be enough.
So the question was, why are people
using such small networks?
So I think in reinforcement learning,
that was a choice made early in reinforcement learning.
And I think the computational cost of getting enough samples
to train a bigger policy network might be significant.
So I think if you can get away with a small network--
and people have now seen that those small networks are
very capable.
So there hasn't been a huge push to make them bigger.
I think a lot of the heavy work is coming
from the perceptual side.
I think even in this imitation learning setting,
we're often in a setting where we
have large corpus of visual data.
And relatively, you want to minimize the number
of demonstrations required.
So having less expressive power in the policy
can be seen as an advantage.
Yeah?
Is there any difficulties in getting enough imitation data
to sample the full spectrums?
Yes.
But if they go--
I'm imagining it seems too good, maybe,
and doesn't get them the same interest value.
That's a great question.
So yeah.
So the question is, how do your demonstrations get coverage?
There's two aspects of that, I would say.
You want-- and I'll maybe even cover it a little bit
at the end.
But having a good enough demonstrator
is important, because if someone is a little bit random
and they take--
from the same image, they take two different actions,
then that is annoying.
It's not described as a function.
You have to learn multimodal representations and things
like that.
And that's a real problem.
The other question that you're talking about
is, if the human is only demonstrating
the sunny day behavior, then--
there's a very famous paper about this called Dagger,
which they made the point on a Mario Kart driving game.
But you're driving along in Mario Kart.
You're training.
It's by Drew Bagnell and Ross and a few other people.
Yeah, if you drive along and you only
see examples of the Mario Kart staying
in the middle of the road, and then as soon as you go,
your training data was just a little bit--
you didn't fit perfectly.
You slightly-- or you find a new situation.
You're a little bit off the side of the road,
and you never saw data when you're
driving off the side of the road.
And it just goes, whoosh, right off the end.
And so the Dagger strategy, an older strategy
of teacher forcing, would be that you tend to not only
collect demonstrations, stop.
You would collect demonstrations,
fit an initial policy, and then allow the demonstrator
to try to correct the policy and have
a blended control for a little bit,
and then eventually let go.
So you allow the policy to make some mistakes.
The human now has corrective actions.
That's one of many several answers
to this sort of trying to get coverage
of the relevant distribution.
And that's a response to not trying
to cover every state, because that would be a hard problem.
Great question.
[INAUDIBLE]
So in that particular work, we used the dense correspondences
I told you about before as our Z.
So we would actually train dense descriptors,
like you did in your problem set.
And then we would identify a few not key points,
not labeled semantic key points, but just picked
a few random points in the color space, in D,
and then turn them into XYZ with our correspondence function.
We would use that for our lower level.
And that turned out to be, I think--
we tried to analyze against the other alternatives,
and it generated robust controllers
and lots of-- at a category level.
This is what it looked like.
So Pete had a mouse teleop at the time.
He was really good at it, actually.
But we did a couple different versions of it.
But on the order of 50 to 100 demonstrations,
Pete would just do in lab, flip a lot of shoes.
It was actually super useful, if anybody's
thinking about imitation learning for their project
or anything, to just set up the entire imitation learnings
pipeline in simulation, where it wasn't demanding
human users' input at all.
He wrote a simple controller in simulation
that used the full state feedback.
And then he just tried to clone that.
And make sure that that all worked.
And then you had unlimited demonstrations
for free, basically.
And you just tried to make sure that you
could capture the task.
It was using a recurrent network.
It needed a recurrent network for some of these tasks.
Although, even tasks where we felt
like technically a static feedback controller
would have worked well, we still saw better performance
from a recurrent network.
And this is sort of, Karamek, to your question,
is the generalization power of this.
So machine learning folks will talk about generalization
versus extrapolation.
There's absolutely no claims here of extrapolation.
So generalization would be kind of,
you're interpolating within the data set that you've seen.
And extrapolation would be, you're
able to do something beyond what you've seen in the data set.
And very much, the sort of every way
we could think of to make a two-dimensional plot,
you could kind of make the convex hull of the training
data.
And the robot worked really well when it was in the convex hull
and not so well when it was outside the convex hull.
And these demonstrations, I think
they were so compelling in lab.
And this is how we do dough rolling, for instance, at TRI.
And these are places where, again, a few years ago,
I wouldn't have even had an answer
to the question of, what's the state representation for dough?
How would I write a feedback controller for dough?
Or for noodles?
We haven't done peanut butter yet,
but we did do sauce spreading.
Again, this is kind of the peanut butter, right?
This is apparently how real chefs spread sauce.
It looked a little weird to me, but we actually
studied some chefs and then did it.
This is work by Siu-Wan Feng at TRI.
And that's a representational question
I wouldn't know how to answer, but we're still
getting good controllers out.
It's interesting.
This just came out the other day, so I put it in.
There's an article by one of the leads
at Google Brain for robotics.
He's talking about the push and pull
between reinforcement learning and behavior cloning.
And so BC is behavior cloning.
And then BC methods started to get good, really good.
These are links to all his papers.
So good that our best manipulation system today
uses mostly BC with a sprinkle of reinforcement learning
on top to perform high level action selection.
Today, less than 20% of our research investment
is on reinforcement learning.
It's actually the research runway for BC-based methods
feels more robust.
That's not what people would have predicted,
I think, a year ago.
Andy Zhang gave a talk here at MIT.
You hosted it, right?
He had-- the whole talk was good,
but the second slide was just-- captured this so well,
the imitation learning.
He says, how to make a rock star behavior cloning
demo on a real robot.
These are the steps.
First of all, collect your own expert data.
Don't trust anybody else to make it perfect.
So this is about multimodal demonstrations
and some of the subtleties you just asked about.
Avoid no action data.
That's a weird thing to say.
Try not to have anything in your data set
where you're not moving, because your robot will get stuck.
That's kind of-- it seems like something's wrong
with our formulation.
If I accidentally pause in my demonstration data,
everything breaks.
Still not working?
Collect more data, right?
Until extrapolation becomes interpolation.
And the last one's real, right?
It says, train and test on the same day,
because your setup might change tomorrow.
But given that-- and these, by the way, I linked to the seminar
and he's in slides.com, too, so you can even see his slides.
Yeah, but that's real, right?
So if you follow steps one through four,
you can make some of the best robot demos
that anybody's seen, right?
But it is important to understand its limitations.
He also talks about the hunger for data.
So some of the simpler demonstrations
were in the order 50.
He's got some really nice implicit behavior.
Someone's doing a project on implicit behavior cloning.
Some of my favorite examples of these feedback policies
for contact.
But that was an order 500 expert demonstrations.
And then some of the rich ones where
you're picking up and moving berries and stuff
was up to 5,000 expert demonstrations.
All right, so this is an opening discussion about control.
And I think exceptionally cool that you can do--
you can get a taste of what good control would look like.
We've learned that high rate feedback from cameras,
we didn't know how much we were missing it
until we saw what it could do.
And I think behavior cloning is a short-term path to study it.
And it works incredibly well on real robots,
given those caveats.
I would say, for me, it's a tool to study the problem
and come from the other direction
as I move up from understanding why underactuated and control
through contact and whatever is hard.
The misnomer that I don't want you to walk away
with this lecture from-- so the possible impression I could
give, but I don't want to give-- is that because the problem is
hard, you need to use learning.
That is one way to do it.
If I give you the equations of motion
and they're just complicated, there's
nothing about that that says you have to use learning.
I think the representational power of deep networks
is awesome.
But it's not clear you have to take samples in order
to optimize them.
There's many different ways to optimize them.
And we'll explore that over the next few weeks.
OK, I'm going to call it, but I'm
going to show you-- if anybody wants to stick around
for a minute, I did try-- in case some of you
found it useful for your projects,
I made it so you could play with game pads through MeshCat.
I'm going to play with a game pad through MeshCat
for just a few seconds as we wrap up.
All right, I'll actually do the non-manipulation one first,
because I think it's fun.
OK, this is-- OK, to be honest, I did it first because-- I
mean, I love you guys, but my kid
wanted to use it for FIRST Robotics.
So I was like, oh yeah, I thought hard
about the problem she was having.
I was like, you should use Drake, which is crazy.
That's totally-- but I was like, oh, I can help you,
but I'll do it in Drake.
OK, so this is a mecanum wheel base, right?
And it's simulating with the full physics.
So those are just ellipses.
The only way that it's applying torque--
it's applying torques to motors, doing velocity feedback
on the wheels.
And the only way it moves through the world
is through the contact forces between the mecanum wheels
and whatever.
And it's fun.
It's just fun to do that.
And you don't have to install Drake.
You just go on DeepNote.
And I mean, anybody can write a GameStick controller.
The only thing that was a little clever about it
is that we did it in JavaScript and plummet back
through the web sockets, because the JavaScript is
the only thing that you're running on your machine
when you're running on DeepNote.
So the only thing that could touch the gamepad
is the Meshcat browser.
Meshcat's listening for the gamepad if you wanted to
and allowing you to do that.
So then, of course, after I did that, I thought, oh,
I should do the manipulation station.
And I just added to the back of the-- so
if you want to use this for your projects or anything,
I made the manipulation station.
Teleop have one more version.
If you have a gamepad, pretty much any gamepad should work,
I think.
It's a pretty standard interface.
Oops, I forgot to press a button.
So you have to opt in with JavaScript.
It won't just read your gamepad without doing anything.
So you press the button once.
OK, here's the standard manipulation station.
Now I can drive it around with my gamepad.
I was saying, I don't know if it's like the-- there's
a bunch of tricks for mapping gamepad robustly
to real commands.
I've implemented maybe half of them or something.
I'm really bad at this.
I don't know if it's my brain to the gamepad that's bad
or the gamepad to the thing, but it's really hard to do.
OK, but I can definitely pick up a red brick.
It's not that bad.
So you guys could use this and make it better, hopefully.
Oh, I missed.
[LAUGHTER]
Yay.
Fun.
Not quite as cool as like avatar, but useful maybe.
I'm happy to take a couple questions.
I have to run today, but otherwise I'll
see you guys next week.
[BLANK_AUDIO]