[INAUDIBLE]
So the real problem is not that [INAUDIBLE]
I'm just asking what causes the sale, what do you do?
And I think that the second half of the strategy
is to reduce the number of cash that catch this growth.
Because we do not need to do it with cash all the time.
So the second half, the cash growth, I mean,
if this was a reason, I'm not in an ideal trajectory.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
Welcome back, everybody.
So today I'm going to try to split the lecture roughly.
I mean, probably do a little bit more than half
on planning under uncertainty.
There's a lot to say there.
But I think in the spirit of this
is a boutique lecture, kind of at the end,
we're going to give you some of the reasons
why you might want to learn more and just
some of the key ideas of planning under uncertainty.
And then I'd really like to spend a little bit of time
just kind of summarizing what we did.
We picked up a lot of tools.
I think the connective tissue that puts them all together
is still forming.
And I think it's just useful to kind of make
some of those connections again.
Remember what we learned, why we learned them,
how they've come up in your projects,
and wrap it up like that.
So let's give a few examples about why
you might want to do planning under uncertainty.
So maybe--
[INAUDIBLE]
Maybe one example would be at the task level, right?
So if I asked one of Boolean's chatbots or whatever,
if I said, hey, robot, get me-- I don't know,
I have to think of something that has uncertainty,
but get me the mustard.
And maybe because of our massive understanding of the way
kitchens are laid out and where people put things,
maybe there's, I don't know, a 40% chance
that it's in the fridge.
I don't know if you refrigerate your mustard or not.
I know it's a personal choice, right?
Maybe there's a 30% chance it's in the cupboard.
Maybe there's a 10% chance there's one in the pantry.
And maybe, I don't know, a 20% chance we're just out.
You've got to go to the store, right?
So a planner thinking about the task level that's only
thinking about, let's say, the most likely scenario
is going to be impoverished in its ability
to accomplish the task, for sure, right?
But not only in the total success, right?
If it's not in the fridge, it fails.
But also, maybe if the robot is already
in the pantry for something else,
even if it's a low probability, maybe
it's worth a quick check before you take the time
to drive over to the fridge, right?
So reasoning about probabilities at the level of decision making
is hugely important.
And I think at the task level, it's sort of clear, I think.
I guess with all the large language models
that Bojan was talking about, maybe there's a 10% chance
that it'll tell you to pour water over your head
or something like this, too, right?
But that's the wild west.
OK, but it turns out it's super useful down
at the dexterous manipulation control level, too.
So let me think of a good example.
So I actually brought a plate so I can make--
one of my favorite examples is one
that came up when we were loading dishes a lot, right?
So I brought a dish.
I would have brought the dish rack, but that didn't work out.
OK, so it turns out the way that the robot--
imagine this is the rack in the bottom of the dishwasher, OK?
And the way that our robot loaded dishes
was very characteristically, it would grab the plate,
have a pretty good thing, and then it
would line up the plate above and go down, right?
And that always bugged me.
It always bugged me, right?
Because humans don't do that whatsoever.
They do it much faster, first of all,
but they also take a fundamentally different
strategy, right?
They come in.
They almost always make contact.
They're compliant, and they go in like this.
Does that make sense, right?
Instead of having a sort of straight line trajectory
where the plate-- you kind of estimate, possibly
with some accuracy, the location of the tines in the tray, right?
And line up the plate perfectly and try to put it straight down.
And I think a human would come in at an angle,
intentionally make contact here, then passive mechanics
would have it rotate up a little bit,
and it would kind of slide down.
The only explanation for that is something
about being more robust, something about uncertainty,
not needing to accurately understand
the orientation of the plate or the position of the tines,
right?
And it's actually just a fundamentally different
strategy at the level of the controller
because we are implicitly thinking about uncertainty.
We saw another one, too, in our journey here, right?
Remember the example of pushing the book?
This was the example of force control
where you wanted to control the friction cones between the finger
and the book.
You also wanted the book and the table.
[AUDIO OUT]
But right there, what's that motion right there, right?
And then he's going to go around and pick it up.
The only justification for that second motion
was that he could reduce the uncertainty
of the orientation of the book, right?
So as he slid it around, he even rotated the book,
it was all about the friction cones, right?
And the exact orientation of the book
was some relatively subtle function of the friction cones.
But by coming in with this known position of the fingers,
even if the book was at a relatively different orientation,
if he starts pushing, it's going to line the book up nicely.
It's a very robust strategy that would get it
to the end of the table at a known location.
That's the only justification for that middle move.
Otherwise, it was completely worthless, right?
So even at the level of planning control,
reasoning about uncertainty really matters.
And I think the hallmarks of a system that
is reasoning about uncertainty and planning and control
are pretty clear, right?
So one of them is certainly just a level of robustness
that you can obtain if you're thinking about all the things
that could possibly happen, not just planning optimistically
through the world, right?
And there's various ways to talk about robustness.
And some of them I would certainly
put under this umbrella, but there's other approaches that
can achieve robustness, I guess.
But I think the absolute hallmark identifying feature
of a system that's reasoning about uncertainty
when it's making its decisions is information
gathering actions.
We will see examples throughout the lecture
here of cases where the robot does something fundamentally
different.
You need to program it fundamentally different,
not for the sake of accomplishing
the task of getting the book to a certain orientation,
but actually just for the sake of gaining information,
reducing uncertainty, and using that reduced uncertainty
to accomplish the task with higher confidence.
So I think that's the hallmark of a system
that's reasoning about robustness.
Using uncertainty to accomplish the task with higher
confidence.
So really, if you don't have uncertainty
flowing through your system, you will never
see robots making actions just to gain information.
That's a property that only happens
if you're trying to think about optimizing uncertainty
or something like that.
OK, so you need a whole stack to start
reasoning about uncertainty.
You need to think about uncertainty
at the level of perception.
And then we're going to talk mostly about how
to use it in planning and control.
Luckily, our perception systems are actually pretty good.
There's lots of ways that we already have probabilities
flowing through a lot of our state-of-the-art perception
systems.
So the image recognition was putting out
probability that it was a sheep, probability that it was a dog,
probability that it was a cat, so on and so forth.
That's just one example.
But we talked about pose estimation,
where it was outputting entire distributions
over possible orientations of the mugs.
We talked about key point estimators
that weren't putting out x, y, z coordinates of the key points,
but were actually putting out a heat map
over possible locations of the key point.
And over and over and over again,
you'll see people have-- I mean, certainly neural networks
are capable of putting out lots of interesting things.
Oftentimes, those interesting things
include distributions over possible outcomes.
And I don't think there's a big barrier anymore
to asking your perception system to tell you a little bit
about how confident it is.
There are different types of uncertainty.
You might have heard about aleatoric
versus epistemic uncertainty.
And there are different ways to ask
neural networks to address them.
I won't dig into those.
But they are great, actually, at the perception level.
I think there's many good ways to think about uncertainty.
The challenge, though, becomes-- and the thing we'll focus on
here-- is how do you consume those estimates of uncertainty
down through the planning and control stack?
Because we haven't said anything about that yet.
So how do you make long-term decisions
that reason about uncertainty?
Well, if you're going to make long-term decisions,
if you're going to make a plan, you need a model.
So we need to think about a model of how
our uncertainty is going to change over time
if we make certain decisions.
So that I know if I make this decision,
my uncertainty might evolve in some way.
If I make a different decision, I
would like it to evolve in some other way.
And that way, I'm going to choose my actions
based on the way the uncertainty is going to evolve.
So we need a model for the way the uncertainty evolves,
the dynamics of the uncertainty.
And there's lots of ways to think about this.
This is stochastic processes and stochastic dynamics.
There's lots of things to think about.
But we've actually already written down
everything we need.
When I write this general form of f of x is potentially x,
n, where I had my randomness coming in here,
if I've authored my systems in this way,
where the randomness, the random variables come in here,
then I actually already have a model of uncertainty
and how the uncertainty can propagate through the system.
But so far, we've been just talking about this dynamics
here.
And we've been only saying, for simulation, for instance,
we've just been saying, I'm going
to take a random draw of this.
I'm going to evaluate what the next xn is.
For planning, we've so far pretended
that that's just 0, for instance.
And we've done deterministic planning.
And today, I want to say, well, let's say
we want to do planning where we admit that this one's not 0.
And I think it's easiest to think about that first,
if we look at this just for notational reasons,
if only, to look at this in the case
where I have a finite state, x, u, and finite noise, w.
So that would be the standard tabular Markov decision
process.
Or we're going to do a partially observable Markov decision
So to start, let's say that state, action,
and observations are all discrete.
So there's a finite number of discrete and finite--
there's a finite number of states
I could be in, a finite number of actions
I could be in, a finite number of observations.
That's not what our manipulation systems look like.
But that's just how I'll write the-- I'll just
avoid writing more probability notation than I need to,
in order to tell that basic story.
So this, I could have done-- there's
nothing in those equations that say that x is a continuous
variable or u is a continuous variable.
I could write exactly those equations where x is just--
this is a transition map.
But when we talk about belief space planning,
we normally write this in a slightly different way.
We'll write now the probability over initial conditions,
let's say, would be a function of x,
which would be the probability distribution
over initial conditions.
And then I'll write the dynamics here,
which is coming in as a random variable here.
But I can write that just as a probability of transitioning
to some new state, given I'm in some current state.
It depends on p, but it doesn't depend on w here.
This would be my transition probabilities.
And similarly, I can write my observations
as being probabilities that are conditioned
on my state and my action.
So is that-- I don't know how comfortable everybody
is with probability notations, but I just
want to make it clear that this is sort of a deterministic way
to write a stochastic equation, where
I say there's a random variable coming in,
but this is a deterministic function.
I could equivalently write that as saying,
I want to know, given x, u, and p, for instance,
what is the distribution over y?
And that sort of removes this from the argument,
and I have a distribution over possible.
Is that clear how I could write the same thing
in two different ways, with two different notations?
For instance, if this was a Gaussian,
and I'm pushing this through, and maybe this
is a linear equation with a Gaussian here,
then I could write the output as a Gaussian distribution.
That would be not a function of w.
Or I could say, make a specific draw,
and tell me the specific value that comes out
on the other side.
And the reason it's so nice to do the fully discrete case
is that I can represent each of these
just with a finite set of numbers then.
So how would I represent a probability over possible x's?
Well, maybe if x is drawn from just some number of possible x's,
or maybe I realize I've got a notational overlap there,
but I've got some notational-- some finite set of x's,
then my probability over x-- I'll write of x0.
That'll clear up my notational overlap.
My probability of x0, I could just
write it as a vector, which is the probability that x0 is x
like this.
Probability of x0, x1.
It's just a vector.
And similarly, the transition probabilities,
they're going to be-- it's almost a matrix,
but since I've got two variables,
it's actually a little easier to think about it as a tensor,
actually, now.
I wouldn't have done that a few years ago,
but now I can just say tensor, and it's good.
Think about that as a tensor.
For every u, I have a matrix that maps from my current x
to my next x prime.
And all the machinery goes through very nicely when you
just have tables of numbers.
And the question of how do you represent a probability
distribution is just not there when you
have a finite list of numbers.
OK, so what's going to happen now is we're going to have--
we're going to watch how this system can evolve
under the probability distributions.
What is the sort of state evolution of my probabilities?
Sorry, I moved twice.
OK.
The state of the system, I would say,
is clearly-- the state of the plant is clearly x.
That's what we've always been calling the state.
But from the perspective of the observer,
someone who's trying to track what's happening going on
with x, we need a little bit more than just x
to summarize what's going on.
So it actually gets very deeply into the things
we've been talking about.
We've talked about how to learn different state
representations, what makes a good state.
Do people know what's the definition of a state?
What is the fundamental property that sort of defines a state?
You.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
So he says minimal and sufficient information
to predict the next state.
Yes, I mean almost.
So we could argue about whether states
need to be minimal or not.
I think you could talk about a minimal representation
for state.
I'll forego minimalism for now.
OK.
The question is, so a state is something
that lets you fully predict the next state.
That's a super good definition.
But it's not actually the definition we want here.
Because the system is stochastic,
we can't perfectly predict the next state.
So we need a slightly richer notion of what's state.
A slightly richer definition, but completely
consistent, is that a state is a set of information,
a set of numbers, for instance, that
lets you forget all of the other things you've seen.
It's a sufficient statistic for all
of the history of your observations.
OK.
So if I wanted to write the evolution of this system,
if I wanted to predict, for instance,
what is the probability of y at the n-th step being,
I don't know, the i-th y, conditioned on all
of the things I've seen so far, u0, u1, u2, up to, let's say,
un minus 1, but also y0, y1, up to yn minus 1,
potentially the next y I expect to see,
or the distribution over y's I expect to see,
is a function of all of the things I've seen in the past.
OK.
What we want is to summarize all of the things
I've seen in the past, so that the prediction based
on a state that represents this is the same as if I
had all of the histories.
So I want to say the probability over yn equals yi,
conditioned on some b-- I'm going to call it b here-- bn,
and maybe un, since that's coming in right now,
is equivalent to having all of that prior information.
OK.
So this state here, what does it mean to be a good state?
It means it's a sufficient statistic for the history,
or a sufficient summary, let's say,
of my entire history of observations.
OK, so for the purposes of the observer,
the state that you want to track, this state,
this thing called b, is called a belief state.
And we want to make sure we get our head around that,
and then use it for planning.
OK, so a belief state is some efficient, hopefully,
not always, but some, let's say, numerical summary
of all the things that I've seen in the past that
is sufficient for me to predict what's
going to happen in the future.
OK?
And for these sort of Markov processes
and dynamical systems of this form,
there's a natural choice for the belief state.
It's not a unique choice.
It's certainly not a minimal choice in most cases.
OK?
A minimal choice would be to say that the belief--
let me say the-- I'll use it as a vector again,
since everything's nice in the continuous thing.
So I've got a belief vector.
And the belief for the element i of that vector
is going to be the probability that x at n
equals xi conditioned on u0, u1, y0, y1, and so on and so forth.
So the belief, a sufficient statistic
that allows me to forget everything I've seen,
is a probability distribution over all the possible states
I might be in.
OK?
That's a super powerful thing.
It says that all I need to keep-- no matter how long my history
was, how many observations I have,
if I just summarize my current estimated probability of what's
in the-- of being in state 0, in state 1, state 2,
it's just a vector, one vector, right?
If I can just keep track of that, then I have everything.
I don't need to remember anything else about the past.
And more because of that, because it's
sufficient to summarize the past and to predict the future,
it's also sufficient for optimal decision making.
So it turns out we know that the optimal controllers,
optimal policies, must be of the form un is some pi star--
it could be a function of n, potentially-- of bn.
Even when the system is partially observable, right?
So in the case where y just shows me x without noise,
for instance, then x actually-- b can just be x.
And all the things we already know still
work if they still fit in this framework.
Because my probability distribution
collapses to just a single point.
But in general, I have to keep an entire state distribution
over x.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Sir, would you mind explaining a bit more
why the probability distribution of x at the point
captures the whole [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
Yeah.
I wish I had a one-liner for that.
But it is true.
So you can derive it recursively from these equations.
If I wrote out all the equations,
you can see it recursively in the algebra
and everything like that.
It's also the tenant of filtering.
So the Bayes optimal filter, for instance,
takes exactly this form.
But without all that machinery, I
have to ask you for a little bit of a leap of faith maybe.
Yeah.
But thank you for asking.
OK.
So now our new commodity is to traffic in these beliefs.
Now the problem, caveat, spoiler alert,
sometimes it's hard to keep track of all the possible--
to write a distribution over big, complicated things.
This might be the shape of the mustard bottle.
It could be the time of the day.
It could be that there's a lot of things
to potentially keep track of in the world.
And it becomes untenable to try to keep
track of all the distribution over everything
that could possibly happen.
But in the smaller problems, and with selected, targeted
reasoning about uncertainty, you can do very well with this.
OK.
So this is amazing.
I mean, I'll give you a few examples here.
So there's a classic example that people
talk about in the partially observable Markov decision
process of discrete worlds that have discrete observations.
One of them is a cheese maze.
It's a silly thing, but there's, I don't know, cheese here.
OK, and the mouse has to go and find the cheese.
OK.
And there's a discrete number of places
that the mouse might be, for instance.
And there's observation.
So when you're in a certain place on the board,
if the mouse-- I'm not going to draw a mouse.
Well, maybe I could draw a mouse.
But yeah, something with the tail and the ears.
OK.
There's a mouse running around the maze.
Luckily, the mouse can see the numbers
that we put down, which are like signposts, which
tell it where it is.
And the interesting cheese mazes are
the ones that have observations that don't tell you
exactly where you are.
They give you an indication.
They give you information about where you are,
but they don't instantly determine where you are,
because maybe there's the number 2 appears in multiple places.
OK.
Something like this is a classic one.
Maybe there's 5 in all these places.
6, 7, 6.
OK.
So what is the evolution of this belief going to be?
So if the mouse wakes up and is following Bayes optimal--
it's a Bayes optimal mouse, then it's
keeping track of a finite list of probabilities.
B at 0, maybe it thinks-- I think there's 11 things here.
So maybe there's equal probability everywhere
that it could be anywhere in the board.
And then it sees-- maybe I should have started down
at a more interesting place.
But maybe it sees 2 at the first time step.
And after one observation, it's collapsed its belief
to being 0 in most places.
But there's still half of probability
that I'm in this place and wherever the next one is.
And the rest are 0's, right?
And as the mouse moves through the board,
it's updating its probability distribution
over possible states.
And the recipe for updating that falls directly out
of Bayes' rule applied to those forward dynamics.
For a more complicated and more robotics version of that,
people might know a lot about state estimation and Monte
Carlo filtering and the like.
This is one of the first ones, the kind of popularized
probabilistic robotics.
So this is a robot, a trash can robot moving around
with a sonar, because that's what we had back in the day.
And you could think about this as being a much more
complicated cheese maze.
And the observations are now the depth returns of the sonar.
And if I start it over again, it starts off
with probability all over.
This is sampled versions of that probability.
And as it gets sonar returns, it gets information
about where it is, but it doesn't completely
determine where it is.
And it has a probability mass, which
is like that vector, all over the space.
And as it evolves, it can do pretty complicated things.
That's just a more sophisticated version
of this super simple example.
Now, what's essential?
Now, this is the point of this part of the lecture.
What's essential is that the rules that
govern the update of the belief distribution
just have dynamics that we can write down.
It's just another system.
You can write down the evolution through Bayes optimal filter.
B is a function of n plus 1.
It's just some function of B of n, U of n, and Y of n.
It's a system that looks like this.
U going in, observations coming in.
It's got an internal state B inside it.
Maybe you can put the B on the output board if you want.
That isn't actually essential here.
And if you have goals that are specified, for instance,
that I want to get to a certain belief,
I want to, with high probability,
be where the cheese is, or I want
to be in some room in the map with high probability,
then the task is just like what we've done before,
where it's a task of choosing the U subject to the dynamics
F that moves around the target B.
As a result, all of the tools that we've already
talked about-- well, with some caveats--
but the basic tools we've talked about can work.
So once you have this problem, for instance,
you can do trajectory optimization.
And I would say the dominant approaches, maybe,
for large scale things would be a trajectory optimization
kind of approach, or a sampling-based motion planning
type approach.
, OK?
And so we've talked mostly in this class
about kinematic trajectory optimization.
This is really a dynamic trajectory optimization.
That's the biggest caveat I have for you,
is that you do have to think about the fact
that you can't take arbitrary paths through B.
The dynamics of this function F do limit you.
So it's an under-actuated system.
Pretty good, right?
But it is actually interesting and hard,
because it's an under-actuated system.
You don't have enough actuators to control your entire belief.
And so actually, the trajectory optimization versions
we do in under-actuated are more suitable
than the kinematic trajectory.
But it's a small extension from the types
of things we've done.
So you can do trajectory optimization over U,
subject to constraints that B has some initial condition,
final condition.
You could put a cost on B, so on and so forth.
Now, almost, right?
So there's one important difference here.
Why, as I've written it here, is this system's perspective,
why is still a random variable coming in?
It's a function of X and U, but also it
could be a noisy measurement.
So you actually have to do a form of stochastic trajectory
optimization, or you can make a choice
to be optimistic about your observations, y.
But people have studied nicely how you can do this.
You could do stochastic trajectory optimization.
If you've heard of iterative LQG,
that actually would be-- if I were to recommend one thing
to solve these problems, I would recommend iterative LQG.
We had some work that tried to be optimistic about y
and used deterministic trajectory optimization
to do it.
But actually, the flavor of this is very much just trajectory
optimization.
Gets you pretty far.
So let me tell you that version of it.
So this is a toy version of the problem.
Imagine you're a point robot.
Starting here, that's the initial conditions.
We call this the light-dark domain.
It's the simplest kind of instance
of a problem, which has state-dependent observation
noise.
So the basic thing is that it's dark over here.
Your position sensors are noisy when it's dark.
And over here, it's light.
Sensors are pretty accurate when it's light.
Your goal is to get to 0, 0, 0.
If you didn't reason at all about uncertainty,
and you felt like you were in this initial condition, that
was the mean of your initial conditions,
then you'd take a straight line here.
But if you have process noise, too, for instance,
you might end up actually very far from there.
If you write an optimization to say, I'd like to get here,
but I'd like to get here with some confidence--
I'd like my belief to be narrowly distributed
around that goal-- then it actually
makes sense to go into the light in order
to come back to the dark.
So this is explicitly an information-gathering action
that you don't get from deterministic reasoning,
but you do get from reasoning over belief state.
The reason there's two curves is that we're
talking about two different ones.
This is one just based on linearizing the whole equations
and doing basically one step of the iterative LQG
kind of algorithm.
And this one's based on a direct trajectory optimization,
dynamic trajectory optimization.
But the principle is the same, is
that only because you're learning about uncertainty
did you choose to go into the light to come back.
The specific objective here-- oh, yeah,
please.
So in this method, it's like you need
to know how the uncertainty will evolve
in all possible different future--
That's true.
--in order to figure it out.
But then in real life, I don't know--
at this time, I don't know how my uncertainty would evolve
10 steps down the line.
So how can I find an optimal trajectory right now
all the way to the end if I don't know how it will evolve?
You don't know-- so this is a very deep question.
Thank you.
So the question is, now I can't know how my distribution is
going to evolve.
So you can know how the distribution over distribution
is going to evolve.
So you don't know what sensor measurement
you're going to get at time 3 in the future.
That you have to either think about all possible,
the random variable of possible measurements I get at time 3.
Or you can say, I'm going to propagate
where I think I'll be at time 3 and then
assume that I'm going to get a particular measurement at time
3 in order to keep going.
But actually, you do-- this is a complete-- if we
agree that we have a dynamic model of how things go
and what my measurement noise is, for instance,
I do have-- understand things like if I
were to look around here, I would
have a different view of what's behind here.
And I would expect to get-- I don't know what's behind here,
but I know that I get more information
to reduce my uncertainty about what's behind this paper
if I were to move here.
And that turns out to be very powerful,
enough that it causes you to take information gathering
actions.
And then, because you might be surprised,
and what you find there might very much determine
what you do, we often use this in a replanning cycle.
So you plan, but if you ever see something
that then dramatically changed your view of the world,
you just replan.
But that's a great question.
The particular objective here, just to think about it--
so instead of representing this as a table of possible
locations here, the representation here
was a mean and covariance over possible locations.
And the goal was to say, I'd like
to be here where my mean was at the goal,
but my covariance was as small as possible.
Find a trajectory, and there was some cost on--
I should have put in the cost on action, too.
But it would go across here, and then come back
with as small as possible.
And it was better to go into the light
than to take the straight path.
OK, so that's still a little abstract.
Here's a robotics version of it, a manipulation version of it.
So let's say that you know there's
going to be two boxes in front of you,
but you don't know the size or location of the boxes.
Let me just read it carefully.
The robot must localize the pose and dimensions of the boxes
using a laser scanner mounted on the wrist, on the left wrist.
It's relatively easy when the boxes are separated,
but when they're squished together like C on the right,
then it's actually pretty hard.
So this is a simple example of if the robot is taking
information gathering actions, it'll actually
do something different in order to increase
its confidence of the location of the box
before it picks it up.
And you put this into the trajectory optimization
simulation where you take measurements as laser scanners
out there, and it actually decides
to go off and push on the left in order
to get a better sensor reading of the right.
And it's tracking a distribution over possible poses
of the box and the like.
And it makes the decision, just with trajectory optimization,
to take that information gathering action
to reduce its uncertainty.
And then it goes to pick up the box.
But that same algorithm, if the boxes started off separate,
it did its first scan and found it was fairly confident,
would have just gone in to pick up the box.
Same thing here.
You can actually see the-- this is
a rendering of the distribution over those possible locations.
Of course, it's a high dimensional thing,
so it's plotted down in a way that's a little bit hard--
that's why it's periodic is because it's
the raft of higher dimensional things plotted
on a single line.
And the big robot would make those decisions.
[INAUDIBLE]
You're saying local minima of trajectory optimization?
Yeah.
It's a really big question.
Is this kind of trajectory optimization more sensitive
to local minima, for instance?
In some way, I actually think it might be less sensitive,
even though it's solving a harder problem.
Because for the same reason we talked about with
the randomized smoothing and the whatever,
I actually think that putting distributions
over possible outcomes smooths out
some of the kinks in the cost landscape,
and it might be a little less sensitive.
But it would still have-- the big local minima
will still be there, but it might get rid
of some of the small local minima.
[INAUDIBLE]
Awesome.
Yeah, that's actually the last point I want to make.
So that's really good.
So just to be clear, this is doing information gathering.
That is, that push I would consider
to be only valuable for the sake of gathering information.
[INAUDIBLE]
Nope.
The goal here is to, with high probability, pick up the box.
And the only reason it does that is to reduce its uncertainty,
to gather information.
OK, but the second part of Leroy's question
was actually the biggest last point I want to make here,
which is that this really does have deep connections
to the state realization questions
we've been talking about.
I'll put it in a different slide,
just so we're not watching that.
OK, so now imagine I'm doing system ID, right?
Input output system ID, for instance,
to try to learn a state representation.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
In order to accurately predict my future observations,
if I'm going to learn a state space model for this,
in the linear system ID setting, we thought about this
as we've got a deterministic system we're trying to recover.
And it did recover the A, B, C, D matrices pretty well.
But if I have a stochastic system here
that is trying to recover, and its objective
is to predict y with its highest confidence possible,
then the state it has to learn is actually, I think,
better thought about as a belief state.
Now again, the belief states are not unique.
All the stuff we talked about with similarity transforms
and the like is still present here.
And it might be that the belief state is not minimal,
that tracking all the things that the real state might do
might be more than you need to predict y.
When we talked about approximate information states,
that's exactly the idea of finding a state representation
in here, which is an approximate belief state.
Similarly, if I'm doing RL, let's say,
let's say via policy gradient, or if you
do a policy gradient with a dynamic policy,
like an LSTM or something, or if you have a value function or a Q
function that has some dynamic, some states-- by the way,
I think if you do that, you've walked away from RL theory.
I think there's-- I mean, people are working on that theory now,
but that's not the standard thing to do in theory.
But if people do it in practice now,
they'll put an LSTM representing the value function or the Q
function.
And the states that this thing has
to acquire in order to accomplish the task-- let's
say we had an oracular agent that would just
solve the RL problem and solve the representation along
with it.
Then the dynamic, the state in the controller
is probably best understood as being
an approximate state of the belief space of the system.
That's what's required to make optimal decisions.
Similarly, the value function, if trained--
so this would be a task-relevant approximate state.
And this one, similarly, would be just the part
of the belief space you would need in order
to accurately predict values.
So I do think RL is potentially doing this.
And I think that the language of belief
is exactly the right way to think about what
RL is doing in those cases.
So you should learn more about belief space planning.
It's good stuff.
OK, let me step back and just cover the course again
in a few minutes.
I think it's really helpful to just sort of connect it
all together.
So we've done a lot of things, covered a lot of tools,
sometimes at a level that I wish I could spend four lectures on.
We spent less.
But I hope you came away with a lot of tools.
And it's been very rewarding for me
to see you guys hit some of the subtler points in your projects,
for instance.
So let's do a kind of a where have we been.
People also asked in the survey for things
like predict manipulation 40 years in the future.
That's hard, but I'll try to say a few things about where
it's going, too.
So we started off, after the basic introduction,
we started off with just basic kinematics, Jacobians,
stuff like that.
The multibody notation is something
that I doubt too many people will move forward
with as part of your major, part of your life.
But if you do, you'll be happier.
I promise.
I've seen bugs in notebooks that-- I mean, I've made my own.
If you find yourself frustrated that the Jacobian you got out
of diff IK is in the wrong frame,
or your forces somehow seem to be in the wrong space
or something like this, more careful use
of multibody notation will save you.
Consider it.
It really does help, I think.
And I think the general view-- I try
to push sort of less about the mechanics
of the kinematic equations, which is a slightly more
standard treatment.
But I think thinking of it as a spatial algebra
and understanding the basic operations of how rotations
affect frames and stuff like this,
that's a lesson that we came back to multiple times.
And I really do think a lot of you
found that the differential IK pipeline became
a workhorse for your projects, a lot of people using it.
And some of you really, I think, got to appreciate it.
Or maybe you're mad at it.
But a month from now, you'll be really appreciative of it,
maybe.
For instance, one of my regrets is
that a bunch of people copied the IWA Painter notebook.
And that had only used pseudo-inverse control, not
the full diff IK.
Because that was sufficient for that notebook.
And I hadn't sort of pictured everybody
copying it and trying to use it for more than it was good for.
The pseudo-inverse controller can run into singularities.
And some of you did.
And it blows up.
Unfortunately, the way it blows up
is it causes multibody plant to say, I can't--
or it says the integrator-- I run into time step
equals 1e to the minus 14.
And that's not a very clear message.
But fine, that was just the pseudo-inverse
being insufficient.
And if you switched over to the diff IK, which
was the least squares interpretation, which
allowed you to have constraints, then those issues went away.
So the differential IK, as an optimization,
I think is a workhorse and a thing I
hope you feel like you learned.
We jumped into geometric perception.
There's a party going on somewhere.
Of course, we learned iterative closest point and its variance.
I would say both the kinematics and the ICP kind of work
helped me start talking about many of these problems,
kinematics problems as optimizations, too.
And I think the takeaway that some of you
are seeing when you're playing with perception on the project
is that these point cloud processing algorithms
are very good for refinement if you have a known geometry.
But they're not great for the global part
of the perception problem.
And you really wanted to bring in the deep learning
pipeline to help with the bigger part of the problem.
And it requires those require models.
They're great for accuracy, let's say for refinement,
if you will.
But they need an initial guess.
And remember I said that if you were to take away--
if you told me I could only have RGB or I could only have depth,
my answer would have flipped a few years ago.
And I'd say, take my depth.
I'll keep my RGB.
We built up more into the clutter clearing
was the example that I used for a few reasons.
We started to talk about perception in clutter, richer
perception that could handle the occlusions and things
like that, about more complicated simulation
mechanics, and about even programming at the task level.
So this was scaling up the basic recipe
into a really much more sophisticated version
of the problem.
It also helped make the point that we didn't
need to estimate the pose perfectly in order
to be successful.
Because that clutter clearing demo
was just using antipodal grasps.
It wasn't even thinking about what objects were.
And it went pretty far.
We jumped into deep perception.
We talked about Mask-RCNN and the like.
That was the first workhorse.
If you're starting to do perception in the real world,
you might very well still be using Mask-RCNN.
We talked about deep pose estimation,
the category level versions of this,
with, for instance, dense descriptors and key points,
for instance, being an alternative to actually
estimating the pose.
Maybe key points are enough, or dense descriptors.
These are super powerful methods.
They're getting better.
They're data hungry.
I think if there's one thing that we're
seeing as today's trend that will continue
is that a lot of the pipelines that started off
being hugely successful based on supervised learning
are now turning over into self-supervised learning
versions of these problems.
Finding good ways to train a visual representation that's
sufficient for these kind of downstream tasks
using unlabeled data is the big new trend.
Not even that new anymore.
We did motion planning.
We covered a lot of stuff.
We did motion planning, which started with just richer
spelling of inverse kinematics.
All the power you use.
And a lot of you guys are using inverse kinematics only,
actually, I'd say, calling a lot of sequential inverse
kinematics calls.
And a handful of times I've been saying,
maybe you should turn that into a kinematic trajectory
optimization.
Why?
Because solving a bunch of inverse kinematics
calls independently is good, but it doesn't actually
ask them to be related to each other in any smooth or subtle
way.
And so I tried to say the kinematic trajectory
optimization was just inverse kinematics with the constraint
that the inverse kinematics solutions are
consistent with each other.
They can all be described from one spline.
And we talked about sample-based motion planning, too.
I'll say sampling-based.
Some powerful tools.
I threw in some stuff about graph of convex sets there,
too, of course.
If you remember RRT and PRM, then you've
got that basic vocabulary.
Do you remember then all of the stuff about the different ways
we're doing control on the manipulator?
We had our next foray into force control and manipulator
control.
Can you remember why PID control is good,
but inverse dynamics control is better if you have a model?
And why we actually use joint stiffness control?
In a lot of cases for the robot, we
like to think about executing joint trajectories,
but relatively with a low stiffness controller,
so that if we bump into stuff, we're
still compliant enough to keep moving and not
break our robot or the environment.
But we also talked about direct force control,
where you're thinking explicitly about the forces,
or indirect force control, like Cartesian impedance control,
or Cartesian stiffness control.
One of my favorite examples that came up with that, actually.
Remember the-- a few people are doing writing projects, right?
And I gave the Meshcat painter a little thing that just says,
put a chalk, weld it to your hand if you want,
and draw some lines.
And it was interesting to have the conversations with people,
because in the case where the chalk is welded to your finger,
the difference between force control and just a Diff IK
control, for instance, with joint stiffness
controller, or inverse dynamics, is small.
Because you just put yourself into a reasonable amount
of penetration, you move yourself around,
and that's all good.
The robot will-- you might have to do a little tuning
to not push too hard, because otherwise the chalk will
get stuck.
If you don't push hard enough, it might not draw.
But pretty much, you just tune in once how deep to push.
You follow your trajectory.
Life is good.
But the people who switched from welding it to the finger
to holding the chalk had a different experience.
So as soon as you push down, the chalk
might move in your fingers.
As you draw, it might start moving in your fingers.
And suddenly there, if you just picked a nice trajectory
and started moving around, then you
might have drawn for a little while,
and now you stopped drawing, because it
moved in your fingers.
And it's hard to know where the chalk is in your fingers.
So actually, this is a beautiful case
where, if you think about the space of forces,
you just say, I'd like to be pushing down
with a certain amount of force.
Then even if the chalk moves, the end effector
will move for you in order to keep yourself
in contact with the table.
So we talked about controlling not just the robot,
but then the objects in the world.
I used the language of visual motor policies
to talk about that.
I really think something great happened
when we started putting cameras at high rate
into our controllers.
And we need to understand it better.
Right now, I'd say our ability to get visual motor policies
is still a little weak.
We did it with behavior cloning.
We talked about it with RL policy search, for instance.
But we should have more powerful, reliable ways
to get visual motor policies.
They're very good.
We're still working on it.
But this is the stuff that's making the rock star
manipulation demos right now.
I showed you rolling dough.
There's all kinds of things that visual motor policies
can do that are surprising.
And then we wrapped up with intuitive physics,
learning models, task and motion planning,
and a little bit of belief space today.
So that's a lot of coverage.
We've covered a lot of things, some of them more carefully
and some of them just quickly at the end.
But I think it's a pretty good representation of what's
happening in a modern manipulation system.
When I reflect on the class, and maybe what I'll do next time,
let's say, but the one thing that I
think this overly emphasizes, and maybe I
wish I would emphasize more, I think
I'm going to put mobile manipulation earlier
in the class.
Because I think it opens up-- I didn't realize-- I mean,
I think the tools are actually not that different to solve
mobile manipulation.
The math is the same.
But the ideas you would have for your projects, I think,
are going to be different.
I think Brian's lecture yesterday really
emphasized that, right?
You wouldn't ask a chatbot, what should I do with-- go get me
a Coke or something like that, if you're limited
to the world of your table.
And I think the open vocabulary ideas,
the anything could happen in the world,
you're going to send your robot off and do anything,
wheels help you think about that.
You could bring a lot of things to yourself in a conveyor belt,
and that's not the same.
So even though the math is actually very similar,
I'm going to probably make a bigger
emphasis on mobile manipulation next time.
There are some different parts of the math
where people think about navigation and mapping
and other scene level kind of perception problems
that would come along with that.
But I think the biggest thing for me
is just the needing to think about the open domain,
open vocabulary part of the world.
[PAPER RUSTLING]
For me-- and I'm saying this partly so you can agree with me
or disagree with me over anonymous feedback is fine.
You can shout it out right now, that's fine.
The other thing that I think I want to emphasize--
and I said it on Tuesday-- I want
to give a few more tools that you could, in your projects,
for instance, use for the task level reasoning.
I think if you could have just written a Pudittles
specification, you might not love writing Pudittles.
It's kind of weird.
But it's very powerful to be able to think
about longer term tasks, more abstract tasks.
And I'm thinking that the presentation focused
a little bit more on the dexterous part of manipulation
and a little less about the world part.
But you can leave with a slightly-- knowing
that there's other parts.
In fact, it's interesting to think about--
when I was thinking about that dichotomy,
it just happens that at TRI, the org chart is kind of telling.
So there's a dexterous manipulation team.
But there's also a mobile manipulation team, separate.
And it really does bring-- they're complementary.
There's a lot of problems that you get into,
where you don't need-- the mobile manipulation team,
I showed you their grocery store robot.
They were happy with a suction gripper for a lot of things.
They weren't thinking about the dexterity required.
But they're moving through the world
and experiencing things that my robot on the table
is not experiencing.
And once I said that, I realized, OK, well,
I haven't said enough about soft robots.
There's a soft robotics team.
And there's also a human-robot interaction team.
I'll write it out.
We mentioned soft.
And I offered to spend a lecture talking about tactile sensing.
But we didn't get to that one.
And human-robot interaction is hugely important.
It's just not my expertise, really.
But any thoughts or questions or anything
about that high-level scope stuff?
Feedback?
Yeah?
What would be the next steps?
What would be the next steps for you
as a manipulator, a robot programmer?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, for you as students, yeah.
There are a lot of really good classes.
I don't know which of them you've taken
and which of you haven't.
I'll be teaching underactuated, which
I've advertised a few times in the spring.
But there's great classes by Luca Caralone
about perception and state estimation and the like.
In fact, I could just summarize a list
of some of the great classes, maybe on a Piazza post.
I'd be happy to do that.
We have a lot of good classes on campus.
Maybe not enough, actually.
I'd love to see more.
Yeah?
Is this more of a research toolkit
rather than what people are applying to robots
when they start a robot?
That's a great question.
Is this a research toolkit?
Or is this a, I need a robot to move today
to make my startup work kind of toolkit?
I think there's a lot of robots that
do things that you'd consider to be manipulation that don't
use a big part of the stack.
But they are the places where the world is more constrained.
So the classic example would be a factory room floor
where you're welding or something like this.
It uses maybe force control, a lot of position programming
and the like.
But it doesn't need to think about perception.
It doesn't need to think about all the uncertainty
and complexity or even planning that
comes with the fact that the world could be very diverse.
And I think in industry, startups, big companies
are now investing a lot in the next generation of robots,
starting with more flexible manufacturing,
flexible logistics, the Amazon problem, the delivery problems.
And I think that they are hitting this straight up.
This is core material for that kind of a job.
And then absolutely, there's research
that is taking every one of those
and pushing farther.
But I think as soon as you start needing
to perceive the world in order to do your manipulation,
and that's driven by the task, then the old stuff
isn't getting it done.
And this stuff is bread and butter.
Yeah, thank you.
So people ask me to predict the future.
I can't do that.
But I'll give you a few thoughts if you want.
So in fact, Rod Brooks, another famous roboticist
that got to-- went off and was lab director
and then started a company.
But I took his class when I was a student,
embodied intelligence.
I think it was called embodied intelligence, yeah.
He always says that people have a tendency-- he reminds us.
It's not his quote, I guess.
But people have a tendency to overestimate
the importance of a new technology in the short term
and dramatically underestimate the potential
in the long term.
So I'm just saying everything I'm about to say is wrong.
But I do think there's some huge trends that we've
seen enough of to lean into, right?
I'd say, actually, Bojan's talk last time
is one of the biggest ones.
The idea that we could have more common sense, priors,
to make decisions with robots, I think,
is the biggest change coming to the field in a long time,
maybe.
And it's starting-- we've always wanted it.
And I don't think we're quite there with large language
models.
But I'd say the large language models
and the visual language models and the like that Bojan talked
about, that's the first compelling approach
to say we're going to get something
that smells like an unnatural intelligence common sense.
And I don't even know how to measure
the potential change in that that's
going to happen with that.
It's going to be weird.
I can guarantee that.
That's a high probability prediction, right?
But I think it's really one of the biggest things that's
going to change what we're doing.
It's sort of interesting.
The people I talk to about this, they actually
say that-- maybe they're just trying to make me feel better.
But they say it's interesting because there's
so many people are excited about this.
And they want to think about how to make robots
do these multi-level tasks that, in some ways,
it actually puts a premium on motion planning that just works
and feedback control and skills and other things.
The stuff I did maybe emphasize a lot in the class
is suddenly really important because there's
engineers everywhere that don't know that yet.
And the robots don't work all the time.
But if they did, we could do incredible long-term tasks now.
So I actually think, in a weird way,
this not manipulator equation driven thing
is probably going to put a premium on some
of the core manipulation skills, let me say.
The slightly lower level stuff, including
extra style manipulation.
I would say that we're going to see--
so I obviously like simulation.
But I think we've turned a few corners with simulation.
And I would expect that the use of simulation is--
I think it's just like at the beginning of what we're
going to see in this field.
And it's going to continue to change rapidly.
I think some percentage of the robotics population
is converted and says, I believe that if it worked
in simulation, I'd have a pretty good chance of it working
in reality.
The people that are training perception systems
on simulated data are pretty convinced, I think.
I think less people are convinced about the contact
mechanics.
I mean, we focused on it more than a lot of people.
And there's a sim-to-real gap in the contact mechanics.
And you definitely have to be a skilled user of simulation
to make that transfer.
You could set parameters wrong.
But I think if you're a skilled user of simulation,
then more and more people believe
that you can do your work in simulation.
The bottleneck there is content.
How do you get your robot, your art assets, your objects
that you want to manipulate into simulation?
And I think there's going to be just probably
a huge change in content.
We're already seeing it with-- it's funny.
When someone says-- like five years ago, let's say 10 years
ago, just to be safe, people said, I built a simulator.
They mean they wrote like F equals ma down.
And maybe they wrote a renderer that's part of a simulator.
But now if someone says, I've got a new simulator,
they don't even-- they built something
on top of a physics engine.
And they don't even cite the physics engine.
But they're like now-- there's these, I think,
very important content aggregators, people that just
say, I've scanned a bunch of houses.
And I've put a bunch of different objects
in those houses.
And that's my new simulator offering.
And I think that's valuable.
That's hugely valuable.
So we're seeing people generate that data
in lots of different ways, sometimes with manual effort,
sometimes with procedural generation.
You can make a program that spits out random living rooms.
And increasingly, what we're seeing
is real-to-sim kind of work.
I think this is just going to be a huge component.
The fact that you can drive around Stata
with just an RGB camera, come out
with a perfect neural radiance field representation of it.
And then, so what do you do with that?
How do you get that into a simulator?
It's not enough, it turns out, to feed the simulator.
But people are thinking about this now.
How do I just ingest so that the robot, every time it
sees something new, it adds it to the simulator.
And we build the matrix.
I predict that that would be a huge-- that's
going to just ramp up more and more and more.
I guess along that route, I think--
maybe an easy one to say, but let's just
think about it for a minute.
I think big data hasn't come to robotics yet, but it's coming.
It's come through large language models and visual models.
But the thing that we're waiting for is, let me say,
interaction data, data that has forces.
We talked about in the system ID world
that if I watched an object fall on YouTube,
there's limits to what I can learn about it.
I can't learn its math, for instance.
And I think we're getting to the world
where people are deploying enough robots
and thinking seriously about how to aggregate that data.
Fleet learning is a huge potential.
All the robots as edge nodes pool their understanding,
pool their models, pool their data
to learn something more about the world
than they can learn by surfing the web.
And that's coming.
But every year we say it's coming,
and it's still taking a long time.
Considering how important it is, it's taking a long time.
It's sort of frustrating that we don't quite have it yet.
It's hard to-- because the data that you
generate on your robot, that's not exactly the data
I want to generate on my robot.
And so it's not immediately useful.
You have to think about off-policy RL and all these.
But even the distribution shift can be really tough.
But there's going to be a crossing point where
we have enough robots, and they're similar enough,
or we have enough copies of the same robot,
and maybe we consolidate hardware or something
where suddenly I'm going to program my robot completely
differently because you generated a lot of data.
Also, the same thing, too, is that a lot
of the work we're doing here, we're
kind of programming the robot as if it's the first time it ever
experienced this.
And we think a lot about learning as, OK,
I started with my policy parameters as random numbers
around 0.
How do I do that?
And that's not the world we're going to be living in.
We're going to be living in a world
where there are many robots that have already
done most of these things, and I should start with their hive
mind global model and maybe specialize
for my current situation.
So that's definitely coming to this neck of the woods, too.
And maybe just to say a last one,
I think I've said it a few times,
but I'm just very optimistic about theory of ML, RL, control
coming together with empirical stuff.
I think the empirical success of these things raced ahead.
But now we have many of the best theorists
in the world that are excited about understanding
those better, and I think that is just going
to be a very harmonious future.
I mean, we have Scott Aronson, right,
is our quantum computation guy.
He saw GPT-3, and now he's open AI for, I think--
I hope I'm not wrong, Scott.
But the quantum computation people
get so excited by these large models
that they have to go figure them out.
That's good.
That's great, right?
That's like bringing all the really great people together.
And I'm just very--
I mean, the controls people are so smart.
They're so, so smart.
And they now see that some of the things that
have happened in RL, and they're moving in that direction.
And I'm very optimistic about that
and how that changes things.
So if I were to just, at a meta level,
try to convince you of something,
it's maybe-- I think it's in this space, which is--
and I said it on day one, and I'll say it again
to close this off here.
I mean, for me, this class, even, and the notes
as they slowly evolve, and the way I think about it,
I think because the systems we're building here
are so complicated, we have to think rigorously about them.
And I think having a foundation of the things we know
and rigorous thinking about the things
that we're still inventing is just so important.
And I think if you talk to the best empirical machine
learning people and the most influential papers,
and you look at the authors, or you look
at the style of the papers, they're extremely rigorous.
I think people get the impression
that you can put a quick algorithm together,
you can make some curves, and you're good.
But those aren't the papers that are having massive impact.
And so I really want us to take the time
to think deeply about these problems
and build a foundation across these complicated disciplines.
And I think that's what's going to push the field forward.
Maybe more now than in some other times.
There's just been such a bubbling up of ideas.
And it feels to me like it's time
to consolidate a little bit and then push forward again.
Good.
OK, so that's it for me.
It's your turn.
So Anthony sent out the logistics for Tuesday.
But basically, I think-- and his text
is the gospel, if I say anything different right now.
But the basic gist is please come.
Come at 2, because it's going to take longer than an hour
and a half to do it.
If you come at 2.30, that's fine.
But if you can come at 2, it's great.
It really is like the best part of the class.
And please, when you're presenting or making
your videos, think about what you
learned that you wish other people knew.
That's the value.
I get tons of value out of that, of learning about the things
that you thought were going to work that didn't work.
Algorithm you tried that we haven't covered
or I haven't thought about that much.
I hear your experiences.
And I understand things better because of them.
And so I think you can all get that out
of each other next week.
The goal is-- so once you put your name on the sheet,
we're going to march down the sheet.
People in the room will put up first.
We've had a few times where someone would sit
in the room for a really long time watching
people who aren't there.
And so if you're here in the room,
and you've marked your video as public,
so when you upload to YouTube, you
can make it public or unlisted.
The public videos means we're going to show it.
And we'll show it even on the live stream,
because some people will watch remotely.
If it's unlisted, it's still on the spreadsheet.
So you can watch everybody's videos.
I mean, the class-- your members of the class
are your audience, whether you're unlisted or public.
But the broader world is only your audience
if you mark your video public.
And I've got a room till 5.
We'll see what we do.
We're going to march through as many as we can.
Try to give a little space for questions.
There's a lot of you, and it takes time
to march through the videos.
But please come.
It's really, really a fun part of the class.
I know there's people all over that
are going to be watching, because they've
seen awesome projects in the past.
And I think they're going to see awesome projects this time.
And it's not about how well your robot works.
It's about how much you learned and how
you can communicate that.
OK, good.
See you Tuesday.
I'm excited.