[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, welcome back everybody.
I think we've determined, by the way, there is a shade up there.
But you can see the canvas being crinkled in the corner.
But the buttons that allow you to move it are inoperable.
So they've hopefully adjusted the camera settings and it'll be less washed out.
But we'll keep fighting the fight.
All right, last time we did a sort of quick tour of robot hardware to sort of
as background for the class.
And today we're gonna start into some of the real core material.
Where this time we really do want you to understand every equation and
build up a solid foundation that we're gonna use for the rest of the course.
Okay, so make sure you slow me down, speed me up whenever if there's any
questions today.
But I don't wanna just drop in and start teaching you the approach until I
motivate it with an example.
So I told you the whole course is gonna sort of unroll with making a robot do
something very simple.
And then making the task harder and harder and
trying to build up our capabilities.
So for today, we're gonna do just a basic pick and place.
This is what we're gonna achieve here.
We've got a red brick in a bin.
And we are collectively going to figure out how to program the robot to go pick
up that brick and move it over to the other bin, okay?
We're gonna do one major cheat, which is the reason why I didn't bring the robot
in here to do it today, in addition to the logistical hurdle that that was.
But we're gonna assume that perception is given for today.
We're gonna assume that someone has told you exactly the location of the red brick
in the world.
And we're not gonna rely on the process of getting that information from the
cameras, okay?
But given that assumption of someone telling you it's exactly the ground
truth initial position of the red brick and the target position and
orientation of the red brick, we're gonna be able to try to figure out all of the
work we have to do to make the robot do that.
Okay, and the sketch for how we're gonna do that is like this, okay?
First, we're gonna go through a bit of kinematics and spatial algebra.
I think, so the polls, by the way, the survey in the first piece, I love seeing
the results of those.
I read them carefully.
I adjust what I'm doing here because of it.
So it was very helpful for me to see that 27.4, I think, of you said you know
kinematics, right?
That helps me dial it in, right?
But even those of you that know kinematics, you might still benefit from
going through it the way we're gonna go through it.
I'm gonna emphasize things a little bit differently than a standard robot
kinematics sort of treatment.
Really emphasizing the algebra and not the trigonometry, okay?
After we understand basic sort of kinematics, we're gonna start by sort of
pretending the robot isn't there and just thinking about where we want the hand
to move over time, okay?
So we're gonna come up with a sketch for the end effector of the robot,
the gripper, okay?
And we're gonna just even imagine that the block gets picked up when we get
there, okay?
But we're just gonna sort of hallucinate what we want the hand to do.
And that's gonna be a fairly easy thing to program once we have the language of
kinematics and transforms and spatial algebra, okay, and trajectories.
And then we're gonna do the work to then convert the target end effector
locations, trajectory, okay, into joint angles for the robot.
And that's the kinematics problem.
And we do that by thinking about a coordinate frame attached to the gripper.
I'm gonna say all these things again carefully.
This is just the sketch for the lecture.
Okay, so we're gonna figure out how to move that end effector by backing out and
figuring out what all the joint angles have to be on the robot so that we can
turn that into the IWA position command going into our low-level controller.
Okay, so let me start by talking about kinematics, right, and spatial algebra is
the way I wanna talk about that.
So kinematics is the language, the set of tools for reasoning about the geometries.
So geometric properties of the algebra of the system, okay?
It's about geometry.
The concepts of geometry, I'm sure, are familiar to you, right?
Trigonometry is sort of familiar to you.
But even some of the smartest, most advanced roboticists I know often screw up
their spatial algebra.
I have done it for years.
I will do it again, right?
So the underlying geometry is very familiar.
But I would say that getting this right is very subtle.
It looks so easy, but if you don't get it right, you will inevitably mess it up
down the line, okay?
This is how it goes, right?
So typically you'll see someone, you know, a roboticist working on a problem,
it's not quite working out.
They've typically got their right hand in the air, right?
Their head is not upright most of the time.
They're doing something like this.
And then at some point they get frustrated and they phone their dynamics friend,
right?
And in particular, there's a dynamics team that works on Drake and they're just
fantastically good.
And you can phone your friend and ask, like, okay, I've got this series of
operations I'm trying to get right and it's wrong, what do I do?
And they always have, like, a really fast, correct answer, right?
And so what puts these people in their sort of elite group of people that can
answer dynamics queries correctly, right, almost all the time?
You know, they're very smart, that's for sure, but that's not the reason, right?
They just took time to make good notation.
That's it.
If you have the right notation, you can, you know, you can make the notation
make your math work out right, right?
So it just takes a little bit of work up front to agree on a notation that makes
it so you can't write things down incorrectly on paper or in code, right?
So I'm going to be a little fierce here today about telling you some of our
notation because it's going to save you bugs, you know, down the line if you
listen.
Okay.
So we're going to think about, talk about a bit about, you know, emphasis on
notation.
It matters.
All right, let's begin.
So we're going to talk, you know, the notion of geometry of kinematics, it
always starts with just a point, okay?
So let's define, start thinking about a point in space.
We'll call our point A, okay?
We want to talk about the position of this point in space.
We're going to talk about, and we're going to call that the position P of A,
okay?
So P for position, not point, and A is the name of the point.
We're going to name our points, okay?
Now, we have to be a little careful.
If you talk about a position in a 3D space, positions are sort of not
absolute.
They're always relative to something, even if it's the world origin, right?
Okay?
So we want to say it's relative to some other point, for instance.
So we're going to write that as the position of A relative to B.
And I'm going to use this weird superscript before the P, okay?
Everybody hates that.
I hated it when we first saw it, but it's the way that you get things to work, okay?
But even that is still not quite enough, right?
So if I'm saying that I've got a point B and a point A, then I've got a position,
you know, of A relative to B, that's describing the vector between them.
But if I want to write that vector down in three numbers, I have to embed it in
some coordinate system.
How do I decide which the first number is going to be my X coordinate,
let's say, my Y coordinate, my Z coordinate, if it's going to be in 3D space,
but I still need to define some coordinate system.
So we're going to define coordinate systems with the notion of a frame.
That's the right hand that people hold up in the air and look at it from different angles, okay?
We're going to talk about a coordinate frame or just a frame F, okay?
Now, this is where I got my multicolored chalk to help.
A coordinate frame could have its own--it has its own origin,
and then it has an X direction, a Y direction,
let's get this, X, Y, Z, okay?
Now, that color matters.
You should remember it always, and what I was just doing with the mnemonic,
I was just doing in my head to make sure I got it right,
is that X, Y, Z goes to RGB,
and every time you see in pretty much any software,
it could be computer graphics software or whatever,
you're going to see these little triads, they're called,
these little coordinate frames, just like the ones you see, okay?
And you know which one is X, which one is Y, which one is Z,
just by the color code.
And everybody should use the same color codes.
Every once in a while you see someone use something different,
and that's just weird.
But, yeah, so X, Y, Z, RGB, okay?
Those are your three axes.
And our full notation then, for just--we've just done a point so far in a frame,
we're going to say the position of point A relative to B in coordinate frame F, okay?
That's the worst it's going to get,
but it's going to go the distance for us, okay?
So this is our target.
This is our relative to.
And this is our expressed in frame.
Okay, that's a subscript.
Now, writing that all the time is good.
It's explicit.
A lot of times these things are, you know, there's some common choices for these,
so we do definitely have shorthand for it.
So if I were to write P A of F, for instance,
that is just shorthand for when this and this are the same.
There's a really important frame, which is the world frame,
my world origin, which we'll call W.
And if I write just P of A up there,
I'm going to assume that what you mean is A in the world frame relative to the world origin.
So that's just our short.
Okay, so we're going to have a few other really important frames today.
We're going to use like G for our gripper frame, O for our object frame.
This becomes a very nice vocabulary for starting to talk about these things.
So just so you start thinking about the mechanics of these, right?
So for instance, when does, well, let me do it in the other order here.
Here's a little check yourself, okay?
Let's say G is my gripper frame.
By the way, think about, if you see this now, this is just the object frame here, O.
I've got red as the X axis, Y as the green axis, Z as the blue axis.
This is commonly called, you can always use your right hand to do it, it's a right hand rule.
And it's a little weird, you have to remember that Y is going into the board, not out of the board.
That's called vehicle coordinates.
It's used commonly in a lot of robotics, certainly in autonomous vehicles, for instance.
If you're piloting an airplane, they do this.
So don't, yeah, I guess you want to get that right.
But for this class, you can always assume we're in vehicle coordinates.
There's pretty much two canonical choices out there.
Okay, so now take a second and think about this.
Which is a possible value for the position of the object, my red brick, relative to the gripper,
using the notation we talked about?
Yeah.
Good, yeah, yeah, so if I use a frame as my relative to, I'm talking about the origin of the frame.
So in this relative, it's valid to put a whole frame in there, meaning the origin.
Great.
I see some hands, yeah, what's up?
There is benefit for decoupling the B and the F, yeah.
You might have, I mean, even in the world frame, you might want to adjust the difference between two different points, right,
the relative vector between two different points.
That's used commonly.
In fact, in the mechanics of operating them depends on having that ability to decouple it.
Yeah.
Okay, option B.
Correct, right, because G is implied, the expressed in frame, right,
and so when you put your hand up like that and think about it, the object is along the Y axis here, right.
So point three's got to be the big one.
And just to lock that in, if I were to put a W here now, right,
now I want the location of the red object relative to the gripper frame, but in world, expressed in world coordinates, yeah.
Oh, the world, I'm sorry, the world is, yes, that's right, just assume it's right here.
I forgot to say that.
Thank you.
It's at least aligned with the grid, yeah.
Got an A, yes.
Okay.
Now the fact that that changed, you know, with just that one change in notation is going to be important
and you'll understand some of the properties, right.
So you'll pretty quickly understand that, for instance, let's see, I got another example here.
Yeah.
When do these two things match, right, if I have --
if I have different expressed in frames, when are the positions the same, yeah.
The object is this red brick.
Oh, yeah, it's my little foam red brick, it's like my little prop, yeah.
And it's at or near, I mean, the world frame, all you needed to know to answer this question is that the grid is the ground,
I should have said that more carefully, but the grid is the ground and the world frame is aligned, yeah, with,
that's the X axis in the world frame.
Yeah.
Yes.
Student: [Inaudible]
And then I plotted it in world coordinates.
Exactly, so it's going, so that vector that you drew, that in my head that I drew from here to here,
goes X2 and Z negative 2, yeah, perfect.
So when would I have a property like this, if I have two different expressed in frames, but the same points,
what would, when would the, in what case would that, you have a quality there?
Yeah.
Student: [Inaudible]
Okay, that's good, yeah, I mean, certainly if there's no rotational difference between C and D,
if they're just translations apart from it, yeah, then that's going to hold, okay.
Now, so that's a particular property, the notation's going to make it so you don't have to remember,
I mean, you can think about that, but the notation's going to protect you from having to remember every detail.
Okay, but that just exposes some of the subtlety that we want to build the notation around.
This is why we have rules, and why I like to think about the rules as the algebra of the rules.
Okay, I'll leave that here, come over here.
Right, so, you know, in a standard sort of kinematics class for robots, you'll like,
start saying I have theta, and then you'll get some sort of a length,
and you'll get a lot of like, x equals L sine theta, or this is cosine theta, or something like this.
Okay, that, all this stuff that you might have seen before in your kinematics classes,
27.4 of you that have seen that before, right, that is still valid.
But I would like to lift us up, instead of talking about the trigonometry,
we're going to talk about a frame here, a frame here, a frame here, okay,
and we're going to use algebra to talk about how they can be combined, how you go back and forth between them.
When the computer goes to do that algebra for you, it will compute sines and cosines and everything like that,
but we're going to just stay at the algebra level for now.
Okay, so here's the basics of the algebra, the spatial algebra.
We have an addition, right?
If I want to add two positions together, two relative positions together, I can do that,
but I need my superscripts to match for it to be a valid addition operation,
and that is how I get from A to C, right?
These need to match, and these need to match, okay?
There's an additive inverse, right?
So P of A to B, B relative to A, if I take the negation of that, that just flips my vector around, right?
That just points the vector in the other direction.
Okay, now you can see, with a few operations like this,
we can start building up a powerful set of tools that will allow me to think about how my frames move around in space.
But so far, we've only talked about positions and translations.
The other thing I need to talk about is rotations.
And again, there's a lot to dig into in rotations, especially 3D rotations,
but I want to stay first, at least at the spatial algebra sense, okay?
So I'm going to have my rotation here that goes between two different frames, for instance.
This is again my relative to, and my target frame here.
And think about that as the relative rotation that gets me G to F, yeah?
Now, I write this as a capital R. It looks like it could be a rotation matrix.
It's not wrong to think about it like that, but there's actually many ways to represent rotations on the computer or on your pad of paper, okay?
And I'm not assuming that it's a rotation matrix here.
This is just an abstract concept of a rotation.
If you choose to represent it with a rotation matrix, you're welcome to do that.
If you want to represent it with Euler angles, three angles, you know, roll, pitch, yaw, you can do that.
If you want to represent it with quaternions, you can do that, okay?
We'll talk about all those things again, but I just -- to abstract that, it's not necessarily a matrix,
but we're going to operate on it in kind of a matrix-like way in our algebra.
In particular, we will define the multiplication.
I want to take a point that's expressed in one frame and express it in a different frame.
It's the rotation matrix that tells me how to do that.
So --
Right, so this is back to your question, right?
So if I want to change my expressed in frame and leave the other ones the same,
then I need to take -- it's the rotation operators that operate on these expressed in frames.
So I can shift the positions, I can shift -- you know, these other --
the superscripts I can shift with addition, the subscripts I shift with multiplication,
you put them together and you get the full transform.
Okay?
You can also multiply rotations.
So RAB, RBC, as long as those intermediate subscripts hold,
then this gives me a rotation from R to C.
And there's a multiplicative inverse.
I take the inverse of that rotation, that's just rotating me the other direction,
and it gives me -- oops -- E to A.
Yes?
That's great.
So that's a key idea, is that you can change the expressed in frame and the origin doesn't matter.
Yeah?
That's actually an exercise.
But it's a straightforward calculation.
It's a good question to convince yourself of.
Exercise-worthy.
Yeah?
Multiplying positions, no.
Adding rotations, no.
The standard operation, if you want to operate with different rotations, is to multiply them together.
Yeah?
We're going to be able to -- yeah.
You'll see the last few.
But there's only a few operations that we allow, but they become very expressive.
Notice -- and this is related to your point -- we don't actually need an expressed in frame for the rotations.
If you're talking about the relative rotation between those, the origin doesn't matter,
and you don't need an expressed in frame.
Okay?
Now, yeah, the interesting stuff is when you have to put them together and do both.
And that's where you get a full transformation of coordinates, a coordinate transform.
Is that a question or a stretch?
Stretch.
That's good.
Well, I mean, it's not -- you're good to stretch.
I welcome the stretch, but I'm sorry your arm is numb.
Yes?
Ah.
It's -- that's a great point.
So the interpretation -- so certainly in one degree of freedom, if you were to rotate along one axis
and then rotate again with a multiplication of our rotations, that would be like adding the angles.
Completely agree.
It gets more subtle in 3D, but you're completely right.
Yeah?
Okay, so a transform, coordinate transform is what we call it,
is going to be a rotation plus a translation put together.
And we're going to use capital X for that.
This is a rotation and a translation.
Now, you might have heard this by a few different names.
Pose is another word for it.
You might call it a full spatial transform if you're --
These are -- well, they're not quite synonyms.
Technically, pose is a noun and transform is a verb.
So it's okay that we have both, I guess, and they could be used correctly in a sentence in that sense.
The object in code that we use to talk about this is the rigid transform.
Okay.
There's a multiplication for transforms that looks a lot like the rotations.
There's a multiplicative inverse that flips the order of those two.
Yes?
I'm sorry, say it louder.
Why do we choose it to be a multiplication?
Yeah, it's really, I think, to keep things familiar.
All the operations are going to feel -- I mean, we could have chosen anything, right?
We could define our algebra anyway.
But the way you're going to operate on these things, I think, is most similar to what you think about with, like, linear algebra, multiplication, and stuff like that.
I think that will keep your -- I mean, even just the notion of an inverse and stuff like this.
When do you want to use a minus sign?
When do you want to call that inverse?
I think it's the most consistent with our wiring.
Okay, now, it's interesting to think about this.
Now, if -- remember, I tried to abstract away the mathematical concept of a rotation from the representation in numbers.
You know, if I represent this as a 3 by 3 matrix, for instance, you can.
That's one way to do it, is the basis, the x, y, z coordinates, basically.
Then this inverse is actually just the matrix inverse.
So that's another answer for you here, right?
Is that it's going to operate in many cases like a matrix.
It happens that if you were to do a similar kind of representation of this, then typically these are represented with 3 by 4 matrices,
because that's what graphics processors and even CPUs these days can eat up and chew out -- whatever -- chew and spit out very well.
They can crank lots of these.
But then the inverse here, the inverse of this is not just a matrix inverse, even though there's a matrix representation of those things.
It's slightly more -- it's not hard.
It's, again, computationally optimized, but it's not quite a matrix inverse here.
We have to -- we've defined an abstraction here that is independent of the matrix representation.
And the code will take care of that if you operate among matrices.
OK, the most important thing here, then, is that -- I'll put it right here -- is that this pose helps us go move points around in different frames.
It combines the operations of translation and rotation.
So in particular, we have to get the subscripts and superscripts right to get it completely right here.
If I want to transform a position relative to f expressed in f into being relative to g expressed in g,
which if you think about it, that's kind of what we're going to want.
That's the operation that matters the most.
If I've got a point in the world and I want to think about where it is --
let's say my camera took a picture of something and I want to change it from camera coordinates to world coordinates,
this is the operation we want.
And all you would need is the pose of the camera here, for instance.
I could maybe write it as xwc, camera in the world frame.
And that would allow me to take points that were measured by a camera and project them into world coordinates.
And when I do define this multiplication of a transform times a position,
then you could also break that down and it's two steps.
It's the addition and the rotation that are held inside that transform with the subscripts implied.
That's my shorthand.
This transform collects the operations of position and rotation.
Now, I promise, you'll start writing code and you'll twist around saying,
"Should I add the position of the frame first and then multiply or should I multiply or whatever?"
This notation can save you if you choose.
Any more questions on that? I love the questions.
Oh, a series of questions.
I'm adding the position and I'm multiplying the rotation times this other position.
That's to take the total transform from frame F to frame G.
If I want to take this thing that's expressed in and relative to F and put it as expressed in and relative to G,
then I do this, which is just a shorthand for doing this.
Yeah, a transform that contains both the position and the rotation.
I'm going to check their frames.
Their frames, because points don't have orientation.
These are all good things to check.
When I wrote the notes, I tried to think about every one of them and be explicit about that.
I'm pretty sure I answered those right.
I forget what it was. There's one of them that you would think you could use a point, but it just never occurs in practice.
We don't even include it in our notation.
Everything we've said is consistent.
We have a basic language now of thinking about how to operate on transforms.
We need to take the points and move them around between different coordinate frames.
This is our language.
The way we get it right, this language is also going to extend into velocities, for instance, even accelerations, forces.
The same tools go all the way up through the dynamics level.
We've only talked about positions so far.
Here's an interesting question for you.
When I call plant getPositions, some of you thought a lot about that, of the context and the EWA.
What do I get out?
This isn't a Dray question. This is a real question.
What does this thing return?
A vector of joint positions.
How big was that vector?
It's 7 most of the time.
It happens in the Pset problem. I think we used the planar one, so it was 3.
In the full 3D, EWA has 7 degrees of freedom.
In the plane, we locked a bunch of them out, so there's only 3.
This returns a 7 by 1 vector.
What do you think you would get if you called getPositions of the same context--
these are the plant contexts, right?
The plant contexts for the foam brick. I'll just write brick.
What do you think you get out if you call that?
Okay. That's nice.
7 joint angles that you get for the brick.
What are the 7?
What 7 angles do you think about?
The EWA joint angles?
Got it.
That's not what I'm looking for, but it's a good idea.
Yes?
It could be a scalar, but it needs to be a complete description of the position of that brick.
The generalized position means position and orientation.
I know that's confusing, but the generalized position--
everything I need to represent the configuration of that brick.
Good. So he says, I don't know which rotation we're representing internally,
but maybe if it's a quaternion, it would be 7 by 1.
It does come out to be also a 7 by 1 vector.
And it's 7 numbers that represent this.
Why is it 7 numbers?
The 7 numbers are the x position, the y position, the z position,
and then the quaternion x, y, z, w, where this--
I know not everybody knows quaternions, but this is a unit quaternion.
So the magnitude of q is 1.
So it's unit.
There's an extra constraint on that.
My point is not to teach you everything about quaternions.
My point is that in robotics, there are many ways to represent 3D rotation.
And even when you run a single simulation,
you will go back and forth between them often.
And we try to make that easy.
So if you have a rigid transform, you can extract its rotation.
You can flip it to a quaternion representation, to a three angles,
a roll pitch yaw representation.
You can treat it as a matrix.
Each of those are particularly well-suited for particular operations.
If you want to throw it on the GPU and compute series of transforms,
then you want the matrix representation.
And those become matrix multiplies that are heavily optimized.
There are other operations where if you want to represent it in a vector,
if you took your rotation and took the nine numbers and put it in a vector,
then you're carrying around more numbers than you need.
It's not an efficient representation.
You would think you only need three numbers, the roll pitch yaw.
But the roll pitch yaw-- I won't go into great detail,
but it has singularities.
So you can get yourself into problems if you only use roll pitch yaw.
It's not actually a complete representation of orientation in 3D space.
There's something called gimbal lock.
And robots don't like that.
So we carry around four numbers in our configuration,
in our minimal vector representation of an orientation.
And we carry around one extra constraint.
And that's the way we get around the singularities.
Yeah?
Sorry.
[INAUDIBLE]
Good.
Yeah.
So in the context, it actually-- because this is a floating base,
it only exists in world frame.
That's true.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
That'll be super clear in a few pictures, I think.
So call me on it if it's not.
Nice.
OK.
So we're building up the tools and just many different representations
of orientation.
It's interesting, actually.
Everything is beautiful and clean in two dimensions.
If you want to do rotations in 2D, you can represent it
with a single number or an angle.
Everything works beautifully.
When you get to 3D, everything's worse.
There's all these weird quirks about representing orientations in 3D.
We have highly optimized tools to deal with it,
but it's slightly unsatisfying that there's not
one right answer for all of these.
When we get to spatial velocities, angular velocity, things collapse.
And actually, there is a one right representation.
But orientation is bad.
It's ugly.
OK.
So now that we have our algebra, we're going to program a robot.
And I told you the way we're going to program the robot to start
is by making a series of key frames, really.
I'm going to start by--
the world was perceived by an oracle.
So someone like the Oracle of Delphi says, oh, your object is at xwo.
Right?
Someone told me xwo.
When I say oracular or an oracle, it's a weird-- yeah.
The etymology of that sort of is weird.
But we often say, oh, if someone magically
gave you the right answer, we call that the oracle
or the oracular perception.
In this case, I'm going to say the object, which I'll just use as o.
The object frame or the object pose or the object frame,
which I'm going to describe in numbers with a transform or a pose
here in the world coordinates.
Someone told me where the red brick is.
And they told me by giving me this.
OK.
And now my job is to come up with a series of hand--
I want to figure out what xg of w is at many different times.
That's the next step of our operation.
OK.
So actually, there's going to be many different frames
we're going to think about.
Let's take-- I'm going to even call this the object's initial.
That says initial there.
And I want to have a target or a final object frame.
So this is where I want to set it down.
I guess I called it goal in my notes.
And if I don't make them match, then I
will do the wrong thing in 10 minutes.
OK.
And then I need to start designing the gripper key frames.
So I'll make maybe--
I have an initial gripper.
When the robot woke up, the robot is in some particular initial gripper
location.
The object is in some initial that I've been told about.
And then I want to make--
I figure out where the gripper needs to be when I pick the object,
where it should be when I place the object.
And actually, there's a subtlety, right?
Because we don't want to knock the object over when
we're coming in to pick it up.
So we typically make a pre-pick location.
So we first actually just drive the robot simply just above the object.
We'll call that pre-pick.
And then we'll go down.
We'll close our hand.
We'll go back up to pre-pick.
And then go over to pre-place.
Yeah.
Is that good?
I sound silly saying it, but I think you know what I mean.
Pre-pick, g pre-place.
And then maybe the g final.
I'll go to some final position.
All right.
So these are the frames abstractly.
And we're going to represent them by giving them
transforms for each of those.
First in the world coordinates.
And we'll design a set of key frames that do that.
By the way, all that algebra stuff is right in the notes.
And you can highlight on it and change my lectures.
And all the rules are there and careful and the inverse
and all that stuff's there.
So this is roughly what we're trying to do now
is come up with this imagined hand moving through the air
trajectory that goes from object initial to object goal.
And we're going to ignore the dynamics of actually picking it
up.
We're just going to hallucinate.
If I were to do this, what's it going to do?
It's pretty funny, actually.
I made this list.
Typed in the code to make the example.
And I had forgotten an important detail.
There's one more frame that I think you need.
Seems pretty important.
It'll come up in a second here.
You kind of need to go-- you can't go from a straight line,
it turns out, from the pre-pick to the pre-final.
This is a simulation running.
So I'd sheared the hand off because I
forgot to clear the bins.
So we're actually going to make one more in the middle
here, which is G clearance.
Mia culpa.
Look at that.
And that's why we test things in simulation before we
go into the real world.
OK.
So the language that we have now makes it actually
relatively easy.
I mean, it's a little verbose because there's a lot of frames,
but every individual line is actually very simple.
To make-- if someone just tells me the initial gripper,
the initial object, then I can go on through.
I should say, when I write PABF on the board,
to write that in code, we do P_AB_F.
And that works.
So this, hard to write in your software editor.
This is our translation of that.
And similarly for rotations and transforms.
OK.
So given that, you can sort of read through here.
The first thing I do is I try to decide an initial grasp
for the object.
I wanted to find the position of the grasp
by first thinking about where I want the object
to be relative to the hand.
OK.
So the numbers here are 0, 0.11, and 0.
Why is that?
I want it to be above and down the y-axis.
Green is why.
Positive 0.11 puts it right about here.
I'd like the center of the object to be at y, 0.11.
Turns out that's the length of the hand and the fingers.
It's in meters.
OK.
And I'll be otherwise 0, 0.
So that'll place my hand exactly above it.
And then for my rotations, I just
need to make sure that the frame is such that I'm coming down
from above.
So I can do that by just putting the relative orientation
of the gripper frame relative to the object
with a couple rotation matrices.
That's my least favorite line in this.
I could do it a couple different ways.
But I made an x rotation and a z rotation.
I thought that would be the simplest out of the box.
And then I can combine the rotation and the position
that I desire of the object relative to the gripper
into this object.
But that's not enough, right?
I still have to go from--
define from the grasp to the object is the inverse.
And I want to ultimately go from the grasp to the world.
But since I know all of the relative transforms,
I can make all of that work.
I can go from x o initial, x o grasp
tells me what the grasp should be at the time of picking.
It's all just following the algebra.
It was interesting.
We asked separately, do you know Python, which most of you
said yes.
And we asked if you know NumPy, and less of you said yes.
This is multiplication, matrix multiplication in NumPy,
the little add around symbol.
Don't shoot the messenger.
That's not my favorite.
But that's just a matrix multiplication.
So the NumPy abstraction is provided here on transforms.
And behind the scenes, it's doing what it needs to do,
with whatever rotation representation
you've done in order to make that math we just did work.
And with a relatively simple cascade of transforms,
we can come up with a list of grippers in the world frame.
And I just did it in a little dictionary
here that goes through and names all of them.
The clearance one is actually one of the easier,
the more interesting ones, because I wanted to--
I was in some initial orientation,
and I had some final orientation.
And so to be somewhere half orientation between there,
I had to do a little bit of orientation math
to find, to decide what the half angle was in a general way.
And that was easiest to switch to yet another representation
of orientations, which is the axis angle representation.
And then there, you just flip the axis angle,
you divide the angle in two, and you flip back,
and you're good.
So all of these are good at different pieces of the stack.
So that gives us our key frames.
And then we have to somehow decide the timing.
So we need to go from just key frames to the timing.
See, I want to go from xg initial, xg pre-pick,
to just some trajectory that I'm going
to execute on the robot, which is
the gripper in the world frame as a function of time.
So somehow, I need to embed those in time.
So maybe at time 0, I'm at xg initial.
And at different times, I'm going to be at xg pre-pick,
and so on.
But in order to move the robot, I
need to define how I get between the two.
So the language we use for these is
the language of trajectories.
So I'm going to make a pose trajectory.
And it's interesting now, we have to think, in order to do this,
we have to think about what's the right way to interpolate
between poses, between transforms.
So for positions, it's perfectly reasonable to just do
sort of a straight line interpolation.
That would be like, if people know the term, first order
hold.
That would be from filtering or something like that,
you could call it a first order hold.
But for positions, p of g at time 0, pg, say, at time 1,
linear interpolation is fine.
You can get fancier.
Maybe you don't want to have any discontinuities.
Your robot might go--
if you do that, maybe you want to smooth those out,
so you could have a smoother interpolation,
like a cubic spline would be something people would do.
But for today, we're going to just do a linear interpolation.
So I just define the time of this, time initial, time
pre-pick, and then I just take a linear combination of those
to index by time.
What about for the rotations, though?
Once again, unfortunately, we have
to think about the different rotations, the different ways
to represent rotation.
You can do axis angle, but the axis
is changing, not just the angle is changing as you move along.
Interpolating linearly in rotation matrices
is not a good idea.
I could convince you of that if you want,
but if you just took the numbers that
populate a rotation matrix--
so a rotation matrix would be a 3 by 3 matrix.
It would be an orthonormal matrix.
You'd like the vectors to all be of unit length.
You could interpolate between two orthonormal matrices
and get vectors that are not unit length, for instance.
You wouldn't even have a valid rotation matrix
if you just took rotation 1, rotation 2, smash them together.
You wouldn't get a valid rotation.
It turns out that the most natural way to do this
is in the language of quaternions again.
So of our many rotation representations,
quaternions tends to be a winner here.
And basically, you take a--
it's almost to say a straight line in quaternions
is the right thing.
But quaternions have to be unit norm,
just like rotation matrices do.
So you have to do an interpolation on the sphere,
basically.
So that's all good.
It's called spherical linear interpolation.
[WRITING]
Slurp, if you're cool.
Slurp.
Spherical linear-- take some liberties-- interpolation.
Yeah?
OK.
And the code will do this for you.
All you have to know is that don't call linear interpolate
on quaternions.
You'd be unhappy.
Call slurp on the quaternions.
Now, this matters a lot, actually.
A lot of people have thought now about pose estimation
with deep networks, for instance.
So you're trying to train a neural network, let's say,
to output poses.
If you don't get these details right,
you might get zero training error on this pose,
zero training error on this pose.
But when the network goes to interpolate,
you're going to have the same problems.
So the representation people use for your output layer
in a neural network that's trying to estimate pose
matters.
And it's all the same details we're doing here.
This just happens to be our interpolation across time.
But for years, people would--
my neural network's not learning poses.
And it's just, well, you asked it to learn something
it sort of couldn't learn.
And then the field figured out the right ways to ask it.
OK.
Is that clear?
So it turns out that we try to make all this stuff easy
in code.
There's various different trajectories
that you can use.
Piecewise quaternion slurp, for instance.
And a piecewise pose, which just takes the linear interpolation
plus the quaternion slurp interpolation.
It takes the whole pose.
So a piecewise pose will take a pose at this time,
a pose at this time, a pose at this time, a pose at this time,
and give you a nice, smooth linear interpolation
as appropriate with the rotations.
And that gets us our imagined trajectory.
A lot of tools, but hopefully it's OK.
All right, so that was step two.
Step one was just understanding this notion of frames.
Step two was making the sketch.
Step three is connecting the gripper back to joint angles.
And so luckily, forward kinematics
is a pretty simple thing given all the spatial algebra.
So forward kinematics is the operation
of going from joint positions.
Most of the time for most of our robots,
I could just say joint angles.
It's mostly angles, but you could
have a prismatic joint or a linear joint on your robot.
It's more generally joint positions.
You can have a couple different--
you can have helical joints and all kinds
of weird things on robots.
You go from joint positions to poses.
And just to get the language down,
inverse kinematics is from poses to joint positions.
We'll do differential kinematics soon too,
which is going to be basically the derivative of this map.
So it's going to be from joint velocities
to 3D spatial velocities, which we'll define soon.
But this is the family of kinematics methods.
The one we want first here is just forward kinematics.
So forward kinematics would be if I
want to find the position of the gripper,
let's say the pose of a gripper in space,
I need that to be a function of the joint angles,
the joint positions here.
This is the forward kinematics function.
So the way that we do this--
normally, I mean, in the most cases,
the software would do all the heavy lifting for you.
You just need to know how to ask it.
It depends on how we represent positions, our choice of poses.
But mostly, it's the picture you already suspect here.
So where I've got a kinematic frame at my gripper,
step one is to go to the kinematic frame
in my second to last link using my spatial algebra.
And then go to my third to last link, my fourth to the last,
until you get all the way back to the world.
And you just recursively apply the spatial algebra,
and it'll do the work for you.
The only interesting thing is that the relative frame
between any two bodies, when you have a joint in the middle,
depends partly on Q. So you'll get, for instance,
from body one, let's say, from body one to body two,
relies on first saying, from the body frame,
where is the joint, then figuring out
what is the relative-- the transform
as a function of the joint angle,
and then from that joint to the parent frame.
So there's three transforms that will take you from your one
link to the parent link.
So this would typically be, I've got to go from body one
to body two, then it's going to be composed of--
from the-- let me call it, actually,
the parent and the child.
How about that?
From the parent to the child, then I'm
going to go from the parent to the parent joint.
And then I'm going to--
let's say it's Q7 first.
This is my joint, from parent joint to child joint,
and then from child joint to child frame.
And every one of those relative transforms
is made up of a composition, through our spatial algebra,
of those transforms.
Yes?
So that's my seventh joint angle on the robot,
but the point is really that it's just one number
for a revolute joint here that defines the rotation matrix,
if you will, that's inside here.
If it's a revolute joint, it's going to change the angles.
Now, this is not an artificial construction.
It's everywhere in robotics.
You may realize it, right?
But right in the robot description files,
if you look at the way things are defined,
you define first a link, like EULINK1.
You say where it's--
you say its pose, its inertial pose,
where is its center of mass and its moment of inertia.
But then you also say, what's the joint?
You give the position of the joint as a relative pose.
This is not my format.
This is the standard format.
You say, what's the child?
What's the parent?
And the fact that it's revolute lets
you know what this operation has to be
as a function of that one angle.
So it's just a matter of composing these transforms
together, and the order of those transforms
and the values in those transforms
are completely described in our robot description formats.
The EUL is kind of a boring one, because you're really
just going from the tip back to the base.
The Allegro hand is a slightly more interesting hand here.
So if you plot the kinematic tree,
you just plot the parent-child relationship straight
from the URDF that describes the robot description file that
describes the hand.
You'll see that there's a little bit of a difference
there, right?
You'll see that there's a root, like the palm of the hand.
And then each of those fingers has a revolute joint
that connects to the hand.
And then there's another joint that connects to that
and another joint that connects to that.
These are all revolute.
So if I have a red ball, maybe an apple--
is that an apple?
Yeah, an apple relative to the tip of my fingers.
I want to figure out where the tip of the hand.
Then I just apply the transforms up the tree.
And similarly, if I need to figure out what these two are,
I can go up and back down.
Typically, there's a lot of very clever caching that happens.
So you can ask questions of the kinematics many, many times.
And it just computes the tree once and then
makes it fast to ask as many questions of the kinematics
as you want.
Sorry, so I'll give you a hand.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Awesome.
So that's a great question is, are there multiple solutions?
So the map from joint positions to poses is unique.
If you tell me what the joint angles are,
the robot really is in that position.
And the end effector is in a known position.
That is a one-way mapping that's unique.
If you ask me to put it in a pose,
how do I get the joint positions?
There could be multiple joint positions
that could be the same.
So in general, the inverse kinematics problem
is harder than the forward kinematics.
It turns out that the differential kinematics is
also--
it's a little bit easier to think about.
So we're going to do a lot of the work for that demo.
Actually, we're going to avoid solving the inverse kinematics
problem.
We're going to solve those two problems first.
Yeah?
You can ask again.
[INAUDIBLE]
You're right on.
So the follow-up question was, why is that useful?
Why is forward kinematics useful, right?
Absolutely, we need to solve a version of this.
But it turns out that the differential kinematics
version is going to be the best solution for this first version.
So basically, when the robot wakes up, I have a cue.
I'm going to figure out where the end effector is now.
And then if I want to move the hand
in a particular trajectory, it's easier
to figure out differentially how I should move my joints
to follow a trajectory than to answer the question of,
if I'm here, I want you to be over here from scratch.
Decide how to be there.
It's actually easier to have a fully defined trajectory that
takes you there, because you can use the Jacobians
of the kinematics.
And we're going to see that.
So we actually are going to do differential inverse kinematics
because it's easier than the full inverse kinematics
problem.
Great question.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, good, good, yeah.
I was using P for parent, C for child.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, yeah, I'm going to-- yeah.
So think about there's a body.
This is where multicolor comes into play.
I've got a parent object--
parent.
And it has some frame here.
It's 3D in general.
I'm just going to do the two.
And then I've got a child.
And it's got some natural coordinate frame here.
But I need to do all the kinematics math.
I need to find two different things.
I want to define where is the joint that's connecting them
relative to the parent.
And then I'm going to define where is the joint that's
connecting them.
So I'll call this one P joint.
Let me write it not right on top of everything else.
P joint.
What do I call it?
Yeah, P joint.
And then I'll call this one C joint.
And so the location of the joint relative to any body
is a constant.
The numbers are just hidden in the description format.
Similarly, the joint relative to the parent, those are constants.
But the transform that goes from child joint to parent joint
is a function of the current joint angle.
And so for rotary joints, there's
a one function that you would use
to go from this to this as a function.
For prismatic joints, there's a different one.
For helical joints, there's a different one.
And that defines that last transform that you need.
And you just apply it recursively.
No, thank you for asking.
That's good.
,
So when you want to call the kinematics engine in code,
you can ask a multi-body plant.
There's a method on multi-body plant
that evaluates the kinematics.
There's a bunch of methods on multi-body plant.
You can get the kinematic velocities.
You can do accelerations.
You can do forces.
You can do all these other things.
The one that is exactly what we're talking about today,
that computes exactly those series of transforms for you,
is with proper optimizations behind the scenes.
So you can call this as much as you want
and everything like that, is eval body pose in world.
Pretty clear.
And the code says, I'm going to give you
xwb for a body b in world.
And you'll see that notation, the monogram notation.
In fact, it was working on Drake with the dynamics team
that made me change the way I talked about kinematics.
And I adopted the notation when we
tried to get rid of the bugs in my code, roughly.
So if you just have a multi-body plant,
plant.evalbody impose in world will do that.
The context is what holds q.
So that is a function of q.
It's just this.
If you want to do it in-- if you want a different system
to evaluate the poses of the multi-body plant in the systems
framework, you can just pull on the body poses output port.
That has all the body poses available for you pre-computed.
So a downstream system can just chew them up.
So the other-- I mean, there's a bunch of optimizations
hidden in the code.
If nobody ever asks for those body poses,
it only computes the things it needs to compute.
So it's only when a downstream system asks you
for, let's say, the camera output or something like this,
then it would render the camera.
But if you never ask, it doesn't render.
And for body poses, it happens that almost everything
you do with a plant is going to cause
you to compute the kinematics.
So you're probably not saving very much
by not calling that one.
But in general, it only computes things when it needs to.
And then it caches them so you can call it many times.
And again, the body poses output port,
it says this is going to give you
a list of xwb for all of the bodies in the plant.
So that's just the mechanics of using it.
All right, so I'm going to start differential kinematics.
But we left time on Tuesday to finish it.
And maybe I'll just set as a goal
to try to make my answer to your question a little bit more
complete, and we'll fill in the details after.
So let's think about differential kinematics.
So what I want to do is somehow say,
if I make a small change to my joint angles,
what's the small change that's going to result in the end
effector?
So let me use this variational notation here.
I want to say, what's a delta in xb as a function
of a small change in q?
And the math we need to do that is just
taking the gradient of this thing.
Whatever function we've already got,
if I just take the gradient of that,
that's going to give me my differential relationship
between a change in joint angle and a change
in the end effector positions.
And in every field, but certainly in robotics,
that thing is called a Jacobian.
In this case, it's a kinematic Jacobian.
So we would often just write this as jb,
remembering that it's a function of q of dq.
So this is the kinematic Jacobian.
Now, your question about invertibility was good.
So this is still going the good way.
Given a change in velocities, I can
tell you what a change in pose is with no problems.
And then what you're going to see
is that the inverse of this may not exist,
which is because there could be multiple solutions.
If there's a manifold of solutions that
could give me the same end effector,
then the inverse operation could be opposed.
The interesting question-- so we know how to represent--
I think it's reasonable if q is a 7 by 1 vector, joint angles,
let's say, then dq, if I want to say joint velocities--
if I put it in units of time in a second--
it's sort of reasonable to just say,
I'm going to take the seven numbers
and talk about the rotational velocity of each of my joints.
So we'll call that q dot, or you'll
see it written as v sometimes, which
is the joint of 7 by 1 joint velocities.
The interesting question is, how do we represent this?
We had a bunch of different ways to represent orientations.
How are we going to represent this?
And I'll just give the answer, and then we'll
have to continue next time.
So remember, we talked about 3 by 4 matrices
as a way to represent x.
We talked about, if you want a vector representation,
you could have x, y, z plus quaternions.
And there's axis angle.
There's all these different things.
The derivative of this, though, there is a one true answer.
We're back to everything's good again.
In this case, there's a spatial velocity,
which really is--
there's no singularities with respect to it.
It turns out just three numbers are enough,
and they represent everything, and they're
useful for all of our computations.
So it turns out we're going to call this spatial velocity.
And it's six numbers, which is going to be x dot, y dot, z
dot, and then three angular velocities.
So always and forever, we'll use this sort of spatial velocity.
Spatial velocities have an algebra.
We're going to define the same addition, multiplication
operations on these.
If you want to take a spatial velocity expressed
in one frame, put it in another frame,
we're going to grow our algebra to that, accelerations
and whatnot.
So I'll pick up there next Tuesday.
Good.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
The plan, like, context versus, like, spatial context.
Good.
Yeah?
Like, the plan context, like, the plan is, like,
the world, right?
Good.
So we have--
I made the point last time that the simulation is more
than the physics engine, right?
So when you have a whole diagram,
one of the pieces of the diagram is the multi-body plan.
There's also the scene--
[INAUDIBLE]
It's the physics engine.
So--
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, yeah.
That's fine.
So the only reason I want to make that distinction
is because, like, the controller also
has a model of the robot in it.
There's multiple places where you
might want to have a model of the robot in it, OK?
And they all might have some state.
So you have a context for the whole diagram.
If you want to get--
the plant context is just the context for that.
It's just, you know, position.
It's just time, state, and input.
Oh, OK.
Of the plant.
Of, like, the robot.
Of the multi-body plan.
Yep.
Of the physical simulation of the robot.
OK.
And then, like, the station context is, like--
That will be the one that contains
the context of all of the sub-diagram,
the pieces of the diagram.
OK.
So plant context is part of station context?
It is.
Yep.
It's actually just a--
it's a pointer into the middle of a bigger--
Oh, OK.
OK.
Good.
Good, good.
How's it going?
Hi.
I have a question in regards to, like, the undergrad versus,
like, the graduate version of the class.
OK.
Yeah.
So for context, I'm a 416.
OK.
And so this class doesn't necessarily, like,
have any time requirements.
Yep.
So I'm not bounded to, like, meeting at, like, a CIM,
whatever, or stuff like that.
Yeah, yeah.
And so I saw that the grad version is 12 units instead
of 15.
Yep.
Is that because of the fact that the grad--
like, the graduate version does not have a CIM component?
Like, what's the right of the--
That's exactly right.
Yeah.
The recitations and the work that they
do in the recitations adds three more units.
OK.
Now, the problem sets are mostly the same
with, like, a few differences, right?
So, like, this week there's one more problem on the graduate.
It's not always going to be more--
I mean, because they're both meant to be 12 units,
but we are aiming for a little bit more maturity.
So we should be able to do the same work--
that work in 12 hours.
And we're going to--
our survey questions sort of keep us honest about that,
and we can scale it back and forth.
So, yeah, it's designed--
I mean, I think the biggest thing you lose
is all the-- is, like, the super project aspect of it
and the Friday recitations.
So what's this aspect of the project?
Just the communications staff, you know,
talks you through the rhetorical argument of your project,
like, set it up.
How are you going to make it-- you know,
what is the thing you're trying to prove or disprove?
They're going to, like, help you with your project proposal,
help you with the-- right?
And so-- and use it as an excuse to teach you
how to communicate, right?
And then help you make a really good project.
The technical part of the project is the same in both.
OK.
And I guess, like, as a follow-up question to that,
for the grad--
so, like, for the undergraduate one, is it still the same?
Or, like, we can, like, one or two grad students?
Yep.
And what kind of difference in expectation
is there for, like, quantity, which is the product
you're dealing with?
It's not about quantity.
I think just we expect a little bit-- the emphasis
on the project and the graduate is more on the technical part.
The technical, OK.
Yeah.
And I try to say this carefully on the website.
So read the-- you know, read the words
and make sure you're happy with those words.
Yeah.
OK.
Thank you.
Cool.
Appreciate it.
How's it going?
Hi.
I was just wondering--
I know, like, I'm not sure if you're
going to explain this in future lectures,
but you showed, like, the link structure for the kinematic.
Yeah.
Like, the kinematic structure of Drake.
I'm just wondering if the dynamic structure is similar
to that and if that, like, inhibits some models
that you can use, like, in Drake.
Like for example, if you had like two rotors at--