OK.
Welcome back, everybody.
Let me apologize one more time about last Thursday.
I promised I wanted to be here, but thank you
for being flexible with me on that.
So today, we're going to do the plan from last Thursday.
And we're going to talk about a basic--
how do you get the robot moving to do some basic task,
moving a block from point 1 to point 2.
Just on the administrative side of things,
I hope everybody got the note that we
shifted the PSET schedule because of the PSET that
would be due Wednesday recovers material from here.
So there's no PSET due this Wednesday.
They'll both be due next Wednesday,
and the next one will be a little lighter.
The other quick administrative announcement
is that-- or for those of you in 6800, I hope most of you
went to the recitation last Friday,
and you'll be doing the journal clubs in the next recitations
this week.
I thought it was awesome.
Listening to the breakdown of how
CLIP organized their argument, and CLIP
being the research paper that we analyzed last week.
Even if people are in 843 and they
want to join for the next few weeks, you're welcome to come.
We've picked out a bunch of manipulation research papers.
We're going to do a journal club in the next two
sessions of the recitation.
It will be a bit on the manipulation content,
a bit on the rhetorical analysis of how--
is it a good paper?
Did they structure their argument?
I honestly got a lot out of thinking about how
I'm structuring my arguments.
Anyways, so that's all going on, and I hope it's working well.
And I'm actually very eager to hear your feedback
as you go through that.
So let me give you the basic story
for the next couple of lectures here.
So the goals are somehow modest.
We've got our KUKA.
We had it here last time, and I've got my little red brick
again today.
And all I'd like to do is help you guys plot a trajectory,
write the basic controller.
Thank you so much.
That's perfect.
Thank you.
So you can drive that KUKA to pick up a red brick,
grasp it, set it down on the other side.
It's going to touch, actually, a lot of pieces,
and it's going to lay the foundation for things
that we're going to use for a long time going forward.
In particular, I want to introduce you
to the idea of the spatial algebra.
So people-- I know lots of people
who I would consider to be excellent roboticists
who have a basic sense of kinematics.
But here's how it goes, roughly, is
that you'll be working on some kinematics problem.
Then they're everywhere.
Even if you're doing deep neural networks
for a posed estimation, you're going
to have a kinematics problem at some point.
And you're going to have a bug, and your vectors
are pointing the wrong way, or your robot's walking backwards,
or something's going wrong.
And you're just going to start flipping signs,
and taking your matrices, and putting them just like this.
And maybe if I multiply by that, or inverse that,
it happens to the best of us.
But there's-- well, not all of us.
So there are people out there who actually don't do that.
And they're like my dynamics friends.
I have some really good dynamics friends.
And these are the people that you call when
you're flipping matrices.
And they'll say, no, no, the answer is this.
And they get it right every time, every time.
So how do they do that?
So it could be that they spent years--
like they started off reading Euclid,
and then they went up to--
and they spent years with Goldstein, and whatever.
Maybe they did, but they didn't need to do that.
In fact, I don't think it would have helped them actually
get the bugs out.
What they have that most people don't have
is really good notation.
I swear, that's all it takes.
If you do a little bit of work and commit to the notation
early, then the notation will save you
from all of these problems down the line.
And the only thing that those dynamics friends are doing when
you come there with your mixed up signs and whatever
is that they rename your variables,
and they line them up, and the variables match,
and everything's good.
And then the spatial algebra will protect you.
So I swear, a little bit of work today
and embracing the basic concept will
save you down the line.
It will save you these late night,
my robot's not quite working, let's slip some signs,
which we've all done.
So we're going to introduce that in the context of moving
a brick around.
And it's going to go in a couple of pieces.
So first, we're going to think about just the notion of what
is a frame, what is an orientation, what
is a position in space.
There'll be many important frames on a robot.
I'm going to try to point on here instead of walking up.
In particular, we'll have a gripper and a gripper frame.
We'll have an object and an object frame.
And we'll think about grasping as getting the gripper
frame in the right relative orientation and position
to the object frame.
And then we're going to compose the bigger, richer behavior
by taking a bunch of those different position
relative frames of a gripper and just move it through.
At first, first pass here is just an open loop trajectory.
So it's just a trajectory that plays out in time
like a tape recorder that will move the hand
through some series of frames, basically, of moving frames
in order to pick up and drop off the block
at the desired location.
And then we're going to wire it all up to the arm
to turn that gripper plan sketch into a controller that's
going to move your robot around.
So that's our first pass at moving the robot.
So let's start off understanding some frames
and the spatial algebra.
So the basic notions we're working with here are very--
they're geometric, and they live in 3D, typically.
So the simplest concept is just a point
in some three-dimensional space.
Let's say P will be the position of some point of interest.
Let's have a frame of interest here.
A is some frame of interest or a point of interest.
And this P is the position of A.
Now, here's where-- so this is a superscript notation
I've used here.
Positions have to be written in some--
relative to something.
If I want to specify a position in space,
this is where the notation starts.
I want to say, what's the position of A
relative to some other point, B?
So the notation we're going to use for this
looks a little weird, but I'm going
to put a superscript that needs the character,
and then another superscript here, which is now
position of A relative to B.
So if I have two points, A and B,
then P is just the vector between them.
And this concept, for us, is going
to live almost exclusively as a three-dimensional vector.
It just lives in R3.
It means it's the real numbers, three of them in a vector,
so a three-by-one vector, if you will.
Now, there's one more bit of notation that we'll use here,
and this will be most of it, but we'll carry it
through for orientations also.
So I want to be able to describe the position of A
relative to B in an arbitrary reference frame.
So your position next to you is some vector,
but if I turn my reference frame here,
the vector is still the same length,
but the three numbers are different.
So I'm going to put relative to some other reference frame.
This would be, let's say, w would be--
I'll just say c, maybe, for now.
But so-- now, when you see all these weird lines
on the plots, that's me drawing the reference frame.
So the point-- a reference frame has a point at its center,
but it also has an orientation.
And the orientation is typically drawn
by drawing the x-axis, the y-axis, and the z-axis.
We always use a right-hand notation.
It's vehicle coordinates, if those of you
think about that.
And it's always that the x-axis is red.
So x, y, z goes to RGB, red, green, blue.
Simple.
So x, green, y, z.
So when you see those flying around,
that's telling you what the orientation of the frame
is in addition to the position of the frame.
The center-- the origin of the axis, of course,
is the position of that frame and the orientation.
There's a number of ways to represent it,
but it's visually drawn with these three axes.
Now, here's where we start to develop the basic algebra.
We can do it already with positions.
And the basic idea here is that positions
add if the frames match.
So if I can write-- so the standard sort of vector
addition here of having B going to A
and having another notion of A going to E,
that basic vector addition is allowed, is sound,
it works if the letters match.
And we're going to be throwing frames around like crazy.
And the name of the game is going
to be, how do I transform some position in my gripper frame
or my elbow frame or something into some other position
and the trick is I'm going to do algebra
to make the frames match.
Once the frames match, it just becomes trivial.
So this is sort of the basic addition operation is defined.
The algebraic inverse is defined.
If those of you that think about--
they have taken a class in analysis or even in algebra,
meaning modern algebra, you'll know
that you can make a basic set of rules that
define all the operations that form a complete algebra
on these quantities.
So the additive inverse is perfectly well defined.
The negative of that flips the signs.
OK.
Positions are the easy case.
Orientations are where everything gets more dodgy.
Again, hopefully the notation will save you
from flipping signs and the like.
OK.
There's a number of ways to represent orientation.
Let me name a few.
OK.
You can represent a relative orientation
with a rotation matrix.
You can do it with Euler angles, of which there are many.
But the familiar roll pitch yaw that you might have seen
or you've piloted an aircraft or something,
you know roll pitch yaw.
Quaternions.
OK.
In general, we're going to allow you to--
there's functions that will just let you go back and forth
in between them.
And you should use whichever is the right one
for your particular use case.
Unfortunately, there's no one representation to rule them all.
Different parts of the stack will
use different of these notations,
different representations.
But in the spatial algebra, we're
just going to call the whole thing R.
We'll say that the orientation of R relative to B--
of A relative to B, we'll call it R.
So this is just an orientation now.
You could choose to represent it on disk
in any of those formats.
I'm still going to call it R for the actual purposes
of the algebra.
And we don't define the addition operator here.
We define the multiplication operator here.
Operators, rotations, orientations multiply.
So orientations don't have an expressed-in frame.
You don't need it.
You'll come to appreciate that, I guess.
But I can tell you that the only thing--
A relative to B, you can turn your head around.
However you want, you can change your current frame.
And the rotations of A relative to B are the same.
So you don't need to worry about the expressed-in frame.
Just like we had an additive inverse for addition,
we have a multiplicative inverse for rotations,
for orientations.
I'll write it with an inverse like this.
Now, if you want to think about R as a rotation matrix,
then the inverse is really just the matrix inverse.
And life is good.
But again, I'm perfectly happy to define
the inverse for any representation of orientations.
We've abstracted a little bit away
from the underlying numerical representation.
We're just talking about the ability
to go back and forth between these rotations.
It happens that if you have a rotation matrix, a 3
by 3 matrix representing it, then actually,
because rotation matrices are orthonormal,
you can actually just take a transpose too.
But it's still equivalent to the inverse.
So the frame, all together, has a position and an orientation.
Together, we're going to call it the pose of the frame.
And we're going to use x, big X, as the pose of A relative
to B.
Now, there's another word that people
use a lot for this, which is transform.
I try to use--
and throughout, actually, Drake, we
try to use pose as the noun and transform as the verb.
English is a little--
you could use transform as a noun and whatever.
But we've made the decision that we're
going to try to be clean about it.
Pose is a noun.
Transform is a verb.
So again, inside here, we have the ability
to represent this on disk in a number of ways.
But we'll still be able to define some basic operations.
We can say, for instance, if I want to transform the verb,
I can put some points from one frame to another.
Let me be a little bit careful about this.
Let me just say one more bit of shorthand
before I start leaving off symbols and confuse something.
So there is one important frame out there,
which is the world frame.
So we'll define everything in the context
of some canonical frame, which actually always,
in my visualizations, you'll see very small red, green, blue
axes at the origin.
That's defining the world axis.
So we'll use a shorthand, which is basically,
if I write P of A and I leave off
the relative to or the expressed in frame,
then that will be shorthand for any time I've left it off.
The implication is that it's relative to some world frame.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Thank you.
So the question is, what are A and B in this notation here?
A and B are both frames in this case.
So it's really the position and orientation
of A relative to the position orientation of B.
If it was just a point, then it doesn't make as much sense.
The pose is the difference of the frames.
[INAUDIBLE]
No.
So good.
So positions get expressed in.
But this similarly is safe.
Let me check that, actually.
I've got it here coming up.
I want to say the wrong thing.
[INAUDIBLE]
I've got it.
Well, we're going to get in a second.
Is there ever a case where you need the expressed in for frame?
I guess you do actually need the expressed in for frame.
Because the position can change.
I think you do need the expressed in for frame
for pose.
We'll see it exactly in the examples in a second.
OK.
So I can multiply.
I define a multiplication operator.
It takes my transform times a position.
And we'll transform the position from one frame
to the other frame.
I will write it more carefully.
Make sure I get it right.
This is a composition of the position encoded in that pose
plus the rotations encoded in that pose.
[WRITING]
So when I do a multiplication here,
it implies transforming both through the position
and the orientation.
Now, these poses also have a multiplicative inverse.
[WRITING]
But this time, the pose on disk is like--
you can represent it a handful of different ways.
But typically, it's not the matrix inverse.
So this is really just my notation for taking an inverse.
But the operation, although it's simple,
it's still a simple function of the elements of a matrix
representation of this, it's not just the matrix inverse.
A lot of times, we can represent this as a 3 by 4 matrix,
for instance.
Poses are also called rigid transforms.
So compared to the full--
if you've heard of homogenous transforms,
homogenous transforms also allow shear and scaling
and things like this.
But a rigid transform, which is just
changing between frames in the kinematics,
is only positions and rotations, no scaling or shearing.
OK, so we're going to use this stuff a lot.
It happens all the time.
Whether you're a perception person, a controls person,
a planning person, these things are core to manipulation.
One example, for instance, would be if you've got a camera,
like we did-- you saw the couple cameras were mounted around
our KUKA, right?
And each of those cameras are taking,
let's say, some depth measurements,
trying to find out where things are in the scene.
You have a camera in some frame.
The data coming into that camera are
going to be in the camera frame, naturally.
You've got multiple cameras in different frames.
If you want to coordinate all that data
into a common representation, then the core operation
is just going to be converting to some common frame, typically
a world frame.
You'll take all your data coming into this camera,
all the data coming in this camera,
multiply it by x, basically, to get it
into some common coordinate frame.
And you can put them together if the frames match.
You could do it in a gripper frame.
You could do it in a world frame.
The frames matching is what is going
to make everything stay OK.
Poses also multiply with the other poses, right?
All of these things connect.
And in the sense of--
I guess I went out of order here.
But in the sense of an algebra in the notes,
you'll see that I wrote out, really,
like this is the inverse--
this is the addition operator.
This is the additive inverse.
This is the multiplication operator.
There's this sort of n rules you need, which is not--
n is not large.
That will sort of completely define that algebra.
I find myself even looking back at the couple of bullets
in the notes as a very useful way to compose these things
to make sure you get it right.
Mm-hmm?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes, so I did the shorthand here,
keeping them both in the world frame.
Everything's in the world frame.
But absolutely, the way that you change frames here,
you actually, with a rotation matrix,
use rotation matrices to express yourself in a different frame.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Right, so if they were not in the world frame--
so if I had, yeah, c, d, and e, this
would not be a valid equation.
You would have to transform these things into the same
thing expressed in frame.
You can transform this through a rotation matrix, which--
that is, the basic operation is that rotations
will take one position and change it expressed in frame.
OK, so just get your thinking here.
So if you're in the gripper frame here,
g is the gripper frame, o is the object frame, which of those
is the possible value for o expressed--
relative to g expressed in w?
Right?
You know what?
I lied.
I made a very silly mistake here.
There's one other shorthand here that I want to make sure--
I jumped straight to the w.
There's one slightly different thing.
When I write that, actually, and I don't fill in this,
then I don't assume w.
If I put relative to g, then I actually
will assume that this is a g and only assume w if w is not here.
I really apologize for not getting
that right the first time.
So when I write that, I really want p o g g.
This one?
Yeah.
Yes, exactly.
Right.
So this one is implied that it's f.
So this would have to be an f.
And this actually, because it has
the position and the rotation, changes it to g.
The rotation that's inside this changes the expressed entry.
Good call.
OK, so you're in the gripper frame.
You're expressed in the gripper frame,
and you want the location of o relative to the gripper frame.
Yeah.
And x, y, z is RGB.
Yeah, two.
OK, anybody else?
Everybody says it's b.
OK.
If I change that and put the w there,
which I did exactly to remind myself to make sure
not to make that mistake, then what's the new answer?
I want to describe the vector from g to the object,
but in the world frame.
Robotics has spent a lot of time going like this.
I have some drinking straws that I tie together
to make something like this.
OK?
All right.
Getting that notation right, as I
proved by flubbing it a little bit, makes a big difference.
Yeah?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yep.
Ha ha.
Good call.
I didn't make them big enough in this picture,
but they line up with the object frame.
Yeah.
There's a red line right there, and a green line right there,
and a blue line right there.
Can you see it just barely?
Yeah.
I should make those more visible.
Before I did a screenshot, they looked great.
Good call.
OK.
This is just the point that I hope you'll look at.
Really, there's just a list of positions
they had added at inverse.
Multiplications are defined.
Multiplications-- you can multiply two rotation matrices.
You can take the rotation inverse.
These are just all the rules of the game here.
I hope they will protect you.
So how would we-- by the way, if we
wanted to just go between those two frames--
so we saw there was a different answer for the two
different frames.
Is it OK to go over here?
Yeah.
OK.
If I have POG, and I want to go to PWOG in that picture,
for instance, then what do I have to do?
So I've got some vector between Charles and Rachel.
And I want to express it in some different frame.
You have to convince yourself that the positions don't
matter at all, actually.
But the same way that I can add vectors in any frame,
positions are invariant to the frame.
All I need to do is multiply the rotation, which
changes that relative frame.
That's one of the rules on the screen there.
And I did it the opposite way in my--
no, it's just fine.
But I could have taken inverse.
But let's just do the same thing so I don't catch myself
in a minute.
I'll write the G here to be careful.
And on that screen, the way that we could compute R,
you could think about building R as even
a handful of simpler rotations.
So if you were to look back at that example--
let me put it back up--
then you could actually think about this as the composition
of some simpler rotation about the z-axis by pi over 2
times some rotation about the x-axis of pi over 4.
These are approximate.
That's just an eyeball.
But if you think about taking my point in G,
how do I get it to be in the other frame?
Well, I've got to rotate the frames
to make the orientations of the frames match.
And you can do that by taking this and just working it
through these rotations.
The reason that's important is that if you need to somehow
write--
if you need to choose, let's say,
an approach for your gripper to that object,
then you're going to find yourself trying to define
a basic frame by, let's say, oh, I
want to maybe back off a little bit.
I'm going to rotate a little bit.
So you're going to be composing these rotations
with simpler elements.
So let's start putting that together into a plan.
That's enough with just thinking about frames
and how they relate to each other.
That's enough for us to start putting together
our basic plan sketch.
OK.
So there's going to be a bunch of useful frames
if we want to pick up the object.
So you can call them key.
They're important for-- let me just call them important frames
to not sound like that.
So there's going to be some object frame.
But I'm going to distinguish between the initial object
frame and the desired object frame, or let's say,
the goal object frame.
I've got a gripper frame.
I'll call it big G. I've got the initial one.
I've got maybe the orientation or the frame
that I want that is, let's say, the right grip to pick it up.
So let me call it G pick.
The frame my hand is when I'm actually grabbing the object.
But in fact, it becomes extremely common
and extremely useful to not just go--
if you want to somehow interpolate
from some initial position of your hand
to the place where you're picking up the object,
almost always we think about a pre-pick frame that
gets us sort of close but a little bit backed off
from the object.
And then we do a simpler approach.
That way you're not somehow interpolating all the way
from some different position into this frame,
possibly going through collisions as you do that.
So almost always we'll think about a pre-pick frame that
allows me to go--
when I transition from pre-pick to pick,
I can sort of guarantee I'm not going to slam into anything.
And similarly, I might back off, lift off the table
before I move away.
So I'll do it.
I'll have a G post-pick.
OK?
I'll have a G for where I'm going to place the object down.
And similarly, I'll have a pre and a post for that.
OK?
And that gets you most of the way there.
It's just sort of diagramming out a bunch of frames
through the space where we want our hand to end up.
I believe that I've done that on the next slide here.
So we're going to just move our hand
through a series of frames.
The way that we do that is by building up
just this set of possible frames.
OK?
Which I guess I didn't insert.
OK.
Comically, if you only do this, which
I did the first time I did it-- and I'll show the video
in a second here--
then there's one more thing that you need.
Anybody already see the problem with this that I missed?
I guess you can't.
But typically, I've got the object here.
I'll lift up a little bit to approach.
So my pre-pick will be just above my pick.
OK?
Same with the post.
I put this all together.
I ran my simulation.
And hilarity ensued.
What did I forget?
Yeah.
Clearance, right?
I went smash right into the side of the bin.
The fingers bent a little bit.
And then the brick went flying.
Right?
So maybe g for clearance is a good idea also.
OK?
Now, these are conceptually the frames.
I never represent o initial--
o is a frame.
So how do I represent o initial on disk?
I represent its pose, right?
So what I actually have is some pose of x initial--
of o initial-- x of o initial on disk, often in the world
frame, for instance.
OK?
So in the hand coordinates, a reasonable thing to do--
so if you looked at the hand coordinates--
let me put that picture back up.
OK, so you see the hands coordinate system
is centered right in the middle of the body.
Yeah, yeah.
Sure.
What would you say on disk?
I'm being a programmer, I guess.
Right?
So there's a slight gap between going from the math, right,
to what numbers am I going to use to represent that?
When I-- I'm being silly when I say on disk.
That's not common notation in the world,
or in robotics, or anything.
I'm just saying that if I wanted to actually implement this,
I need to choose a representation,
a numerical representation.
So o is a conceptual frame.
It can be represented in my--
on paper, or on disk, in my code with those numbers that
represent the orientation.
Thank you for asking.
[INAUDIBLE]
I mean, I think the pose, in some sense,
captures what o initial is.
But we think of o as being a frame which
defines the semantics of whether you can connect
two poses and the like.
But it's the pose x is the manifestation
that holds the position and orientation of that frame
relative to something else.
O, in some sense, is absolute, if you will,
but can't be represented because you have to somehow make
a pose relative to something else.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Basically, I have some bins.
And I'm going to-- instead of going straight from the pick,
straight across, I need to make sure I go nice and up and down
to clear the bins.
Otherwise, I'm going to smash into the bins on the way there.
So what is a reasonable--
you have to think about, given the language we have,
I want to somehow choose the position of the gripper that
would be a good choice for picking up the object.
There are lots of frames flying around in the world.
The natural one to write would be to say,
I either want to say the position of the--
or the pose of the gripper relative to the object,
instead of saying, come up with the pose in the world--
of the gripper in the world and the object of the world.
Why not do the relative frame, directly
from the hand to the object?
That's the simple place and the robust place
to write my objective.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
So if I have the position of the object initially,
and I want to figure out--
I want to somehow define my picking grasp,
I could choose whichever one's easier for me to think about.
I could think about writing in either direction.
But in this one, where I want to have the object initial
relative to the grasp, to the gripper,
then you can see the y-axis is the green axis.
I want it to be square in the middle of my fingers.
I want the object's center to be something
like a positive y value.
And x0, z0 seems totally reasonable.
So it turns out that choosing this to be something like,
I don't know, 12 centimeters is what we use in the code.
Puts it squarely right in my finger,
that the center of the square-- of the object
gets right into the center of my fingers.
Similarly, I need to come up with the orientation.
And the gripper frame is kind of annoying.
It's in this weird frame.
But if you want to be coming down from on top,
then a series of transformations and knowing
that the object is in a particular orientation,
the cube--
knowing that we have a canonical orientation for a little red
cube is something you will never get from perception,
because that's symmetric and the like.
But if we knew this, then for our simplicity for today,
we can define a relative orientation
so that the hand comes directly down on top,
with a handful of just simple rotations.
And you'll see that in the code.
So this together defines my pose.
I can, again, in the relative frames,
say that in order-- right before I do it,
I'm going to just back off directly in the gripper frame.
I'll do, let's say, negative y to define my pre-pick.
Maybe the same one works for post-pick.
You see?
And by just having that extra frame,
that shows that no matter where I'm coming from, I stop here.
And then that last little segment
is sort of simple and doesn't collide with the object.
My fingers don't go through the brick as I go.
So this pre-pick planning is very, very common.
People will do lots of interesting, complicated
algorithms to figure out how to move through space.
And then they'll just hand code the last thing often.
So that's a pretty cool--
you get pretty far with a little bit of notation
and the software that will let you go back and forth
between them without making mistakes.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
You see the-- yes, the question is, why did I put 0.12--
the 12 centimeters here?
My units are always metric in meters.
Why did I choose 12 centimeters and y-axis here?
So in the frame of the gripper, which
is the red, green, blue on the hand there,
if I want it to be in the middle of the fingers,
I've measured the fingers.
And I know that 12 centimeters is
from the center of the hand to the--
will put me in the middle of the fingers.
So that would be a point like here, roughly,
on that green line.
So I say, I want the center of the object
to be in the middle of the fingers there.
And similarly, I will make sure I'm
coming from the top with my choice of rotations.
OK, so the code attempts to make this easy.
You really just-- we take that same notation
we put on the board, and we turn this in code.
If I have P, B, A, C, I'm on the board.
I mean, I will write this with a subscript notation, B, A, C,
like this.
That's the way you take this superscript notation
and choose a symbol.
And this will, again, allow you to read the code
and see that I can only add positions if things match.
I can only multiply if things match.
I've seen robot software that demands
that every time you specify any point or any vector,
you also specify the frame.
And it programmatically enforces that you can never
add things that are in the wrong frames.
I think that can be super good.
But the burden, then, of every time you do anything simple,
you have to express your frame.
And then you've got two different concepts coming
from two different places.
And they-- oh, I didn't tell them the same frame name.
It tends to be a pain.
So in our world, we've chosen to have the code author make it
readable.
And we programmatically check sizes and other things.
But you have to not shoot yourself in the foot.
And then you can just assemble these.
The pre-grasp is, like I said, the rotation
I can make out of simple primitives.
And then I can just start building up my pick,
pre-pick, place, pre-place, and even my clearance.
The next step of that is to go ahead and specify the timing.
So I've now decided a bunch of important frames
that I'm going to move through, even key frames, if you like.
And I just need to say, how long is
it going to take me to go back and forth between them?
And that's simple enough.
I just listed out a bunch of times
for the different segments.
Sometimes they're just absolute times.
Sometimes, just for the initial one,
since I wanted my code to be robust so that it could go
from any initial pose to here, I just
scaled it based on the total distance between those two
frames so that I didn't make that somehow always happen
in two seconds.
Depending on how far I have to go,
I might go slower or faster.
This is what happens if you forget the clearance
constraint.
Beautiful plan from pick up, post pick up,
start moving across, boom, full physics simulator,
hands not happy, brick fell out.
It's going to keep trying because I'm doing an open loop
position trajectory.
And this is why we want you to prove in simulation
that things work before we let it go in the real robot
because that would either power down the robot or blow a fuse
or something like that.
And it happens often.
So it's interesting actually to ask
how do I interpolate between the different poses.
So positions, if I just say in time, I've got time of pick,
time of place, all my intermediate frames
specified in time.
And I have my position of my gripper,
let's say, figured out that I can--
through my math, I can put them all in the world frame.
I can figure out where my gripper needs
to be at all times.
And it's a three element vector.
Let me just plot the x component.
So the x component of this.
Maybe I've got a sequence like this.
How do I interpolate between them?
There's lots of ways to choose.
We're just going to do the simplest straight line
interpolation, which would be called a first order hold.
Sort of one of the simplest forms of interpolation.
First order, it's got one degree of freedom for this line,
the slope of the line.
Zero order would be--
you guys know the zero order hold
would be if I just went like this.
I just didn't interpolate with the line,
but I did some staircase.
I don't want you to run that on the robot.
That's not so good.
You can do higher order interpolations
to get nice curves through there.
The reason we're only going to do first order for positions
here is actually more because interpolating orientations
gets subtle.
So we're going to do first order for positions, which
we know how to do trivially, and first order
for orientations, which requires a little bit more care.
So how do you interpolate orientations?
Now, this is one case where your choice of representation
can make a big difference.
So some of those representations are easier
to interpolate than others.
Some of them look simple to interpolate,
but then would blow up, could potentially
go through bad states in the middle.
So just as an example, let's say the rotation matrix.
Probably you've all seen rotation matrices in 2D.
The sort of simplest cases, a 2D example,
would be if I want to write a 2D rotation
as a function of some angle theta,
that would be a 2 by 2 matrix.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
Are people familiar with that sort of mechanics?
And I can take a 2 by 1 vector, and this
will rotate that vector by theta degrees.
So just to sort of make the point, if theta equals 0,
what do I get?
I get 1, 0, 0, 1, identity matrix.
That's what you want.
If theta equals pi over 4, let's say, or pi over 2 even,
then I can get 0, negative 1, 1, 0.
That would be, if I've rotated by pi over 2,
I would take my original axes and put my x-axis here
and my y-axis here.
That would be a rotation by 90 degrees.
But absolutely linearly interpolating between those two
is not going to give me a rotation in 45 degrees.
It's going to give me 1 over root 2, which is not half.
These things don't-- you can't just interpolate orientations
like that.
Roll pitch yaw, you think you might be able to interpolate.
You can get yourself into trouble with things exploding.
So the way people typically interpolate these
is with a quaternion representation.
And they do something called SLURP,
which is spherical linear interpolation.
[WRITING]
And it's a safe way to get a smooth--
a first-order interpolation in orientations.
We're toying with a problem that you might do on your problem
set that just make you understand SLURP a little
better.
But that's the basic mechanics, is
that we can almost do this simple picture of first-order
interpolations.
But you need to do it in the quaternion representation,
and you need to use this spherical interpolation.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
So what do I mean by explode when you use roll pitch yaws?
So there are roll pitch yaw values
that represent very similar orientations that
are actually very far in the values of our roll pitch yaw.
So trying to go between one and another representation
of roll pitch yaw might take you through extremely large numbers
for roll pitch yaw.
And this goes along with gimbal lock.
And the quaternions are the way to get around gimbal lock.
[INAUDIBLE]
I mean, grinding noises often happen
when you're chattering or something like that.
This would probably be a velocity command
that your robot refuses to execute
and then goes into a safety mode, and the lights turn on,
I hope.
If you built the robot yourself, you
might throw it across the room.
Done that, too.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
So now the next part of the game is
how do I get from the end effector coordinates
back to my joint commands?
Remember the manipulation station, the whole package
that we made a diagram for?
The controller takes joint positions as input.
So somehow I've got this beautiful plan.
It tells me what the pose of the gripper
now should be over time.
How do I get to joint commands?
How do I execute that?
OK.
So the mapping from joint angles to poses
is called forward kinematics problem.
In particular, we're doing the forward kinematics.
And you can think of it, and you can see already here,
that if I have joint angles theta,
and I want to turn that into a rotation or a pose,
then that's going to be potentially a nonlinear,
almost always nonlinear map from f into these poses.
This is maybe the simplest version of it.
But the math is actually pretty simple,
because each individual joint is just
describing a small operation, a rotation matrix
kind of operation, on a relative transform
from right before the robot's joint
and right till right after the robot's joint.
And the operation of doing forward kinematics
is almost exactly what we did already,
which is I wanted to compute the pose of my end effector.
I do that by computing the pose of my wrist
relative to that end effector.
I do a rotation matrix type thing for the rotation joint
here, which is just a relative pose.
And then I just keep chaining them backwards
and can get all the way back to the world coordinates.
That's exactly how robots are specified.
Like if you look at the robot description files,
then pose relative to pose, six numbers right here,
which is x, y, z, roll pitch, yaw.
When you type in your basic robot kinematics
in the robot description files, it's
just telling you relative poses of each link.
And the joints are just operations
that will, again, make a transformation
from the pre-joint frame to the post-joint frame.
So when I write this vector, this idea of x of my,
let's say, gripper is some function of my gripper,
my kinematics function of q, then you could ask, what is q?
What is q going to actually be?
So for the IWA, it's a total of seven--
it's a 7 by 1 vector of joint angles,
all rotational joint angles.
They're called revolute joints in the code.
And each of them just defines a rotation
that happens based on that joint angle.
It happens in the 3D.
And it could potentially change the positions, too,
but a fixed change of positions.
And it's just going from a vector,
one element of that vector, into one rotation matrix
for one joint, and then the next one.
And I can compose this through a series of frame transformations
into my full kinematics.
But it's a little bit more subtle than that.
So do you remember the Allegro hand I showed before?
My network is not working well.
That's what I was afraid of.
A lot of my graphics are just refusing to show.
There's a beautiful SVG here.
Imagine it in your head.
I don't know why that could possibly have failed.
But the Allegro hand has many links.
It also potentially has a location in the world.
The base of that Allegro hand has some location in the world.
So if I had--
I have a little URDF here that had the Allegro hand
and the red brick in it.
So the question is, how big is Q for a floating Allegro
hand and a floating brick?
How many numbers do I need to represent
the total configuration of that system?
So I can tell you the Allegro hand had
four degrees of freedom and the beautiful kinematic tree
that you would see, hopefully, some people who
are looking at it on their computers
with better internet see.
It came up for you?
Awesome.
I'm going to make it disappear and come up,
but maybe in the hopes--
ah, OK.
Four links per finger.
They actually-- I don't know if anybody's noticed,
but I actually have the same number of fingers
as the Allegro hand.
So I favor the three fingered hands.
That's just a weird coincidence.
And then there's some number of elements
required to move the robot in space.
So the total number of joint angles for my Allegro hand
is four times four fingers, 16, and then
some number of elements for the position in space.
How many elements do you think I tend to have
to position in space?
Six is a great answer.
We almost always use seven, because we
choose to use quaternions in the coordinate representation
instead of x, y, z, roll, pitch, yaw to avoid
gimbal locks and singularities.
So for the Allegro with a floating base,
we get four fingers times four joints plus seven
for a quaternion for the floating joint,
for a total of what?
23.
And if I add the brick in, I get another seven.
So I get a total of 30 in my diagram.
And the kinematics problem then becomes
going from those 30 numbers to a pose, some pose
that I'm computing in the system, the pose of the brick,
the pose of the hand.
Of course, we have methods in any robot software,
certainly in Drake, to do the kinematics for you here.
We just ask you to give which frame
you're asking for the kinematics relative to.
And we can, in general, go from any frame to any frame.
You can do an expressed in frame.
You can do all the things we talked about.
You can give all of these.
But by default, you can just say, for instance,
from some body frame to the world,
and it will just give out this pose.
We don't actually take q as an argument.
We take the context as the argument
because we actually have the kinematics that could be,
for instance, parameterized.
If you wanted to design your robot while you're
computing your kinematics, and maybe the length
could be something that you want to optimize,
let's say optimize the link lengths of my robot,
for instance, then you'd like this kinematics
to also be a function of your link lengths,
or some other quantities.
So we actually take in the full context.
Remember, I talked about the context is just
the state plus the parameters plus time,
or it's just the structure that wraps that.
I'm totally bummed that this isn't working
because I had big plans for the next step, which
is I'm actually running a notebook in the sky
right now, right on deep node, and was
hoping that you could all jointly
control the robot simultaneously and chaos would ensue.
But I think we now have the ability,
if I get a better internet connection in here,
to have a single robot that everybody can control,
and we can watch the kinematics evolve
and watch the Jacobians, which I'll talk about next.
I was going to have fun with that,
but I guess it's not going to happen.
One more piece that I want to land today,
and then you've got most of what you need
to move the robot around.
So kinematic frames, I think we're good.
The ability to put them together with some simple trajectory
based interpolation.
I think the concept, I hope, is somehow OK.
And I think the code--
we're going to ask you to understand SLURP,
but the code makes that simple.
If you give me a bunch of key frames,
you can take different interpolation schemes
to do that.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Yeah, no, that is a central question, which I will repeat.
Thank you.
Yeah, so how do I know that when I've taken my gripper plan
and given something that looks reasonable in gripper
coordinates, I don't have something crazy happening
in my joint coordinates in order to execute that?
All we've done so far is chosen reasonable smooth--
continuous, let's say-- not smooth,
but continuous trajectories for the hand
and had them move at a low velocity
right now in the hopes that whatever
I do to transform the gripper coordinates
to the joint coordinates maintains that smoothness.
Getting that right is one of the next topics,
because there are ways you can mess that up for sure.
[INAUDIBLE]
It is also not always true that it's possible.
You could-- yeah, so there's a notion
of kinematic singularities, I think,
is what you're getting at.
And we'll make sure we understand that.
I've got some cool graphics.
Yes, so we're just--
we're trying to be reasonable here,
but this is actually a great lead-in to the next thing.
So one thing you might want to do
is to say, if I've got a bunch of these frames
and I want to figure out command for positions,
then what I could just do is somehow do--
take an inverse of this function.
This is a nonlinear, complicated function,
but if I could somehow define an inverse,
then that would be--
looks like a very reasonable operation.
And that is a well-defined operation in robotics
called inverse kinematics.
But it is-- you have to do it very carefully,
because while this direction is always well-posed,
you can always go from a good Q to a valid pose.
It tends to be smooth.
It tends to-- all these nice behaviors going this way.
There are many cases where there are, for instance,
multiple solutions, no solutions, going this way.
So you have to be-- if you're willing to--
sometimes we do actually use the inverse kinematics directly,
but oftentimes we do not, because if your inverse
kinematics engine gives you slightly different answers
for very similar poses, then you might--
it might involve crazier movements to do it.
An example of a case where you'd have multiple solutions
would be if I had enough degrees of freedom in my arm,
it could be that I can--
I can't keep my wrist very still,
but if I could move my elbow, for instance,
relative to my arm, it might be that there's many Qs that give
me the same hand position.
If my inverse kinematics engine told me to take this one
at time 1, this one at time 1.111, or 1.1001,
then that would cause a huge--
so we don't-- when we specify inverse kinematics,
we are-- we don't only ask for the inverse.
We also put in some additional requirements for continuity,
or smoothness, or centering, or something like this.
OK.
So I want to just introduce the concept of what
we are going to do, but we'll go through the richer
form of it next time.
So in order to sort of encourage this sort of smoothness,
instead of looking at inverse kinematics,
we're going to look at differential kinematics.
So we're going to examine exactly how
an incremental change in Q makes an incremental change in X.
OK?
[WRITING]
Roughly, intuitively, what I'd like you to think about
is I want an incremental change in my poses, which
is some incremental change in my joint angles.
OK?
And we're going to call this thing,
as people do in all kinds of fields,
we call that the Jacobian.
It's a function of the current--
whatever the current joint angles are.
OK?
Now, in order to start talking about differential quantities,
and ultimately we're going to want dQ dt,
so the velocities, joint velocities, OK,
and some pose velocity, if you will,
we need to understand how to represent this pose velocity.
OK?
So just like we have a spatial algebra for positions
and orientations, we have it for velocities,
the spatial velocity, which has a translation component
and an orientation component.
OK, so this is going to be a 6 by 1 vector,
where these are angular velocities.
These are translational velocities.
OK?
Now, here's something funny, right?
In pose, there's all kinds of problems
that come with your choice of representation
for orientations, whether it's Euler angles,
Rolfe-Jarre, or quaternions, or rotation matrices.
There's no canonical choice for the orientation.
There is a canonical choice for angular velocity.
So you can, with three numbers, have no degenerate--
no problems with degeneracy or anything like this.
You have a perfectly reasonable--
everybody chooses it, everybody agrees
that angular velocities shall be three numbers, which
are the rotations around the major axes.
OK?
So this notion of angular velocity
simplifies everything.
Once you get the velocities and spatial accelerations
and the like, you've got to 6 by 1 numbers.
Everybody's happy, everybody's good.
The representation's collapsed.
The problem is that because we have so many different choices
for q and even for x, we have many different possible
Jacobians to determine how we're going
to go from some velocity in joint angles
to some velocity in some spatial velocity, for instance.
OK?
So we define the one that goes--
it's typically called a geometric Jacobian, which
takes joint velocities and maps that to spatial velocity
vectors.
It's not quite-- because of this extra change of representation,
it's not quite partial f, partial q.
But it's that plus a change of coordinates
into the spatial vectors.
The analytic Jacobian, if you care,
is the true partial derivative.
But we don't use that.
We don't recommend that as much.
There's cases where you might want that.
But almost always, we recommend working
with the spatial velocities.
OK, and so there's still more choices.
Like, there are still multiple geometric Jacobians.
Because while the geometric Jacobian always
is a function of q, how do you represent q dot?
OK, well, there's a couple of different choices
that you've made here in your vector of positions.
OK, you've made-- we said we had 30 numbers in our Allegro
hand plus red brick.
OK, but it turns out, because I had--
some of those were extra.
They were the Gratonian dimensions,
which took seven numbers.
I know I have spatial velocities that
could take only six numbers.
Oftentimes, the velocity vector, the joint velocity vector,
is smaller than the joint position vector.
And it might not equal dq dt.
OK, you can map between them.
But in particular, for the Allegro hand floating,
or even the red brick, or something like this,
I had 23 for just the Allegro hand floating.
23 positions, but only 22 velocities.
When I write this big vector that
keeps track of what's going on in the robot,
I use 23 numbers to keep track of the positions,
and 22 for velocities.
So there's options.
There's many Jacobians.
Some of them can map from q dot, which
is the 23 numbers on the right.
Some of them can map from v, which
is the 22 numbers on the right.
They're all available in code.
So the basic strategy that we'll explore next time
is that we can, for instance, try
to say I've got my x gripper as a function of time
that I've designed with my trajectories.
And I want to go to some q as a function of time.
It's reasonable to start with q0,
and then integrate forward a velocity command that
is approximately the inverse of this Jacobian times
my spatial velocity.
Let me shorthand it with--
I'll just use the proper v--
spatial velocity of the gripper as a function of time.
The only catch is that we want to be careful,
because we have to guarantee that that matrix is invertible
or address it with more sophisticated methods.
But intuitively, we're going to design controllers
that use the derivative of the kinematics
to get this smoothness.