All right.
It's about that time.
OK.
Welcome back, everybody.
So as we've been forecasting for a little while,
it's deep learning week.
So it's deep perception week.
And so just to remind you some of the times
that we've mentioned it before, I
think we've done a lot of nice algorithmic work
with geometry and used it for perception.
But in this example that we were talking about at the end
last time, there are limitations that I
think are fairly fundamental of using only geometry.
So in particular, if you don't really know what an object is,
you just know where the points are in space,
then the systems that we were talking about that
were just using geometry to pick antipodal grasps,
or anything really just based on geometry,
that wasn't about antipodalness.
That was about just not understanding anything more
than point clouds.
You'll get things where you just don't have
any reasoning about objects.
You'll get double picks, meaning that one grab might
have picked two objects, and that
might have been OK or might not have been OK,
depending on the application.
You might pick up the hammer from the corner
and have it slip out because of a huge wrench,
just because you have no concept from the geometry alone
that there's this object there, and there's
a center of mass of the object, and it'd
be better to pick it up at the center of mass
so you don't get a big moment.
If you have geometry sensors and you're dependent on them,
and you can't see behind certain things,
then you have to think about all the pieces of information
that we have in our perception system that's just not
geometric.
Somehow if I see one side of a mug or one side of a whatever
I've got, I can infer that there's probably
a handle on the back side, even if I can't see that handle.
And if the geometry point cloud that I have right now
doesn't contain that information,
then a geometric method alone won't infer that information.
Sort of a practical thing is that our depth cameras
aren't very good at transparency.
But the list goes on.
At some point, in order to do more effective manipulation,
we need more than just a geometric understanding
of the world.
We need to understand what objects are.
We need to understand something about the properties
of objects.
So the approach in deep learning and deep perception
is, as we said, sort of a statistical approach.
So the reason you know to pick up a hammer in the middle
is because you picked up a bunch of things that look like hammers
in the image.
And some of them fell out of my hand and some of them didn't.
Or the reason you know that the mug should be on the table
is because I saw a lot of pictures
and the mugs were never up in the air.
They were always at the table.
And if you can correlate your current perception
with enough of your data, then it
can be a very strong prior that overcomes
some of the limitations and does,
in some mystical, magical way, capture some
of these object understanding, the things
that I would have attributed to really reasoning about objects.
I would say--
I mean, some people ask me, why did you
switch from working on legged robots
to working on manipulation?
Even though I have a bit of a love-hate relationship
with deep learning, just because I think sometimes it's
overstated and doesn't involve deep thinking or whatever.
But I would say it's the reason I changed.
That I think that the fact that perception
started to work so well and open up
so many possibilities in manipulation
really just kind of cracks open this huge, interesting idea
of where you can bring--
for me, it's bringing some of the ideas from dynamics
and control closer to what I think
of as common sense reasoning and about a much more
diverse set of tasks, a much more diverse set of objectives.
So that only happened because perception started working.
And you could start dreaming of doing manipulation
for many more diverse tasks than we ever did before.
And the manipulation of the 1980s
just did not look like what we're trying
to do in manipulation today.
So OK, so the problem--
so even though I do love deep learning in some ways,
I hate teaching it.
I mean, I struggle to teach it.
Let me say that.
Because I know some of you are probably training
deep networks right now.
And some of you haven't touched a deep network.
But I think I've got a pretty good strategy.
You can give me feedback and ask questions or yawn or whatever
and help me walk the landscape.
Oh, that's true.
I can see.
I can guess.
Just do a really dramatic yawn.
And through the mask, I'll understand.
OK, so but I think I can say a few things that will
bring everybody up to speed.
My basic strategy is I'm not going
to talk a lot about neural architectures
for different things.
There's plenty of good resources online.
I will put some pointers in the notes.
I'm going to try to focus in on the parts that
are more relevant to robotics and manipulation
and the way that you feed these tools data properly,
the way you ask reasonable questions of these tools.
And I'll say a little bit about how they work only in the sense
that you can use them better, not in the sense
that I think if you want to architect them differently
and choose different numbers of layers and stuff,
that's not what I'm going to talk about here.
OK, but the basics I think we just have to get out there
is there's some basic questions about just what kind
of questions are we formulating for a deep network,
and then how do we generate training data
if we're going to start manipulating
our objects in our bins.
So let's tell that story.
So the first question is if my deep neural network is trying
to do perception, the simplest version of the picture
is I've got a big neural network.
I'm going to send images into it.
So almost certainly they're going to be RGB.
It's interesting.
Sometimes people send the depth channel in.
Sometimes they don't.
Sometimes they try to change the depth channel's representation
and shove it in.
But I think a surprising amount of--
even when people have depth data,
a surprising number of the techniques use RGB alone.
So let's focus on that first.
So I'm going to send an RGB image in,
and I'm going to ask some question out.
And we'll talk about various questions
that we'd like to have the deep part of our perception system
answer.
For instance, we'll do pose estimation
by the end of the lecture.
Maybe if I've trained this to be the mug pose estimation
algorithm, then maybe I can have a pose coming out.
But to build up to that, we can ask
some of the more standard computer vision questions
and just make sure we understand the types of questions
and the type of loss functions and the like
that people have been very successful with.
So the first version of the question
would just be image recognition.
I think this picture says--
almost is very efficiently explains
some of the basic landscape.
So if I send a picture in, and I'm
asking for just image recognition,
then the output of that is just a set of numbers.
So I might have many outputs.
In this case, I'd have a sheep output.
What is it?
Dog, cat, horse.
I have many outputs of my neural network.
This is just some big function that has a vector output
and a big vector input.
And the most basic question is just,
is there a sheep in the image, true or false?
I can generate a lot of training data
where someone tells me, yes, there's a sheep in it.
In fact, you guys are training deep networks
whenever you're doing these CAPTCHAs nowadays.
Click on the ones that have a traffic light in there,
and you're training all the autonomous cars.
So you're generating training data for these systems.
And if my training data says, for every image I put in,
I have 1, 0, 0, 0 for the ones that have a sheep and only
a sheep, and I have 0, 1, 0, 0 for the ones that have a dog,
then I can answer the basic image recognition question.
And the network will predict a probability.
It'll do its best to predict 1.
The right answer here would be, I guess, 1, 1, 0, 0, maybe,
since there are sheep and a dog.
But it's going to do its best to predict the training data.
And in practice, we say, we'll take the largest detection
and maybe call that a sheep.
Yes, there's a sheep in that image, or we'll threshold it.
One step more refined than that is
if you try to do object detection, where you're
actually not just saying, yes, there's a sheep in the image,
but there's a sheep and it's here.
Typically, with bounding box is the simplest.
In 2D, it's just a bounding box.
In 3D, you have a choice about whether you're
going to do an oriented bounding box or an axis-aligned bounding
box.
But basically, you just put a box around the things
that you're trying to detect.
And you can detect now potentially a dog and a sheep.
And then there's a distinction between whether you're
doing semantic segmentation or instance segmentation.
So a more refined query is to say,
show me the pixels in the image.
Basically, now I have an image in and an image out.
Where did my eraser go?
Labeled image out, where every pixel is labeled either dog,
sheep, or I don't know, for instance.
And this would be my training data
for a semantic segmentation, which just says,
for each pixel, is it a dog, is it a sheep?
And we'll distinguish that from instance segmentation,
where different sheep are colored a different pixel.
So that you can now tell that there are multiple sheep
and you can distinguish their boundaries.
So that's just the basic vocabulary.
There's going to be more questions, of course,
that we want for manipulation than just these questions.
But these are the ones that we have massive data
sets to train with.
It turns out that if you get to instance segmentation, which
is a standard computer vision ask,
you can do a lot of stuff for manipulation.
That already would power a lot of the pipelines
we've already talked about for manipulation.
So if I'm looking in my dirty bin, my cluttered bin,
and I say, now pick out the spam can,
or pick out the cheese it box, or pick out the mustard,
then what you really want here is an instance segmentation
pipeline, where you can say, look down,
tell me the pixels that are associated with the mustard
bottle.
And then I can do, for instance, antipodal grasping,
but restrict my search to the points that are associated
with the mustard bottle.
So if we can use the existing data sets and standard pipelines
and get to instance segmentation,
we're already in pretty good shape.
Now, I think a lot of people know a lot about the--
the history of deep learning getting here
was through large labeled data sets, typically crowdsourced.
And we really did have lots of people clicking pixel by pixel
and labeling these images and making massive--
the COCO data set is the one that goes all the way
through to instance segmentation that has been very famous
and very fruitful.
ImageNet was the biggest first one,
but COCO is the one that added the instance segmentation
labels.
And it was extremely expensive to generate to begin with.
But once we had it, a lot of things happened very quickly.
It's actually kind of fun to look at the categories that
are available in COCO.
It's a little bit small, but the website resisted zooming.
So if you want to manipulate elephant--
did I spell elephant wrong?
OK, is there?
Or giraffe.
So it's really good for manipulating elephants
and giraffes or whatever, because they've
got lots of labeled data of elephants and giraffes
and lots of random categories.
But they don't have every category.
They've got some--
I forget-- 2,000 categories or something
like this of pretty good stuff.
Some of them that if you wanted--
maybe bears are less useful than umbrellas or shoes
for manipulation.
But although they did a very good job
of picking a diversity of categories that provided
a lot of interesting coverage, they
didn't put in all the objects that we have in our bin.
They just couldn't possibly have done the mustard bottle
we care about, the spam can we care about,
the Cheez-It box we care about.
So one of the first things that is absolutely
important to understand is that I
think one of the biggest results about all
of this deep learning for perception
is that these networks actually transfer incredibly well.
So if you train a network on this big labeled cocoa data
set and you want to apply it to your problem,
you don't have to regenerate a data
set that compares with the size or quality of labels
of the cocoa data set.
You can generate a very small data set
and transfer, fine tune a network that
was trained initially in cocoa and applied now
to your system.
So that's an important pipeline.
It's surprising that it works, but it's relatively simple
to understand.
So I've got a big multi-layer network.
It's got my original big ImageNet or cocoa trained model
that I download from the web because someone else spent
a lot of GPU cloud resources to train it from scratch.
And if I want to now apply it to the objects
I actually want to manipulate, not elephants,
but I want to have a mustard bottle detector,
then the approach is effectively to chop off the head.
You take the last layer or layers out of the network,
put a new one in of whatever number outputs
you care about with some random initialization,
but you keep all the initial layers of the network.
And then you just train.
You don't have to retrain on the original data set.
You just train now on your smaller data
set that you've generated that's narrow and curated
for your task.
And somehow, magically, the training
on the ImageNet and cocoa data sets
seem to capture enough general understanding about images,
about objects, that a relatively small amount of training
on the narrow data set seems to transfer.
I think it's one of the biggest success stories that
made all this stuff go.
It's very surprising in my mind.
And I think it took a data set as big as ImageNet
to start seeing that quality of generalization.
So I know a lot of you know this very well, but yeah,
please ask questions.
How do you determine whether or not just a good candidate
or not for this sort of a transfer?
So the question was--
so help me understand the question a little better.
So you're saying, how do you know if the task that you have
is a good candidate for transfer learning?
I mean, this is an active question,
is how far can you be from the original task
in order to still be successful when you transfer?
And we'll talk about--
so I think the big labeled ImageNet COCO data sets were
the first way that people did this.
Nowadays, people are trying to self-supervise and getting
broader initial networks from just snarping up the web.
And I think there's some intuition, I guess,
people have of that there's some distribution of the data that's
been applied here, and you've got
some different distribution.
And probably there's some similarity metric
that we don't understand completely of how far you
can go before that doesn't work.
But it's been surprisingly far.
So how do you generate that smaller amount of data?
Remember, I mentioned this early.
You can use iterative closest point, for instance,
to do this.
So when we first started trying to train deep perception
systems for the objects in our lab--
this is a bench in my lab with the--
it's kind of messy.
And there's a drill we wanted to pick up and manipulate.
And the drill wasn't in the COCO data set.
So what do you do?
You generate a bunch of depth data.
This is now departing from what the computer--
I mean, none of the big computer vision data sets have depth.
That's just starting to change.
People are releasing COCO-sized data
sets that have depth very recently.
So take my depth camera around.
Even if I'm going to train--
let me stop that because it's distracting here.
Even if I'm just going to train an RGB-based network,
if you have the luxury of depth, then what we can do
is we can do a dense reconstruction.
So we basically build a--
very quickly build an approximate CAD model
or a fused point cloud of all of my scans
so I can get the 3D view of it.
And then I can do ICP on that 3D view.
So I can find the drill in that point cloud.
And then I can go back in all of my images,
and just automatically provide a label
saying that these pixels, pixel by pixel,
that were the projected version of my ICP fit
are labeled to be the correct thing.
Did I say that well enough?
So by having a point cloud from all different sides,
you can make a nice point cloud, a nice point cloud which ICP
could work on.
Now I can re-render the image effectively
with just the green drill there labeled in all the pixels.
And I have a lot of training data
now that's just labeled drill or not drill.
Super effective.
I mean, there's a lot of--
I've seen lots of companies, lots of labs
have their own versions of that.
That was our version we called Label Fusion.
But that's a very effective pipeline.
Yeah?
Does that work as in like a generalized pipeline
drill for new rooms?
So that just leans on the generalization power
of the deep network, which has been impressive.
So I mean, I think you'd like to have
scenes with multiple rooms if you're
going to try to generalize in that way in your data set.
I mean, maybe roughly the idea is
that in distribution generalization
is extremely good.
If you try to ask for something it's never seen before,
then your mileage may vary.
So if I can get drills in a handful of rooms
and you put me in a new room, I would expect
it to work fairly well.
Yeah.
So my question was more, you generate 1,000 ways of vision
just by putting the drill in one part of the room.
And that sounds like very large data set.
I see.
But in some way it's small because you only
have to drill in one spot in one room.
OK.
That's a really good point.
So let me say it again for the camera.
So I say you can generate lots of data very fast.
But all of those images are very similar.
They don't cover a lot of different backgrounds,
basically, and there are lots of different scenarios.
So in some sense, even though there's
a large number of images, it represents
a small fraction of the scenes you want to care about.
I totally agree.
So the number there is artificially high
in terms of what you'd want.
In fact, you could probably down sample it dramatically
and do just as well.
So you still want to get some diverse scenes in order
to train.
Good point.
People use that a lot.
So the hope when we started that project
was that we could write strong enough global point cloud
registration algorithms, the global versions of ICP,
so that we could have it completely automated.
If I just let the robot walk around and do its collection,
it would build the model.
It would find the drill in the model, and we'd be good.
We'd be generating data like crazy.
OK, but you guys have now had some experience with ICP.
It's not that robust, unfortunately.
So in practice, in order to make that actually work,
we have a user interface where after we take these scans,
we have a human say, look here for the drill.
Three clicks to say roughly a pose,
and then ICP takes those very approximate rapid clicks
because we have the GUI so they can just go through all
your data set really fast.
It'll find the ICP, generate all the images.
So that's what worked for us at the time.
I still think there might be a future where
the global registration is good enough for that,
or the more global registration.
But that's where we were there.
So it's interesting, though, that even though that
is an effective pipeline and generates lots of data,
even those imperfections that of just the ICP
converge to something close but not quite or whatever,
those imperfections are a nuisance in your training.
If you contrast that with our other super powerful tool,
which is simulation, where we can make absolutely pristine,
perfect labels from our simulator,
the difference between errors in human labeled data
versus simulation perfect data has made this interesting trend
where you would think that their natural data would always
be better than simulated data.
But it's not true.
At some point, because the simulation quality is better,
the pixel by pixel quality is better,
even if the scenes are less diverse,
people have switched their pipeline slowly
from a purely real world data to a lot of people
are using purely simulated data to generate these training
sets now.
Or maybe most common still is mostly simulation data,
sprinkle in a little bit of real world data just
for good measure.
But I can tell you, it's annoying
to do the real world data.
The sim data works really, really well.
And in less and less often, I see
we're actually going to the real world data,
only if you really have to.
So what does the simulation pipeline look like?
So we already had it.
This is how it looks like in Drake.
If you have your RGB sensor that was kicking out the color
images that we were drawing like this,
it's kicking out the depth images.
It's also-- there's an output port for the label image.
So it spits out an image that's the same size
as what the camera was.
But every pixel is just assigned an integer value.
The integer value is mapped with a hash
to what type of object it is.
So this is an instant segmentation.
I changed-- if you were to just take the label image
and just say, plot the label image,
you would see something that looked black.
But I just-- because it uses like 0, and then 1, and then 2,
and then 3.
So I just scrambled those up into our favorite matplotlib
colors in order to make this plot.
But otherwise, it's almost exactly what you'd get out
of the label image port.
You get unique identifiers, pixel by pixel perfect,
based on the raycast in the renderer.
Yes?
So it doesn't have to be the normal object?
You don't have to get any of the [INAUDIBLE]??
So let's-- so the question is, is it only for known objects?
So I think it's helpful to think about this in the known object
case first.
Like in the-- the simulator knows the objects.
It's like, I've put in something from mustard.sdf, right?
And I can label it, this is mustard because of that.
OK?
So the simulator has no problem with that.
In order to have put the data in,
you have somehow a knowledge of what the objects are.
Whether you choose to use the known object
pipeline on the deep network side or not
is a second question.
But I think for the generating the labeled images,
that data is available.
OK, and this is really surprisingly potent.
So-- and I've seen--
when this trend started, it was because video games
got really good.
Flat out, Unreal Engine looks awesome, right?
Unreal Engine 4 looks even better.
Like, there's-- and all--
Unity looks amazing.
There's a bunch of-- there's like this--
it seems that most people roll their own.
Most of the game engines roll their own.
But they've all reached this--
somehow there's this, like, I don't know,
enough employees have shuffled back and forth or whatever.
There's like this common knowledge
where everybody's kicking out these incredible graphics
engines, right?
And they took us above some threshold
and making near photorealistic renders, OK?
But as people have leaned more and more on simulation,
where we first started off worrying
a lot about the render quality, like, I
will do whatever it takes to put the best
renderer on this as possible.
I've seen now increasingly people are like,
you know what, it actually kind of works fine with OpenGL.
You know, you don't even really need
to get the shadows perfectly right.
It still seems to transfer.
And it's been this interesting trend where the concern
about the render quality has gone down.
Now, if you really--
you will start seeing some artifacts.
So if you're really trying to build a high-end system,
you want your shadows to look right.
You want those details.
But you can get pretty far.
If you just want to pick some stuff up,
OpenGL is going to be fine.
OK, so I really don't want to talk too much
about architecture, but I want people
to understand just some of the very basics about why
I can ask questions like, how many objects are in the scene?
That's very distracting.
So let me just sort of step through the basic,
how do I go from an object recognition system,
you know, an image recognition system,
to my object detection system?
How do I go from image recognition
to object detection?
And the idea is, like, you saw it on that slide.
Basically, object detection, in its simplest form,
is image recognition, where I just try--
I move a sliding window across my image,
and I ask the image recognition question for each box.
If I just do image recognition on those boxes,
and I threshold and only keep the boxes that
have a high recognition score, then I
can imagine right there getting a box that's really--
that gives my object detection.
Now, that's not what people do anymore.
That's somehow some of the first things people do.
That's a poor representation of exactly everything
that's in RCNN, but that's the basic idea, right?
You have a lot of different images of different sizes
and different shapes, whatever.
For each one of them, you're basically
running that through a convolutional network
and asking the basic yes/no questions.
And that was how the first--
the mainstream detectors, object detection, started working.
Nowadays, people do more advanced versions of that,
but actually not crazy more advanced.
So nowadays, you don't just try--
so typically, it was expensive to try every possible region.
So we used some standard computer vision
from before 2014, ideas for what regions would
be good regions to evaluate.
So you could try to make it fast.
The fast RCNN was trying to down select some images.
And then the faster RCNN was this series of papers, right?
The faster RCNN said, you know what?
Let's use a neural network to predict where the regions are.
That's the region proposal network.
And then inside those regions, we'll do our image recognition.
And this is roughly the story how these things go,
is that we're like, oh, there's a little piece that
was hand-engineered there.
Let's replace that part with a neural network.
And at some point, we've got a completely deep end-to-end
thing.
The other thing that happened in this pipeline that
is important is that you have a region proposal network
or your initial guesses of where the regions are.
And typically, you will ask not only is there an object in here,
but if you were to do a small crop of that image,
then what would--
you try to predict also a crop, basically,
so that you get tighter images, tighter bounding boxes
by having the network also put out a crop value, basically,
the new bounding box regression.
So I mean, it is interesting to just stop and think
and appreciate, I guess, what's happening, right?
Is that, first of all, I remember--
I mean, I'm old, right?
So I remember when we were doing neural networks,
and it was like we were training the sheep, the dog, the cat
detector.
And it was kind of like, yeah, that works.
But I'm never going to train--
it doesn't really scale to have an output
vector that has 2,000 classes.
No one would ever do that.
People do that.
They do it all the time, right?
And then to think, oh, we're going
to apply a neural network to every single one of those boxes
is just--
yeah, that works too, right?
And yeah, sometimes the number of outputs
that people are predicting with these networks
is just mind boggling.
Like, I just would never have predicted
that we would want to do that.
But things have scaled up with GPUs, and TPUs, and the like
have really scaled beautifully.
I mean, even the fact that--
sorry, one other point I want to make there.
It used to be that we think, OK, well, we've
got just a fixed length vector coming out
of our neural network, right?
So the probability of it being a sheep,
the probability of it being a dog,
maybe the xy value of my new bounding box, OK?
But it's always like a fixed size vector in
and a fixed size vector out.
And so you ask, like, if I want to say I have some previously
unknown number of objects in my scene,
how do you architect the network to do that, right?
How do you have a variable number of outputs?
We have multiple answers to that these days.
But the initial way that that worked
was these region proposal networks,
or just any threshold of regions.
Was that you're going to evaluate the network many,
many times at threshold.
And that suddenly gave this reality to the idea
that you could have a variable number of object recognitions
or object detections in a single image.
OK, and you can sort of imagine that this would work, too,
if I had a neural network that had an image coming in,
and I had the pixel by pixel segmentation coming out,
whether it's semantic or instance level, OK?
You could imagine trying to learn that function, too.
And if you put all those together,
then you get mask R-CNN, which is a little bit old now,
but it's still extremely good.
There's a mask R-CNN 2, which is in Detectron 2,
but it's still incredibly good, OK?
And it's relatively simple, but I
did provide all of the example that you can open up and run
that does all of the data generation, the training,
and fine tuning of a mask R-CNN network,
so you can play around with it and see how it works
for our cluttered data set.
I knew that was going to happen.
But let me just show you kind of how that works.
If you were to grab this from the--
oh, good, it cached it.
And when you start doing this, those of you
that have spent time training deep models,
you know that basically 90% of the work
is like writing the data loader, OK?
So someone gave me an image, and it's in some sort of format,
and its values are either 0 to 55 or 0 to 1 or whatever.
And you just have to--
you spend a lot of time getting that right,
especially because if you get it wrong,
the network still learns something,
but it doesn't learn quite the right thing.
And it's just really hard to realize that you made
a mistake in the data loader.
So I did that for you.
You don't have to do that.
But you can play with it, right?
So the things that come out-- this is my training image.
This is my mask that comes out of MaskR-CNN,
where I just asked for the mustard mask, OK?
It found a mustard bottle in the image for what--
this is an instance-level detector, right?
So it found one of the instances.
I could change the indices that I've asked for,
and it'll show me the other mustard bottle, I think.
And then you can see all of the detections it found
in this image.
It flat out missed the big Cheez-It box.
It's the most easy, you would think, scene.
But admittedly, I trained this network hours
before lecture last year.
So probably it could have done better with a little bit more.
Yeah, but it did a pretty darn good job of finding the Jello.
And you can see it's got the gelatin box and the gelatin box
that SDF.
It's got these-- it's pretty incredible how well it worked.
I generated a reasonably big data set.
I think I could have generated a much smaller data set
and had it work well.
I just didn't want to have nothing for lecture.
OK, and you can go in there, and you can start playing with,
what are the region proposals?
I was actually surprised at how bad a lot of the region
proposals were.
I mean, it happened to get some good ones that, when cropped
down, did the job.
But if you only look at the final output,
then maybe you don't see all the messiness that's inside.
And it still does--
it considers pretty random proposals in the middle.
So that's a pipeline that, like I said,
if we just wanted to use our antipodal grasping,
that's going to do the job.
It said, if I want to, say, pick up a mustard bottle,
I could actually iterate through all the mustard bottles.
But I can just say, these pixels from that RGB camera
are mustard, are a mustard bottle.
If I project that back onto the Jello,
I can actually see the Jello.
And I can see the Jello.
And I can see the mustard bottle.
If I project that back onto the point cloud,
I could use that as my segmentation for my point cloud.
So just remove all of the points that
aren't associated with those pixels.
And then I could find the antipodal grasp on that.
And I picked mustard bottles instead of random things.
It's very cool.
So I hope you play with it.
If you're not familiar, then you can see the whole pipeline.
There's a different notebook for generating the training data,
and one for training, and then one for testing.
So the training takes hours, many hours.
I wrote it so that basically, if you walked away
and Google Colab shut down, just before it shut down,
it tried to save the file to your laptop.
And there might be some lessons there
if you're trying to use Colab in the future, too.
Any questions on that before we go
into some of the more manipulation-specific
representations?
It's a super powerful pipeline.
It's really good.
OK.
So let's just think about the fact
that ICP doesn't work globally.
And we even said back then that it's
hard to beat the geometric perception for really
fine estimation of the pose.
But in terms of going from an image
and having an initial guess, something
sort of in the spirit of just trying to find
the needle in the haystack, I think deep learning pose
estimation is a very nice approach to that.
Caveat-- this is deep perception part one.
Deep perception part two, I'm roughly going to say,
don't do pose estimation.
Because I think once you have a deep network at work,
you can ask richer questions that
are less specific to single object representations.
There's more interesting object representations.
But I think it's very helpful to take the stuff we've already
seen and try to map it into the deep learning context.
And it's the beginning of what we'll see--
I guess I can just erase that.
It's the beginning of what we'll see
as sort of a nice marriage between the ideas from geometry
and the ideas from deep learning.
So I think the big question is, if I do send images in--
I guess I could have just left what I had there.
And I have poses coming out.
I want you to think about this first as one choice
for object representation.
OK.
So this is sort of our--
we've got a mesh model plus a pose as our representation.
So implicitly, in order to generate the training data
or whatever, I had a model, which I generated
a bunch of simulated images.
My mustard bottle, that SDF, right?
And somehow, that model, once I have it,
if I can just say what the pose is,
then this will tell me everything
I need to do to start manipulating
that object in the world.
We're going to look at other alternatives here,
and even slightly richer versions of this.
We'll talk about learning sign distance functions,
or some of you think about learning
NERF or other kind of representations
that maybe don't require the mesh model.
But the one that snaps right in and we
can compare to our understanding of geometric perception
is if we try to predict the poses.
So the question I want to ask you here
is, we talked about all the different ways
to represent pose.
How do I represent-- which representation should I use?
OK.
So I mean, having an x, y, z value,
that's totally not a big deal.
That's fine.
I don't think there's a better choice.
But what about for orientation?
What do you think would be a good orientation
representation for a deep network to kick out?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
So.
So that's, I think, a lot of-- well,
that's not the first one that I saw a lot of papers about,
but that's definitely something that people try.
And it doesn't work well at all, because there's
singularities in that transform.
And so you tend to--
I think the networks actually have trouble
learning real pitchy off.
But that's a great starting point.
What else?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
Quaternions.
So if the quaternions are coming out,
and we just think of them as a 4 by 1,
if you think about it as just as an element of R4,
I have four real valued outputs.
That's part of it.
But you also need to make it a unit quaternion, right?
So plus some normalization, which people would typically
do now by having a last layer of the network that
does the normalization.
And you can just take derivatives
through that normalization function, right?
But you need to include that to have unit quaternions.
So that's a good proposal.
But actually, we've seen people understanding more deeply now
that that can have trouble for neural networks too.
It's a little bit of folklore.
But I think the progress in learning 3D vision,
I think that people would say that more
continuous representations, that this actually
can have some discontinuities.
We'll talk about it.
And that there are better representations still.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Axis angle.
PROFESSOR: Axis angle.
So the axis angle is going to be very similar to the unit
quaternions.
But it doesn't need the normalization.
But it turns out it's going to be plagued by the same stuff.
I mean, axis angles and quaternions
are very, very closely related.
Yeah?
So let's try to understand--
I mean, the other ones we've talked about,
we've talked about the rotation matrix as an output.
But again, you need to somehow make sure you get a real rotation
matrix out.
So did you want to recommend?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: OK, so the proposal is x, y, z of corners of a cube.
So that's not a crazy idea.
OK, so let me understand what you said.
So to some extent, if I'm trying to learn a pose,
if I've learned this x, y, z, and you're saying basically
also learn this x1, y1, z1, maybe this, and all three,
something like that, you could think about how minimal you
could make it and just learn all of those as 3D points,
let's say, or 3D vectors, rather,
and then try to reconstruct.
People have had some success with that.
I think I would call that sort of a key point based version.
We'll talk a lot about key points on Thursday.
But that's a reasonable representation, too.
You have to make sure you still have
to enforce something about the scaling or whatever
when you reconstruct.
But you could imagine trying to fit the closest
rotation to those points.
You could just try to do the rotation matrix directly,
which actually is almost that.
I mean, if you're trying to fit a rotation matrix
as a 3 by 3 matrix, that's basically
parameterizing the x, y, z vectors of the transform, which
is really basically doing that.
But you need to-- so the same way
that you'd need to be careful on this,
you would have to somehow add the rotation matrix
constraint.
So R R transpose equals I and determine it.
So there's a series of work that has been arguing that somehow--
again, it's not a super watertight argument.
But the argument roughly goes like this.
Deep networks learn continuous functions.
You'd like the function that you're trying to learn
to be continuous.
And all things considered, a function
that is a continuous function, as I change angles,
for instance, if I change poses of my object,
the output changes continuously, is
going to be better for the neural network to learn.
There's a series of papers about on the continuity of rotation
representations for deep learning, which
I will cite properly in the notes.
But try to learn more continuous representations.
And the discontinuities in our representations
are a little sneaky.
You have to kind of think about it.
So if you think about in 2D, imagine
I just wanted to use theta, for instance.
So if I just want to parameterize
the total angle of my pose, maybe theta's in 0 to 2 pi.
I'd like to somehow have the output of my network
be between 0 and 2 pi.
Well, then there's two rotations.
The rotations at epsilon and 2 pi minus epsilon
should be close.
The wrapping gives you a discontinuity.
Those should be close, but aren't in this representation.
You say, OK, well, maybe I just do 0 to 4 pi
or something like that.
But what is your training data?
When you've got your training data,
and you say this object is at this orientation,
you've got to pick.
You've got to somehow pick your unwrapping.
And for whatever function you've tried to pick,
you somehow have picked a domain for this.
And it's not easy to unwrap perfectly.
Well, there are things you can do to repair these problems.
But this is the fundamental problem,
is that you think that's good, right?
Because the rotation matrix has a function of theta.
And 2D is this sort of smooth function.
I mean, going from theta to the rotation, the full rotation
matrix, that's good.
But going backwards involves some unwrapping,
some decision.
So the argument is roughly, the network
needs you to be unambiguous in your choice of orientation.
And that's kind of fundamentally what
happens to quaternions or Euler angles and other things, too.
Even quaternions are ambiguous because negative
of the quaternion is the same rotation
as the positive of the quaternion.
So if I have for quaternions, I have a quaternion q
and quaternion negative q are the same rotation.
It was interesting to sort of see,
if you go to the website of the paper
on this continuity of learning, you
can see that they clearly got attacked.
Like, what do you mean quaternions aren't smooth
or whatever?
And they have this, like, fact.
This is what we meant by quaternions not being smooth.
But at some point, let's say you could just
say your training data had to pick a q or a minus q,
for instance.
And they have some theorems in the follow-up paper,
for instance, saying that basically you cannot pick
a transformation from the rotation matrices to q that
doesn't have a singularity.
They always have a singularity.
In fact, there's a topological argument
that basically you can't map the rotation
matrices into a representation in four numbers that
is absolutely no discontinuities.
So they have a series of proposals for ways to do that,
ways to get around it.
So one of them-- it's actually--
it wasn't what I expected.
They call it an ensemble.
But they basically wrote four different functions
that are all choices of q or q inverse differently.
So you could basically write four different rotation matrix
to quaternion maps.
And you could, like, combine all of their outputs.
And you can get a singularity-free output.
That's one way to do it.
So you can repair this with more dimensions.
In fact, one of them would be, I think,
a fairly reasonable one that people use
would be to actually parameterize the rotation
matrix in 3 by 3.
And then the same way we added a normalization,
add basically the singular value decomposition
as the last layer.
So you're projecting back to the closest rotation matrix.
And that's something that seems to work fairly well, too.
Yes.
So for the last thing that you wrote there, I get how having-- like, the fact that the
quaternions are not unique, that's like a challenge in terms of trying to make these
work.
And I get how adding more dimensions can help you get around, like, the times that you
need to be normalized.
But I feel like as you add more dimensions, wouldn't it become more redundant?
Like, wouldn't there be more, like, it's not necessarily a question of, well, what
does this mean?
But I guess I'm not sure that that's the answer.
So I guess I'm not sure that's the answer.
So the question is, if you add more dimensions, are you adding more redundancy?
I mean, that's not always true.
But I like the question.
So I can answer it in 2D.
4D is hard.
Quaternions are hard to think about.
So let's contrast a rotation, which is theta, versus the polar coordinates.
If I were to instead do, let's say-- well, I could do r-- let's just even do cosine theta
and sine theta, which is actually my first two elements of my rotation matrix, which
I-- if I just think about it basically parametrizing
those.
If I were to ask the network to learn cosine theta and sine theta, then for every rotation,
there is a unique answer in two numbers.
And maybe I have to project to make sure cosine squared plus sine squared equals 1 at the
end.
And I guess that constraint is what's saving us.
Maybe that's in the counting game that you're trying.
I think it's the constraint that would then save us.
Maybe that's the simplest answer.
But this is an example where I think you'd prefer, even though it's more dimensions,
you'd prefer to ask it to learn something like cosine theta, sine theta, because you
can give it a unique answer.
That's a great, great question.
The representations in 5 and 6D, I don't have a picture in my head.
One could, but I haven't studied it enough to know.
Because even in 4D, there's a unit quaternion constraint to keep it-- so there's really
natively three variables.
But there's still actually-- so we've listed a lot of good ones here from the key points
and the rotation matrices and all these quaternions.
And then I think the rotation matrices plus SVD is actually a good choice.
It doesn't completely-- so even this picture, it resolves the ambiguity if my object is
rotationally unique or something, if it doesn't have any rotational symmetries.
But in practice, there's all sorts of ambiguity in rotations.
So there are shapes that are perfectly symmetric around rotations.
There are things that are just ambiguous because of partial views.
So I brought some pictures from the kitchen sink.
This is Kunimatsu's work.
And he used something more like what Charles recommended, actually, where you tried to
learn the center point, but you'd also learn some points on the boundary that would construct
the axis.
But he also tried to learn an uncertainty representation.
Because mugs, my gosh, if you can't see the handle, then there's a whole bunch of angles
they could be at.
They're not perfectly rotationally symmetric.
They're partially rotationally symmetric.
You could imagine a handle-less mug that's perfectly rotationally symmetric.
Our plates are always completely symmetric.
But the sort of interesting case is the mug, where if you can see the handle, you'd like
to have high confidence at your label.
But if you can't see the handle, then you'd like to somehow-- well, you have a problem.
If you're trying to ask the network to output a particular pose, then how do you even label
that training set and expect it to give potentially-- if some of my perfectly generated CAD models
are in this orientation, they're in this orientation, they're in this orientation, you could give
identical inputs to the network and ask it to be outputting different answers.
It's not a function.
So networks don't like doing that in general.
And I think the fundamental answer for that is to try to output not just one of these,
but to generalize it to outputting a distribution over poses.
That's, I think, the only fundamental way to get around that.
So in the COSNET paper, we had a particular way to-- it was kind of thinking a lot about
rotational symmetries in one axis, which is that there's a lot of objects that are particularly
symmetric in one axis.
So it focused its distribution representation on each axis independently.
And that was a pretty useful way to do it.
And then you could imagine outputting, let's say, a Gaussian distribution, a mean and a
covariance for if you did Euler angles for each Euler angle, for instance.
And that works fairly well for mugs.
It's a little bit hard for me to talk you through this.
But basically, there's views here where you can just barely see a handle.
And you're supposed to see-- when you see the handle, you're supposed to see pretty
narrow uncertainty.
And when you can't see the handle, the uncertainty gets broader.
So the network's doing a good job.
But actually generating the label for that is tough.
How do you know from your CAD models that all of these poses-- that I should have a
wide distribution here and a narrow distribution?
In general, for mugs, you can imagine hacking it.
In fact, we did have a way that worked using numerical differencing of images, a way that
worked for that paper.
But that's a hard problem more generally.
So typically, you have to change your loss function to do better.
And basically, instead of outputting-- so if your output of your network is a distribution
over poses, you have to do-- you just have to accept that if it's producing the maximum
likelihood of this distribution, has high probability in the true training set, then
you're happy, instead of trying to match the entire distribution to your training set,
because you can't produce that.
So you have to change your loss to a maximum likelihood formulation.
Actually in each of these, the loss function is interesting.
Like the quaternions, you don't want to do loss, the L2 loss.
You want to do a geodesic distance as a loss function.
And each of these representations, you can think about what the right loss function is.
But the interesting idea here is just that you can train a distribution over poses by
only getting samples from the distribution, instead of getting labels that are the entire
distribution.
And I think it's really interesting to ask, what are the right ways to write distributions
over orientations?
And there's an answer that people mostly like.
Anybody know the distribution?
It's gotten more popular, but it's maybe not mainstream yet.
It happens to be named the same name.
It's not-- I think the author was not the person who basically destroyed the Incas.
But there was an explorer who wasn't so good for the Incas.
Anybody get it?
No, OK.
What is it?
It wasn't Pizarro.
Bingham.
I think maybe it's spelled differently.
But I went to Peru last year, so I learned a lot about Bingham.
So there's this famous distribution, the Bingham distribution, which is sort of the right way
to-- maybe the right way.
It's a reasonable way to write distributions over the unit quaternions.
And I think the picture is very, very nice and clean.
Jared Glover was a student with Leslie and Tomas that worked on this.
He did it in the context of a robot playing ping pong.
But it was more general than that.
And to this day, I think his pictures in his thesis are the best-- they give me the best
mental representation of how to think about this.
So the fundamental question is, how do you put a distribution over-- for quaternions,
you'd like a distribution over the unit sphere in four dimensions that is also antipodal.
So that's the question.
Gaussians don't do that very well out of the box.
How do you write a distribution that's antipodal?
But it turns out the trick is not that bad.
It's hard for me to see the circle underneath there, but maybe you get the idea.
So in 2D-- so I want to write a distribution over the circles.
And I'd like to have-- what you see on the right is some Gaussian-like thing that happens
to be sort of centered here and centered over here.
Then the way to do it, or a way to do it, the Bingham way to do it, is to make a Gaussian
in the higher dimensional space in 2D, and then just apply the constraint after the fact
that I'm only going to-- I'm going to renormalize the Gaussian so that it's only sampled on
the unit circle.
That's the Bingham distribution.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
It is the word people use.
I didn't make it up myself, but it's a little made up, maybe.
I would like the probability of picking q is equal to the probability of picking minus
q.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
I mean, you could say that.
That's fine.
Yeah.
I'm happy with that.
So yeah, I mean, I think that is the right picture for the Bingham distribution.
But it gets more beautiful in high dimensions.
So you can change-- just like if I change the covariance of this Gaussian, that parameterizes
the covariance of the distribution on the circle.
And like I said, it gets more beautiful.
And Jared did a great job of illustrating it.
So if you have a narrow uncertainty on the unit circle, you get these nice little peaks
on the circle.
If you have a broader distribution in one axis, you get things like this.
And the limit where you've got a 0 eigenvalue there, then you get the ring.
So if your object was perfectly symmetric in one axis, you might actually get this.
If you're pretty sure about it in some orientations, but it could be anywhere in rotation, then
you'd get a distribution that looks out like that.
The normalization is a pain.
It's like a big, ugly function integrating on the sphere.
So you try not to do that.
If you don't actually need a true probability, and you're OK having an unnormalized probability,
then you'll be happier with Bingham's.
But in general, we know how to compute that.
Is Jared estimating the point as a [INAUDIBLE] ball?
The best application of Jared's using of Bingham's was actually he was trying to estimate the
spin while the ball was flying.
And he picked ping pong balls with big labels so you could have some sense.
But then he still had uncertainty.
And he was trying to do fancy ping pong with spin.
So maybe unsurprisingly, there's now deep Bingham networks.
And actually, I feel there were papers that predated this that came pretty close to it.
But I guess the people that picked deep Bingham networks picked the right title.
So I think this is applied quite effectively to registering point cloud data.
And I think it's a good representation of choice.
They had a really nice paragraph in their introduction.
I don't normally read things.
But let me just read this or paraphrase this for you.
This is a Leo Griebus paper.
And there's a number of authors.
So they say, a myriad of papers have worked on finding the unique solution to the pose
estimation problem.
They cited a lot of papers.
A pose per view scan.
However, this trend is now witnessing a fundamental challenge.
A recent school of thought has begun to point out that for our highly complex and ambiguous
environments, obtaining a single solution, the correct pose, is simply not sufficient.
Instead of estimating a single solution, methods now propose to predict a range of solutions,
providing multiple pose hypotheses and solutions that can associate uncertainties to their
predictions or even solutions in the form of full probability distributions.
I do think that's a trend that is happening.
And I think it's required for more sophisticated manipulation pipelines.
So they did the Bingham distribution as the output where they would train basically the
covariance matrix of that Gaussian is the thing that's coming out of the network.
And you can parameterize even that more or less cleverly.
And for richer uncertainty distributions where you really have multimodal, you can just do
a mixture of Binghams.
So just sum over a handful of Binghams.
And again, you have to do the loss function the right way with the maximum likelihood
loss so that you don't pretend that all of your-- all the ones that you basically would
have-- they call it mixture death or something.
What do they call it?
When the ones that are not getting sampled could just sort of disappear, choosing a maximum
likelihood objective function can protect you against that.
So this whole notion of choosing the right output of your network for the poses makes
a big difference.
There's other alternatives.
There's people that talk about implicit.
I have a snapshot from this idea of trying to overcome orientations by training basically
an implicit function where you're basically trying to render the image.
You take a bunch of random samples.
You run it through a renderer.
And if the image looks the same, then you say that's-- you try to find an invariant
representation to the rendering.
I'll tell you more about that when we talk about the implicit representations on Thursday.
But there's a handful of these ideas out there.
And it really-- it can matter.
Euler angles don't actually work.
OK.
Questions on deep pose at all?
Yes.
Do you think this continuity issue is actually like a big factor in like the final algorithm?
Because if you just consider this as like a little bit of a-- like a little bit of a
[INAUDIBLE]
It's a good question about whether this really matters in practice.
If you've got a bunch of data sets and every once in a while you get a-- you happen to
sample right around the discontinuity, how big of an effect that is.
The papers that started highlighting this talked about experimental observations that
people had made where you'd see big errors that never went to zero in parts of your space.
In various different representations, they talked about empirical observations that forced
the investigation.
I think-- yeah, it depends how varied your data set is.
I think you could say the same thing about Euler angles and humanoid robots.
As long as you're-- I mean, I can sort of choose the-- I could choose an Euler axis
representation that works really well for Atlas.
But if I ever end myself completely horizontal, I'd be in trouble.
And I think the same sort of thing.
If you can kind of guarantee that your application isn't going to see objects that are near the
singularity and you don't have to worry about it, you could be fine with a simpler representation.
But doing a little bit more work, I think you can just defend against it.
It's more recent that these results have come out.
We've been applying networks pretty effectively without all those tricks.
Cool.
OK.
So just to call out, because you guys-- the 6 to 800 folks talked about CLIP in the first
paper.
But it's sort of an interesting-- if I return a little bit to the generating training data
for manipulation, we talked about fine tuning as an approach to this, is that I'll use the
ImageNet or COCO data set, or whatever the biggest, closest data set I have is.
And then I'll lop the head off and I'll train it for my task.
So a really important trend that I just kind of want to call out-- we'll talk about specific
instances of contrastive learning when we get to it.
But I think even here, it's worth knowing that that idea of fine tuning or retargeting
of transfer has sort of enabled even a bigger idea, which is that I can train a different
task potentially.
It doesn't have to be an image recognition task.
Maybe I can train a slightly different task, something that would be easier to generate
training data for, lop the head off that, and hope that as long as that task was similar
enough, then I can do fine tuning on my particular task.
So that's just a question of how far can you go with your retargeting?
So there's this wave of results of trying to find-- in self-supervised learning-- of
trying to find surrogate tasks where you don't need a human to provide labels.
You can answer some different query, possibly just by looking at the data.
And the backbone from that network might be learning relevant enough features that you
could transfer it with a small amount of data on your task.
So an early example of this that I like very much is something that people do is they'll
train monocular depth.
So here's what-- you take two cameras.
You have a stereo image pair.
You put it on your autonomous car, whatever you're going to do.
And you've got a lot of data with two cameras.
And you just ask, can you make-- so you can produce the depth from the stereo data.
And then you can just ask, could I have predicted the depth just from one camera?
Just take away the second camera, predict the depth from one camera.
That's the monocular depth estimation problem.
That's easy to train in a lot of settings.
It turns out training that task seems to learn a lot of geometric information about the world,
maybe unsurprisingly.
If you lop the head off that network, you might be able to apply it to your problem.
It's pretty cool.
The CLIP paper that some of you read for the 6800 was trying to-- if you think about overcoming
the limitation of the however many labels in the COCO data set, the CLIP paper was mining
the web just trying to find correspondences effectively between words on the web and images
on the web.
And that's something that nobody needs to supervise.
You could argue that the web is supervising it, that every person who made a website was
somehow the supervisor.
But for me, it's free.
Or for open AI, it's free.
So you can just go out and mine existing data, have a loss function which just says, could
I predict-- given a new image or a new sentence, can I predict which image it came from?
That's a self-supervised type signal.
And it could generate huge amounts of data without any labeling.
And it might be that it's close enough to the task you care about that you can reuse
that training for your task.
I've even seen people-- so there's a version where you can just now-- if you have learned
from watching from image captions to images, learned a bunch of stuff about the web, you
can ask questions that will turn CLIP into basically an object detection algorithm.
And people-- so Kevin, who played with this, just started putting it on random images and
asked questions like, where's the microwave?
And it just-- it was never trained.
It was never fine-tuned on this data.
It was just kind of like, out of the box, having looked at enough images on the web,
can I use this without fine-tuning in the wild?
Does it have enough classes to actually sort of provide a general purpose object detection
system?
And it's not perfect.
It's pretty good.
Pretty good.
It's pretty cool.
It's pretty funny, because sometimes you get better answers if you ask questions.
Like, you have to think, how would someone have written a caption about this?
My dog is really cute.
It might work better than dog or something.
I don't know.
That's a bad example.
But sometimes the queries I've seen people put into the system to get good results sometimes
look totally ridiculous.
And they're not the minimal thing.
But that's what it correlated.
OK, awesome.
So hopefully we talked a bit about training data for manipulation.
We talked about the recognition and segmentation pipeline.
I've given you a notebook so you can play with MaskRCNN.
And that alone can feed a pipeline.
Pose estimation is definitely a thing you can do.
You should think about your geometry understandings as well as your deep network understandings
to do it well.
And we'll keep going on Thursday.
[END PLAYBACK]
Thank you.
[BLANK_AUDIO]