and
yeah i'm all excited about being back
just uh...
some of you
so
they're having trouble finding us
you know i think that uh...
my optimism is is window a little bit uh... i think we are
occurred
at his visit
are available as possible and and getting through it
being is created yet to get through that so
i don't have all the answers but i'll answer any questions i can answer
asking and asking asking
there were some alternatives like you know
it's the class of saturday mornings at eight thirty a m
but that i
i think that's it
i think that i think this is what we've got
uh... yet concerns or questions let me know if it doesn't
big classes appealing i totally understand so
okay good
today we're going to talk so most of the class actually we're going to talk about
and uh... the sort of the a_i_ behind
but today
to get in
uh... into it i want to talk a little bit about her
give you a sense for the hardware we're going to be thinking about
in in the class a lot
uh... this is the group uh...
he would
in in the flesh if you will and uh... it's been bigger and more real than
that it looks on the
cartoons
uh... brought a few hands
uh... danny's got some cool hands in the overflow room too
so you guys will be able to
uh...
so uh...
let's let's begin so first of all i do want to just remind you that if you do
uh... useful but
all of these some of my click here
isn't pointing to this anymore but uh...
don't click their click there and uh... but i could even click there right now
and anybody can on the textbook right and it opens up the people
started using
he says
some of you realize that
uh... when you duplicate apparently it doesn't show this by defaults you have
to sort of like if you want to get to the exercise you got to do that
anyways uh...
the chapter
has some cool things i think it is
uh... the ability to just drop in any robot provided for
the people who had more
and just like you
move them around get a sense for what they're like
and it steps you through a bit of what it takes to simulate and some of the
more
subtle aspects of simulation which we'll talk through on the board a little bit
playing with the code
hopefully
you know there's a lot of hardware out there
uh... we talked about this
the signals and systems the dynamical systems abstraction last time
and i want to dig in a little bit more
so there's this view of
this sort of pure view of control
or even uh... in reinforcement learning these days
you'll see a lot of people that
draw that simple version of the picture
where i just have
my robot
which has some sensors coming out
actuators is just a slightly more general term than motors, motors i think of as being
electric motors, actuators could be hydraulic or anything
motors are
one type of actuator
and then my control here
and really your control should take your sensors in and put out the actuators
and you'll see
the sort of idealized version of this
or the stylized version of this
in RL maybe I would say
we're just going to go from pixels to torques
I actually like that as a charter
I try to think how do you go all the way from
if your sensor is a camera
and ultimately the thing you send to your robot is a torque
then how do you close that whole loop and what has to happen to make that happen
but if you look down at the details and it's not just an implementation detail
I think it's fundamental and it's worth talking about in lecture here
you know you have some control box that you're allowed to access
through your drivers to the robot
your robot
the EWA actually
has an input
that looks like torque
we'll talk about exactly what it is
but really most of the robots out there
don't actually
let you send torques
into the actuators, that's an idealized view of the world
and it's actually not
what's happening on most of our robots
and there's reasons why, you don't want to probably send raw torques
directly to your robot
so even if
ironically simulation often you think about it as just a torque source
but
actually there's a lot more going on
and that can dramatically impact your success or failure with control strategies
so we'll dig in a little under the covers there today
what you find under the covers will depend on which arm you've taken
so my goal today is to talk a little bit about some of the robot arms out there
the hardware choices you make matter
we picked
the EWA as the one to think about mostly in the class
I'll tell you why, I'll tell you some of the things that's good about it
I want to really emphasize this point that
that physics, the physics engine is a big part of what you need to do the simulation
but actually
simulating that control box
and all the other stuff
is a big part of simulation too, so simulation is actually bigger than just physics
and
even though we're going to abstract a lot of that away with the signals and systems abstraction
it pays to at least have an awareness of what's happening underneath there
and then I've got a bunch of robot hands too, we'll talk about some of the cool robot hands out there
some of the different approaches people have taken to building
robot hands and we picked a simple gripper
for class
for this WSG and I'll tell you more about it and why
okay so
the mandatory intro robot slide here is that
you know robots are normally behind a fence
right this is actually where robots have seen most of their success and even in
newer fulfillment center kind of
workflows a lot of times
robots are behind a fence
and this is a type of robot that's been incredibly successful in industry
sometimes it's very powerful
it tends to be very rigid
it can move very quickly
be very accurate
but it's very different than the sort of
robots in the home that you might
that we're starting to envision now
and there's been a big movement in the last
twenty years now
certainly the last ten years
of trying to make co-bots
robots that are more
interactive more
heavily I guess more willing to
operate directly in the vicinity of humans and have that be okay
that's Rod Brooks who unfortunately the company isn't around anymore but
he started Rethink Robotics thinking about
how do you make robots that are fundamentally safer to interact with and lower cost
and that could be like in a bakery and
not behind a fence
and maybe the dream is that we're all inspired by the movies I think but
I love Baymax right and
we've been working
on projects that are inspired by Baymax and the like
okay so
how do we get to more cuddly robots I don't know
we'll work through it
so you know here's some mug shots of some of the robots that you've seen
probably in robotics papers these days and in robotics labs these days
you can see a lot of them
in the building if you walk around
so there's the UR
series with the universal robot series there's three five depending on
the number is the kilogram payload at the end effector
that's the Rethink
that's Baxter there's a Sawyer robot
there's another one you recognize the Kuka
Konova
JCOs are actually a great series of robots
they were originally designed to be on the end of a
wheelchair
so unlike actually most of these
one of the great things about Konova is it doesn't have a massive
a massive control box underneath that's hiding it's actually a mobile robot arm
ABB
a maker of some of those enormous strong robots has gotten
come towards the
Cobot
with Yumi
Alberto's lab has a Yumi at least one
Frank a Panda is a new one that's kind of a
younger lighter
less expensive version of the Kuka
so there's a lot out there
and I would say it's an extremely exciting time for the field in the sense
that a lot of people are
are trying to innovate in cheaper hardware
potentially
I think it's easy to argue that
the robots most of the robots we have today were optimized for the factory
workflow where they were high precision
and high speed
and that's probably not what we need in the home
there's going to be a new generation of robots coming into the home
so we're
we're seeing startups and the like build them starting to build them aggressively now
okay the fundamental thing that's going on there
uh... since I asked a question
why is it not torques coming in but why is it positions coming in
like what you have to know
about what's underlying that and that includes this
Kuka robot it includes almost everything I
think everything I put on that picture list
is that they're electric motors driving the robot
but they're
you know especially in an attempt to be a lightweight
mobile robot
they try to pick
small electric motors
and they make those small electric motors which spin fast but don't produce a lot of torque
they gear them up like crazy in order to produce meaningful like human scale forces and torques
okay so you can it's not
it's not unusual to see gear ratios in excess of a hundred you know
two hundred kind of gear ratios okay
and you know mathematically that's just a
a scaling law that's not a big deal
but in practice it's a mess so
I'm trying to remember to stay closer to the
you'll see me keep going like this and then remembering and then going like this
so let me just maybe point on here
okay so
yeah this is just a just a random picture of a planetary gear box okay but
you know
typically in order to get big gear ratios you need
series upon series of gears
that involve lots and lots of complex interactions which include
new sources of friction
backlash
you know those gears bend under load there's all kinds of messy stuff there
okay so
we'll have you work out a little bit of in a problem set there's some nice details about it but
you know this there's a simple view of motors which is that
you know current in is proportional to torque out
and that I think that is a good model for motors you know with a couple extra details
until you put it into this gear box
and then
this the current you put into the gear box
is transmuted by some incredibly complicated
frictional and whatever you know
backlash effects
into something that is no longer
simply proportional to current on the output
so the conventional wisdom is that if you've got a gear ratio let's say greater than ten or something like this
then don't expect your current to be proportional to your torque on the output
so how do you get around that
there's a few ways that you know this is what leads to position control
as a defining
concept
okay huge
nonlinear transmissions
I guess the fact that they're nonlinear is less essential than that they're just unknown and hard to model
in fact I've seen I mean
you would expect maybe some of you when you when I say something like that you think
oh we should learn that in a deep neural network
and I think you should probably I think people are you know every once in a while
you hear people saying oh I just you know
I could totally model that in a deep network but it's
it's not easy it's not it's you know it's not just that there's like a complicated function
there's also a hidden state
there's a discrete state from the backlash back and forth
you know so every once in a while people say oh you know I
I don't need a gear box you know I figured I've solved the gear box problem
and then you know we don't hear anymore and then it's you know but one of these times someone's gonna say it and it's just gonna be solved and we're gonna be in a better place
what people have done instead
that has been very successful
is you have to add sensors on the output of the transmission
okay and the first bedrock sensor that we know how to add
we know how to work with we we can you know
we can totally rely on is a position sensor
you know you can there's a handful of ways they come
to geometers and coders optical coders
the most common but not the only ones
but basically
you sense the thing you're specifically trying to control
and position sensors are easy, inexpensive to add
okay so
you know why are we doing position control
you know and why are we doing this feedback
it's almost like the question of you know why are computers doing digital electronics instead of analog electronics
there's just so much mess in the world there
and closing a tight feedback loop
takes care of a lot of that mess
so what we do
in the internal control laws
they typically at the pulse width modulation right down at the electronics
the high power electronics going to the motor
we're closing a tight feedback loop around that position sensor
okay so
I mean I think
the details are can get subtle but
I think it's perfectly reasonable for our purposes to think of this as sending a motor command
that is proportional to the error in position
proportional gain
it's sort of like a spring law
a derivative gain
I have a desired velocity maybe
I've got an actual velocity
a lot of times that's zero or perpendicular
integral gain
mastered it
D for derivative gain instead of velocity but all good
so
what's the right way to think about
a system like that
if I have
some joint with an actuator
let's say I'm trying to hold up a pendulum that's being pulled down by gravity
and I'm trying to hold it at some desired
let's say I'm trying to hold it horizontal
I'm measuring some angle
this term here
is almost acting like a rotary spring
pulling me back up
towards that
equilibrium
as such
that term alone
won't get me all the way to the equilibrium
it will the spring will pull me
to fight gravity but at some point it will actually come to equilibrium
balancing
gravity with the spring force
a little bit below
this term adds some damping so you get nice convergence instead of oscillation
is what's watching that steady state error
and slowly saying okay I've got to push a little bit more
to actually achieve my desired
so in position controlled robots conceptually
I think of kp, kd, and ki as being very big
the robot is really
capable of tracking desired trajectories
with very high accuracy, very high precision
and it's very stiff
if you were to bump into it while it's moving
it's going to move you out of the way
which is I think an essential point
what would happen if I put my hand in here
if I put an obstacle in here that was impeding
the robot's ability to get to the steady state
first of all
if those gains are high this is a really stiff spring so I might already fling against it
and then if I'm not careful
I'm going to just push harder and harder and harder
until I fault my motor basically and my robot will turn off
and maybe there's smoke
which did happen one year in a live demo
not this year
okay so
so position control is a natural super effective
effective approach for controlling robots accurately
but it does run into limitations when you're starting to
work environments where you have unexpected contact
where you might bump into things
whether it's a human
whether it's some part of the environment that you didn't expect
some of these robots are just not well designed
they're just not meant to be operated in a place where they could suddenly have
unexpected contact
so we're going to
think a little bit carefully about
the alternatives and how those play out
I mean this picture
does that make sense the basic picture yeah
you know you could argue that it would do okay
like it's really not that bad to just kind of
push up against the obstacle and it got as close as it could
you know that was a reasonable accomplishing of the objective
if you have a multi-link arm
you know
and they're all these joints are independently trying to achieve their objective
and they don't realize they're stuck
you know things can get more ugly more complicated right
so
a lot of times
these gains are set
the feedback law is set
on each joint or each motor locally
and they don't talk to each other
there's a reason for that that you'll explore in the piece set
but things again things can go wrong when you start having incidental contact
there's a different approach
which is actually
was popularized in our mechanical engineering department that's
Harry Asada some of you will know
that's Kamal Yusuf Dumi I don't think he always is holding fish
sorry I picked a random picture
but they wrote I mean Kamal's thesis was actually about these direct drive robots
and
there's a beautiful book that got published out of that
thesis work
and I'd actually recommend it
it was ahead of its time
back then to make a direct drive robot
it meant
enormous motors like remember I said you know you've got these small motors and you gear them up
okay if you want to get rid of the gearbox then you end up with an enormous armature on your electric motor
okay so
it's just like
big old motor little arm you know
like a t-rex or something
big old motor little arm and
but when they did when they put their motors in that regime
then they were able to get very low gear ratios and
control torque directly
and that was I think
you know one of the first times we really got to see torque
controlled robots in action
now
our motor technology has gotten better our designs have
have evolved
you can find
torque direct drive or almost direct drive robots in much more reasonable form factors
even if anybody remembers the Barrett Wham robot which was a
cable driven robot that was you know eight to one gear ratios because of very clever cabling
and you know it was a
fairly lightweight robot that could move around and you thought of that as having torque control
Songbase group actually has you know has done great work on direct torque control
in legged robots especially
okay so there's an idea there which is you just build your robots differently
in fact
some of the new new robots I told you I thought there's a new new breed of robots that are coming out
they are closer to direct drive and they're using outrunner motors you know
this great thing that happened when when drones got popular right UAVs got popular
everybody started making these outrunner motors and in you know they
optimize the design and reduce the cost
and those outrunner motors are pretty awesome for generating a lot of torque
that's what they just flip the armature out to the you know
this is a slightly different design of a motor but they're much higher torque lower speed motors
and they are enabling the next some of the next generation of low-cost robots
okay but
the KUKA takes achieves some of this in a different way okay
so we talked about you know what you have a fundamental approach to this is to sort of
add sensors to the output of the transmission
most people add position sensors but you can also potentially add torque sensors
okay it's yeah
[inaudible]
yep so
I think the danger here is that
in order to get good tracking then you end up having a high stiffness here
and I think for moving through position only command it's great
but when you enter situations where you have unexpected collisions and the like it gets more dangerous
so I will continue to make that point when I finish with torque control
but I think it's going to allow us to deal with more uncertainty in the environment
so can you repeat that question?
I can repeat that question
after the fact yes of course
right so remind us why the question was basically can you remind me why torque control is a desirable thing to have
so this is a blowout of the mechanical design on the inside of every one of the joints on the KUKA
okay it's incredibly nice design work
in particular I mean you can see there's a lot of details go into these there's a big harmonic drive
so it is high high gear ratio okay but they have a torque sensor embedded in the output shaft okay
now torque sensors depending on who you talk to some people say torque sensors are like black magic
you know you have to like some people get them to work really well but they're really hard to get
get to be very performant you know I've seen more and more people accomplish that but I think
DLR was the name of the German space agency that did the initial design of these robots
I think they surprised people with how effective a torque sensing based on strain gauges and the like
at the output shaft could be for a high gear ratio robot so this was really an exceptional design
that that changed I would say our thinking about force control in in practical robots
so I say we have torque sensing on the output that implies that we can do something like a low
level feedback loop directly on torque instead of directly on position but it also becomes essential
in these sort of unexpected contact situations so to answer the question in a different way is if
you want to do things like this you know this is Sammy Haddaden oh I hope my internet's good enough
okay yeah right so this is Sammy when he was a student and he was working with the
the German space agency and he was making the point of these robots being you know
human robot interaction and when he talks about human robot interaction this is
physical human robot interaction and there's a great series of videos that I think added to the
impact of that work if you will and you know he's got him if we let it go long enough he'll
he'll hit himself in the head and there's even a series where the robot's got a sharp knife
I wasn't going to show that one but but the fact that they could be moving at high speeds
with an inertial robot detect the changes in torque and stop quickly I mean that's important too
it's pretty good
all right yeah
good I'm gonna I'm gonna I hope I land that if I don't answer that in a second so the question was
why is torque control safer in collisions right and I I think I will land that in a second
okay let's just to say that there's so adding torque sensors is not you know position torque
sensors and this is not the only approach that has been successful for making torque controlled
robots atlas actually had torque control we thought of it as having torque control on the legs and it
was more position control in the arms but atlas this is version one the new one is much more
it's a beautiful design I mean this was a beautiful design too but it's
generation one of something even more incredible you know this is a hydraulic robot right so it had
a big pump in the middle of its chest and it was pumping hydraulic fluid and shunting it through
these valves in order to control how much force how much work was being done at each at each joint
and the way that you would measure torque on this was it didn't have a transmission as per se but
it would have we would measure the differential pressure across the valve and that would be a
surrogate for torque but not a great one we had to we had to try to calibrate around it a lot okay
but we thought of this as having torque control and and for walking robots a lot of people believe
that torque control is essential again for interacting with the you know if you don't
know exactly where the ground is then being able to be in a more torque control mode instead of a
position control mode is excellent for a legged robot I would say legged robots promoted torque
control early in fact I would say most legged robots try to act like they're in torque control
when their leg is in contact with the ground and in position control when they're swinging
and then torque control so they do their best to emulate both
okay if you have torque control and you have an exceptionally good model of your robot
those two things go well together so this is a part of the answer to your question so
our mathematical models of our robot at the level of torque in motion out you know given by newton's
equations if we can control torque then we can do things like gravity compensation
so let me actually pause that and tell you what I'm saying
that shows here I think it would be easier for me to stay on this board I guess
so let's talk robot equations okay so the dynamics of our robot whether it's that robot or atlas
the physics of our robot are basically f equals ma right but we're going to do better than that
so I say f equals ma is my starting point the particular shape of the forces that we get from
gravity and the way we think about we can write out this term for robots that are in the canonical
manipulator form this set of equations will take on something that will be familiar to you by the
end of the class a slightly more general or I would say it's more specific actually but it's a
a more tailored version of those equations specifically for our robot case for our rigid
body systems multi-body systems
so this
is ma okay and this
is our forces but let me break it down to be clear so we think of this as the mass matrix
for the inertial matrix
okay we should say the q is the
vector of positions generalized positions
let's say positions for now
you like the grounding mechanics you know the generalized positions
q dot is the velocity
q dot is the acceleration
so
we're all for a robot like this these are all joint positions joint velocities joint accelerations
okay now why do I say those terms together this is a coriolis matrix
so
those terms go together to make up the mass times acceleration
it would take a longer time maybe to fully convince you of that but
but those two go those are those are the the inertial effects okay and this is my force due
to gravity my force due to gravity
and this after the view taking it as my controlling force
so if you were to take a free body diagram for the kuka or for atlas and you would turn the crank
on f equals ma or your electron gene mechanics you would get out something that you could write
in this form now what is gravity compensation okay so gravity compensation is basically
i'm going to choose u to be negative pow g in the simplest form it's just this
so that means you have a model of your robot you know the lengths the masses the inertial
even potentially the friction sometimes the gravity cap also tries to cancel out the friction
okay and your goal is to basically make your robot act as if it's in you know
increase on the issers it's taking gravity out of the picture
yeah are they measuring you or are they measuring the entire right hand side it's subtle it's super
subtle right so the question was is when i have the torque sensors are they measuring you or they're
measuring the entire right side we're going to actually derive when we get to the force control
part we're going to see the stiffness controller because yeah it's way subtle it's a mixture and
for a good reason and yeah but that's a great question
okay so so if i were to have gravity compensation and also i should really call it gravity and
friction compensation because you might also have additional forces here due to joint friction
okay and you'd like to cancel those out too i won't write them all on the board okay
but these demos of gravity count are kind of like how you strut your stuff if you've got a force
controller and you want to say like i've got a good model of my robot i've got a good force controller
then the demo you do to make people ooh and ah is you you put it in gravity count mode and you make
it look like it's not there right that's success and so that so that's what i was showing here
ah come on
sorry for those of you following along just click again
okay so you know you're in space or something and someone just pushes you
the robot has a lot of friction in its joints it's got a lot of inertia he shouldn't be able
to push it with his pinky his pinky right this is you know you can even see him smiling you know
this is this is how you show off when you've got really good torque control right
okay so again that's that's not just good torque control that's also a good model of your robot
because you need to know what torques to apply
all right so now torque control plus good model is the longer answer to your question of how does
that make me do better against contact okay
so um let me i'm going to just cartoon the idea of we're going to do the
the real derivation once we have more tools but i think i can get the basic idea enough
to realize why we fixed you out here
so stiffness control is roughly let's say gravity plus inertia plus the force
okay so stiffness control is roughly let's say gravity and friction
compensation approximately plus the pid controller
the simplification bugs me a little bit but but i think it's still the right way to
talk about it here so um so let's think about even in our simple example here okay so
i draw my pendulum again i've got gravity pulling down on me mass okay i'm trying to go to the
horizontal so um remember i said that the pid control was error driven yeah
all right are you talking about the pid position error or the torque error?
ah good this is for pid position control
so when we talked about pid position control only you know trying to regulate this we said
it was an error driven controller the gains had to be high and then i would have an integral term
that took out the slot okay most of that was just trying to compensate for this gravity term that
we didn't know about okay if i add in an extra term that just removes the gravity portion then
what that effectively lets me do is turn the gain way down on my pid control okay this is the longer
answer to the question right is that um i can even i can even show it so let's think about this as a
as our equations of motion of our pendulum are super easy especially if i think about it in
steady state at steady state i must have a torque being applied here that has to balance
mdr in order for those to be in balance right if i say i'm going to apply that
i'm going to find that torque with just p control
and that
that in order to derive this
to be a small error i need to choose kp and kb to be large
if i instead choose for my controller
i have to be a little realistic i don't know the mass exactly i'm going to approximate it
gravity i can pretty much say i know exactly i'll say that's not approximated i use the path
as an estimate
let's say i just put in a gravity term that i expect to be happening and then my
a e
a b term
now if m and l are spot on and that's just going to cancel out this term the only work this has
to do is if there's some unexpected disturbance in the world okay but my mathematical model that
those that those should do no work i didn't it's out of the zero so the only thing i have to respond
to is not the friction in the joints the gravity i'm restricting i'm targeting my feedback just to
the unexpected things in the world as a result i can choose these things to be much lower
and that matters in practice right so there's demos that we have done that i even showed you
before that you know i always think of the the dish when we open the dish rack or the dish
washer door okay like we don't know exactly where that door is we kind of approximated it we pulled
it down you know if we if we were just a little bit off and we you know we pulled it down it's
got some constraint here and then we even shove the thing from the top okay if we didn't use a
low stiffness control mode for that we would have been highly dependent on the accuracy of that of
all those transformations if we weren't exactly dead on and we didn't carve out exactly the right
curvature in our arm then that wouldn't that demonstration wouldn't have worked okay the
position controlled robots have a much harder time dealing with any of the uncertainty or tolerances
okay in the from the world you know this we just make it kind of soft and squishy and if it's i
would be surprised if we were very close to the desired trajectory i would guess that the hand
being in the um you know in the slot there as we execute that i should try to make a plot i would
guess that we were pretty far off our originally intended trajectory because it was then letting
itself bend to the will of the dishwasher tool right so for me force control and having a good
model can dramatically change the way you interact with the environment you can do like you can get
incredible performance out of a position control loop and you can make a torque a great high
bandwidth torque control loop like a position control loop you know mathematically you can
you can do anything sort of you can make one look like the other all of these details become in the
quality of the signal that you're measuring the bandwidth of your controller you know it's all
the details that make one of those better or worse than the other any questions on that
oops okay so um let's think a little bit about how we actually um model some of this stuff so
maybe i i convinced you that there's at least a little bit more going on the sort of gravity
comm there's a pid control maybe going on okay so when i go to give you an abstraction which is
this robot station which has an ewa it has a hand we didn't bound in time we didn't or i didn't want
to break off in the elevator there's cameras around we're giving you some abstraction but
the details under there are not just the physics of the arm they're also the control cabinet and
all the other stuff okay so we have concepts for all of these things in the system's way of thinking
okay
okay so the f equals ma are the manipulator equations
okay we do think of that as a mathematical model that takes torques in and has positions
and velocities out okay you know in break is called multibody plant
term plant comes from controls weird but we all know and love it okay and because it's a
many-body system so we are leveraging all of the structure that you get from recursive equations
of motion and the like okay you can make multi-body plants of all of your robots very easily right
the multi-body plants are such a common thing to simulate that there are description formats
that you just basically find on the web a description format for your favorite robot
this is the this is the one for the ewa it's in xml format this is the sdf is one of the robot
description files and you just type in you know where the what are the inertial properties you
know what are the meshes that define it you know what are the material properties of those meshes
the relative transforms between the different links and there's just text files that will
basically in which you almost never have to author because you can just download when you're
building your own robot you author the file okay but for for the robot itself you tend to just find
those okay the suppliers the robot makers will supply those files at this point okay and you
can just parse that directly into the multi-body plant okay and that will do that you'll do that a
little bit if you go through the chapter notes so that gives you this you know this first system now
the multi-body plant can be used in many different possible ways the one we're talking about here is
the actuation input port which we're thinking of as tau and we're getting
continuous state out is q and q dot okay but as you can see you can get reaction forces out you
can get contact forces out you can apply disturbance forces in there's it's a general physics engine
sitting inside okay but the way we the first pass that we'll take the simplest version of modeling
the controller box is going to happen in a few steps so we're going to have this inverse dynamics
controller here which is an approximation of that stiffness controller
okay so what does inverse dynamics do i already have the equations
we'll go through this in more detail when the time comes but i can i just want to give you the
sense today
so given those manipulator equations there's two canonical problems with them
sense the A. So given those modulator equations,
there's two canonical problems with them.
One is the forward dynamics, which
is given q, q dot, q u, output q double dot.
There's the inverse dynamics.
Given q, q dot, q double dot, tell me what u I need
to apply to achieve that acceleration.
Yes?
Is there a difference in what is the difference
between a forward kinematics and a reverse kinematics?
No, that's great.
So we're going to do forward kinematics and the like too.
I think in both cases, well, the notion of an inverse problem
is common in lots of different domains.
So the only thing that's, I would say,
different about the inverse kinematics in the sense
is that I think of the forward kinematics as being very easy
and the inverse kinematics as being potentially
under-specified or whatever.
In this case, somewhat oddly, the forward dynamics
is actually a little bit harder.
Well, it's in the simple case where
you have enough actuators, one actuator for every joint,
then actually the inverse dynamics is easier.
I can just plug in my terms on this side
and just get u out.
The forward dynamics, ironically, I actually
have to at least have to take an inverse of this matrix, which
is more expensive.
The forward dynamics is what you need for marching a simulation
forward.
There are many reasons to think of it
as the more essential dynamic quantity,
and this is more of a control quantity.
But you're going to see those connections.
Good question.
And I don't know if I repeated the question,
but the question was, are there similarities between forward
and inverse dynamics?
You can yell at me immediately if you want.
I'm doing better.
OK.
So the inverse dynamics controller
takes in an estimated state and a desired state.
So it's actually going to--
requires that information to come in
to know where the robot is actually in,
what state it's currently in in order
to compute these quantities.
You also pass in q and q dot desired.
OK.
And then there's also a desired acceleration,
an optional player acceleration.
If you read the fine print, this inverse dynamics controller
is actually doing a little bit more than just computing
the inverse dynamics.
It's also closing a PID loop on this,
so it's doing something like our stiffness control inside it.
Even inside here, if we were to open it up,
we'd see a couple of different layers of complexity inside it.
OK.
And then still from here, I have to get all the way out.
All I actually send to my EWA is a desired condition.
OK.
So there's even another step here, which if I step out,
I have to somehow model the way that this control
box is taking a stream of position commands,
differentiating it, inferring from a stream of position
commands of an intended velocity also.
And it's this state interpolator through this creeper.
OK, so I would say this is still a relatively coarse level
of fidelity.
We're getting super high quality simulation of that robot.
You can go in finer detail.
You can talk about exact control rates.
You can talk about encoder counts.
You can talk about quantized this and that.
This one has served well.
At some point, this is a good enough model of the robot
that the stuff you're bumping into in the world
dominates my lack of modeling of the encoder counts.
But I actually think you can do better
without watching too much work.
And I really mean it to be another example of this idea
of somehow that we're encapsulating this as this is
just the physics part of the manipulation station diagram.
There's also the cameras and other things
that are all mocked inside there with proper simulations.
What's the QD outside and the QD inside different?
One is position, one is torque?
They're the same.
In fact, so this system, it actually
just passes through the desired position, takes a derivative,
and turns it into both position and velocity,
which is our best guess at the first level of implementation.
It's our simple model of what we think is happening inside.
This would not be a great model of a much stiffer position
controlled robot.
This is something that is more unique.
And in particular, I get to pick the gains
to be much lower in these controllers
in order to model that robot complying to the dishwasher.
I'd say the other reason we picked EWA
is because it doesn't break.
And that really matters.
It just really always works.
We've blown a fuse once or twice,
but you just go to the hardware store
and get a new fuse, roughly.
And it is a luxury to work on a robot.
I worked on walking robots often that I built myself,
which always broke.
And then, I mean, Boston Dynamics robots
didn't break very much.
But still, to have this almost never break
is really pretty cool, especially if we're
doing class projects on it.
Of course.
So to find the gains for the controller in simulation,
do you have to do a lot of experiments on the hardware
to ID those gains?
So that's a great question, which I will repeat.
How do you find the gains in simulation?
The first point is actually, because we
don't model the extra details, the gains in simulation
tend to be different than the gains in reality.
So that is one of the places where I think
Sim2Real is not happening.
We carry two sets of gains.
And yes, we tune them separately to get a--
you can do it through a full system identification.
We tend to approximate it and get pretty close
with some round numbers.
That's a great question.
Any other questions on torque sensing and control
or why we picked Evo?
OK.
I also made the point that physics
is a piece of simulation.
And we didn't even simulate cameras or anything yet
or sensors.
But simulation really is a lot bigger than just
having a physics engine.
OK, let's talk about robot hands.
I've got some fun robot hands here.
This is what I think of when I think of robot hands.
I think of the fully dexterous hand.
This is an Allegro.
This is the shadow hand.
They're always holding light bulbs or something fragile.
An apple is a common--
a lot of glamour shots with robot hands holding apples
for some reason.
OK, but you don't see as many robots using those hands
as you'd like.
Allegro is starting to get more popular, I would say.
But as beautiful as they are, they
are bigger than you might think, first of all.
The shadow hand is actually pretty close
to human form factor.
The Allegro hand is bigger than the human hand.
They're not as wonderfully dexterous as the human hand
yet, and they break a lot.
Unlike this, these things break a lot.
I actually think if you've seen this open AI finger
gating example, if you talk to the people who did that,
or I think even said it in the articles,
but that's a shadow hand.
I think they spent--
I mean, they banged on that hand.
They were doing reinforcement learning hours and hours
a day on that hand.
And I think there was a lot of work
trying to make that hand more robust enough
to survive the experiments.
It was a major engineering effort to keep that hand going.
And there's an argument that you don't need it.
So here's the argument.
I think you could go to the toy store
and buy one of these things for $1.99 or whatever.
And if I asked you to do some really impressive thing
in the home, like fold my laundry or something
like that, I bet you could do a pretty good job
with those little grippers.
So I think, of course, having a fully dexterous hand
would be enabling.
But if you've got good software up here,
I think you can probably do pretty well
with a pretty simple hand.
So that has taken--
there's a different camp, I would say,
in the robotics manipulation world, which
does the simple hand version of this.
This is a famous video of the PR2
when it was just being born.
And it's being tele-opt in this video.
So this is a long time ago now.
But it was just like, OK, two-finger gripper.
This robot can do anything you want in the home, basically.
This would be a totally useful robot in the home,
despite having relatively simple kinematics and especially
very simple hands.
There's a whole series of these videos.
They're like getting beer out of the fridge
and all the things that you want.
So the Shunk WSG, which is what we picked here--
it's right here.
You can put whatever fingers you want on it.
You'll see us using lots of different fingers
and lots of different applications.
But it's sort of the IWA equivalent
of the two-finger grippers.
So you can get two-finger grippers at the Toy Store
for $1 or whatever.
You can spend $15,000 on this.
And you get force control, basically.
And an incredible amount of logic,
which is hard to simulate, that will squeeze until it thinks
it shouldn't squeeze anymore and not overheat
and do a lot of clever things, which are sometimes--
you wish it would just do the linear equation.
But it's been a very good hand in terms of a high-quality hand.
It's the luxury two-finger gripper, I guess.
But I'd say most of the story we took from the IWA
is also the same reason here.
Maybe we needed a little less here.
I don't know if we're getting as many benefits of force control
when we squeeze our fingers together.
I brought a few other hands.
And Danny, who's in the other side, has the Sandia hand.
So we actually have a bunch of robot hands around the lab.
Many of them were on Atlas at one point.
We were trying lots of different hands.
And we learned a lot about robustness of hands
by trying to have a 400-pound humanoid pick up lumber and stuff
like this and occasionally fall down
because your walking algorithm is still in development.
And you land on your hand, and that's not
what they want you to do.
It voids your warranty instantly.
So pretty much every cable on any one of these hands has been broken.
And despite having this beautiful dexterous Sandia hand that actually
has cameras in its palm, we ended up doing most of the competition
with this Robotique, the one in the bottom corner
here, which is a Robotique three-finger gripper.
In fact, the one Danny has with her is battle scars.
It looks like it survived a nuclear war
because I think Atlas did fall on it in the competition, unfortunately.
But there's a lot of great hands out there.
This is a very clever one.
It's underactuated in the sense that it's got clever four-bar linkages.
And when you just close the hand like this,
whatever object it happens to be coming into contact with,
it will close its hand around that object
without knowing what the object is, just using the clever four-bar linkage
mechanics of the hand, which is super, super good.
This is the iHiHand, which is a collaboration between iRobot
and Harvard and Yale.
It was similarly underactuated and cable-driven, nice and light
and good, although we did get stuck carrying a 2x4 for a long time
because we snapped the cable.
It was a really bad day.
There's also some things that don't look anything like a human hand.
So this is one of my favorite extreme examples,
which is one of the jamming grippers.
So it's a bag of coffee beans, roughly.
You put it on the end of a hand with some suction on one end.
And when there's no suction, no pressure, the coffee beans move around
and it's just this flexible hand.
But then when you suck, you get a jamming effect on the granular media.
And basically, it will retain its shape, even jam onto the objects.
And this little jamming gripper can pick up pretty much anything.
And they picked up all-- I mean, really impressive-- eggs.
See?
See apples and eggs.
So I think there's something to be said that maybe we're overly fascinated
with the human hand and we should just be willing to explore more.
I mean, there's a lot of people now using suction in applications,
which I think makes total sense for a lot of applications.
OK.
There's also a variety of soft hands, which,
depending on which boutique lectures we end up with,
we might talk about some soft hands and the like.
This is-- these are like gelatinous fingers, right?
That use changes in pressure to do roughly the OpenAI--
and this is obviously a play on the OpenAI demo.
But you can see all skills are executed without any sensory feedback.
So there's really an argument-- oh, I didn't
know they actually directly head-to-head themselves
with the OpenAI in the video.
But there are some beautifully clever soft hands
that can do a surprising number of dexterous things.
Now, I think there's still a debate about how far we're
going to get with those fully squishy soft hands.
Like, it might be hard to button my shirt or some-- you know,
dress shirt or something like this.
I think there's probably things that it wouldn't be very good for yet.
But probably the evolution of hands will be something
like those kind of soft things and the fully dexterous things.
We'll see.
This is a soft two-finger gripper that was done at TRI.
It's got big bubble sensors and the big bubble grippers.
So-- but one of the great things about it is it's got cameras behind
the gripper and these dot patterns.
They used to be depth cameras.
Now they're even just RGB cameras.
And so you can see through the skin and basically get
some tactile sensing back also.
That's an evolution of a lot of important ideas
that I will talk about.
But we're starting from gel-site and gel-slim.
And there's a lot of related work that I'll tell you about.
But-- OK, wait a second.
So I have to set this up.
Best robot video ever.
Maybe.
But certainly one of my-- when I get asked,
like, you're at a robot conference
and you have to write your favorite robot on your name tag,
right, to this icebreaker.
I always say this robot, OK?
This is a normal robot hand where they basically
took all the safeties off and overclocked the motors,
like, just beyond reason.
And they did the same thing with these gimbal-based cameras
to track things, OK?
And this is like--
probably the robot smokes if it's
run for more than a minute.
But they do just incredible things with this robot.
OK, here we go.
Dribbling, right?
And spinning.
OK, here we go.
It's also, like, giving us the finger at the same time.
[LAUGHTER]
I hope the best one's at the end of the video.
That one's pretty good.
Let me see if I can get ahead.
[LAUGHTER]
Whoa.
Yeah, I'm going to skip ahead to my favorite.
Let's throw a cell phone up and catch it just like that.
Whoa.
That's the best one.
So I think, you know, who knows if our hands are
going to be like that in the future.
But it's nice to dream.
Cool.
That was what I wanted to discuss today.
Any other questions?
That's the Ishikawa group.
Yeah, I think I almost certainly referenced it in the notes.
I love that hand.
I think-- so I met some of the people that worked on it.
And I don't think they caught the phone very often.
You know, like, that was a pretty good shot.
But the hardware is just awesome.
But the hard work was awesome.