[SIDE CONVERSATION]
All right, welcome back, everybody.
We'll get started.
So today is the sort of second day of manipulation
with clutter, a.k.a.
bin picking.
There's a couple of different terms I've used for it.
Let me just make sure to put the roadmap up again, just
so we remember why we're doing what we're doing.
So we started with basically a single known object,
assuming we knew the pose.
We advanced to a single known object with an unknown pose.
And we spent some time thinking about geometric approaches
for pose estimation, with point cloud registration,
iterative closest point, for instance.
And what we've been graduating to now
is trying to do many diverse, potentially unknown objects
with unknown poses.
But while that could encompass the rest of manipulation,
we're doing a relatively simple version of that
and looking at a case where you can get a lot done
without knowing a lot about what the objects are, effectively.
So this clutter clearing task is this sort of nice task
that I showed you last time, where you kind of pick up
anything from one bin, put it in the other bin,
and that turns out to be a great way
to sort of feed the data pipeline when
we want to start generating lots of random instances,
lots of random picks, and start doing
more learning-based manipulation.
So the problem for today is you've
got a camera, but a depth camera.
So it's both RGB and depth available.
You're looking down into a box of stuff.
And it's got Cheez-Its and Spam cans and mustard bottles
and all the great things you find in the YCB data set.
The question is, where should you grab?
And that's what we're going to talk a lot about today
is we're going to talk a bit about grasp analysis, grasp
selection, our basic strategy, how do you get it
from point clouds.
And we'll go into some details.
But let me just, since I ended a bit before I meant to last time,
and I'm not going to go into details,
but I just want to sort of make sure
that the roadmap from last time was clear.
We talked about a couple of different ways for--
well, I tried to show you that we're doing more advanced
simulation now, and we need to understand our simulator
a little bit better.
If you get yourself into weird situations,
I hope I gave you a little bit of intuition
about the complexity that lies underneath.
But there's a few parameters, like the time step
or the stiffness of your contacts,
that can have a big effect on how accurately you simulate
or how fast you simulate.
There's also a bunch of subtleties, like the fact
that we use extra collision geometries.
For instance, if we represent a box,
we actually drop in a few extra spheres
for our collision geometries.
I've written this all up in the notes.
And you've been working on it on your problem set.
I've given some examples here.
But the key idea I was trying to get to there
was that we're going to start our simulation
in some initial conditions.
We've got a bunch of random objects and random poses.
What is the defining feature of that initial condition?
Well, everything's still.
So that puts some pretty strong priors
on where the objects could possibly be.
If I've generated a bunch of random objects,
there's only a subset of possible configurations
that are viable initial conditions, where
everything is at rest.
You can write down with your free body diagrams
the conditions for finding an equilibrium where
the forces balance on all of the objects.
It would imply that everything is at rest.
And that's the kind of thing you're
going to do on the problem set.
One of the key ideas there is this friction cone.
So we have contact frames.
And we have a friction cone.
I drew two different friction cones
in this particular picture.
And I hope all the simple versions of the equations
are in the notes for this example.
So you can imagine writing a small optimization,
saying, OK, I'll take some random initial poses.
They might have some penetration.
They might be floating in space.
And I'll solve an optimization problem, which solves
for the static equilibrium.
I like this very much.
I think that should be the right way to sort of bring
an initial guess that is not a viable initial condition
into alignment with the viable initial conditions.
That's a beautiful way to think about it.
And no one does it.
And it makes me very sad.
I don't do it.
And it makes me very, very sad.
And the reason is that the optimization problems, when
things start in deep penetration,
have all the problems that we've talked
about with the collision geometries and strange normals
flipping signs and things like this.
It's a very ugly, very bad optimization problem.
So you'll get local minima where objects are still
stuck inside each other.
And they're-- it will--
SNOPT will fail to solve.
So instead, what we do is we just start things clearly out
of penetration by just staggering them vertically.
We run our simulator, wait till everything settles.
It's like, it makes me really sad that we do that.
But I mean, OK, so what's the positive spin on that?
The physics engines are solving optimization problems also,
right, but are just highly optimized.
They're solving these things very, very fast.
But they've optimized the case where things are not
in deep penetration.
And staying out of penetration, everything is clean and good.
And you can use your physics engine to advance time
and get pretty quickly to a steady state solution.
Pulling yourself out of penetration
is just the hard version of the problem.
And I think for our optimization, for SNOPT,
for instance, to compete with the simulator,
you'd have to bring loads of all these clever optimizations
that the simulation people have done.
Even though they're solving sometimes the wrong problem,
they're just forward simulating and waiting till it settles.
And you could say, just go straight to the equilibrium.
The advantage that you get from just
having all these super highly optimized codes,
SNOPT isn't competing with yet.
I think we'll slowly bring more of them into SNOPT
and eventually be able to do these kind of things.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK, so the question was, why do we even
want static equilibrium as an-- I
guess I'm thinking that we're walking up to the sink.
Things probably aren't moving.
The initial conditions, in my mind, of the world
have settled at some times.
And so there's a set of equilibrium.
There's probably nothing floating
in the air that's still falling.
There's nothing sliding.
It's already slid.
So I think the reasonable initial conditions
of walking up to a sink and you start to pick
are things that have already settled.
And so the question is just, how do you
find the already settled configurations,
the viable physical configurations,
as well as possible?
Good.
Good question.
Is that clear?
The problem with this approach, of course,
is that it works for clutter clearing.
But I think I said it in the notes.
If you were trying to populate random kitchens,
you probably don't just drop refrigerators and toasters
and stuff from the sky and hope they land in reasonable places.
When your scene has more context, more structure,
then this approach doesn't work.
And then I think that's where the optimization-based
approaches can somehow take some prior of, for instance,
like toasters tend to be on the table and other things,
some initial guess, and then lock it in with physics.
OK.
So that was a bunch of talk about simulation
and how we get here.
But now we're here.
We've got our image.
We've got our point cloud.
And I want to talk today about how
do we start deciding what to do in that point cloud.
Where do we pick?
OK, this is the Springer Handbook of Robotics.
It's pretty big, second edition.
It's awesome.
It's a really good resource.
And it's all online, so you don't
have to carry around the big book.
But it's a really, really good resource.
So on page 955, there's an amazingly good chapter
on grasping.
And it has pictures like this, what
I'm showing on the screen here.
That's figure two, I guess, from that chapter.
And there's just this huge wealth
of literature on grasp analysis and grasp optimization.
And it dominated manipulation for many years.
And we're spending relatively little time on it
in this class.
I almost feel like it's sacrilegious.
OK, sorry.
But here's the thing.
So this was done in a different time,
I mean, with a different set of objectives,
where the assumptions were that you
knew a lot about the object.
You potentially knew a lot about your hand.
And you had to optimize against torque limits in your fingers,
things like this.
And there's a lot of good things to know in there.
We're going to use some of them over and over again.
For instance, if you wanted to evaluate
the largest possible wrench, if someone were to come up
and pull something out of your object,
what's the largest possible wrench
that someone could pull on the object such
that you stay inside your torque limits,
and therefore inside your friction limits,
and you can sort of say you'll resist a wrench?
These are the kind of optimizations
that you'll find in this book.
And they're really good.
But they assume a lot about your hand,
knowing a lot about your hand, which is probably OK.
But well, even that, I mean, I think
we don't really have torque sources in our fingers
most of the time.
We have little itty bitty actuators
on cables that are kind of not perfectly modeled.
But it also just assumes a lot about the geometry
of the object, the mass properties of the object,
the friction properties of the object.
So there's been, I think, along with the deep learning
revolution and the geometric depth camera revolution,
there's been a change in the basic formulations.
So we don't think quite as-- we use a lot of the tools
from this.
But I think we're going to try to do it
in a slightly more messy situation.
So there was this sort of wave of new results
that came in a handful of years ago.
These are 2016, 2017, 2018 kind of dates.
And they just, I think, did a really nice job
of sort of turning the problem statement on its head.
All three of those were powered by deep learning.
But I think more important than the way they solved it first,
it was just changing the problem specification, where it really
was more like this clutter clearing.
This is the first one that I spent time
understanding by Rob Platt.
They all sort of came out in similar times.
But this was a very big surprising thing.
I mean, it was not the way people typically
formulated grasp problems, where you really just
dumped random objects.
You don't know what they are.
I mean, we've been saying this for clutter clearing.
But this was a new thing then.
And it was very interesting to ask,
how do you take some of the stuff from the handbook
and apply it to a problem like that?
And the basic story in most of these papers
is that you learn from a map from the depth
cloud about where to grasp.
Or typically, you will learn a grasp evaluator,
basically, where you say, if I were to grab here,
what score do I expect to get?
But this was cool.
This was like the first time we saw
robots sort of manipulating random objects like ropes.
I mean, there's a couple objects here that were intentionally
like, ah, you've never seen a robot really
manipulate a rope before or a cord before.
And so when we started thinking more about this
and watched this revolution, I think deep learning gave us
the sort of the bold--
the ability to sort of push beyond what we had originally
done.
It was sort of like confidence, I guess.
Deep learning gave us the confidence.
But I don't think it actually--
I think people underestimate how well the geometric tools still
work on those problems.
So as we're going to transition from--
this is our lecture from transitioning
from the geometric methods to the deep methods,
let's spend a little bit more time
with point clouds and geometry to do this task.
The reason I want to do that is--
this is another one.
This was from a local--
well, I guess Andy Zeng was the first author
on all the visual parts of the perception parts.
But this was an effort along with Alberto's lab
here at MIT, M3.
Did I pick a really boring part of the video to start?
Yeah, I guess.
But OK, they're talking through this idea
that you take RGB images, you learn basically good places
to suck.
OK, this is suction, sorry.
Right.
OK, but Lucas was in lab at the time,
and he spent time thinking about what--
do we actually need deep learning
for this kind of things?
This was when we weren't sure how well deep learning was
really working.
And so he implemented this system,
which was based on not--
no deep learning, just geometry alone.
And the basic strategy we're going to cover here
is about looking for antipodal grasps, which
I will tell you about.
And basically just looking for a good place to grasp
based on the geometry of the scene.
And this does pretty darn well.
Like it achieved rates pretty similar.
There's limitations.
There's things that the deep learning approaches can do
that this cannot do.
And we'll talk about those.
But this is the basic setup.
Let's do this geometry-based first.
OK.
Good.
So that was my little old and new background
on grasp analysis.
OK.
So let's start our basic strategy for grasp selection.
The basic strategy is going to be very simple.
I'm going to reach down, obtain a point cloud.
We have to clean it up a bit.
We're going to have multiple cameras looking at the scene
so that we can see from all sides of the object,
hopefully, roughly.
We're going to have to merge the point clouds,
crop the point clouds, estimate different quantities
on the point clouds.
OK.
Then we're going to look for antipodal grasps.
What's an antipodal grasp?
OK.
So I have some interestingly shaped object.
Anywhere along the object-- I have my colored chalk
here somewhere.
I left them here last time.
OK.
At any point on the surface of the object,
I can define sort of the normal to the surface
and the tangent to the surface.
Right?
OK.
And I can evaluate this in lots of places.
And what I want to do is find places
where I can put my hand around it.
That might be too big, depending on how big your hand is.
OK.
I'd like to find places to put my enormous hand.
That was a little bigger than I had in my head
when I started this.
But OK.
Enormous hand coming in.
OK.
I'd like to find places where the hand is going
to touch the object at two places
where the normals are pointing in opposite directions.
They're antipodal.
They're pointing in the opposite directions.
OK.
Now that might be not as true if I were to pick here and here.
Right?
If I picked here, I squeeze too hard,
it'll shoot out potentially out the side or whatever.
OK.
Idea of picking antipodal grasps is
going to be central to our thinking.
OK.
And importantly, we can start estimating antipodalness
based just right from the point cloud
without knowing exactly the object.
OK.
And then we're going to avoid collisions,
try to respect joint limits, et cetera.
OK.
This is going to be our strongest heuristic.
We're going to look down in the pile,
try to find a place where we can stick our hand around,
get a good antipodal grasp, and pick.
Yeah.
So for the antipodal normal vectors,
they have to point in opposite directions.
So do they all have to be collinear?
Yes.
Sorry.
Good.
So you'll see when we get there.
So we want them to be both antipodal and collinear.
Yes.
Because that's going to be embedded in our sampling
strategy, you'll see.
But yeah, we're going to actually,
when we find a normal, we're going to just penetrate
through directly and ask what the normal is
on the other side.
So it becomes for yes.
But we'd like the places where-- so if I had, let's see,
this and this, for instance, could be almost antipodal,
but they're not in the same line.
So that's no good to me as a grasp.
They need to be antipodal and along the same line.
Yes.
So in two-dimensional, it's clear that this always
exists, but in 3D, it's not possible to see that you can
always find an antipodal grasp on an object,
especially if you only have the object in 3D.
So the question is, in 3D, can you always
find an antipodal grasp on an object?
I don't know that there's any guarantee that you can always
find an antipodal grasp.
I think you'd like to find the most antipodal grasp.
That's the heuristic we're going to use.
Whether you can find something that's perfectly
antipodal, I don't think there's any guarantee.
Even in 2D, it's not clear that you always
find one collinear antipodal grasp in 2D, right?
[INAUDIBLE]
But it might not be collinear.
Like a star.
I'm trying to think of-- there's probably adversarial shapes
or something like this, right?
Yeah, I'm not saying that there is any guarantee
that a perfectly antipodal collinear grasp exists.
We're going to prefer grasps that are more antipodal.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Exactly.
Awesome.
So if my hand was not enormous, if I
had a little hand coming in here,
this would be no good to me, right?
So we're going to bring that in through asking
for-- to try to find these kind of possible grasps
and find one that, if I were to put my hand there,
it's not going to be in collision with the object
already, so that when I squeeze, I'll be outside the object.
[INAUDIBLE]
Do you have to continuously solve for the optimum ones?
Because I think they want to start
coming into contact with the object.
The object might itself start changing shape
like a star or something like that.
Awesome.
OK, so the question is, are we sort
of updating our antipodal estimations on the fly?
OK, because like squishy objects,
they might change their normals as you grab them.
So here's the dirty sort of secret of manipulation,
is that all the grasp analysis, like this entire book-- well,
not-- just the manipulation chapters of the handbook,
right?
They analyze the system when it's already making contact.
The dynamics of going from out of contact to in contact,
we pretty much just kind of go like this
and hope for the best, right?
People do use simulation to try to--
so one grasp metric that people like
is actually to train a deep learning system, for instance.
You might pick up a thing at a certain point on the point
cloud, and then lift it up and shake it,
and then just see if it stayed in your hand.
That's like a way to sort of test,
and if that gives you some score,
and then you train whether that worked or not.
But in general, the grasp analysis
has always been about statics and not about dynamics,
because the coming into contact dynamics is very complicated.
We know how to simulate it.
We don't know as much how to optimize through it.
Yeah?
Are we only looking for the antipodal grasp
on the context of the object?
Or can I also get them on the normal point
and then use those?
So this is-- so the question would
be like, if I had an hourglass, for instance, right?
If I found those, that might not be a very good grasp
candidate, right?
I think that was sort of your implication, maybe.
It was the question was, are we looking only
for the concave antipodal grasps?
Yeah, I was going to say the normal [INAUDIBLE]
on the hourglass, or I could [INAUDIBLE]
Let's go through that.
OK, so we're going to try to define the normals.
I mean, so you could say that the normals could
be pointing in or pointing out.
We're going to always try to have them pointing out.
And the curvature does tell us something, right?
And we are going to be able to estimate the curvature very
easily, or from the point clauses directly, right?
But I haven't included it.
The heuristics, the examples I've given you in the notes
are a fairly simple grasp strategy,
but they don't involve any notion
of the curvature in the score.
This kind of a grasp would be ruled out more
by the collision again.
So these two together get you pretty far.
These are great.
I love the questions.
So please keep chiming in.
OK, so let's see.
Back before deep learning, if you
were doing image processing, there
was sort of a library of things that you would
learn how to do with images.
You could find edges in images.
You could expand blobs to try to find regions of similar color.
There's sort of a library of image processing techniques.
They still exist.
They didn't disappear, but they're not as necessary now,
because we just pattern match everything.
There's a similar library of things
you can do with point clouds.
There's no books on them, unfortunately,
but there's documentation for the software.
The PCL library's documentation is extremely good.
And I feel sort of sad that there's not
like a point cloud processing book that I know of.
But I pointed to the few references that I know.
But there's lots of good things you can do with point clouds.
And we're going to do--
I'll step you through a few of them.
Some of them are natural, but they're
going to be very important here.
So in general, let me just even set this up.
So this notebook here, I've got a hairy mustard bottle.
Let me make it less hairy for a second here.
Good, so I've set this up where I
have the initial point clouds.
I have three cameras.
This is the same situation I gave you before.
It's three cameras around the mustard bottle.
So those cameras see--
they're going to see the mustard bottle.
They're going to see the bin.
If I put it in the bin, they see the other cameras.
I get returns from the first camera looking this way that
gets off all of these different objects.
There's another camera over here that
sees that side of the object.
And there's another camera.
See, that's point cloud one and point cloud two.
So altogether, I've got three pretty good views
of the objects.
But I need to do some basic processing,
get rid of these junk outside.
I'll crop them, merge them, estimate normals on them,
down sample them.
Sort of reasonable operations.
I think the most interesting one is
the normal estimation because you get local curvature
information from that too.
But there's a basic library of these things.
So cropping a point cloud is pretty reasonable.
If I've got a bunch of x, y, z points,
I tend to put a bounding box.
If you think I'm going to reach into a bin
or I'm looking at the top of the table,
then just making a bounding box in the frame
to get the points of interest to rule out the cameras.
Very simple operation and essential.
I'll write them down and we'll go
through the normal estimation a little bit more carefully.
But we can estimate the normals, which
is what I showed with the vectors
here that looks like a crazy pin cushion thing.
That's a normal estimation.
At every surface point here, there's
a vector coming off showing the local normals of the point
cloud.
Say a bit about that.
We can take those three separate point clouds
and merge them into a single point cloud,
some fusion operation.
And we can down sample.
Now, before we dig into each of them,
let me just say that I've chosen to do them
in this order for a reason.
I think the order does matter.
It's cropping.
Just get rid of the extra points you
know you don't need right away.
But the normal estimation should come before down sampling,
for instance, because you're going
to try to use as many points as possible
to try to estimate those normals.
You get the densest point cloud you can deal with.
It will give you more accurate normals.
But the normal estimation also is
going to come before the merging the point clouds.
Anybody know why I want to do the normal estimation before?
[INAUDIBLE]
So she says, so you can merge similar normals better
together.
That's pretty much what I want to say.
There's a twist on it that matters, I guess.
I mean, we talked about it before, too, when we said,
you lose some information when you go from the depth
image to the point cloud.
As soon as I've merged the point clouds together
into one big cloud, then I've kind of implicitly forgotten
where my cameras were, or I don't know which ones--
which corresponded to which camera.
So in this question that Alex was asking here--
so I'm getting some returns here.
I have a question of which of these is my normal?
Is it the one pointing in?
Is it pointing out?
How do you robustly find the point cloud,
the normal pointing out?
My camera's coming this way.
In all these point cloud libraries,
there's a flip normals towards camera,
where you basically say, here's my camera position.
Here's my list of normals.
Flip them so they're all pointing towards the camera.
So I can do that on the unmerged point clouds
and get my normals pointing in the right direction.
Then I'll merge them together, which in general can
be a fusion operator, like the point cloud,
the iterative closest point type algorithm.
And then we'll use voxels for downsampling.
Let me tell you a little bit about normal estimation.
So how do we get those porcupine normals out
of a dense point cloud?
[WRITING ON BOARD]
In broad strokes, we're going to find the k-nearest neighbor
for every point, let me say, for every pixel,
every point, find the k-nearest neighbors.
You can put a max distance so you don't find--
if you don't have k local nearest neighbors,
you don't end up including somebody too far away.
We're going to fit a plane similar to what
you did in the ransack problem to the local point cloud.
And then flip the normals.
We're going to be able to get out-- the way we fit the plane,
we're going to be able to get out the curvature too.
It's pretty elegant.
But finding the k-nearest neighbors,
let me even show you what that looks like here.
I've got a-- hopefully my thing is still alive here.
For those of you watching the slides.com,
I'm sorry, I'm going to flip to--
you might want to flip to just the video
stream for a second here.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
I spent a ridiculous-- you guys wouldn't
know what I go through with some of these, but let's see.
I almost have DeepNote working for everything.
By tonight, I think I will have everything
ported to DeepNote.
Open3D, which I was using for some of the point cloud
processing, doesn't work.
The versions that we use doesn't work on Mac 3.--
Python greater than 3.7.
But everything else is using Python 3.9 on Mac.
And it's on, on, on.
Anyways, I'm running it from Colab today.
But tonight, everything will be good again.
Nice.
Let's see if I can get a new tunnel without--
it's encouraging.
[END PLAYBACK]
You only get two tunnels.
So if this one doesn't work, I'm dead.
But I'll have to restart Colab.
Two free tunnels, and then you have to pay for ngrok.
And I can't pay for ngrok on Colab.
I don't mind paying.
I just don't know how to do it on the cloud,
where my IP address is different every time.
So this is roughly what I want you to see here.
My normal estimation-- it's very hard to see in this.
Let's see if I can make that bigger.
And I tried to make it brighter, but the old meshcat
won't let me.
[AUDIO OUT]
You can kind of see this, what's going on there.
There's a blue line there, a red line there.
Yeah, that's my triad sitting there.
So I pick a sample point.
And I've got a little GUI for you here,
where you can just literally just change
which pixel am I centered on.
And there's a lot of pixels, 10,000 some,
or 15,000 pixels in the mustard bottle point cloud.
And for each pixel, I'll just use that
and find the k nearest neighbor.
That's going to give me the blue region.
I'll only pick one that's not inside another blue region
on the French's label.
And there you go.
So I'm going to pick a handful of nearest neighbors.
I'm going to fit a plane to that, take the z-axis to be
the--
we're going to see the math for how to do that,
to find the z-axis.
And actually, we're going to draw the other two axes
of the frame along the dimensions of relatively
maximum and secondary curvature.
Now, what's amazing to me about this--
and I remember when we first started
doing a lot more of this.
I was like, surely you're not going
to go through every single point of a dense point cloud,
take every k nearest neighbor, fit a plane,
and then go to the next point for 15,000 points
in a real-time perception algorithm.
And my students who were doing that at the time
were like, no, it's fine.
And I was just wrong.
I think that people do that, and people do it all the time.
And that was a few years ago.
And now computers are even faster, more parallel.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
It seems expensive.
I agree.
But it's in this--
computers are fast.
[LAUGHTER]
So people do this all the time.
It's a standard pre-processing step
where you go through your even dense point cloud.
In fact, dense is recommended because--
I mean, you could choose to evaluate it
as a subset of the points.
But you'd like to find dense nearest neighbors
to get a more accurate representation
of the local curvature.
So I've done it for the entire thing
and drawn most of the normals.
And in general, I would say that is a theme,
that people do pretty significant processing
on the point clouds.
And it's faster than you'd think, than I would think.
[INAUDIBLE]
It is true.
So the point was about the k-nearest neighbor.
So the k-nearest neighbor uses typically
FLAN, which is a fast lookup.
I don't know, approximate nearest neighbor.
But it's a common library that people
use in robotics for fast nearest neighbor lookups.
And yes, I think having very good data structures
for very fast approximate nearest neighbor queries
is essential to making this work.
No question.
So how do you fit a plane to a local point cloud?
If you've got a bunch of points-- now,
what I want you to see, at least at broad strokes,
is that this looks like the optimizations we were already
doing.
And there's some geometry about that problem
that I think will help you understand how you
can get the curvature out, too.
Let me just step through that one.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
OK.
I've got a bunch of points.
I'd like to fit a local normal.
And I'll do that by sort of fitting
a local plane to my points.
The normal I'm going to write here.
I'm going to ask the normal to have magnitude 1.
And I'm going to define the plane in terms
of the normal and the point at which the point P--
let me draw here-- the normal plus the point
can define that local plane.
So what I want to do is now search for n and P
in order to maximize the fit of these points.
So the distance from any sample point to the plane
I can write with a dot product.
So I'll take a dot product between the vector here.
I've got some vector.
This is Pi.
This is my P. So I'll write Pi minus P here.
And the distance from the point to the plane
is the dot product of this vector with this vector.
So I drew that small.
Is that clear?
I could make it bigger if it's helpful.
Dot product gives me this distance,
which is the distance from the point to the plane.
So I'll take this vector and I'll dot product with n.
So that gives me a scalar number.
I want to minimize the magnitude of this number.
So if I were to just take this and say minimize that,
it would drive me to very big negative numbers.
So I'm going to take the squared of this
and sum over all of my points.
And I'd like to minimize over P and n, subject to a constraint
that n equals 1.
This looks scary.
It turns out that it has a nice solution.
The reason it has a nice solution
is that you can actually solve for P as a function--
the optimal P as a function of n,
just like we did in the other point cloud processing
algorithms.
It's not surprising that the strategy
will be pretty similar.
Bless you.
[WRITING]
I went through it in the notes before,
but not on the board before.
I don't know if people want or don't want this.
I'll subject it to you this time and you can tell me after.
So the way you try to optimize a constrained optimization
is you write the Lagrangian.
You bring the constraint in to the optimization.
So I can write the Lagrangian, which
is my original cost function.
If this is foreign to you, try to appreciate it
at a higher level.
And it's written up in the notes.
So this is my original objective.
I'm going to write plus a Lagrange multiplier times
my constraint, which I could write
a handful of different ways.
I'll write it like that.
It's called the Lagrangian of the constrained optimization.
The amazing thing about Lagrange multipliers
is that if I take the gradient of this Lagrangian--
so this is called the Lagrange multiplier.
That one I think you've seen in various capacities.
But it turns out that the optimal solution
of the constrained problem is going
to be a stationary point of this problem, which
means the gradients of this with respect to the parameters
and with respect to the Lagrange multipliers
are going to have to be 0.
So that was a long way to say if I
were to take the gradient of this with respect to p,
at an optimal, it's going to be 0.
So I can write the gradient of that with respect to p.
Let me expand.
It's a little bit-- you've got to get your head around that,
this thing being squared.
But I'll write it out completely in transpose pi minus p.
And these terms don't depend on p.
So partial L, partial p, it gets to looking like this,
minus 2n, n transpose.
I'm going to write the transpose of it just
to keep it looking a little bit more friendly.
It looks like this.
This is just a quadratic form.
It looks a little scary, but it just looks like that.
OK, this has special structure because n is unit magnitude.
But mostly, the thing that it implies for me
is that if I want this to be equal to 0,
then the sum of these has to be equal to 0.
Sort of a simple version of it.
And p star equals 1 over n sum over i pi.
There's a few steps there, but it gives you
roughly what you'd expect from the original--
the same thing we saw in the point cloud--
or in the point registration problem
where the optimal p is like your average p.
I think geometrically, that's not surprising.
And it comes through an optimization.
And the steps are also in the notes, I hope.
You don't have to write everything down
if you're worried about it.
OK, if I substitute this back in,
then I can write the entire optimization.
I can solve away p.
I can write the entire optimization now in terms of n.
And it just looks like this, where
W is our data matrix, just like we did before.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
OK, I actually don't care as much.
I don't care as much about the algebra steps.
I want you to understand the intuition here.
Is that this optimization is now a quadratic form in n.
So if I were to plot the 2D version of it, I had n1 and n2.
W is this symmetric quadratic form.
It's going to be a convex objective.
So I'm going to have the level sets of W of x transpose W
is looking like this.
So this is n transpose Wn equals 3.
This is equals 2.
So this is my quadratic bowl I had before.
OK, and it goes through the origin,
despite my artwork not being great.
I also have the unit circle constraint.
This is the n equals 1.
So now, what's the optimal solution?
Where is the optimum for this problem?
I'm trying to minimize this objective
where I've drawn the level sets.
It's 0 if n was 0.
It's going up.
It has to live on this equality constraint.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
This tangent or this tangent?
The second one, right?
So that is an optimal point.
That's inside the lower level set.
It's the lowest level set that touches the constraint.
It's also at this one.
Again, artwork, that should be touching there too
if I was a better artist.
So there's two equally good normals.
They're just the opposite of each other, a sine flip away
from each other.
And that's exactly what we're-- that's
the into the object and out of the object
would fit the plane just as well.
So this corresponds with one of the eigenvalues
of the optimization.
And this other direction here, actually, is a second.
This is the eigenvector corresponding
to the eigenvalue.
Eigenvector 2 corresponding to eigenvalue 2.
So which one's the bigger eigenvalue?
Which one's the bigger eigenvalue?
This one?
This one.
This should be the smallest eigenvalue.
It's like twisting, right?
For a unit length here, I get a smaller number there.
The cool thing is that I have these other directions here.
This is actually the steepest descent.
So this is the place where the cost function
is largest, this vector along here.
And if I did it in 3D, I have two other eigenvectors
that are corresponding to two other eigenvalues.
The larger eigenvalues correspond to a larger value
here, which corresponds with a larger dot
product with the points.
So let me see.
So if I had a point that were along some local curvature,
and I'm trying to fit a plane to it,
then there's a vector that goes through this point, which
fits these points with the highest possible dot product.
The largest eigenvalue should go with the place
of lowest curvature.
The smallest eigenvalue is going to be my normal.
And the middle eigenvalue is going
to be my other normal-- because the eigenvectors are going
to make an orthonormal matrix, the third eigenvector
is going to give me my last row of middle curvature.
So it actually parametrizes the surface
in terms of it ordered by the directions of curvature.
So some of the grasp heuristics-- this
gets to Alex's question earlier--
do use local curvature.
They might find a place that has a good antipodal grasp,
but is also curved in.
That's an easy thing to now include in your grasp
heuristics.
Now, I did do this real-time estimate.
I realized when I typed it in-- so every once in a while,
you'll find a point that doesn't obey the right-hand rule.
You could still get an improper rotation
if you just take the eigenvectors.
So that's my bad.
I'll fix that, too.
But if you just took the eigenvectors out
of your random eigenvector algorithm,
there's no reason that they would
be ordered in a way that would obey the right-hand rule.
So you have to sort of check for improper rotations
and flip them and other things.
And that will be happening in this notebook shortly.
I apologize.
I forgot to do it.
The things you notice right before lecture.
So that's pretty cool, right?
Local point processing, little optimization,
solved in closed form just by taking eigenvectors
and eigenvalues.
Gives me normals, gives me local curvature,
fast enough to run on a whole dense point cloud.
It's part of your library, part of your toolkit.
Once we do that, merging the point clouds,
the next step is merging point clouds.
So if you have two-- think about the way
that these point clouds look, these partial point clouds.
So I'm going to flip back to this one.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[END PLAYBACK]
OK.
I've got two point clouds here.
Point cloud one, point cloud two.
How do I find their alignment?
How do I merge them into a single point cloud?
If I know my relative camera positions perfectly,
and I think the points are clean enough,
then you really can just add them together.
But in reality-- and so in simulation,
that's actually what I did.
In reality, you don't do that typically,
unless you've got really good camera calibration
and you have rules so that nobody leans on the cameras.
And you can always tell a theorist
when they come near a robot, because they're like,
lean on your cameras.
You're like, I just spent an hour calibrating that.
So I like theorists, but I just don't like
when they bump my camera.
OK.
So in general, we already have the tools
for estimating these, to find these things into alignment.
So if I have point clouds that overlap in some capacity,
I can just run a point registration algorithm.
ICP is sort of the right tool for taking
these almost aligned point clouds
and snapping them into place, or ICP and its variants.
So the full version of merging point clouds
is really just running a point registration algorithm.
We talked about it before as having
an object-specific point cloud.
You can do it on the dense point cloud that
has lots of objects.
There's no reason.
You're just doing-- it's also called scan matching.
You just bring two scans into alignment.
Good.
And then downsampling is the last big step.
And this is really just a simple algorithm.
And the question is really, what's
the right data structures that enabled this to be fast?
And the right data structures tend to be voxel grids.
So you're going to tile your space with a bunch of cubes,
cubes of a certain fixed size typically,
and just fill your space with a whole grid of these cubes.
We'll use good data structures so that we only represent
the cubes we're actually using.
We don't actually enumerate all of the cubes.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: When you're doing the point cloud merging
with the ICP, does it matter which point cloud
you use as the target point cloud?
Good question.
So in the ICP, we specified the model versus the scene points.
Now I've just got two scene points roughly.
Doesn't matter which one you calibrate to.
I mean, the math should be symmetric.
So you should be able to either translate camera 2
into camera 1's frame, camera 1 into camera 2's frame.
So up to the heuristics, when you
start doing nearest neighbor--
there's places where you break that symmetry
in the optimization with some of the tricks we used.
But the basic operation is roughly symmetric.
Yeah?
So voxelization is sort of the standard strategy
for downsampling your point cloud.
If I wanted to now run it into a more expensive grasp selection
algorithm, I probably don't want to carry on 15,000 points
in my point cloud.
So I'm going to take my sort of a representative 1,000 of them,
let's say, or 100 of them.
The way that people do that is they
will break the space up into little cubes, voxels,
take all of the points that land inside the voxel,
and summarize them with a single point.
The cheap way to do it is you put a point--
if there's any points inside the voxel,
you just use the middle of the voxel
as your point in the point cloud.
If your voxels are small enough, that's fine.
A slightly more expensive one that they did in PCL--
I don't think they do it in Open3D--
is that you just take-- of all the points
inside that little voxel, you take the centroid.
Just a little bit marginally more expensive,
but it gives you slightly better down sampled points out.
But roughly, collapse all of the points in some small volume
into one point.
That's a natural way to sort of down sample.
This is a version with the voxels being pretty darn big
and kept the color code from there.
But you can make your voxels pretty small.
And they use sparse data structures.
And you can get arbitrarily good reproductions
of your original as the resolution gets down.
OK?
I want to make sure that there's no hole on the--
There's no guarantees of watertight.
So the question was, are there going to be any holes?
Most of these things do not guarantee watertightness
or anything like that.
You will often-- like, for instance,
the bottom of the mustard bottle is always going to be empty.
So it's always going to look hollow in that sense.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes, so good.
So typically, you'll average the normals, too.
So if you have to take all those points,
and you just take an average of the normals.
Even the people that just keep the centroid
will average the normals.
Yeah.
Because it doesn't make sense to do anything else.
Cool.
Let me flip back to this.
OK, so putting this together, we've
got our local estimating normals and local curvature.
Now, how are we going to use all that information
to score a grasp candidate?
OK, I made a little GUI.
But let me tell you my rough-- my coarse approximation,
sort of simplified version of the heuristics people use,
which is going to take my hand.
OK?
[WRITING]
It's got my mustard bottle here.
OK, I'm going to first crop the point cloud.
I'm going to move the point cloud into the hand frame.
[WRITING]
You can apply those rigid transforms
on the dense point clouds.
It's efficient enough.
OK?
And then I'm going to crop all the points that
are not between the fingers.
[WRITING]
OK, so I'm just going to take-- I
want to only consider points sort of in that region.
So I'll just crop my point cloud down
to just being that region.
OK?
And then each of those points has
a normal associated with it.
I'm going to score the grasp as being good
by summing up the component of the normal that
is aligned with my hand, aligned with the x-axis of my--
I forget which axis it is.
But basically taking a dot product with the line
here and trying to reward points that contribute
a normal close to this vector.
The more points you get, the more reward you get.
And for each point, you get more reward
if you're aligned with the normal.
That's not a super special magic.
This is the best thing to do.
This is just one of the heuristics people use out
there for antipodal grasping.
You can invent your own.
You'll find cases where this one does something you don't like.
And you might tweak it.
I don't have a magically better optimal solution for you.
OK, but I do have a cool GUI for you, which I hope runs here.
OK, here's my cameras and my bins,
my hand with magic glowing point clouds that are the ones that
survived my cropping.
Let me see if I can orient this a little better.
You see what's happening there?
And I have sliders so you can move the hand around
and evaluate your score.
OK, so this is a cost negative 39.97.
That's pretty good.
I don't want to play with this in front of you.
I want you to play with it.
It's in the notebook, right?
So what happened there is I went down a little too far.
And the top of the mustard bottle
is intersecting with the geometry of the hand.
So I got an infinite cost.
Gripper is colliding with the point cloud.
But you can lift up, check out your costs,
check out your normals.
You can roll the hand around.
And putting those basic point cloud operations together
gives you something that you can evaluate quickly at runtime
and give you some geometric heuristic for how good
that grasp is going to be.
So why is that antipodal a good heuristic?
I think-- oh, please.
For that first step where we move the point cloud
to gripper frame, we do have to make a choice of where
we're going to put the gripper with respect to-- do we just
like search a bunch and--
Good.
So my setup so far here is we talked
about point cloud processing.
And then this is scoring grasp candidates.
So I'm telling you where the hand is.
You give me a number.
The next step is going to be how do you find a good one.
And that's where you start making those choices.
So it's not surprising that the antipodal
would be good from just trying to make good contact.
But why do you want to make good contact?
I think there is an important lesson
that you should have from the handbook of robotics.
So if I'm making contact at these points
as I'm about to squeeze, then the contact I have
is going to produce some amount of friction.
It's going to give me a friction cone.
Each of these places, it'll be attached to that normal.
I had to pick to draw next to the finger.
But when it collides, that friction cone
will be at the side of the bottle.
The other thing I have is I have a gravity vector.
Or maybe adversarially I have somebody pulling on the bottle
and trying to get it out of my hands.
But let's just say we have a gravity vector.
Now to get static equilibrium, as you're
doing your problem set, you have to find a vector
inside these friction cones such that everything's
in equilibrium.
So those two forces have to equal and opposite balance
in order to have equilibrium.
The horizontal components and the vertical components
has to be enough just to cancel out gravity.
So you need that friction cone to be big enough
and tilted away from gravity.
So you can imagine other heuristics too.
In fact, I do put a heuristic saying your hand shouldn't
be too tilted because you'd like to have
your normals oriented horizontally there.
But that's the picture.
These forces have to fight this gravity that's
trying to pull it out of your hand.
So the bigger the friction cone, the better off you are.
Having antipodal grasps, potentially with curvature,
gives you more-- it's kind of a subtle argument.
It gives you more friction because you're
going to have more surface contact in the object.
So you imagine that actually changing your friction cone.
And that will resist a bigger wrench.
That's the thought process.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: How do you actually know what the friction cone is?
PROFESSOR: You don't.
Good question.
So how do you know what the friction cone is?
You say 0.8.
Roughly.
No, no.
That's just being silly.
But I think it is not something that you
know with high accuracy.
And I think that is a place where
some of the original works that were very model-based,
you would say, I have a detailed model of my hand.
And that's very fragile.
So it's safe to underestimate your friction cone.
But picking a number and going with it
is sort of the strategy.
The antipodal grasps don't actually
use the coefficient of friction anywhere.
They just say, between two things that are equal,
pick the one that is likely to have a bigger friction, better
surface contact, and therefore a better friction cone.
So it doesn't have any explicit dependence on the number that
is your friction.
It's a good question.
So I think assuming you know the friction
is a bad assumption, typically.
OK, so now the question is, I have a scoring function.
I have an objective.
How do I pick where my hand should be?
We said non-penetration constraints
are difficult optimization constraints.
We could use SNOP to get stuck sometimes.
This one is a very hard optimization
with all these point clouds in the middle and everything
like that.
So we don't hand this one to SNOP.
We just sample a bunch of candidates,
and we take the best.
It's partly because the SNOP formulation
would be very hard in terms of the solver would get stuck.
It'd have lots of local minima.
It's also because we have pretty good heuristics for where
to sample.
We can use our geometry intuition
to pick reasonable sampling heuristics.
So the one that I use in the notebook
there is going to be-- I'm going to take an arbitrary point,
take its normal, align the hand.
I'm going to sample a grasp.
It could be a grasp at any orientation, which
puts the finger's normal in alignment
with the normal coming off the bottle,
and just backed off by some amount.
Then I'm going to shoot through.
This is the question about collinear.
I'm actually going to do a raycast operation, effectively.
Find the normal that's directly on the other side of it,
and ask, can I basically-- actually, that's not true.
What I ended up doing in the notes,
because Open3D didn't have raycast,
was I just put the hand here.
I just picked this number arbitrarily, put the hand here,
and then did that evaluation of cropping the point cloud
and asking how good my score is.
And am I in collision?
So I'm going to just pick a point at random in my point
cloud, pick a grasp where my thumb is a little bit away
from that, but aligned with that particular normal,
and just pick a bunch of grasps like that, rotating just
around in that one axis around that normal.
And I'll just go through and pick a bunch of them.
And I'll take the best five, or something like this.
How many did I keep?
I drew a handful of them.
That was a bad--
, OK.
Each time, I don't know why it was disconnecting,
but I threw a bunch of random bins in the--
lots of objects in the bin.
I ran my little sampling strategy like this,
kept the best handful, and you get typically
a pretty diverse set of interesting grasps.
Yeah, see?
And then you just pick the best one, for instance.
I drew the best end, but typically, you
pick the best one.
Yes?
So when you're doing the sampling procedures,
is there any utility on maybe doing
a handful of gradient descent steps on your best candidate?
Or is it just trying to like, [INAUDIBLE]??
It's a good question.
The question is, is there any utility?
I said the optimization problem is hard.
Why not do at least a local optimization
after you've sampled?
I think the question is just how to shove that data, what data
to shove into the optimizer.
I think it'd be great to try.
People, I think, typically don't.
But I would like it.
OK, so this gets you pretty far.
So roughly, reach down, find the antipodal grasps,
avoid collisions, reject anything that has a collision,
keep the best one, grab, pick it up,
and drop it off at the other side.
That gets pretty far in clutter clearing.
What can't it do?
I hope you'll play around with those notebooks.
There are limits, I think, really,
sort of fundamental limits to the geometric-only version
of it.
It really doesn't have any sense of what an object is.
And we'll rewind that here.
So one of the things it does, for instance,
is it will do these double picks.
Sorry that the angle's not good there.
But there were two boxes with the sides
like happened to be lined up.
There's absolutely no way that it
can understand that those are two objects.
Just geometrically, it just doesn't have that concept.
So you could train a system that would understand
that those things should be separate objects
and should not be picked together.
But the geometry doesn't tell you it.
There's something more you have, some more information
you have.
Another common case would be like you pick up a hammer.
I think this is Rachel's research.
You pick up a hammer, right, or an eraser here.
And by my grasp candidate, this is just as good of a place
to pick up as this.
There's no concept of object anywhere in the scene.
So the notion that the center of mass
would be a good place to pick it up
doesn't exist anywhere in this metric.
I have just as good of a chance of picking it up here.
And then I've got a big torque that's
trying to wrench it out of my hand.
And that's just missing from this formulation.
Partial views.
So I do think that there's some opportunity for a deep learning
sort of approach to learn, having picked things up,
basically what the backside of an object looks like.
If I had a point cloud that was only coming from this side,
the geometry alone, the instantaneous geometry alone,
doesn't tell me anything about the backside.
And it would limit my ability to try to take a grasp
on something I can't see.
There's nothing I said here about hallucinating normals
in places where you don't have them.
But if I trained and picked things up and dropped it,
you could potentially learn something
that sort of hallucinated the backside of objects.
People do-- explicitly, there's a whole field
of sort of shape completion that you
could do with a neural network.
But this is doing it sort of implicitly.
If you just say, find good places
to grasp on these point clouds, you
might be able to find something that sort of does
a little bit of shape completion for you.
Another reason-- another limitation of this
would be the fact that we talked about our limitations of just
the point cloud sensors.
If you're fully dependent on point clouds
and you want to pick up a transparent bottle,
you're going to be sad.
So RGB-based methods are going to work better for that.
But overall, this is a pretty effective strategy.
It really can move a lot of different things out of the way
and feed your data--
feed your data pipeline.
I will say that when we started implementing this
and tried to make it useful, there
are a bunch of corner cases that you have to start dealing with.
So big shunk hand getting into the corners of the bins
is bad news.
It just doesn't-- or there's kinematic limitations
of the arm that come into play.
I separated now good positions from the hand.
I didn't actually think of the kinematic limitations
of the arms.
So in practice, things would have a way of--
the remote control would always get in the bottom back corner.
So if you watch that clutter clearing video,
again, you'll see that there's extra little things that
will try to brush things out of the corner into the center.
And then it'll flip back to the antipodal grasp.
But if you layer a few of those pretty simple, very general
point cloud-based operations together,
then you get a pretty darn good system.
Any other questions about that?
Yeah?
Just to clarify, the collision detection
does not just take the collision onto objects.
It's going to grasp it for other objects.
Awesome.
So the question is about the collision detection.
So we have collision geometry, simple collision geometries
of the gripper, maybe of the bins,
maybe of the cameras.
So we want those to not collide.
But we also want the points in the point cloud
to not collide with the geometry.
Now, if you had noisy point clouds,
you'd have to probably threshold that and allow
a little bit of collision.
But in general, I'm actually collision-checking
the point cloud with the closed-form geometry of the hand.
So if there's any points inside my simple geometry collision.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes, there's no notion of--
so that's exactly right.
So I think if you were to think about grasp selection one
object at a time, you would get a very different answer
than what's a good grasp given you're sticking
this thing in clutter.
Because the places where you can actually grab
are very highly constrained by the objects that are around it.
And those collisions are essential to take into account.
So there is no objectness here.
It's just the big pile of points that
may be one or more objects that I should not collide with.
[AUDIO OUT]
Good.