I guess I didn't take off all the relative advertising things, but we'll have some funny
background.
Okay, good.
Hey, welcome everybody.
Thank you for coming.
Some of you I haven't seen, but I'm glad you're here.
Yes, so this is how it's going to roll.
I'm going to just mostly rifle through.
I think that'll keep us, I mean, we have a lot of great presentations to see.
It'll take us about the hour and a half, maybe a little bit over.
We have the room until five if we need it.
I want to leave space for questions, especially if you're here and you want to stand up real
quick if your video starts playing and people know that there's a chance to ask questions
right afterwards, we can do that.
But mostly I'm just going to sit and enjoy it with you.
So they're going to go right down the order from the spreadsheet, only the public ones,
as we said.
Please let me know if there's any audio or technical difficulties.
And remember to fill out your subject evaluation.
So okay, here we go.
Let the show begin.
Hi, everyone.
For my final project, I made a robot that can handwrite letters.
I chose this problem because handwriting is a universal skill, but it's something a lot
of people take for granted.
But having a robot that can handwrite actually increases accessibility.
It can save time and it can even be used in an educational setting, as we see on the right
here.
This image comes from a really interesting paper from the Georgia Institute of Technology
showing the usefulness of learning from demonstration.
For my specific implementation of this handwriting robot, I'm using the Ewa robot and the Shunk
Gripper hand to represent a pencil.
I have a cylinder in the image on the right, that's the object in yellow, and the writing
surface is going to be this big purple wall.
The pencil is actually welded to the robot's hand to simplify the problem a little bit.
Given this setup, the robot is presented with a string and then its task is to write that
string on the wall.
Here we have a couple pictures of the starting position.
The bulk of my project came with the motion planning, creating a trajectory for the robot
to undertake given the string.
I'll let this video, one example of the robot writing a string play while I talk about my
implementation.
So I actually created a list of key poses for each English letter, spaces and periods
that rely on the position of the previous character to determine the poses of the new
character.
I then used Drake's linear interpolation tool to create a trajectory based on these key
poses.
It might seem like curves are hard given that I'm using linear interpolation, so I actually
used a parametric ellipse equation and took sections of that to be able to create curves.
To render this text after it's written on the wall, I used matplotlib, which has a nice
collection of lines functions.
So I can check whether or not to render a line by seeing if one pose and the next pose
are both in sufficient contact with the wall, knowing that if they are, linear interpolation
would mean that the line connecting them should be rendered.
I can then use that to choose what to render and get these nice images on the right.
The bottom text is actually what the robot wrote in the video we just watched.
For future work, I could possibly extend my robot to be explicitly used in education,
perhaps waiting for a student to write a character after it demos it.
I could also use machine learning to switch from a static implementation of characters
to a new framework where the robot is able to teach itself characters.
Thanks for a great semester.
Awesome.
I don't see Isabella here, but I learned that I need to make it easier for you guys to get
rid of those stupid bins.
I apologize for that.
Everybody's got these bins that are completely irrelevant to their task and their simulation.
Sorry for that.
Yeah.
So, I mean, a little bit more, but it won't be as much as you think.
Right?
That's how slides.com rolls.
Yeah.
Good question.
Okay.
Here we go.
And somehow my auto-play is not...
Hi everyone.
My name is Sung Ho Yeon.
My final project is about playing piano with a robotic hand.
I hope you enjoy the presentation.
As an introduction, I want to present my result of the project first.
In this demonstration, the robot is playing the classic piano song, "Salute to Amour."
[music]
For the rest of the presentation, I will give you a very brief overview about the project.
The goal of this project is to manipulate the robot to play the piano based on the music
sheet input.
It is roughly consists of three major blocks, offline planning, dynamic simulation, and
sound generation.
While all three blocks are developed and implemented, this project has a strong emphasis on exploring
practical offline motion planning strategy.
Instead of covering all the details, I will highlight a few interesting points in this
project.
In constructing robot arm on Drake for simulation, I attached Allegro robot hand on Kuka Iwa
arm on Drake.
As a result, I got 23 degree of freedom robot arm shown in the center.
The virtual piano model is also constructed with a door hinge type of rotational joint
on Drake.
This is a brief summary of the offline trajectory planner.
Given the music sheet input, the trajectory planner generates time domain joint space
trajectories through finger key correspondence matching and inverse kinematics.
In order to find finger key correspondence, I formulate a simple heuristic optimization
algorithm where the correspondence is chosen by minimizing the sum of corresponding finger
key distance.
This approach is largely inspired from the point cloud key point registration approach
in ICP algorithm.
With chosen finger key correspondence, I formulated the inverse kinematics problem to find feasible
trajectories of the robot for pressing desired keys and moving from a chord to another chord.
The slide shows a simplified formulation of these inverse kinematics problems.
To describe an important formulation in pressing keys, I used fingers positions and orientations
as constraint for desired key contacts as well as palms clearance from piano for avoiding
undesired collision.
For contact mode switching, I used a simple heuristic such that I planned the contact
mode of each finger in offline planning phase and used that information to control the torque
gain of each finger depends on the desired contact state of them.
Through this project, what I really want to show is that even with very basic building
blocks of robotics, proper integration of these blocks would enable the robot to do
many wonderful things.
Thank you.
I don't mean to single you out, but he's right here if you want to, everybody wants to throw
a question at him.
Yeah.
[inaudible]
I'm the microphone, so I have to pass my...
It picks up for me when I walk, so I'm going to have to pass myself around.
Robust stacking of convex polytopes.
Robust object stacking is application in a variety of industrial settings.
Games such as Bandu demonstrate the human ability to perform stable stacking even with
challenging constraints and irregular objects.
Here's the static equilibrium problem formulation.
The main constraints are force balance, torque balance, and linear complementarity.
It is straightforward to set up a mathematical program to optimize most of these variables.
The hard part is developing a differentiable model of contact, which involves parameterizing
the contact points and non-penetration constraint.
To understand how our contact model works, let us introduce this scenario with two blocks,
one in free space and one above the table.
We treat the contact points as decision variables and initialize them inside the objects.
The four contact points are shown in red.
We also initialize separating hyperplanes.
We then jointly optimize over the contact points, hyperplanes, positions, and forces,
and show an example of the optimization process.
The blocks are now in static equilibrium.
Having written a complete set of constraints for static equilibrium, we perform the optimization
using the SNOPT solver and it converges.
We initialize the blocks in the equilibrium state and perform forward simulation.
The blocks fall over.
What went wrong?
Surprisingly, solving the static equilibrium problem as formulated resulted in an unstable
solution for nearly half of our trials, stacking just two cuboids.
The problem is that unstable static equilibria are admitted in our constraints.
When the blocks are initialized in unstable static equilibrium, numerical issues may result
in imperfect balance and tower collapse.
In practice, though, the solutions the solver finds are actually small perturbations from
static equilibria due to constraint relaxations.
These are not equilibria at all.
To resolve this issue, we consider the addition of an external torque robustness constraint.
Instead of solving for a single equilibrium, we solve for multiple instances of static
equilibrium problem.
Each instance shares object poses and hyperplanes, but has separate forces and witness points
to compensate for a different torque applied to each body.
We find that this formulation converges for 95% of two block stacking trials and all solutions
are stable during forward simulation.
This animation visualizes the witness points optimized to balance an external torque perturbation
of 4 Nm.
We apply four perturbations, one on each axis, to avoid unstable edge cases.
You can see the witness points spread out in a diamond around the center witness point,
which solves for the static case.
Previously, we showed results where we started close to the correct solution and solved locally
for equilibrium.
This strategy won't allow us to be able to automatically generate many novel towers because
we have to solve for each correct initialization by hand.
What if we want to automatically generate diverse towers, as seen on the right?
We could sample initializations uniformly.
However, we find that this never succeeds when there is more than one block.
To scale tower generation, we instead sample from smarter distributions.
Our strategies include sampling non-penetrating object poses and sampling contact points inside
the polytopes.
Now we show the optimization process.
Here are five generated structures.
We can see there's a reasonable amount of diversity, especially in the bottom two blocks.
Finally we show results for two additional convex shapes.
And we can see that the first two blocks didn't compute.
So this is a very good example of how we can optimize our model.
[INAUDIBLE]
Nice work.
To the people watching online, I'm sorry.
I will not get perfect audio from the middle of the room.
Yeah, it would be ridiculous.
For our final project, Nick and I investigated the task of uni- and bimanual use of a power
drill.
We were struck by the ability of humans to easily bimanually manipulate objects, which
may introduce coupled or contact instability.
The task of using a power drill is especially interesting, as instability may arise for
several different reasons.
Touching on a drill generates destabilizing torques.
Grasping the drill with both hands creates a closed kinematic chain, which may introduce
coupled instability.
And the drill itself generates destabilizing torques of its own as it rotates.
In this work, the task was accomplished by superimposing several controllers.
An impedance controller regulated the gripper translation and rotation.
A null space projected joint impedance controller resolved the redundancy.
A feedforward torque compensated for the mass of the drill after it was picked up.
And a torque compensated for the gravity of the EWA itself.
The impedances were chosen to be in a range achievable by a relatively strong human, 1,000
newtons per meter translationally and 100 newton meters per radian rotationally.
Minimum jerk trajectories smoothly moved the nominal position of the gripper between waypoints.
These waypoints were specified relative to the drill.
Using this approach, the system was able to move into stable contact with the ground and
generate a contact force of 32 newtons.
In the bi-manual case, the exact same controller was used for the first EWA.
After the second EWA makes contact, the Z component of its impedance was set to zero.
In this case, the second EWA only adds impedance to stabilize the task.
This is the block diagram for our simulation.
While it may seem overwhelming, there are a few points of interest that we would like
to call attention to.
As you can see here, we used the standard inverse dynamics controllers for our two EWAs,
but set the PID gains for the position control to zero, making these act as gravity compensation.
Part of the reason we chose to have no position control in the inverse dynamics controllers
was to have impedance set by our main controller to let it vary.
In the EWA torque controller, we run our control scheme mentioned in a previous slide.
The EWA torque controller output combines with the gravity compensation in the adders,
which are then passed to the actuation of EWA1 and EWA2.
We also have gripper controllers that actuate the grippers, and functions that compute the
rigid transform of the forward kinematics of each EWA to allow for easier computation.
In order to simplify the task and make the simulation faster, we chose to simplify the
contact geometry of the drill to a few simple shapes, instead of using the mesh.
On the left, you can see the visual mesh of the drill, next to the simplified collision
model.
On the right, you can see the drill and collision geometry overlaid on top of each other, showing
the decent but not perfect approximation of the geometry.
The inertia properties of the drill were also estimated.
To prove that we didn't simply hard code all the positions, and to prove that the null
space projection works, here are two videos showing the unimanual task with different
initial drill positions and different nominal joint configurations.
Good.
Any questions?
It looks like you had a little bit of the null space dance happening there, right?
Do you think that's just tuning, or do you think that's-- is there something missing
in the formulation that's letting you wiggle a little bit on the null space?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
I think some of the ways that those things integrate through the system, through the
EWA controller that's there, I've seen those.
I think that's not just-- yeah.
I think those do pop up from some of the integration pipelines.
We wanted to actually keep them closed without adding null space to get the all the [INAUDIBLE]
I know a few people figured out that you had to turn off the stiffness of the controller
to do torque control.
And that's actually what you do on the real KUKA, too, because that's-- by default, it
wants to do both, and you have to just pretend that the position gains are zero to make it
work.
So that's great.
Great stuff.
OK.
Hi, everyone.
My name's Portia Gaethkel.
And my name is Julia Wyatt.
Our 6800 final project is a joint perception and manipulation system for multi-shaped peg
and hole tasks.
Our project is designed around a simple children's toy that we've all likely seen before, shown
on the left.
This is our system's representation of the same toy.
The task consists of recognizing differently shaped blocks and putting them together in
a single, single-piece.
The goal is to make the toy look like a toy, and to make it look like a toy.
So we're going to start with a simple toy.
And we're going to start with a simple toy.
>> Hi, everyone.
My name is Ben.
And I'm the lead developer for the robot.
And I'm going to be talking about how to use the robot.
So let's get started.
So first we're going to start by looking at the first step.
We're going to look at the first step.
And we're going to look at the first step.
So, this is a problem that we're going to look at.
This is a problem that we're going to look at.
>> Good morning.
I'm going to be talking about the first challenge.
The first challenge is object diversity.
The second challenge is partial observability.
The only observations are partial point clouds.
You must complete each scale in two seconds of simulator time.
The first challenge is to create a point cloud tree that updates state based on
incoming point cloud observations.
Our method processes the point cloud, uses the process point cloud to update
the state and behavior tree, calculates the desired joint positions using
inverse kinematics, and finally uses the PID controller to convert desired
joint positions to desired joint velocities.
We will now discuss how each of these steps are implemented for each scale.
The first challenge is to find the center point of the chair using the
principle components analysis.
We will now discuss how each of these steps are implemented for each scale.
The first challenge is to find the center point of the chair using the
principle components analysis.
We will now discuss how each of these steps are implemented for each scale.
The first challenge is to find the center point of the chair using the
principle components analysis.
We will now discuss how each of these steps are implemented for each scale.
Next, we discuss the details of our behavior tree for each task.
To open the drawer, we go to the pre-grasp, grasp, and pull all the way out.
We will re-grasp when the handle is lost from the gripper.
We can do a similar thing to open the door, but the time constraint limited
the number of intermediate gripper poses we could select, resulting in a
lower overall accuracy.
Once we open the door enough, we will use the body of the robot to push
the door open.
To push the chair, we go to the back of the chair and push it towards the
target.
But because the dynamic of the chair is unknown, we might push it to an
unwanted direction.
We do this reactively by actively measuring the center of the chair while
we go and nudging it towards the center while we close.
For moving the bucket, we also have two strategies.
The first is to pick the bucket up with using two bone scrappers.
The other is to hug the bucket.
While the picking one has a much higher accuracy, it cannot pick the bucket
if the rim is too thick.
So in our behavior tree, we check how thick is the bucket and decide which
strategy to go.
Here are our results.
As you can see, we vastly outperformed methods that learned from
demonstrations.
Contrary to the learning methods, our method has no discrepancy between the
testing and training scores.
This is evaluated by the challenge two weeks ago.
This is our latest result using Drake to solve inverse kinematics.
The next step would be to look into the failure cases and adjust the
behavior tree to account for those failures.
We're also interested in using these controllers in a task and motion
planning setting to achieve complex non-horizon goals.
As a first step to that, we've implemented our manipulation policy on a
real-world mobile-based robot.
Thank you for listening.
[ Applause ]
>> We're going to go a little bit further.
We're going to go a little bit further.
You're going to hear a little bit more about the challenge and the
manipulation.
So how does it differ from the challenge?
How does it differ from the challenge?
How do you make it different from the challenge?
I wasn't pulling for that one, but that's good.
All right.
>> Hello.
This is wiping bot.
This is an optimization-based surface wiping approach.
I'm Drake.
>> And I'm Nishant.
To start off, we want to convince you that wiping is both an
interesting and useful manipulation problem.
It's useful because it's a good way to get rid of dirt that's
against the surface and also because of the planning problem of
which order to wipe various dirt locations in.
Wiping is also very useful because it's among the top requested
services by users of robots.
And a very important component of cleaning.
Okay.
So let's start off by talking about our simulation setup.
For actually wiping in this project, we choose to weld a
sponge directly to our EWA.
To simulate dirt, we leverage Drake's mesh painter functionality,
which lets us update the texture of one object when it comes into
contact with another object, namely our sponge.
Now, we were only able to do this for our dirt on our table.
And so dirt on our plates still has a simple particle-based
representation.
Okay.
So now that we have the simulation setup, let's talk about
actuating the robot.
For wiping, in addition to a simple IK-based position
controller, what we need is a hybrid force position controller.
Our first attempt at designing this, we did a PD controller on
X, Y, and Z and output zero torque on RPY.
But this didn't work for seemingly obvious reasons in
hindsight.
So we decided to implement a PD controller on roll, pitch, and
yaw.
However, while this did better, it still didn't work because of
the circular difference property of angles.
So this makes a naive P controller on RPY bad.
So we settled for a simple D controller on RPY.
And this produces a great trajectory that keeps constant
force contact with the table, just like we need for wiping.
Now that we have a hybrid force position controller, we need to
generate a trajectory for our wiping motion.
We took four different approaches for generating this
trajectory, ranging from a naive approach to where we assume
that the dirt locations is just our trajectory.
So we'll go from dirt location one to two to three, to four, to
so on and so forth.
But as you can see, this may lead to unintelligent behavior
with respect to the displacement of the robot.
So we also formulated this problem via constraint
optimization problem, which tries to minimize the
displacement of the robot while also satisfying strict
constraints and threshold constraints with respect to the
dirt location.
Now that we have a simulation, a hybrid force position
controller, and a wiping trajectory that we want to move
along the table, we can now talk about our overall control
strategy.
How it works is from an initial configuration of a gripper, it
moves to a location on the table using pure position control.
When it's at that location, it then switches into our hybrid
force position controller, which moves along our wiping
trajectory that is given by our optimizer, while maintaining a
force in the Z direction that is weak enough to allow for moving
along the XY direction, while also strong enough to make sure
that our plate doesn't move when we're doing the wiping
motion.
To conclude the project, we set up a simulation in PyDrake in
order to simulate the table, the plate, the gripper, and the
dirt.
We also made a controller that uses pure position control for
navigating and hybrid position control for wiping.
And we generated trajectories via different optimization
approaches for our controller.
And then finally, we evaluated our trajectories on a set of
experiments.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> I think poor guy just left like a minute before I started
this video.
And I do know it's going to be four, so if people have to
leave, I understand.
But we're going to keep going.
>> Hi.
We are Alex, Pete, and Anand.
And we're the team that developed the first-ever
programmable method for certifiable collision-free
motion planning.
We introduced a system of 2D robot arms with three degrees
of freedom in total, depicted on the left, for which we can
visualize the configuration space.
The system consists of a one-link serial manipulator in
green and a two-link serial manipulator in red and blue,
surrounded by a bounding box.
On the right, you can see a rational parametrization of the
configuration space, where the red region contains all
configurations that are not in collision.
When we change the joint angles of the robot arms, the green
sphere moves to the corresponding location in
configuration space and changes its color to yellow when the
arms are in collision.
While sampling-based methods, like the rapidly exploring
random tree on the left and the probabilistic roadmap on the
right converge quickly for this example, the paths are
typically jerky and require post-processing.
More importantly, these methods require significantly more
samples and a non-trivial amount of parameter tuning when
scaling up to higher dimensions.
To get smooth paths, like from trajectory optimization, while
keeping probabilistic coverage, we focus our attention on
set-based methods instead of point-based methods.
The idea in the set-wise decomposition approach is to
clear entire regions as collision-free instead of only
individual samples and edges.
In our project, we use the Iris algorithm adopted for
configuration space to decompose the collision-free space into
convex polytopes.
In broad strokes, the algorithm starts off with a chosen seed
location and tries to grow the largest possible collision-free
polytope where its size is measured by the volume of the
maximal inscribed ellipse.
It does this using nonlinear programming.
This can be repeated for multiple seed points and the
resulting regions can then be used for collision-free motion
planning by solving a shortest path through graph of convex
sets problem.
There's a renewed interest in this formulation in the robot
locomotion group at MIT because of a recent breakthrough.
They had in solving these kinds of problems.
They kindly provided us with example implementations of both
Iris and the shortest path problem.
But due to the fact that we are using nonlinear programming
and the resulting formulation only provides locally separating
hyperplanes, not all generated regions are collision-free.
This in return can be exploited by the shortest path program,
which can lead to collisions.
We therefore need a method for identifying, violating, and
we now present the problem formulation we use in order to
certify when Iris regions are collision-free.
First, recall that two convex bodies are collision-free if and
only if there exists a separating hyperplane between them.
If we suppose that all of the collision bodies are convex
polytopes, we can pose the search for this hyperplane as an
SVM problem using quadratic programming.
However, we want to find a plane for all configurations in a
given region.
To do this, we start by constructing a plane for all
configurations in a given region.
To do this, we start by converting the trigonometric
functions defining the positions of each vertex into a rational
function using the stereographic projection.
We introduce two polynomials, a(t) and b(t), which will give
hyperplanes for different values of the configuration.
Therefore, we want to search for polynomials a(t) and b(t),
which satisfy these two inequalities for all t in the
Iris region c(t) less than or equal to d.
How does one do this?
The answer comes from Putner's positive Stellensatz, which
states that a polynomial p is positive on a set if and only
if it can be decomposed into polynomials s, which are all
sum of squares, summed with the set itself.
These polynomials are called multiplier polynomials.
This theorem gives the following program, which is a
sum of squares program.
SOS programs can be solved in polynomial time, and we exploit
this to search for the polytopes.
If the program finds a violation of the region, it is
not always obvious that we wish to discard it.
Violations can be fairly minor, and so we consider
slightly tightening the constraints, which corresponds
to shrinking the regions.
This minor adjustment to the previous program finds the
smallest tightening, which certifies the region.
Unfortunately, there's a bilinear between the
multipliers and epsilon, and so it is non-convex.
Therefore, we suggest alternating between searching
for the planes and multipliers and tightening the constraints.
Using this program on our simple example as before, we
have allowed our program to edit the original iris regions
to be guaranteed to be collision-free.
We show the separating hyperplanes between the active
links in this example.
The red plane separates the blue and the green links,
while the green plane separates the red and the green links.
While all these methods can be scaled up to realistic
examples, we note that planning through iris regions has the
advantage of generating smooth trajectories natively.
These trajectories are guaranteed to be collision-free
along the whole trajectory, rather than just the sample points.
Additionally, it requires less tuning of hyperparameters.
However, we note that this technique is not a cure-all,
as iris and the shortest path formulations are sensitive
to the seed points and the connectivity of the resulting regions.
Additionally, our current implementation of the certifier
is quite slow, limiting scaling, though we are confident
this can be fixed.
[applause]
We have to do quick questions at this point, but these guys are here.
Anybody have a quick question?
I have tons of questions, so I'm going to save mine until after.
[laughter]
Okay, I'm going to keep going.
Hi, I'm Andy Wing, and today I'll be presenting
the stacking plot.
Let's set the scene.
So I was thinking about what project to do, and I sort of
saw a p-set lying there, and I was like, well, wouldn't it be cool
if a robot could do a p-set for me?
I saw the door-opening p-set, and thought about it, and I was like,
well, that's not really possible.
So if we can't make something that college students can do,
what if we made something that babies can do?
Well, what do babies do?
They crawl around, they call, they cry out quite a bit,
they eat Legos.
So I went, okay, what if we made a robot that can build Legos,
that can assemble Lego structures?
Now the challenge was really just, how am I going to turn that thing
on the left, the stack of Legos, into an actual structure?
Let's set the problem.
So first, robots don't really have the creativity to build
Lego structures.
So this creativity is going to be brought in by a human,
and it's going to be brought in via the form of a Lego blueprint.
So if you look at the bottom left, this blueprint is going to be
provided to the stacking bot, and it's also given sort of
a list of what pieces to put first, so an assembly order.
And the reason for this assembly order is to prevent some really
difficult situations where like pieces that are placed
don't have bases yet.
Second, we're using modified Legos, so the pegs have been reduced
from 0.0048 meters to 0.004 meters,
and this allows for easier attachment.
And finally, we're only considering simple structures,
where we're only considering things on the top right
with the stable attachments.
We're not considering the other two cases.
Now, for implementation, the actual Lego placement needs
to be extremely precise.
So initially, I wanted to try using forward kinematics.
This actually failed, and instead I decided to use inverse
kinematics for greater precision.
Here, we use a quadratic cost on the distance from the
comfort position.
This was inspired by the door opening problem, and similarly,
we're going to box the gripper position within a desired
position bounding box, and this allows us to ensure that
the gripper position is where we want it to be.
For a general motion plan, we can't sort of just like tell the
arm to go to the Lego and then close it and then bring it
to the desired position.
We actually need a more divided plan, where we move above
the Lego, descend, grab the Lego, raise it, and repeat the process
to set it down in the desired position.
Now, for the main challenge.
So when I actually tried to use inverse kinematics on sort
of like the eight positions shown here, it caused a lot
of wild movements and instability.
So, for example, it would sort of create these really wild
joint movements between different positions, and as a result,
it'd sort of get tangled up and it'd be really difficult
to progress to other positions, also collide with a lot
of other Legos.
So I, taking inspiration from the door opening problem
once again, decided to divide this up into a lot
of intermediate positions that you can sort of see
on the top right here, where for maybe like a lower action,
it's split into five or 10 different intermediate positions
that it travels to, which allows for these minimal joint
movements in between each position.
Finally, with this established, it's really hard to move
through the center of the arm.
So if you consider moving from the one position
to another, sometimes that's going to cross the central
axis of the arm, and this actually is very difficult
to do and it gets the joints tangled up.
So instead, I decided to move to a designated reference
point, rotate to another designated reference point,
then move from there to the final position.
And you can sort of see that arc motion occurring
on the top right.
And finally, I decided to have a variable bounding box
so that when it lowers, you can see it's really precise
and close to the pose that it's meant to be in.
But when it's moving, it doesn't need to be so precise.
So you can see it's not fully following the pose
that it's been provided.
So just for a quick demo of what ended up happening,
this is arranging the pyramid that I showed at the very start,
and this has been sped up like maybe 10 times.
You can see it's just putting each block,
and you can see it's following the arc motion described
to prevent the joints from being caught up.
It's a little hard to tell because of the low resolution,
but it's sort of stacking each block pretty well.
And finally, as it places the last block,
the pyramid is complete.
For some future works, I originally
wanted to use reinforced--
OK, and we got apparently a room booking thing
happening here, so there's a small chance we'll
pick up and move next door, but hopefully not.
So let me keep going and be optimistic.
Hello, everyone.
Our project is titled Fast Online Search and Retrieve
Using Learned Spatial Arrangements of Common Objects.
So let's break that down.
Imagine a messy but structured environment,
such as a kitchen.
In your kitchen, you have your shelves, your cupboards,
and your counters, and oftentimes, people
will store the items in their kitchen in an organized way.
For example, I might like to have my condiments
on my shelves and my cups on my counters.
So maybe this information could be useful for us.
Imagine the following situation.
It's Kevin's turn to make dinner again,
and his food is awfully unseasoned.
So maybe my robot can help me find my hot sauce.
So the robot might know from past experience
that the hot sauce is usually on the shelf, which
is usually above the sink, and can use these associations
to search for and retrieve my hot sauce.
The robot doesn't know where the sink or the hot sauce
or any of the items are just yet,
but it knows that if it sees the sink or the shelf,
it must be close to the hot sauce,
and will guide the search in that direction.
OK, so let's talk a little bit about our approach.
So given that we have associations between objects,
but we don't initially know the locations of any
of the objects in the scene, the question
is, how might we search for a target object?
And so the first thing that we can do
is we can partition our space into a 3D grid of cells,
and then from here, we can run a few standard algorithms.
So for example, one of our initial ideas
was to formulate a graph search problem, where
basically each of the grid cells is a node in the graph,
and we could use an algorithm like A* to search over the space
and use our associations as a heuristic to guide the search.
However, we decided not to pursue this algorithm,
because in order to explore the nodes in the graph,
the robot needs to physically visit
the corresponding locations in 3D space, which
can be quite expensive.
And so instead, we decided to go for a grid search algorithm.
So the way that the algorithm works
is that we essentially define a belief, which
is a probability value which we associate
with every cell in the grid, and it defines the probability,
given the robot's current knowledge of the scene,
the probability that the target object
is located in that grid cell.
And so what our robot does is, until the target is found,
it will choose a cell to move to and observe using IK and RRT,
and then it will make an observation
and then update the belief.
So for example, if the robot sees an associated object,
it will increase the belief values,
and if the robot sees an object that is unassociated
or it sees empty cells, it will decrease the belief values
at those locations.
So how do we actually solve for these associations?
Well, in our project, we consider them to be 0, 1 values
for every--
values ranging from 0 to 1 for every pair
of objects in the scene.
And so for example, at a high level,
the way we collect this data is we simply
sample a bunch of views, and we basically
collect the data as to which objects
are located near each other.
Our experiments are as follows.
We run our search in a complex environment
with many bins and shelves where certain items can
be located randomly with high or low probability.
Additionally, there are some walls that obstruct the views.
We compare our approach with random search,
as well as grid-space search without associations.
But it also collects information about the scene
but cannot leverage associations to guide the search.
All right.
So here's our setup in action.
A robot tries to find a can of tomato soup
among all the clutter, and the only perception it has
is a camera attached to its end effector.
Before we arrived at our cool solution with associations,
we tried both random search and grid search
without associations.
As you can see, random search fails
to converge on a good strategy and essentially
makes arbitrary movements.
And the grid search without associations,
while it does better, it doesn't have any knowledge
about the spatial arrangement of objects.
So we have to expect it to search the entire space
before it can find the solution.
By contrast, here's our method with grid search
and associations.
On the left, you can see visualizations
of our goalie space as 3D plots.
And if we play the video, you can see the robot first
move into a neutral position before looking
to the top of the scene, where it catches
a glimpse of the cupboard, which is tightly associated
with the tomato soup.
So it goes to investigate the cupboard.
It performs a few other actions before finally realizing
that the tomato soup is at the bottom of the cupboard,
where it currently finds the solution.
Along the way, we encountered several unexpected
tactical challenges.
For example, IK's gaze constraint
did not come out of the box accounting for occlusion.
So we had to attach a cylinder to the end of the end effector
to ensure we have direct line of sight with our target.
Regarding the algorithm, we observed several problems
in the initial stages of testing that we tried to address
using the following three measures.
First, to account for the trade-off between runtime
and resolution, we adjusted the grid size,
the barcodes for titation.
To avoid nonsensical actions, we adjusted the goalie space
prior, and to prevent weak association propagation,
to avoid having our goalies explode and vanish,
we had to modify our update rule.
To make such a system more useful in the real world,
we'd first like to investigate moving occluding objects out
of the way by some kind of online interaction,
and of course, to make sure to test and learn
over more environments.
That wraps up our presentation.
Thank you for watching.
Super good.
I have to power forward, but that was super impressive
and probably the most objects I've ever seen in Metcalfe.
Today, we are going to teach you how you can throw
like you catch.
For that, we have developed an end-to-end robotic throwing
and catching system.
Robots have started to improve efficiency,
increase productivity, and enhance human experiences.
Warehouses and manufacturing is a prominent application
that we've identified to move objects around
and more efficiently and safely than humans.
Enabling robots to both throw and catch with one another
would expedite the process of obtaining particular packages
or materials and moving them from one location to another,
as shown on the left, versus our system on the right.
Our catching method has four main components.
The first is pose filtering, then KUKA arm trajectory
planning, KUKA arm closed loop control,
and then the gripper trajectory planning and control.
The first step is pose filtering.
We assume that we have perfect knowledge of the ball's
trajectory from when it's launched to when it hits the
ground.
We then take these poses and filter them based on the ones
that are reachable by the KUKA based on joint position
and velocity constraints.
And then we reorient these poses so that their z-axis
aligns with the velocity vector of the ball.
We then take the longest segment of reachable poses
and use this as the region of poses where we catch the ball.
Once we've determined this catching region,
we re-sample time steps such that the arm arrives at the
ball's positions before the ball gets there.
Eventually we converge such that the ball and the gripper
coincide at the same time at the same locations.
It's during this matching period when we are able to close
the gripper and catch the ball.
And after that, we decelerate and come to a pause.
Even though we have now re-sampled the times,
we are still asking a lot from our system.
Because, I mean, after all, our robot arm is trying to
catch, like someone is using chopsticks, a sphere.
That is really hard.
So we have to get the most out of our system.
For that, we have figured that we don't only need the desired
state, like the joint positions and velocities,
but also the desired acceleration to get the most out
of the EWA inverse dynamics controller.
For that, we have chosen to use a differential IK system
that outputs the desired joint velocity so that whenever we
integrate that or take the discrete derivatives,
we get nice and smooth integrals and derivatives.
To make this even better, we are making this closed loop
so that we feed in the measured joint positions back into
the differential IK system.
The final component is defining the gripper controller
and trajectory.
We can then make the gripper start closing the ball once it
matches its position and close before the arm reaches the ground.
This, however, wasn't sufficient.
We noticed that the gripper would sometimes close at the
right time, but still wasn't able to catch.
To fix this, we actually increased the KP gain to the
upper limit so that it was able to grasp the ball much harder.
On the next slide, I'll show the video of the gripper
actually catching the ball in slow motion.
Here we can see that the arm gets to its initial position
and waits for the ball to fall a little bit more.
Now it starts to follow and match the ball as it catches.
On the next slide, you'll see a couple more examples in
normal speed.
On the left, you can see that the gripper seamlessly
catches the ball.
On the right, you can see the initial condition of the ball
is far on the left, but it's still able to catch it on the
right.
>> So now that we have figured out how to catch very
reliably and we have developed a nice stack to generalize
that to a set of many different initial conditions, we're
wondering how to throw.
Whenever we played our video backwards, we noticed, huh,
this kind of looks like throwing, right, even though we're
doing catching.
So we figured, hey, can't we just, you know, give our
system a desired position and velocity where we want to
throw to?
Just reverse the velocity and plan for catching and then
take that plan and reverse the poses and, you know, the
times and just throw it along the trajectory.
The answer is, yes, we can do that.
Look at that throwback.
And that also enables us now that we can do throwing and
catching that we can pass the ball and throw it back and
forth between two robots.
>> One of the main limitations of our system is that we
assume we have perfect pose and velocity estimation of the
ball, which isn't feasible in real time.
So in order to make this work in the real world, one of the
things we'd have to do is build a perception module which
does pose and velocity estimation and creates a closed
loop trajectory update system.
So now we are only able to catch uniform spheres and we'd
like to increase our system to be able to catch any
geometric shape with non-uniform densities as well.
>> Further for the throwing, it is more relevant that we
also take an account for non-linear dynamics.
Like the contact force doesn't drag so that whenever we
throw it back, we actually get it to the position where we
want it to.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Super good.
Ria and David are here, I see.
I love the drag, little aerodynamics coming in from the
aero-astro.
We're on borrowed time.
We have a room overbooked so I'm going to power through.
But please ask them if you -- this one, Brandon is not here
so I'm going to advance.
>> Hi, I'm Michael Fernandez.
This is my final project, a robotic pipeline for the
box and blocks test to be used in the evaluation of advanced
robotic prosthetic arms.
Mobility impairments significantly decrease someone's
quality of life.
They hamper their ability to do activities of daily living
and lessen their independence.
Amputees are one group of people who have mobility
impairments.
To analyze the severity of someone's impairment, various
dexterity tests are used.
One common test is the box and blocks test, which I will
demonstrate here.
In the box and blocks test, there are a number of blocks on
one side of a barrier and then there's a goal region on the
other side of the barrier.
The objective of the person completing the task is to move
the blocks one at a time from one side of the barrier to the
other.
Completing this task requires a high degree of dexterity and
also a high cognitive load in planning how to move the blocks.
So I decided to implement the box and blocks test in an
automated fashion in Drake for the robotic manipulation final
project.
Now I will discuss how it went.
The project consists of four modules, the simulation setup,
the perception pipeline, a motion planner, and then the
actual arm controller.
Here we see the simulation setup.
On the left is the random block positions above the starting
region and on the right are the settled blocks with the
prosthetic arm and the camera loaded in frame.
This is the perception pipeline.
We start with a depth image, which is masked to get the
pixels the appropriate distance from the camera, then eroded to
separate any blocks that might be touching before flood fill
segmentation is used to identify each block uniquely.
After segmentation, the center of mass of each block and the
corners are found, which will be used in pose estimation.
The key points and the depth camera intrinsics are used to
project the positions of the blocks from the camera frame
into poses in the world frame.
The results at the end of the perception pipeline are shown
as mesh cat triads in the image here.
The block pose is used as a key frame for motion planning.
The other frames include a starting position, pre and post
pick and a drop location.
The full trajectory is calculated using linear interpolation
and quaternion slurp.
The output of the motion planner is visualized here in 3D.
Finally, we attempt to execute the motion plan using a joint
level PID controller, such as is found on the Luke arm hardware.
This part of the project did not work very well because the PID
games are very difficult to tune.
With more time, an inverse dynamics controller may have
been deployed, but this would not be as accurate of a
representation of the hardware in simulation.
In this image, we see someone who uses the Luke arm in his
day-to-day life.
I hope that this simulation pipeline can increase the pace
of research in prosthetic control to help us grant more
independence to amputees.
Thank you for listening.
[Applause]
>> I hope so, too.
That's awesome.
>> Good, good, good.
You're hiding.
>> Hi.
I'm Miana Smith.
I'm working on robotic assemblers for discrete lattice
structures.
To automate the construction of larger scale voxel structures,
we want to use swarms of relatively simple robots that are
able to traverse the structure and place new blocks of
material.
I wanted to use this class project as an opportunity to
explore some variations of this type of system and methods for
having robots collaboratively manipulate objects.
I have a set of three modules, a wrist-style actuator, an
elbow-style actuator, and an unactuated voxel.
These can be assembled in Drake to form a variety of different
robot configurations.
I am using this five degree of freedom assembly as the basic
robot.
In the actual physical robotic system, the connection between
the robot and the voxel structure will be made with some
sort of on/off system.
For this project, I am modeling these connections as welded
joints in Drake.
This means that the condition for a successful grab is just
that the gripper face of the robot makes contact with the
target gripping face.
Let's look at a motivating scenario where the robot needs to
collaborate to achieve the desired goal.
I have two identical robots and a 1x2 voxel stack.
The robots need to move the voxel stack to the other side of
the divide, which is a wider gap than they can individually
traverse.
To do this, Robot 1 picks up the voxel and passes it to Robot
2.
They readjust their position so that Robot 1 can grab the
opposite face of the voxel.
Robot 2 releases from the ground and is swung to the other
side of the divide.
Robot 1 lets go of the voxel stack, and Robot 2 places it on
the ground.
The robots then reattach to each other, and Robot 1 swings
Robot 2 back onto the original platform.
In the course of the overall trajectory, joints are welded
and un-welded a lot.
To accommodate this, I split the overall motion of the robot
into many subsections that are structured fairly similarly.
Let's look at the first handoff as an example workflow.
The multibody plant consists of the robots, which are welded
to the floor, and the voxel stack that is welded to Robot
1.
The initial positions are set using the final positions from
the simulation of the prior segment.
Drake's inverse kinematics method is used to solve for the
joint configuration that satisfies the given constraints
and costs.
This process for generating the initial and final positions is
used for every motion segment, with occasional changes in
formulation, usually in terms of using costs versus
constraints.
Next, I find a trajectory between these points.
I tried out a few different strategies for this, but here I
use direct collocation with the collision-free versions of
the geometry, and enforce the initial and final states as
constraints as well as joint limits, and use proxies for no
collision constraints.
I take the state trajectory from this, and feed it into the
inverse dynamics PID controller, and then run the simulation
forward.
From there, we advance onto the next segment of the motion.
Another formulation I used for creating the trajectory is
running inverse kinematics on offset points from the target
set of keyframes the robot then advances through.
I would like to be able to adapt this project so that I can use
it as a tool for generating trajectories in joint space that
I can then run on a hardware version.
Thank you for watching, and thanks to the course staff for
a great semester.
[Applause]
>> That was super good.
So much came together.
That's awesome.
Congratulations.
That's great.
>> Hi, my name is Daniel, and for this project, my colleague
and I were exploring the idea of blind grasping using a low
inertia arm.
The main motivation being that excessive information can
quickly become unreliable due to occlusion, particularly in
clutter environments and poor lighting conditions.
Additionally, forced torque sensors usually only work well
in the quasi-static regime.
So the main idea was what if we can use purpose of the
information from a low inertia arm to find objects when these
other sensor modalities are unreliable.
On the system side, we create a robot model of the low inertia
arm that we plan on using on our custom simulator, which models
the dynamics for our system and visualizes the robot.
Then we build a simple Cartesian space trajectory follower.
However, since integration with hardware still requires a lot
of engineering efforts, we instead output the joint
trajectories directly into the hardware and add gravity
compensation and track them online.
Then we do some simple contact detection using the purpose of
the information.
We use a 6 degree freedom robotic arm with a simple 1 degree
freedom gripper, which all uses low gear ratio actuators.
And the arm in general is very light and most of the mass is
concentrated at the base, making it very suitable for high impact
and contact-rich situations.
We built a simple trajectory tracker using the pseudo-inverse
velocity controller that we learned in class, where we
receive a list of waypoints, and we calculate the velocity in
the world frame to reach the next waypoint, and then we do
some low-level joint velocity control.
Then we built a simple finite state machine in which we go to
an arbitrary set of waypoints.
We probe the environment with our gripper, and if contact is
detected, which we only check in the hardware, then we execute
a pre-computed local trajectory to try and grab that object.
So now moving on to the hardware.
On the left, you can see there's no gravity compensation.
So the mass of the arm overcomes the friction of the actuator
and falls to the ground when I let go.
On the right, you see where gravity compensation is
implemented.
The motors are exerting a torque to make it seem like the arms
are massless.
This is helpful for demonstration purposes and for better
trajectory following and position control.
Now we are going to incorporate everything to run the trajectory
output of the pseudo-inverse simulation.
So on the right, we can see the robot, instead of snapping to
the initial pose like it did in simulation, it takes a more
conservative and safe trajectory.
Then only after when it gets to that initial pose, it begins to
start following the horizontal velocity across the workspace
like you see in the simulation.
For contact detection, the benefit of using low inertia
actuator is the access to clean and sensitive current feedback
in the environment.
On the left, the gripper hits the 200-gram weight without
stopping and knocks it over.
On the right, by monitoring spikes in the current, we are
able to detect and stop before knocking the same 200-gram weight
over.
Now it does the same for the 100-gram weight.
However, it reaches its limit when it can only detect but ends
up knocking over the 20-gram weight.
Another feature that will be useful in the future is
playback of human guided trajectories.
On the right, we can see the robot does a great trajectory
following of the human demonstration on the left.
This could be very useful for authoring complex behaviors and
learning from demonstrations.
So we weren't able to fully integrate the contact detection
into our pipeline because of many hardware bugs and having to
build the pipelines from scratch.
We do plan on exploring ideas like rapid pick and place,
contact detection and clutter, and human robot safety.
That's all for the presentation.
Thank you, Russ, and all the TAs for an amazing class and
amazing semester.
[end]
[BLANK_AUDIO]