So it's motion planning week.
There's a lot of cool tools in motion planning.
I think it's a pretty rich and well-developed subject.
We're breaking it up into two pieces.
We'll talk about the optimization viewpoint today, and we'll talk about sort of the randomized
algorithm sampling-based strategies on Thursday.
Let me just start, though, by talking a little bit about projects.
We sent a couple of piazza posts about it.
So I mean, the basic details-- so thank you for submitting the pre-proposals.
I had a blast reading them.
I think we all had a blast reading them.
Some of you guys are really ambitious and wrote really good proposals.
So thank you for that.
Please, everybody, do submit again, even if the feedback-- I said this on piazza-- but
even if the feedback was like, you're good to go, just submit it again so we have the
one canonical place where everybody's full proposals are.
And if you do just have to touch up a few things, add a few details for us, then just
do it with some sort of track changes so we don't read and have to find exactly what you
changed.
But I think a lot of them were in very, very good shape.
We're going to try to support you through that project.
We're going to turn down the p-sets.
They're not going to be as heavy now.
We'll try to be more in project mode.
We'll be available if you want to ask questions.
I think certainly on piazza, if you need to reach out to us, please do reach out to us.
If you have questions about Drake, you can post on the Drake sites too.
Then you'll have even more people to answer questions.
Actually, I wanted to make sure that people know something good has happened recently
in Drake.
You can actually just pip install Drake now, or apt install Drake.
That's actually been there for a while.
But if you decide that DeepNote isn't quite enough for you to do the full debugging that
you need for your project, and you want to do local installs, we can help you through
that.
I think it's gotten easier depending on exactly what platform you're on.
It could be as easy as pip install Drake, which I'm super excited about.
That was a long time, a lot of work behind it.
But in general, I think there's a couple of different workflows you could decide that
works well.
I'm more interested to hear if you think DeepNote's exactly the right tool for your
group project.
That would be really interesting for me to find out.
It's kind of built for that.
But if you like hitting breakpoints and doing all the things you've got in an IDE on your
desktop, then I could see how it's not quite what you want.
I'd be very interested to see how you guys decide.
Yeah?
If you run locally, does Meshcat work the same way?
So if you run locally, Meshcat should just work the same way.
In fact, you'll see if you look carefully today, you'll just say local host instead
of the DeepNote URL.
The start Meshcat script checks if you're on DeepNote and does the right thing.
So, yeah, Meshcat should work everywhere.
Good.
Yeah, there's also a bunch of things that -- a few of you got feedback from me, for
instance, saying like this thing that you would want could work.
We might have to help you through that, like the writing example I put.
If some of you wanted to write on paper, there's a lot of things that we kind of have code
lying around somewhere to do that in the simulation in Drake, and we can help you.
Someone wanted to throw objects that would require aerodynamics, and that's actually
not too hard to add in.
But I'm trying to now -- for me, I'm in the mode where I'm like, let me figure out what
features people most need and try to knock them off, and so please -- if you think there's
like something that you really need for your project, you're not sure if it's there or
not, that's a really good time to ask me and get that on my list, and I'll try to knock
off as many of them as I can.
Actually, it was totally random, but a few people were talking about painting or writing
or wiping or whatever, and almost by accident, you know, Terry in the lab was writing a paper
he submitted last night, and I come in and he was writing -- like the robot was writing
in lab last night when he was making this paper and writing this paper.
He thought that was a good example for his force control with the soft tactile sensors.
And if you've noticed a lot of robotic videos at MIT, always do something where, you know,
we've had quadrotors flying at high speeds through obstacles that happen to be shaped
like MIT.
We've got like, you know, carrots moving around the table that end up looking in piles like
MIT, and if you're handwriting, you have to write MIT.
But that's actually a pretty cool project.
He's got one of these Puno soft bubble grippers showing that he could do force control just
by watching the deflection -- by the cameras inside, watching the deflection of the bubbles
was sufficient to act like either a stiffness or a force control right at the end effector
without using the KUKA's joint torque sensors.
So anyways, you know, I think writing is possible.
Many of you kind of asked or implied that you'd like to get onto hardware.
I think if you are able to show us in simulation and you're far enough along, we do have robots
upstairs that I'm willing to try to, you know, let you guys run things.
Someone wanted to throw darts on the hardware, that one, and I'm a little afraid of, but,
you know, that's maybe paper airplanes are safer.
You know, but within reason, you know, if you're not going to break everything, there
are robots available.
And the idea is that you really, if you're able to run in simulation, it's almost just,
you know, pull that one away, put the real robot in and the code works.
There's a bunch of setup, but the code should actually mostly work.
Okay, any big questions about, you know, projects, how that's going, administrative parts of
projects or?
Oh yeah, we're going to -- we're trying to figure out -- there's a few of us and a lot
of you, so we're trying to figure out exactly how much we could like require a face-to-face
check-in because that's, I think, a great way.
So we're going to do that at least once, you know, we're aiming for the week of November
15th, which is, you know, before Thanksgiving, you know, enough time for you to get things
going from now.
So we're going to try to schedule, we'll put a sign up for you guys to sort of fill in
and pick a time to sit with us.
But we're also going to ask little questions on the P-set just to kind of say, you know,
we'd love to see, you know, can you just give us a snapshot showing you've got your simulator
working because if you don't have your simulator working, you know, then things start getting,
you know, late in the term.
So we'll try to guide you with a few of our survey questions on the P-set, but one big
check-in.
So I think that means you should really reach out if you want to, you know, ask more questions
because I think some of you could benefit from talking more.
Good.
Okay.
So let's talk about motion planning.
So we've already, you know, we've done the simple version of motion planning where we
just designed a handful, hand-designed a handful of end-effector configurations.
You know, we called inverse kinematics maybe, or we found some initial way, actually I guess
we just took the initial pose of the robot and we just started interpolating with differential
IK, right, to get down and to move through them.
And that works fairly well, but as the world, remember the theme is that the world is getting
more cluttered, more constrained, and we have to think more about both of our perception
system but also the plans that come out of our robots.
So today we're going to try to embrace the more rich versions of planning trajectories,
which is going to be ultimately the goal is to have a trajectory in Q, the joint angles
of the robot.
Q is a function of T that is going to satisfy a bunch of constraints, avoiding obstacles,
reaching to the mug, you know, doing all the, you know, opening the door.
Okay.
There's a bunch of tools that will be available for that, but actually a lot of it starts
with just understanding more deeply the inverse kinematics problem, right.
So we've talked about inverse kinematics a few times.
We talked about the differential view of inverse kinematics.
We've talked about writing optimization problems that would take clutter and try to pull them
out of penetration, which in some sense is the simple version of the inverse kinematics
problem.
But there's a lot more that you can do in this sort of space of writing optimizations
to solve inverse kinematics.
And if we understand that and understand some of the geometry that we're up against with
our solvers, then actually the rest of it follows pretty quickly.
The trajectory version of that as an optimization follows pretty quickly.
I think a lot of the work here is understanding what you can do and what's hard to do in the
kinematics space.
Okay.
So let me walk over here.
So we've talked about it a few different ways, right.
We said that in general maybe we have a pose of the gripper, which is some forward kinematics
of our joint angles Q. And of course inverse kinematics would be to try to find some form
of the inverse map, which may or may not be unique, may or may not have a solution.
But if we want a function that takes the pose of the end effector in and returns Q.
Now, this is the simple version of it.
If we really have just, let's say, one end effector constraint.
You'll see why I think of it that way in a second.
Then there's opportunities to do a lot of nice work in trying to invert that mapping.
In particular, for the standard robot arm, very commonly we have six degree of freedom
arms or more common than seven degree of freedom arms.
And the standard sort of just like what we have with the KUKA, there's sort of a standard
revolute joint up the arm configuration that accounts for a lot of the different arms that
you can get out there.
Of course, the exact kinematics, the lengths of the links, the positions of the joints
are a little bit different.
But the kinematic topology is very sort of characteristic across a lot of arms.
So people, of course, have for decades spent a lot of time thinking about the right way
to solve the inverse kinematics problem.
There's a special case of six degree of freedom arms where this, if you have six degree of
freedom arms, then Q lives in R6.
And we know that there are some parameterizations of pose, row, pitch, yaw, x, y, z that could
have six numbers.
And so for the special case of six degrees of freedom, we can actually know that there's
a finite number of solutions.
And we can potentially enumerate them all.
And those solutions can be written in essentially closed form.
It involves a bunch of trigonometry.
It's actually really-- the study of kinematics is the study of polynomials, actually.
You might be surprised to hear that, I guess.
But we see a lot of like L1 sine theta 1 plus L2 sine theta 1 plus theta 2.
So you see a bunch of sines and cosines lying around when you write your kinematics.
If I'm writing like the position of my end effector, it might be something like this.
So there's a lot of sines and cosines.
But you can always do a change of variables that turns those into polynomials.
You can change sine into s and the like.
And the way maybe to convince you is that really the fundamental idea here is we have
rigid bodies.
And the rigid body assumption says that the distance between these points is a constant.
So P1 minus P2 squared, which is a polynomial in those joints, is some constant.
The distance constraint is a polynomial constraint.
And in fact, you can write the fact that if there's two joints and they're connected by
a revolute joint, then you could write that as an extra constraint saying point P1 on
link 2 has to be in the same place as point P2 on link 1.
That can be written as a polynomial constraint.
So what you end up with when you think about the detailed mathematical solutions of these
equations, you end up with actually a list of polynomials.
And the study of this is actually in the study of algebraic geometry, typically numerical
algebraic geometry, which is the study of basically trying to find the zeros of a bunch
of polynomials.
And there are serious tools out there for that, both mathematical tools and numerical
tools for algebraic geometry.
And there's a book that I cite in the notes that I just think is awesome, where they have
effectively closed form solutions for these ridiculous complicated serial chains of four
bar linkages or Stewart Go platforms, which are the ones that have a bunch of different
legs on springs.
And they're all crazy kinematics.
I actually put one in the slides, I think, here.
And this is kind of a four bar linkage.
But if you think about the path that the links follow when you rotate the joints, they follow
these pretty crazy curves.
But those curves, because they are the solution to a set of polynomials, you can actually
do numerical algebraic geometry to solve, even design the kinematics of your manipulators.
And this was a big aspect of robotics decades ago.
It's one of the earlier things that people studied carefully in robotics.
It's really interesting to understand those tools, if anybody cares.
So I mean, one of the ways that you find-- like the way that this paper finds the zeros
for a large set of polynomial equations of high degree is you typically-- you can look
at your complicated equations, you can put an upper bound on the total number of roots
of the polynomial system.
You make the unit circle that has that many zeros around it, which is a trivial polynomial
system where you know exactly where the zeros are.
And then you basically morph the trivial polynomials into your polynomials with a continuation.
Basically just like you say, let's say, my trivial polynomial where I know all the zeros
are plus 1 minus alpha times my interesting polynomial.
Interesting.
OK.
And you change alpha from being 1 to being 0.
And you watch, you track where all the zeros of the polynomials are.
And these are called continuation methods.
And there's a whole science of this, I guess.
And you end up writing tools that do variable precision arithmetic.
Doubles aren't good enough.
You have to do however many degrees of precision in order to track zeros that go arbitrarily
close together and then split, and they're complex.
Anyways, there's a lot to be known about kinematics.
There's also, in the specific case of 6 degree of freedom arms and 7 degree of freedom arms,
those tools have been bottled up pretty effectively.
So you don't actually have to study anything about polynomials.
You can just download the software and call IKFast or something and use the benefits of
that.
And IKFast is a popular open source version of this, which provides the closed form solutions
for 6 degree of freedom manipulators.
And that works so well that if you have a 7 degree of freedom manipulator, you just
sample a bunch in the last link and ask the 6 degree of freedom for a solution.
And this is just fast enough because it's closed form that people do that.
And if you're a floating base robot, you might sample around it and just use the 6 degree
of freedom solution a lot.
Sorry, I got a little carried away with my kinematics.
But I think there's good stuff to know here.
And I cite it, but we're not going to dig into more details than that.
But I want you to realize that this is somehow not what I mean when I say inverse kinematics.
This is from Q to one end effector constraint.
And that is inverse kinematics.
But there's a much richer version of the inverse kinematics problem, where if I want to pick
up a mug and simultaneously avoid putting my elbow in the table-- and actually, I don't
care exactly the pose of my hand relative to the mug.
As long as I'm somewhere where my fingers are going to get a good grip on the mug, that's
a different specification than having an exact pose constraint.
And these non-penetration of my arms into the table, we know a little bit about that.
You can write that as a non-penetration constraint.
So we're going to generalize this into the optimization-based solutions and get a bigger
tool that can solve a lot of problems.
It's very analogous to the way we generalized our differential IK to add more and more constraints
like velocity limits, acceleration limits.
We're going to do the same thing for the actual kinematics, the inverse kinematics problem.
And this is a tool that we've used a lot over the years, this philosophy, maybe, that we've
used a lot over the years.
Even on Atlas, this was a core tool.
If you think about Atlas, like in our differential IK, we had this comfortable configuration
that was our happy place for Atlas.
So the objective was always be as close to this as possible.
But then you'd start adding constraints, like I'd like my end effector to be in a certain
position.
I have joint limits.
I have collision avoidance.
In Atlas and also in other manipulation, you might need that your hand stays where your
cameras can see.
That's what the gaze constraints were.
It's particularly important on Atlas because the first version of Atlas they gave us, so
the cameras could see here and the hands could reach here.
You couldn't quite see your hands.
It was just like, I don't know.
They just didn't think about that part of the problem very much.
So you had a kinematic workspace that was a little too small and just barely in the
camera.
So we spent all of our time trying to make sure we were only doing things where we could
see.
For a humanoid, you want to make sure that when you're in the solutions, you're not requiring
the feet to slide around in order to reach something.
So you put your feet stay put.
You want your center of mass to be over your support polygon.
These are all just constraints that you can put directly on Q.
In most cases, they are inequality constraints on Q. And if you can put them all into a solver,
then you can solve these big problems potentially.
What you'll find out is you can solve these at basically interactive rates.
And that's what this video showed.
This is real time.
That was the plan.
But you'll see there's a little interactive marker here.
And you'll see Pat just pulling the hand around and adjusting some constraints.
And it's just solving in real time.
And that was back when computers were slow.
All of these things are available.
So you should just look that there's a library of these constraints.
You can add position constraints, saying I've got a point in frame B should correspond with
a point in frame A with lower bounds and upper bounds.
We'll use that one in a minute.
You can add orientation constraints on two points in two different frames-- or two different
frames being at a different orientation relative to each other with some bound on theta.
You can add your days constraints, which is really just like this point needs to be inside
the cone.
The minimum distance constraints are the non-penetration constraints.
You can add just a bunch of these different-- there's a rich library of constraints.
And that's just wrappers that build up, that call the right queries in multi-body plant
and just give you a mathematical program.
And then you hit Solve.
And it'll solve those problems for you most of the time.
It can get stuck.
We'll talk about its limitations.
So I told you, I think, about the big robot in the little car.
So one of the big jokes was that they gave us this huge 400-pound robot.
And then they gave us a little Polaris.
And they said, the big robot has to drive the little car.
So we spent a long time even figuring out how to get the robot into the car.
And it turned out the only way it could actually get under the steering column was if it drove
from the passenger seat and put its foot across and used its left foot to drive and its left
arm.
And then it had to get out of the car, which was a real doozy.
But we solved all that with this interactive inverse kinematics, where we were dropping
on-- you can see multiple pose constraints.
And we'd play around.
And that's how we worked out.
You can see we didn't have a CAD model for the Polaris.
But we just took point cloud scans and started working with that.
And just as a human, we played with this until we understood what happened.
Now, if you watch super closely at what was just happening there, watch the elbow.
It was actually pretty good that time.
Again, this one you'll see.
He was trying to turn the steering wheel there.
First of all, the foot's sliding around a little bit, even when he was turning the hand.
And even the-- you'll see the elbow kind of jumps a little bit.
So we'll write down the optimization.
But it's interesting that the solver can solve these really hard problems.
But sometimes you haven't specified them well enough.
Sometimes it's solving it approximately.
So it's not really guaranteed that a small change in your problem will lead to a small
change in Q. You can do your best to ask for that.
But compared to differential IK, these are more global solutions.
But they are not necessarily smooth solutions.
So it was very rare that we would go straight from this and immediately send the real-time
output of the solver directly to the robot, because the robot might jump around in order
to do that.
We would tend to filter it and check it before we sent it down.
And this is just another example.
But the great thing about this is it's really not robot-specific.
You could put any different-- this was just 10 minutes of effort.
You put in a different robot in, and you could immediately start making trajectories and
plans for a very different robot.
This was the NASA humanoid.
So we're going to try to generalize this with those richer formulations.
I want to think about what that solver has to do, because it's going to make you appreciate,
I think, the problem we're asking for solutions for.
So let me use a toy problem here, which is-- actually, let me do one more thing before
I do that.
Sorry, Rachel.
I actually have all of this coded up so you can play with it, I hope.
And you will.
So for the EWA in the notebook that I just updated to DeepNote and pushed to DeepNote
this morning, you can just do this interactive kinematics.
This is it running in my system.
I forgot to delete the example I ran before.
So basically the same demo.
I didn't draw the interactive markers, but I have all the sliders here.
So you can do the same thing.
You can move your end effector around.
It looks a lot like what we did with the kinematic teleop before, but now we're solving the full
inverse kinematics problem instead of solving the differential inverse kinematics problem.
So that should all just work.
Now I want to make that point, though, that this is solving a bigger version of the problem.
So let me just throw a obstacle in the middle here.
And let's just look at what's happening here.
So every time I move a slider, it's making this new inverse kinematics problem.
It's adding the position and orientation constraints, just saying the pose is exactly what I'm asking
for in the slider.
And then it says add minimum distance, basically saying that I'm not in penetration.
The links of the robot are not in penetration with that column I just put in front of the
robot.
And other than that, it's just calling solve, basically.
I set the last-- or I set the comfortable q as the initial guess.
And I put that q minus q desired-- q nominal as the cost.
So it's trying to prefer the sort of default position, but otherwise solve that problem.
And now I put it in a position here where it's kind of annoying.
There's a column right in front of my robot.
Don't do this to your robot.
It is annoying.
But now if I move this around, it's all good if I go that way.
What's going to happen if I go this way?
So if I go right in the middle, you'll see IK failure.
It's doing its best effort.
It's actually trying to do a good job.
But it's claiming that it can't satisfy the constraints exactly.
But if I keep going, it actually snaps to the other side and proceeds.
So that is something you would never have gotten out of the differential IK.
It would have gotten stuck there.
It would have refused to go to the other side.
But this is solving the full inverse kinematics less well.
It's a non-convex optimization.
It's not guaranteed to succeed.
The differential one would find an answer if it existed.
But it can solve this bigger version of the problem.
There's a very important point I want to make here,
which is that you should add the minimal possible constraints.
So the philosophy that we have in the group-- so I would say,
in general, I would say the philosophy that I would recommend
here is keep your cost function simple.
So for us, it's almost always minimize q, q minus q nominal
squared.
So I've got my comfortable position of the EWA.
I'm just using this like my joint centering.
And then add the least restrictive constraints you can.
, OK?
So like I said, if you're reaching for a mug,
you might have-- it might be that you must pick up
the mug from exactly this orientation.
But rarely is that the case.
Typically, you have some freedom in your choice
of exactly how to pick up the mug
if you can leverage that all the way through your pipeline.
Things are going to be better.
So let me make that point with another of these examples
here, OK?
This one is going to-- oh, I forgot to stop this one.
This time, it's trying to grasp the cylinder, OK?
So I actually stopped.
I'm not commanding.
If you look at the code here, the pose
that I'm sending in from the sliders
is now setting the cylinder's position, not the robot's
position, not the robot's hand.
And then I'm just saying, B, I'm going-- we'll
write this on the board in a second here.
We're going to constrain the hand relative to the cylinder.
But I can tell-- all I care about
is that the cylinder is somehow in the hand.
I don't care about the orientation
of the hand around the cylinder.
And I don't even care about where on the cylinder.
In this toy example, I don't care where along the cylinder.
So I can write much less restrictive constraints
if I embrace that extra ambiguity.
So if I move the cylinder in x, then the robot's
going to do a good job.
You see that the orientation is changing in order
to satisfy that constraint.
If I move it in y, when I get to the end,
it's going to chase because it's constrained to stay
along the thing in y.
But if I move this way, it's happy.
There are multiple solutions, so sometimes it jumps.
But that's a much less restrictive constraint
to add on the end effector.
And any time you can express with less constraints
the same problem, you win.
Your solver is going to have a better chance.
You'll be happier with the results.
You'll be able to add more other interesting constraints.
I am continually impressed, too, by just the collision avoidance
capabilities of this.
That's the-- it's going to dance around, try to chase.
I actually even have a version of this.
If you set grasp cylinder to false
when you're playing with it, then it's like--
just tries to avoid the stick.
And you can make it limbo and stuff.
But I won't do that here.
So how do I-- what are these two constraints
that I wrote do?
How do you write that version of the constraint?
There's many ways to write it.
I chose to add it with two position constraints.
So how did I do that?
So basically, I have the gripper in this frame,
where this-- if you remember the gripper's coordinates--
sorry, Rachel-- you remember the gripper's coordinates,
where it's kind of annoying, but x is the-- it's RGB, right?
x, y, z.
So if I draw this from the side, then this
is going to be my z-coordinate.
This is going to be my y-coordinate.
And what I want to say is that basically all I care about
is that the cylinder is somewhere like this.
I chose to say, let's pick a point in the gripper frame.
Pick one right here.
You'll see the numbers.
It's like 0.1 down, 0.02 to the side.
And I picked another point in the gripper frame.
And I just said both of those points
must be exactly on the center line of the cylinder.
My claim is that that's a version of that rotation.
I basically wanted to say I put a rotation around the center.
You know, the middle of the hand can rotate arbitrarily
around this.
And it also gave me a convenient way
to say that those points actually
are on the line segment of the cylinder,
so it didn't go off the end.
Is that picture clear?
OK.
If I were to look at the gripper from the other dimension,
it's saying that those points are right
in the middle of the gripper here.
There's two of them directly there.
They have to be dead center here.
So because that's x, y, z, that really just came up
as being in the code that the gripper frame--
there's a point in the gripper frame, which is down one
in y, which is positive y right there.
And then I did to the left in z and to the right in z.
And both of those have to be somewhere on the cylinder
where the x--
so the cylinder is--
coordinate frame is the long axis of the cylinder is in z.
So this is saying that exactly on the center
line of the cylinder, exactly on the center line of the cylinder
in the x and y, and in z, it's anywhere
along the length of the cylinder.
That's a really rich way to specify the dynamics.
And it's important-- or to the kinematics, I'm sorry.
And it's important for things like reaching
into tight spaces where you get very, very constrained
very fast.
Does that example make sense?
OK, so let's do something a little bit more fancy.
Let's make the robot now--
I can even put it up here, I guess.
Let's think about the robot reaching into a set of shelves.
So I want to think about this problem for a little bit.
Now, the reason I want to think about this problem
is I had to think for a while about what
would be an interesting geometric problem where
I could plot everything.
So what I did here was I--
this is a three-link KUKA.
I froze all of the joints that were out of plane.
And I just kept the ones that were aligned with this axis.
And we're going to only think about--
the robot actually can't rotate.
This version of the robot can't rotate.
So now I've got Q1, Q2, and Q3.
And I can make 3D plots for you.
And I want to think about what the collision geometry
engine and our optimizer is up against.
If we just say-- you see, I put a little target inside here.
And I said, reach the sphere.
Reach into the shelf and reach the sphere.
And how do we do that?
I want you to appreciate the richness of configuration
space.
[ Writing on Board ]
So the configuration space is the set of queues.
In this case, the set of queues that avoid collision, you know, the standard name would
be the admissible queues for this robot, which avoid penetration.
In this case, it's respect joint limits, avoid collisions.
Our optimizer is hunting inside the configuration space of the problem.
And it's a potentially very challenging space.
So let's just even, for a simpler problem, a two-link I can draw on the board.
It's also-- you'll almost always hear us call it C space, short for configuration space.
So I'll take a two-link robot, my standard sort of two-link robot, theta 1, theta 2.
I'm going to pretend that there's no collision geometries here or here.
And I'll just make a sphere collision geometry with radius r at the hand, OK, just because
I can do all that on the board here.
And I'm going to stick it in sort of like it's reaching into a shelf.
But I'll put it between some walls here.
So this is length 1, this is length 2.
And that was supposed to be right dead between the walls.
But you'll humor me and pretend that was symmetric.
Those are both w.
And I'd like to ask, what are the admissible theta 1's and theta 2's?
What's the admissible q's?
And the punchline is it's not a simply described set.
We'll animate it in a second here.
But it's got sines and cosines floating around in it.
In fact, it's not hard at all to solve this one.
In this case, the kinematics, the center position here, is really just L sine theta 1, L1 plus
L2 sine theta 1 plus theta 2.
That gets me to the position in the middle at that point of the hand.
And because there's a sphere geometry here, in that one particular special case, I can
just think of-- I can take the sphere away and just move the wall in by radius r and
get the same answer.
So this has got to be less than the wall minus r and greater than the wall plus r.
And that's my configuration space for the simplest possible picture I could possibly
draw.
And it's already interesting and hard.
So not super hard, but foreshadowing, let's say.
You can think about what happens just in the simplest case, then it gets pretty complicated
pretty fast.
So if I start moving that wall around, then the overlap here-- I've drawn each of my constraints
in different colors.
So the overlap region is the valid configuration space.
That's the limit of my plotting ability in this program.
If I move it around, those look-- when it's small, you could almost say, well, that could
almost look like I could approximate those with lines and have a nice convex constraint
or something like that.
But it's really not a convex constraint.
These are curvy lines.
The set is interesting and rich.
If I go too far, it starts wrapping around on itself.
So what is that?
That's when the arm goes up again around the top, and it's wrapping around.
They're valid solutions like that.
Of course, if I move the wall too small, then I've got no solutions.
But it's a rich space.
If I now take the same idea, and what I want to plot is the configuration space of the
three-link arm reaching into the cupboard, this is what it looks like.
Sort of.
I can approximate it with like a merchant cubes, and it's kind of scary and bad.
So let's just even-- you can run this in your notebook too if you want to play with it.
So let me-- OK, it looks the same.
I was worried that it looked out of date.
Let me turn off the collision constraint first and first just draw this grasp constraint,
the green region.
So the green region already looks pretty cool and crazy.
So what is that?
This, by the way, is just my initial comfortable configuration.
The x, y, and z-axes here are my q1, q2, q3 of the robot.
Why is the successful set of grasps ignoring collisions look like that?
Do you have a sense for what that geometry is doing?
Why does it look like this sort of ring?
There's joint limits.
It would go all the way around if it didn't have joint limits chopping it off.
What is that axis if I were to walk along that annulus or whatever?
Yeah?
>> Does that look like the elbow moving?
>> But it's in the plane.
So a lot of times the elbow would walk out of plane.
So I hear you, but it's not this one.
It's in the plane.
I mean, the elbow is involved, so that's correct.
But I think that's not the most important feature.
>> The grasp is when the supposedly going through that shelf?
>> No, the shelf is not drawn.
This is as if there was no shelf.
I'm just trying to reach with my 3-link for that sphere.
I disabled the shelf constraint for a second.
Yeah?
>> Isn't it better to do that at the same time because you have 3 links, so you can
have multiple solutions?
>> Yeah, so what are the multiple solutions?
I didn't specify a position constraint.
Well, sorry, I actually did specify a position constraint, but a sort of low rank.
It's not a pose constraint.
All I said was that the center of the sphere was in the middle of my fingers.
>> So is it only the elbow?
>> I mean, yes.
So I think maybe I have to-- so of course, the elbow is involved.
But it's really-- it's the hand rotating around all the different possible configurations.
And the arm will reach or not reach based on-- I think I can draw it better than I can
say it.
So if I have the-- there's kind of a solution here.
But there's also a solution with the hand sort of coming down from on top that maybe
it has to go a little bit more like this.
And there's also probably a solution like this where the hand is coming from this way,
and maybe it's a little bit more like this.
It's this kind of-- I think of it as the hand orientation that's really being rich, if you
will.
OK?
OK, so that's already a little bit quirky.
It's just I've only got three links.
I've got to reach this sphere.
So that sends this annulus of possible constraints.
But then if you take the KUKA geometry-- by the way, I think every time I plot something
like this, I, again, once again, thank my geometry friends because there's a lot of
stuff going on in all these geometry engines behind the scenes.
But it can solve these hard problems where it's checking if the KUKA's approximated geometry
intersects with the shelf, which was a simple geometry.
And the way I plotted this was I made-- in XYZ, I made a huge grid.
And every point of the grid, I called the collision checker.
And I able to either 0 or 1.
And then I called the marching cubes algorithm, which tries to find the level sets.
It's trying to draw a smooth curve that interpolates between the 0s and the boundary between 0
and 1.
And for like, if you have a sign distance function of the bunny, it gives you these
beautiful things out.
When you have the configuration space-- and I sampled it a little coarsely because it
already takes a long time to run-- it gives you these gross things out, especially with
the truncations.
It's not closed.
But that's what it looks like.
Crazy.
So this is the problem that we're going to be trying to solve for paths inside.
We're going to try to find sets of cues that walk along inside this geometry.
That's the problem.
Even if I just solve the-- yeah, please.
Are the initial and the full [INAUDIBLE]
Are they what?
Are they connected by [INAUDIBLE]
The initial guess was this blue region.
Let's see.
Initial guess was that blue region.
And the IK solution is like hiding-- let me see if I can-- well, I turned the grasp constraint
up, turned the collision.
That's the solution.
It's inside the grasp, the successful constraint, which is what you'd want.
And it's hiding down here inside that.
We're not done.
I like my visualizations here.
So OK.
No, not this way.
This is what the-- if you write the optimization problem that you're asking it to solve, this
minimize-- wherever I just erased it, I guess-- but minimize q minus q desired, subject to
nothing from my arm is inside the shelf.
And the point in my hand is here, is within some tolerance of here.
I had to make it a little bit of a tolerance.
That's why you got a whole annulus instead of just a line.
This is the optimization problem that it's faced with.
Let me see if I can get it here.
So I've got my cost function, which is the simple small q minus q desired.
So that's a nice quadratic form.
But it's nestled inside these nasty constraints.
And the optimal solution is hiding right down in there.
I did a beautiful job solving it.
But that's the local landscape.
Even better, this is the global landscape.
This is what I fed it.
Here's the cost and constraints that I gave to SNOPT.
Now you can see-- so first of all, props to SNOPT for finding this in the middle of there.
It might not have found the optimal one.
It's possible that it's in the wrong trough or something like that.
So not guaranteed to find the global optimum, but props for finding any of them.
And it's not going to guarantee that it'll find that.
You could have come up with another similar setup, and SNOPT might have failed to find
a solution even though it existed, because it was hiding in one of these little canyons.
But that's the kind of geometry we're throwing at these solvers.
OK, so I think we understand-- I hope we-- if you feel like the sort of rich inverse
kinematics, it's just adding more types of constraints to the type of optimizations we've
already been writing.
But the big difference compared to just the poses and everything is we're really living
in this configuration space of the arm, curvy, complicated landscapes.
The inverting the forward kinematics is a lot of non-linear, non-convex constraints.
OK, like I said, if you've got that, then you're almost done.
So if I wanted to now reach into the shelf, what I need to do is take my initial conditions,
which was-- the initial-- let's say the robot was in the initial-- actually, the initial
guess was in penetration, so I had to move it out a little bit.
And I just need to find a series of points that gets me from the initial conditions,
never runs into the shelf, and finds my way to the goal.
Now again, if I over-specify the goal, if I say-- if I were to, for instance, solve
the inverse kinematics problem once, take the solution, and then try to find a trajectory,
that is potentially a harder problem than finding a trajectory that still has all the
flexibility of the problem given to it.
So if I draw this configuration space again-- so I had this sort of interesting-- you know,
configuration space.
This was the good region.
And I have some initial guess here, like initial configuration.
I'll call it q0.
And I've got some target here, which is-- as the picture shows, I've got some set of
possible targets that are all admissible, right?
q goal here.
And the task now is to basically-- the kinematic trajectory optimization problem is find a
bunch of q's by solving multiple inverse kinematics problems simultaneously that somehow parameterize
a path that gets me somewhere-- lands me somewhere in the goal.
Right?
Now, they can't be completely independent.
I'm going to need something that sort of connects the two-- the points together.
But this is the most important idea.
OK?
So now, instead of where I was doing minimize q, q minus q0 squared, now I'm going to minimize
over a whole bunch of q's.
I'll say q-- say k equals 0 to capital-- maybe k is a bad-- on the board.
OK?
I'm going to try to find many q's simultaneously-- q0 to n, n minus 1.
Subject to a bunch of constraints, right?
I'd like that for all n, qn is out of collision-- satisfies joint limits.
OK?
And then I'd say that at least one of them is inside my goal region, which for me was
that the position is within some ball of the middle of the gripper.
And we're almost done.
We've done a lot of the work here.
OK?
If you just solve this, though-- maybe I also have to say, sorry, q0 is my initial guess--
or my initial configuration.
If I just solve this, then I might get a solution that puts like almost all the q's here and
one q down here, right?
Or all the q's down here somehow and just one point up there.
I need something that somehow relates these together.
OK?
And there's different ways to do that.
The most natural way, I think, is to somehow put a constraint saying you can't move too
much-- if you start thinking about this as time, and you say I'm going to take five seconds
to go from here to here, and I have a velocity limit, then that constrains those points to
be somehow close enough together.
Joint velocity limits.
So you could say qn plus 1 minus qn is less than-- maybe even every element of it-- qi
is less than q dot max.
Something like that.
I missed the times t, right?
OK.
Yes?
I was just saying the-- so this would be joint 0, 1, or 2.
So this would be for each joint.
I could do-- I have some joint limit for each joint.
You could do it a total velocity if you wanted, but I just did it one at a time, which is
a more standard-- where the place where the constraints come in.
Thank you for asking.
This is enough to do reasonable trajectory optimization.
OK?
The extra bonus stuff is about asking for-- trying to parameterize continuum solutions
through here a little bit better.
OK?
So if you want this to be described by a trajectory that maybe has some smoothness properties,
if you'd like to do extra work saying that even between the points, I don't leave my
joint limits or joint velocity limits or whatever, then we're going to do a little extra work
in the last part of lecture here to try to put those into a trajectory formulation.
OK?
But the key idea really is that I'm solving many IK problems simultaneously, and I'm doing
some work to just put some constraints across those different points to make them mutually
consistent.
This is-- I mean, this is the same thing in, for instance, autonomous driving or other
places where you're doing trajectory optimization, right?
I think the constraints-- the shape of the constraints you get in manipulation tends
to be richer, and so maybe a little bit more emphasis on the kinematics constraints.
But the philosophy of this trajectory optimization is similar.
I will put-- it's different than what we tend to talk about in underactuated, if you have
taken or will take underactuated with me.
I'm emphasizing the kinematic nature of this optimization.
And the choices we make in terms of the trajectory parameterizations are going to be different
in the kinematic trajectory case, where I'm more worried about saying I'm not in collision,
and I don't have to put on dynamic constraints on the trajectories.
I'm going to make slightly-- I'm going to have different preferences on how I specify
those constraints.
OK?
But the tool chain is-- at this level, I've described it so far-- is actually very general,
right?
You can make airplanes land on a perch, and you can do all kinds of cool stuff.
OK.
So let's think about how to specify this now in terms of a trajectory.
How do we parameterize a trajectory?
I'm being inclined towards the middle board, but I promised I would stay here.
Old habits die hard.
Trajectory parameterizations.
We've already seen a few of them, right?
There's actually-- there's a whole bunch of different ways to parameterize a trajectory,
right?
We used piecewise polynomials when we were parameterizing the end effector translation.
We used quaternion slurp to parameterize the orientation changes.
Do you remember?
If you look inside the piecewise polynomial classes inside Drake or other trajectory library
kind of things, you'll find all kinds of-- even in the class of saying, I'm going to
have a piecewise polynomial, there's just so many choices.
There's a standard cubic spline.
There's Hermite splines.
Most of them are implemented.
All the ones that we find useful.
You can do Chebyshev polynomials.
You can do-- there's a lot of choices.
The ones we did before made the choice where if I specified from t, and I had some nominal
configurations t, q at t3, q at t4, for instance, a lot of these parameterizations try to find
a path that goes through all the points that I've specified, and maybe has some-- they
have different properties in terms of smoothness up to some derivative.
You might want to constrain the derivative at the end effect-- at the end point, or there's
different ways to spell that.
There's lots of different polynomials you could choose of certain degree that will go
through a set of points.
And a lot of the variation there is just picking the way that you choose that.
We tend to not use those-- I think there's a slightly better choice for kinematic trajectory
optimization when you have joint limits, and velocity limits, and acceleration limits.
There's a different family that I think is probably in most cases the winner, which is
the Bzier curves.
I think it's I-E-R, right?
Bzier splines, B-splines.
They are also polynomials, but they're parameterized a bit differently.
You don't think of them as being parameterizing directly the coefficients of a simple polynomial
expansion, or you don't think of them as being points that you try to go through.
They're parameterized a little bit differently.
But they have some properties that are super nice for doing this kind of motion planning.
People hear about B-splines before?
Yeah?
Bzier splines, right?
So people feel comfortable with them?
I find many fewer people say yes to that second question.
Even people who use them a lot, actually, I think the notation is a little bit cumbersome.
There's a sense of what they're doing, and then there's the details, which are ugly to
get right, in my opinion.
Maybe I just don't understand them well enough.
But it's just a slightly different way to parameterize a curve through time.
The parameters are-- you have your break points.
There's an additional thing, the not points, if you know, but I'm going to de-emphasize
that detail for now.
The break points and the control points.
So let me draw two pictures here, one of them in configuration space, Q1 and Q2, and one
of them in time.
And I'll just write Q1 here.
Just pick one of them.
So I'd like to have a bunch of samples in time, which I'll say Tk, Tk plus 1, and so
on, Tk plus n, let's say.
These are my break points, my breaks.
And then I have my trajectory Q that will evolve in time.
But different from this, I'm not going to parameterize directly the points that it travels
through in time.
Instead I'm going to sprinkle some control points in the configuration space.
So I'll do Qk, Qk plus 1, plus 2, all the way up.
I'm going to have a bunch of control points in my configuration space.
And there's a particular polynomial basis, the B-spline basis, which has some beautiful
properties, which says that in the configuration space-- I need more colors of chalk.
In the configuration space, there's a super useful geometric quantity, which is sort of
the bounding box-- or sorry, the convex hull of my control points.
And one property that it has is the convex hull property, which says that the trajectory
here that comes out, it will not go through those points directly, but it will be inside
the convex hull of those points.
So it has a super useful convex hull property.
It also has this very nice locality property.
So more precisely, if I'm at some sample point in the middle of my trajectory, there is a
finite set of control points before and after me for which I'm in their convex hull.
And that set moves in a sliding window as I move through time.
And the number of points that define that convex set is the order of my spline.
Just a bunch of terminology, but I think what I want you to get essentially is that this
is a good choice, first and foremost, because it has this convex hull property.
Why is that important?
So if I have joint limits, if I pick sample points in Q and I parameterize with a lot
of the standard polynomials, there's not a guarantee that my interpolated trajectory
doesn't do something like this, which badly violates my joint limits.
In the B-splines, you do have that guarantee.
As long as all of the points, the control points, satisfy your joint limit constraints,
then the entire trajectory, the continuous time trajectory at all times, it stays inside
the convex hull.
More valuable.
There's a locality property, which people normally emphasize, but I think I've made
the point enough.
And then I think the other one that's super useful for us is there's a derivative-- are
also B-splines, time derivative, and they are B-splines where the control points still
enter linearly.
They're nice B-splines.
So for joint velocity limits or acceleration inequalities, like limits, bounding box kind
of limits, you can put them in a convex way onto this parameterization.
They're easy constraints to guarantee that your joint velocity over all times stays inside
your joint velocity limits and your acceleration stays inside your acceleration limits.
So the picture down here is you end up specifying a handful of times.
The transcription looks almost exactly the same as this.
It's just that the cues that I'm going to think about here are parameterizing-- they
are the control points of my trajectory.
They might look a little different.
And what I get is that each local convex hull I stay inside of, and that convex hull moves
on each sample to be a different thing.
I don't know if I did the geometry carefully enough, but each segment stays inside.
So I'm not parameterizing-- the cues in this optimization are not the actual points on
the path.
They are the-- they define these moving bounding boxes that gets me through that tunnel.
Like I said, this is just the extra richness in order to guarantee that whole path stays
inside the configuration-- sorry, the bounding box constraints.
So question for you-- how does it do on these non-penetration constraints?
Does that bounding box property protect me from non-penetration constraints?
Unfortunately not, because these curves, these active constraints that are coming from the
collisions can be sort of arbitrarily curvy.
So even if I have points that are-- if I had a bounding or a convex hull that was here,
and I choose trajectories that stay inside that because they all satisfy my joint limits,
it could be that my configuration space obstacle snuck inside there.
So for q less than or equal to q max, q dot less than or equal to q dot max, q double
dot less than or equal to q double dot max, these are all bounding box constraints.
This stuff works great.
It's awesome.
It's not quite enough to save you from collisions with the complex geometries.
But it's still a good-- it's still, I think, a natural choice because of these benefits.
Now for those of you that have taken underactuated, let me just call out that the reason this
is maybe not as a good choice for the dynamics, you can imagine I'm parameterizing sort of--
I'm not parameterizing the exact trajectory.
So if I wanted to say the slope of this line at a certain point is exactly this, if I had
an equality constraint on the dynamics, q double dot is exactly f of x, u, or whatever,
then that's not naturally expressed here.
This is really about knocking out regions.
So when you have big inequality constraints, that's the natural thing.
But once you have this sort of library of B-splines, which we have libraries of B-splines,
you can construct a lot of interesting things.
For instance, if you'd like the initial trajectory to have zero velocity and to be at a certain
exact point, which we said we wanted to start at the current position of the robot, I don't
have to be wishy-washy and have it be inside some region.
If I just put-- if I have a k-order spline, if I put k points on top of myself at the
beginning, then there is a first cell, which has a convex hull, which is a point.
And I can put my initial conditions directly inside that point.
And I can even leave with a small velocity, with a zero velocity, and interpolate up.
So there's a lot of richness in this parameterization.
You just have to work through it.
In practice, we have kinematic trajectory optimization classes that you can call.
They take some of the same constraints that you saw in inverse kinematics.
You load them up, and you solve these sort of problems.
One more point I want to make here.
So let's say we're doing something like this.
So I've got a trajectory.
When I see this, I almost said my point too quickly.
But when I see this, I see this broken up into a handful of different trajectories.
There's the reach down until I touch.
There's close the hand and then move the arm, the mug, through the world.
And then maybe I'll move again.
You could imagine solving that as one big optimization problem, but people often don't.
And let me illustrate why.
So the worst case is the plate.
The collision geometries change when you pick up an obstacle.
So classic first dishwasher video is like, you reach down, you pick up a plate, you go--
sorry, didn't mean to scare you.
And you just move your hand through, and your hand is perfectly collision free.
And you've got a broken plate in your hand.
So you really have to think about-- we tend to think about composing.
You can solve them jointly, but we think about explicitly composing the segment which has
collision constraints based on just the hand up until a contact, the grasp, and then moving
with the collision of geometry of the plate welded to the hand in the grasp that I've
chosen.
So this is the standard thing.
Make sure that is collision free.
Let go.
Now it will stay fixed in its final location.
And then do that again.
That's a little bit-- that's limiting.
This is the same way in-- we talk about choosing your footsteps in a certain order or whatever
in underactuated.
But that's a limiting constraint that I have to pre-specify exactly the order.
If I wanted to pick up two plates, maybe one with the left hand, one with the right hand,
it gets a little bit more annoying.
Do I-- did I have to pick up the left one first or the right one first?
Or if I'm doing it with a dexterous hand, you start getting more subtle.
So it gets limiting.
But for a two-finger gripper picking up a single object, that's a pretty good assumption.
You can solve all of those trajectories simultaneously with just putting different constraints on
the different parts of the trajectory.
A very useful heuristic is to solve a piece of it first.
So the first thing you do is you solve two-- a joint inverse kinematic problem, just two
points.
You solve your pickup configuration, your put-down configuration.
You want to solve those at the same time because you want to find a single graph, a single
relative pose of the object relative to your hand that works both for picking up and putting
down.
Otherwise, you're going to find yourself-- you chose-- you made a choice picking it up,
and then you can't get there with the plate in my hand and this.
You tend to solve those jointly.
Once you do that, then that breaks the trajectory into pieces.
And I can now plan to get to that, plan to get from here to here, and plan to get the
other one.
You can parallelize all that, and it's all good.
It does defy what I told you-- that's exactly what I told you not to do earlier, which is
to try to leave as much richness in your optimizationist problem.
So you can do versions of that where you try to leave a little bit of space.
That's one way in which it's a conservative heuristic.
But it really makes the problem scale bigger, and it doesn't cost too much in some cases.
Cool.
I'll call that good.
Yeah, it's at 55.
So I will see you on Thursday, and we'll do--