All right.
Hi, everybody.
I want to talk today about-- this
is sort of the prelude to reinforcement learning.
And I know I sort of--
we polled you and asked you if you want to even hear a lecture
about behavior cloning or not.
And what I was thinking at exactly what I wanted to say,
I thought, you know what?
It really goes first, right before the RLs.
And plus, we have the one day--
I don't have lecture on Thursday because of Veterans Day, right?
So I'm sneaking this one in.
Sorry to have polled and not waited for your answer.
But I hope you'll like it.
I think it makes sense as sort of the prelude to RL.
So let me--
well, let me-- actually, I had a couple administrative things.
So for the project feedback, we're
going to try to give you quick feedback from the same people
that read your pre-proposal on your final proposal,
just to make sure you got a green light on everything
you need.
We'll also try to--
so that means the person who read it before
will read it again and confirm that any concerns they had
or whatever were addressed.
But we're also going to try to just--
I'll try to read all of them.
I think we'll try to give you a little bit slower
trickle feedback as--
to the extent possible, too.
A few people have been asking good projects
about how to set things up on Piazza.
Please keep the questions coming.
In particular, I marked as, please read--
we do have a Python-only version of the manipulation station,
which I wrote last time, in exactly this time of the year,
when people were asking, how do I make the manipulation
station do x?
That's not quite what it's meant for.
And it's buried in C++ and hard to change.
But it really can exist completely in Python now.
And so there's a notebook there in one of the Piazza posts.
If you find it useful, it's easy to change.
And I guess that's the main-- those
are the main announcements, yeah?
Good, OK.
So let's talk about feedback controllers and visual motor
policies.
So last time-- last week, I'd say,
we talked about trajectory motion planning, right?
So given either a cost function in the trajectory optimization
case or just a start and a goal in the randomized motion
planning case, typically, we had a start and a goal.
We were designing a single trajectory through space.
And we had some good tools to do that, and potentially,
tools that scale pretty well to large dimensions.
As we transition to RL, RL is trying
to solve a bigger problem, right?
So maybe bigger problem where the output of a motion planner
is a particular path or trajectory, right?
And now we're trying to solve--
trying to find a policy.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
So that's synonymous with a controller for people
who want to think about it that way.
But even in the motion planning picture,
if you think of this original motion planning gives me
q as a function of time, what I'd
like-- the simplest analogy for a policy would be maybe I
want to do a vector field.
I want to represent potentially the same sort of behavior.
But instead of having just a single path,
I'd like to say for every q, not just for every time,
but for every q, I'd like to say what direction I should
be going in in order to accomplish my desires, my cost,
or achieve my goal, right?
So it's potentially trying to solve a bigger problem.
This is for all q, I'd like to have some instructions.
And you could think of them as representing-- certainly,
this captures-- if I were to start at this one
and follow the vector field, then
you can pull a trajectory out of that one.
But it's potentially saying much more.
It says what happens when you're away from the trajectory.
Yeah?
So if I were to just give you the trajectory of an RRT,
I'd say it's probably more like a QT.
But an RRT feels a lot more like that cycle.
Good.
Yeah, yeah.
So I'm going to try to make that connection, too.
So the observation was-- actually,
what I'm drawing here doesn't look
so different than maybe the PRM or the RRT in its full glory.
So yeah, there's good connections there.
In fact, since you asked, why don't I show slide one?
Yeah.
OK, so my favorite version of this,
actually, is the optimizing version of RRT,
which is RRT*, where they very explicitly make the point
that if you do that rewiring, then you can have a system--
it's a little bit small.
I hope you can see.
You can have a system that finds a path fairly quickly.
But if you just keep adding, keep sampling, keep sampling,
keep rewiring, then what you end up with, really,
is more than just a path.
You can end up with a policy that
tells you the vector field over the entire space.
So you can really go from a lot of the planning algorithms
to something more like policies.
OK.
So a lot of the variance, you could think of it that way.
Alternatively, another connection
would be if you were just to do replanning.
If you can plan fast enough, and then
if you look at whatever state you're currently in,
then you can execute a plan on the fly, online planning
is a policy, basically.
And that's what people talk about when
they talk about model predictive control, for instance.
OK.
So there's lots of connections between these two.
And actually, even in the details,
I really don't want it to be you're
either a plan or a policy.
Because I think there are beautiful ways
to sort of blend the two.
Like if you've looked at alpha 0, for instance,
I think that's a very nice way of sort of planning and then
using the planner to build a policy and vice versa.
We'll talk about that one later.
OK.
So let's just compare the relative merits.
As a representation, as the goal of an optimization problem
or a planning problem, you would think that Q of t
would be asking less.
In many cases, it's not asking what
should the behavior be at all possible states.
It's just asking along one particular path.
So in a sense, you do benefit from that in a very real way.
But you can often plan for systems
of very high dimensionality.
And you're roughly immune to the curse of dimensionality.
The number of possible states that I
might have to cover with a description of a policy
can grow badly.
If I were to make a grid and have
to give a discrete answer for every point on the grid,
then it's exponential in the number of state variables.
And a path, because it's only parameterized by t, not by Q,
t is always dimension 1.
So you can say the vector you have to put out
is a little bit bigger.
But that doesn't really matter.
So what matters is that I have a single path
through a potentially very high dimensional space.
So in that sense, you might think
that planning can scale much better.
And I think there's certainly places where that's the case.
The counter argument is that sometimes plans
can be extremely complicated to represent.
And sometimes very simple policies
can actually describe behavior, even
in very complicated systems.
Can describe rich behavior.
And I've mentioned a few examples of that before.
My favorite of all time is the hopping robot
from Mark Raybert, where it's just--
to this day, I just love the fact
that the whole controller fits on one page of this super small
book.
And it's basically a picture and then a few PD controllers.
And it makes robots throw themselves through the air
and had a huge impact on the field of leg and locomotion.
So very simple controller saying roughly
when you're on the ground, jump.
When you're in the air, put your leg out in front of you,
roughly where you want to land.
And the resulting behavior, when you
couple that with the dynamical system, which
is the springy hopping robot, gives you
this beautiful rich output.
And actually, if you had to plan a path for that,
it might be a harder problem.
And I think that's also true if you start thinking about--
this is an example of it can be very robust,
even if they're relatively simple plans.
That's what I showed you before.
But now think about this as a very manipulation-specific
example.
If you have to plan every detail of that multi-fingered hand
and every contact that comes in contact with the plate,
that can be an enormously complicated plan to generate.
But if you have a simple controller that just kind
of goes down until you touch and then squeezes the hand,
it might be that you can write that controller very easily
and maybe or maybe not get beautiful performance out.
I would say this is an open question and one that
we'll discuss a bit today.
I got to find one that's not going to be irritating.
I think I can pause this one.
OK.
Maybe I can go on to the next thing here.
Let's see.
OK.
So I do think the concept of planning
and the concept of feedback control and policies,
I think both of them need to probably live
in our future manipulation systems.
We talked about motion planning at one level,
but even higher than that was our task level planner.
So deciding that I'm going to first pick up the mug,
and then I'm going to open the dishwasher drawer,
and then pick up the mug, and then put it down.
That's a high level logical planner.
When I've described it before, quickly, we
talked about that as a planner, not a policy.
And my favorite thing from Leslie Kelbling,
Leslie likes to say, imagine you're trying
to book a vacation to Paris.
You don't have a policy for booking a vacation to Paris.
It's not that you've like every possible place
that you're ever going to vacation.
You've already pre-recorded a solution for that.
And then you just look up the solution to that.
It seems like there are places in our lives
where we solve problems on the fly,
and do some deductive reasoning, and do effectively planning.
Now at the very low level, we've got very continuous motions
with very complex contact mechanics or whatever.
We'll talk a little bit.
I think it's still a little unclear,
but that feels more like a control problem
where you really want to know what's
going to happen from all the different states.
And the exact details of what happens
along a particular trajectory are probably not
as important.
So maybe at the low level, we kind of have policies.
And what's super interesting is to think
about how that transition happens,
and where up and down the ladder, I guess,
does that transition happen?
And how does it happen?
How does it happen gracefully?
We talked about motion planning of the arm.
That's a case of a super powerful set
of tools that we have.
Does it belong in our long-term solution?
Maybe depends what the task is.
I would even say that my position on this has changed.
So in legged robots, I think it's
very natural to think about having low-level controllers.
You're constantly trying to not fall down.
So balance is a premium.
The lowest level thing you want is to be a stabilization
based thing.
And roughly, there's kind of a nominal thing that I do.
I have a nominal gate.
I'd like to have that programmed in.
I'd like to know what's going to happen if I'm near that.
If I take my foot a slightly bad step,
feels very much like a policy to me.
And you could imagine having a handful of maybe a step reflex
or just a handful of policies that you could combine and be
a very effective walker, like a locomotor.
In manipulation, I would have initially--
I did initially, a handful of years ago,
thought it was different because the sheer diversity of things
that we do with our hands.
It's amazing, all the different things we do with our hands.
And to some extent, we are not in this sort
of periodic, very regular pattern.
To some extent, it feels like every time we
do something with our hands, we're
doing something different we've never done before.
And maybe the situation that we're seeing in front of us
is kind of, if it's never been seen before,
then it really puts us in a place
where I just need to figure out this one thing,
the single query RRT view of the world,
rather than the multi-query if you
try to solve an entire feedback policy.
And I still think there's good logic to that.
But I've changed my mind a bit.
I think now that we probably do have--
I mean, I don't know how high up the ladder it goes.
But I do think a relatively small set of policies
down at the low level can probably
describe a lot of the details of what we do with our hands.
And there's lots of evidence of--
people talk about if you just watch
the kinematics of people's hands when they're doing maneuvers,
it's actually relatively low dimensional.
There's like eigengrasps, and there's all kinds
of discussions about this.
But I would think even fundamentally,
I think there's handfuls of things
that we do that was not intentional that we do that I
think we probably could, through practice,
get very good at a small number of policies
and assemble them and achieve a great diversity of motions.
But I don't know.
I mean, I think somewhere--
we have to live somewhere in this balance.
OK, there's another problem actually with this picture.
So if I put this back up again--
or another thing that it doesn't address
that I want to call out.
So this view of policies from plans,
this sort of Q dot is some policy.
We almost always use pi for policy.
And that's the RL notation.
OK, this presumes that we somehow have a measurement
or even know what Q is.
It presumes that we know Q and have estimated it, let's say.
And-- OK, and this is obviously a major assumption.
So for an arm moving through, when
Q is just the state of the arm and I'm doing motion planning,
that doesn't feel like a bad assumption.
We have very good sensors.
We've paid for the nice KUKA instrumentation.
It gives very accurate measurements
of the joint positions of the arm.
But if we're in this bigger view of manipulation,
where the policy really needs to know not just
the state of the arm, but it's really somehow I'm
making some control decisions based
on the entire state of the arm plus the world, right?
This now is Q of the robot, V of the robot in general, right?
Q of the world of the environment obstacle, object,
V, and so on and so forth, right?
I don't have good instrumentation on the red brick.
And the red brick is as easy as it gets.
It doesn't get easier than the red brick.
It only gets worse from there.
OK?
So already, implicitly by saying that I've
written my policy like this, it sort of
assumes that I've been able to estimate those positions
and velocities.
OK?
Sometimes I don't even know how to write them down.
Not just-- I don't want to assume I estimate them,
but maybe I don't even know what choice of Q
is a good state representation for the world, right?
So my favorite example of that is just
thinking about the problem of chopping onions, right?
And if you think about trying to write the pose and velocity
of all the pieces of the onion, and maybe it changes in number
every time I make a cut, right?
So I don't even know what the x of this state of this system
should be, right?
So that's when I say, presumes that we know Q, right?
I don't even know a good representation for that yet.
OK, so what I really wanted to talk about here
is a broader view of what a policy is.
It's not just a map from state to actions.
It's potentially a map from observations to actions,
and it's a dynamical system.
OK, so let me come over here.
So really, what we have is our dynamic systems
view of the world.
I've got my plant, which is the robot, plus the onions, right?
OK, I've got my sensors coming out.
I've got my actuators coming in.
There's a view of the world, which
says that I should just write a state estimator first.
And that gives me some estimate of x,
and then I can write my policy u equals pi of x hat,
and I could feed that policy around to the plant.
That means that the implications of that model
here, which is a classic model that we've gotten from control,
is that this thing has to be a perception system that
estimates the state of the onion in addition to the robot.
It has to be running at full frame rate
according to this diagram.
If you think about how we've used them so far,
we've really said, let's do perception and then
plan a trajectory, and we basically close our eyes
while we go and execute the trajectory.
But this is asking for more.
This is asking for a constant stream of sensors
to be coming in and put out a constant stream of x estimates
coming out in order to make these decisions.
OK.
And this has been good to us in control,
but it's breaking down when it gets to manipulation.
This assumption of having a state estimator in the middle
and having its requirement to output x hat is just too great.
And I would say that this burden of state estimation
is just too great.
And it's not necessary, necessarily,
to estimate the full state to make good decisions.
OK, so I think one of the great things
that manipulation is doing for control
is it's fighting down some of this model
of trying to do state estimation and then control.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
So this definitely has the multibody state.
If I just think about what state variables
did I have to declare to simulate the thing,
in this model, this could be a simple function.
Input output function, no state.
We're going to generalize it, of course.
And if I think of this as like a Kalman filter, for instance,
or an extended Kalman filter, has a state.
It's running an internal estimate x hat.
That's not the only way to implement that.
You can write state estimators that just have sliding windows
or whatever, but that would be a natural approximation.
So there would be state variables here,
state variables here, and that could be a static function.
That would be the classic view.
As I was thinking about this, I was
kind of reflecting on my own journey through this process.
So even when I was purely focused on legged locomotion
and UAVs, I guess, we were feeling the pain of this.
And I would say, when people ask me,
what do I think, why aren't I working on legged locomotion
right now, and am I going to work on it again,
I think this is still a limitation.
We're leaning hard on this paradigm
in our legged locomotion.
Atlas has an incredible state estimation system.
I think they would tell you that it could even be better.
But the inclination would be, if I
want to improve the performance, I
can make my state estimator better.
I think it's going to take a big leap to break that mold
and try to do control differently
in legged locomotion.
But I was already feeling it.
And I was writing--
I remember, I actually looked back,
just to look at the dates this morning.
And I was looking back.
I wrote proposals, like in 2011, that were saying,
we have to do integrated perception and control.
That was what we called it back then,
integrated perception and control.
[WRITING]
Saying, don't break those up into two separate processes.
Put it into one system.
Solve them jointly.
And a lot of people were using those words at the time.
And it sort of evolved.
Another name for this is output feedback.
We'll talk about that.
In particular, it would be dynamic output feedback,
where I have to take-- where I'm trying to design a feedback
controller that goes all the way from sensors to actions.
That's an output feedback, as opposed
to a full state feedback.
[WRITING]
I remember struggling and struggling to convince people
that this was important.
Even my students would kind of be like, yeah, I hear you.
But can we just make the state estimator better?
And in UAVs, we started to finally--
started to see was we were flying very fast
through forests.
That was the first project where we really started doing--
I think letting go a little bit of the full state
and trying to just say, we need a minimal sensing
of the upcoming obstacles.
And that's sufficient to make our short-term control
decisions.
So our first papers and talks about integrated perception
and control actually came in the UAV space.
And it really-- deep learning happened around 2015, 2016-ish.
People started calling it visual motor,
especially in the manipulation space, visual motor policies.
And I think, in my mind, they mean the same thing.
And this is the word to use today.
And it's really this sort of bigger view
of trying to write a controller that goes directly
from your sensors to your actions.
And we'll ask the question of, does it have state inside it?
But this is a beautiful view of visual motor policies.
And in my mind, this is the reason
to do manipulation for me.
I think this is forcing big questions that we don't know
how to address solidly and control yet when the sensors
are cameras or depth cameras or RGB, right?
And we're trying to come in and write the best
controller we know how in order to make an action based
on a stream of rich visual motor sensor inputs.
OK.
So this view of visual motor policies--
I just draw that same thing again here,
but zoom in a little bit.
OK.
The simplest thing I could write here
would just be, as Alex was asking about,
I could write that just I call my sensors y, which I always
do because I come more from the control, I guess, these days.
Right?
I could just have a static function
that maps from my current observation
to my current action.
That's a reasonable thing to do, but it's limiting.
We already know that it's limiting,
because even for sort of basic control,
the simplest versions of control,
the simplest versions of output feedback in control
would be like linear quadratic, linear Gaussian optimal
control, already demands dynamic policies,
dynamic controllers, which is exactly the column and filter
state plus the LQR.
OK.
So another way to think about this
is that this is a new dynamical system.
It has its own internal state.
OK.
One version of that is that inside,
it has the state estimator, which has internal state.
It has the controller here.
Right?
That is a version of a dynamic controller.
That is the optimal thing to do in a linear Gaussian
quadratic optimal control problem, OK,
is to have a dynamic controller that estimates the full state
and makes decisions.
But that's not true in general.
It is true in general that having dynamic policies
can do great things.
Question?
Yes.
What's the trade-off between having a dynamic policy
versus augmenting your policy with a history of observation?
Yeah.
Good.
So let's first just jump to say, think of this--
this is a dynamical system.
We think of this as an input-output dynamical system.
It's got a stream of actuator commands.
It has to predict the stream of sensors.
I want you to think about these controllers
as having the same stream of sensor inputs
and a stream of outputs command.
Right?
So this is just a dynamical system.
OK.
So now in this weird case, it's sort of y's coming in
and u's coming out.
But these are signals coming in.
And I have a system in the middle.
OK.
There are many ways to represent a system.
You could have a state space representation,
which is what we've been using most of the time
and which we're most familiar with.
I could say maybe xc is my--
maybe it should be x pi, but I'll call it c.
xc of n plus 1 is some f of c xc of n.
y of n is coming in.
And then I'm saying that u coming out
is like my pi, which depends on both the internal state
and my inputs coming in.
That would be a state space model
where I have explicitly written down the state.
I move forward with a difference equation
or a differential equation, that state,
and I'm producing my outputs.
But there are also other perfectly good models
of differential equations.
I think the one you're referring to
would be like an ARA model or ARMA or ARMA
with exogenous inputs, which is--
this is an autoregressive model with--
yeah, it doesn't really matter.
But it's with exogenous inputs.
But roughly, it is now pi takes a history of observations.
So pi coming in.
It also potentially takes a history
of its own outputs, which is a little bit goofy to write it
the way I've got u and y flipped here.
But luckily, the message is the same.
You need both of them in there.
That's why it's autoregressive, because it
gets to see its own output.
And it now just predicts its next controller.
Maybe it's not allowed to see this one.
This is another perfectly good input-output dynamical system.
The question is, are they equivalently expressive?
So in the limit, yes.
So certainly, for any finite horizon history,
I could take the history of y's and call that my state.
And then that would be a state-space model.
So you can certainly always go this way.
You can also-- so again, in the limit of infinite states,
you can always go both ways in the limit.
But in practice, if you have a truncated history,
then this is good at some things.
And this is good at other things.
So what's an example of-- this is one of the points
I wanted to make.
So thank you for asking it anyway.
So something that would be good, that this would be perfectly
adequate for.
Let's say my observations, which are y of n here,
are let's say-- some of you are working on ping pong, right?
So it's the position of a ping pong ball in my camera image.
[TAPPING]
Clearly, if I want to take a swing at the ping pong ball,
and I have to make a decision just purely based
on a single image, that seems inadequate, right?
If I don't know what direction it's moving,
I need to know something more, right?
If I have even just two images, let's say,
or positions of the ping pong ball,
then I could estimate the velocity of the ping pong ball.
That's already pretty useful.
And you could imagine if I had a slightly longer history,
maybe I could filter out a little bit of measurement noise
or something like that.
But that would be a very reasonable local estimator
of my velocity of my ping pong ball.
If I wanted to, for instance, remember--
if I'm looking at the sink, and I
want to remember if I already opened up the dishwasher top
drawer, because I'm about to pick up a mug
and I'm not looking at it right now, that would be potentially--
if I have to remember that a long time into the future,
that would be maybe a very painful thing
to try to represent with a history of observations.
So this is good for short term, not so good for long term.
Memories, let's say.
But it can be very clean.
So I get to, for instance, if I'm taking just a bunch
of images in, I could just use a feedforward neural network
to make my prediction.
That's a very appealing thing to do.
We know we're pretty good at training those things.
In the states-based representation,
I want to remember the mug, let's say,
or remember the dishwasher drawer.
Now, that feels like a state.
I could have x 32 being, is the dishwasher open?
These are very familiar concepts.
I mean, if you look at even just linear control theory,
we know a lot of things about how to fit these models to data.
We know a lot of things about how
to do motion planning with those models,
trajectory optimization with those models.
Same thing for these models.
There's nothing new, really, about visual motor policies
in this discussion.
I think there is a choice you get
to make about how you represent a dynamic controller,
either with histories or states-based representations
or possibly combinations.
A very nice combination would be, for instance,
maybe take a simple filter bank of recent observations
and use that as a surrogate for state.
There's all kinds of intermediate solutions.
So when you think about the way people--
I jumped to this kind of description here.
So if we have an input-to-output dynamical system, in general,
you could do it in states-based form.
We can do it in autoregressive form.
Ah, I forgot the other part of it.
Shoot.
I was basically going to write down here
that when you think about a recurrent neural network model,
those are states-based models.
So if you see someone talking about recurrent neural
networks, that's going to be a states-based model.
So for instance, LSTM, the long short-term memory,
or other sort of recurrent models.
And this would be, for instance, feedforward networks.
Again, there's nothing here about--
I mean, if we start representing them with neural networks,
we've gotten into new tools.
But the modeling framework is old and well understood,
I would say.
For those of you that think about partial observability,
if you think about POMDPs or whatever,
if I want to have a dynamic controller that's
reasoning in a partially observable environment,
then x--
the Kalman filter view of the world,
you'd think of x as being the state of the system.
But really, you should think about my state of my controller
as being my belief representation,
or some approximation of the belief representation.
So this x could be a compressed belief state, for instance.
So you'd like to think that if I'm training a recurrent
network policy, that somehow the internal dynamics are somehow
building up a belief, or whatever
is necessary to accomplish the task.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
The biggest thing to change, though, is that basically,
we learned how to do computer vision.
And neural networks got big, and data sets got big.
And so now people are writing the policies down
with taking the entire image in.
Oftentimes, if you look at some of the original works--
and actually, a pretty standard framework
that you see for visual motor policies throughout--
is to have a big pre-trained, typically,
network that gets you from RGB space down to something
smaller, like a 32-dimensional feature vector.
How you design z is something we can talk about.
But oftentimes, there's a relatively small policy
that you're going to represent, a relatively small network.
These tend to be a multi-layer perceptron
with three layers and 255 units.
That's the standard thing.
And this tends to be like a ResNet, millions of parameters.
And the reason is you can pre-train this
on an image-only task, for instance,
and get potentially very good features out.
And then if you're going to do reinforcement learning
or behavior cloning, you can train a relatively much
smaller network for the control, given good features.
Because often, our control training algorithms
are more data-hungry.
And training all the way through the ResNet would be tough.
Some people try to do it or certainly fine-tune through it.
But that's considered hard.
OK, so the million-dollar question, then,
is how do we design the weights of our LSTM
or our feed-forward network?
How do we design pi?
And again, the new thing here is the cameras coming in
and the neural networks in the middle.
Actually, I would say even control people
have thought about neural networks for a long time also.
So I think the biggest new thing is the size of these
and the fact that we're jamming images into them.
And the perception sort of works now.
All right.
The big answer these days is reinforcement learning.
That's what we're going to mostly focus on.
I really want to think about this being good, certainly
down at the low level of my ladder,
where I'm doing really dynamic things.
And I want to represent a policy instead of a plan.
There are lots of people that think about RL for higher level
decision-making and the like.
I think that's not the use case I'm going to emphasize here.
It's not the one I believe in as much.
OK.
Even RL, people ask me, even in the context
of projects for the course, I don't even know--
so this is the big answer these days.
I don't know if it's really a good answer.
And it's not because I don't like RL.
I think RL is awesome.
But I think given this problem formulation,
we should understand that RL is a very general purpose
tool for trying to solve pi.
It makes very few assumptions.
As a consequence, it is statistically very weak.
So it's kind of--
I mean this with much love, but it's the thing
you should do if you don't know how to do something better,
roughly.
And I mean that RL research is very good.
I've done it.
That's what my thesis was on.
But I also think that there's a lot of things
we know of from control, and they
should be blended together.
And there's many ways to find pi.
In particular, today, I think there's
a shortcut, which is we can talk about behavior cloning.
And the reason I want to take that shortcut
is because RL has a lot of challenges with it
in terms of sample efficiency, in terms of just
whether it's going to converge or not.
And it mixes up questions about the fundamental questions
of representation of the policy, is putting cameras in.
What should my architecture be?
What should my action space be, my observation space be?
It mixes up all these questions with did my RL algorithm
perform well?
Did I feed it and give it enough samples
or give it enough rollouts?
Did I roll it?
All these different things.
And I think you can sort of slice those down the middle
if you take a shortcut and try to do behavior cloning instead.
So what is behavior cloning?
Behavior cloning is a subset of imitation learning.
Imitation learning is also known as learning from demonstration.
OK.
I would say there's kind of two major camps
in imitation learning.
One of them would be sort of the behavior cloning,
where the goal is to try to use supervised learning
to mimic a demonstration.
And the other big branch would be inverse optimal control.
Or inverse RL, similar.
Where instead of trying to basically take a demonstration
and learn the policy directly, you
might try to learn the cost function, then do planning.
Or control or some other form.
So these are kind of the two big camps in imitation learning.
I think behavior cloning is immediately useful for us.
And it's very popular right now.
And it's producing just amazing demonstrations and manipulation.
So the basic setup is, if I have a human demonstrating
we'll talk about how they demonstrated
examples of dexterous manipulation on a robot,
you could think of that as feeding me input output
data, the sensor to action map.
And if I just want to find a function which
describes the same map from sensors to actions,
that's almost a supervised learning problem.
Certainly I can apply supervised learning techniques
to try to train pi.
That's the behavior cloning paradigm.
It's an old paradigm, sorry.
This is 1995, but '89, '90 are the papers
that are sort of the seminal papers in the field.
But maybe they're harder to Google
because this is Australian.
But already there was a rich understanding
of behavior cloning, its promise and its problems early on.
And I think we've only continued to understand
how to make it work well and its limitations.
So the biggest limitations in behavior learning,
I can sort of--
let me see, I think I have a couple of good examples here.
So this is one of the early examples
of how you might provide that imitation learning
data for a robot.
That's Zoe.
That's a PR2.
PR2 is still alive upstairs?
Yeah, just barely.
This is obviously the virtual reality interface.
Actually, if you watch this video,
you'll see that the initial version that they used
had sort of like robot gripper, special purpose robot grippers
you had right there with IMUs on them.
She had a little claw on her hand
and was manipulating things through the eyes of the robot,
which is important because if you
want to give exactly the same inputs and outputs
to your policy, then you really need
to use the same actuators as your robot
and give the same sensor readings based
on the same sensor readings.
In the paper that they wrote and then they
went on to use extensively, they switched
to a more commodity interface.
So it was just HTC Vive controllers in this.
But I think it's pretty cool to make a little PR2
hand for your fingers.
And there's a big question of just
like how much can you make that scale?
I'll show you some of the scaling efforts at the end.
But if you put that into a system
and just do supervised type learning on it,
that's how we did some--
really, I think this is what changed
my mind about behavior cloning and about visual motor policies.
It was just like really, really impressive for me,
robust controllers that came out of this thing, which
were making--
the hallmark of these controllers
is that they are making real-time decisions based
on the camera-based feedback, as opposed to stop,
perceive the world, make a plan, go.
These things, as you knock them around,
they're constantly adjusting via the camera-based feedback.
The value of doing that is just so high
that we're in a regime right now where our control synthesis
algorithms, I think, are relatively weak.
But I'd rather apply a weak algorithm on a rich input
and get this kind of feedback out.
So there's a couple of things that people definitely
know about behavior cloning that I want to communicate here,
some of the big ideas and things to watch out for.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
The first one is distribution shift.
I'll just write them up here real quick, and we'll begin.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
, OK.
So what's this problem of distribution shift?
So I said we've got a bunch of input/output data.
We have a bunch of examples of y coming in, u going out,
that we got from Zoe or somebody else tele-opting our robot.
Pete did it a lot in the videos that are on the screen
right now.
So you can use supervised learning to train.
But I think Drew Bagnell, for instance,
says behavior cloning, imitation learning is not
equal to supervised learning.
Even though we can use the same gradient descent type
algorithms to train it, there's some really important
differences.
The biggest difference is because of feedback.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
And the classic example-- I don't think you can really do
it better than the driving example, which
is what everybody uses.
So if I've got someone training my autonomous car to drive,
or my video game car, and Drew's original work for it,
and I've got a bunch of examples of people driving and staying
in the lane, then I've got a bunch of data,
u equals pi of y.
Maybe this one only requires instantaneous y.
If I have an approximation that I
get from supervised learning that's pretty close,
maybe it's the original plus just some epsilon.
I've got an epsilon perfect supervision-based loss.
Then what happens is after a single run,
I've predicted almost perfectly.
But now I'm maybe slightly away from where
I was on the original training data.
And what happens in the case where I take my output,
that's now the new state when I pass it through the controller
and I feed it back through, then I can quickly drift away.
Whereas the original training data maybe
has lots of data in the lane, it doesn't
take very much to have compounding errors
and instability, which quickly takes my system off
the original training data.
And it has no idea what to do once it's away from the data.
And you'll spiral out of control.
Bad things for autonomous cars.
So this is the problem of distribution shift.
Why is that called distribution shift?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It's reviewing the training distribution
that we saw.
PROFESSOR: Right.
The training distribution is some distribution here.
The closed loop distribution is very different, right?
The on-policy distribution.
All right.
So how do you fix that?
[WRITING]
People know the fix?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: The Dagger--
PROFESSOR: Dagger's algorithm is Drew's version
of the algorithm, absolutely.
I would say-- so it stands for data aggregation.
For me, I always think of first teacher forcing,
which is similar in spirit.
Dagger added the analysis, I would say,
to the teacher forcing idea, which is basically
keep the demonstrator in the loop
as you start giving control to your policy.
So the teacher forcing version, which
is the older kind of version of it, it's Williams '89.
It was the--
1989, that is.
This is the real-time recurrent learning paper
that I learned about a long time ago, right?
They basically said, OK, you have this problem where you're
going to drift away from your data.
So what you should do is you should start
by training with only the data that's
coming from your original demonstrations.
But then keep the demonstrator in the loop
and slowly add control.
Maybe there's a knob from--
alpha goes from 0 to 1, right?
And at the beginning, it's completely driven by the human
and 0 on the controller.
And I start slowly moving the knob,
taking the training wheels off, and letting the controller
drive, as opposed to just immediately stopping
the demonstrations and starting the policy driving.
The reason for that is you start--
if you can keep the training wheels on,
then you'll start to get data that is off the original human
only demonstrations.
The policy, when it's on a little bit,
will pull me away, but the human will pull me back.
The demonstrator will pull me back.
And it starts to broaden the distribution.
And similarly, as the policy gets trained off
the nominal trajectory, it will become a stable system and not
an unstable system.
And it will tend to stay close to the original data.
Dagger is the one that Drew came up with,
which is data aggregation.
It gave some nice analysis to that, talking about the--
if you assume just you have an epsilon erring policy,
then you get cascading errors.
You get something that grows at least the squared of your time
horizon.
And you can, by just feeding back in extra supervisory data,
the simplest case would actually be just let your human provide
sensory supervision on the bad data.
And you throw that into your system to aggregate,
and you can sort of remedy this basic problem.
So teacher forcing, or somehow keeping the human in the loop,
is a good remedy for this problem.
Data augmentation is another big one.
And people have done this for autonomous driving.
NVIDIA did this famously for autonomous driving.
They basically just took their original data.
They actually had cameras facing off to the left
and to the right, looking sort of this way
and looking this way, so they could make real data that
looked like it was a little bit off in the wrong direction.
And they basically said, the human
told me to drive like this, but I'm
going to augment my data with a simple corrective policy.
That if I hallucinated myself, I didn't actually
get data off this, off the main trajectory.
But I'll hallucinate that I was off the trajectory
and would have taken the simple stabilizing controller
that would have gotten me back to the human-based data.
And that's data augmentation.
That's one approach to data augmentation.
In fact, Pete and Lucas used data augmentation,
a very similar form of data augmentation in that work,
where they basically, as they pushed the hat or the box
around, they would just take their data set
and just add random pose perturbations
to the object they were pushing, and then just move it back
towards basically the next frame in the data.
Assume that the finger would have pushed it back
into the trajectory that the data actually followed.
And you hear over and over again,
people that are training these behavior cloning policies,
they're like, if you don't do this, it just doesn't work.
You will not get a good policy out.
A little bit of data augmentation,
it works amazingly well.
There's other ways that people do it.
People do it by just adding noise directly
into the supervisory signal.
So another version of this would be--
I know we've said Dart four times in the class,
but Mike Lasky had a version, I think in probably '17
or something like that, where you basically add
noise to the demonstrator.
[TYPING]
It lives in this space clearly.
But basically, right as the demonstrator
is doing their thing, you take their action as a suggestion,
you add some random noise to it.
It causes this same sort of walkabout behavior,
and it causes you to get some data off the nominal policy
that is supervised by the human.
And if you just get enough data in the vicinity,
then that can already solve the problem.
There are other interesting ideas.
I've seen people do forecasting models, where you don't just
predict the next step in the trajectory,
but you try to predict an entire rollout.
That's, I think, a popular thing.
But yeah, just to say there are many other ideas out there.
So let's see how that plays out here for this example.
By the way, this is just some, I guess, hot off the press,
just a teaser of some of the behavior cloning work
that's happening at TRI.
But they're getting this stuff to work for incredibly
hard manipulation problems now.
So you can roll dough.
I don't even know what the state space
would be for these problems.
We can have-- there's Eric Cousineau
wrote a beautiful little joystick controller that
would drive both pandas around and spent very little time,
surprisingly little time, rolling the dough.
And now he can walk up, he can pick it up,
he can throw the dough down, and it'll just--
all day long, it'll sit there rolling the dough.
And C1's-- we're thinking about lots of food preparation
kind of examples.
And C1's got it doing a lot of the sort of kitchen type tasks.
He's just-- the form of antagonization
you can do when someone's trying to put an egg on your plate
is minimal, but it's using constant real time
camera-based feedback to do these kind of things.
It's shockingly powerful.
But maybe misleadingly so.
So I think it makes incredible demos.
And the question is really, can you
make it robust enough to field for the real system?
So let me just tell you how Pete and Lucas did
their version of it.
So we took the same sort of deep network front end.
And there's lots of different ways
people try to choose the z, the output of the deep network
perception part, to put into a small policy.
Pete and Lucas had just done their dense descriptor work.
So they chose to have dense descriptors
as the representation that they would put into their policy.
And they asked the question that, how does that perform
compared to some other choices for z
based on autoencoders or other kind of representations?
So the idea was, you remember the dense descriptors, right?
So we have some canonical colors.
If d equals 3, then we could render the descriptors
of the object as colors.
And you would basically just pick
some small number of random values
in this dense descriptor space and try to find--
at runtime, you would find the closest points
in the current image to those values.
And you just give the x, y, z location
of those dense descriptors.
You could think of this as an unsupervised form of key
points.
You push those into the policy.
And maybe that's a very good representation for some tasks.
I think it's a very good representation.
OK, so the setup looks like this.
And I'm actually going to try to reconstruct this so you guys
can play with it in simulation and have the whole pipeline.
So in simulation, there was a couple of tests
that was just pushing a box around or flipping up a box.
We have a mouse space.
You can see the teleop on the real robot.
This case, they actually wrote a simple hand-designed controller
and just tried to clone from a hand-designed controller
into the neural network as a unit test
just to make sure all the cloning was working,
all the dense descriptors were working,
and everything like that.
But even just a mouse--
so Pete didn't have a virtual reality interface.
He was just watching, standing there next to the robot,
using a mouse and keyboard, and did very effective teleop.
This was flipping up a shoe.
He got pretty good at it.
There is a thing where you can have
people that are good at demonstrations or not
good at demonstrations.
And that's for reason number two, primarily,
which we're going to talk about.
OK, the network representation there
was an LSTM because it seemed-- first of all,
the hand-designed controller that pushed the box
did have some internal state.
It had some notion of, was it in contact with the box yet or not?
So when they wrote the controller by hand,
they decided that it was useful to have a state variable.
And in fact, it turned out that having a small network of--
a recurrent network actually did outperform
the non-recurrent versions.
This one, I didn't-- did that play fast?
Yeah.
I think I was talking about flipping up the box at the time
and they did it pretty easily.
OK, it's a very useful pipeline, very powerful.
We talked about the distribution shift problem.
The second problem-- and it's a real one, a big one--
is this multimodal demonstrations.
So in the simplest model here, we'd
like it to be that the controller is-- in our simplest
form, if I say u equals pi of y, and let's just
say it's a static function, you'd
like it to be a perfect function of y,
that there's not ever two--
let's see-- a situation in your data
where y is the same value and there's different u's that come
out, a perfect function.
And this comes up all the time, even in optimal control
problems.
So if you remember the example I used for motion planning
last time of just going left or right around the box,
where I had my goal up here, my start down here,
and there was a solution that went like this,
and there's a solution that went like this.
So even if I have an optimal controller,
they're not always unique.
In this situation right here, there's
two perfectly valid optimal decisions I could make.
Those are both perfectly good control decisions.
If you've asked someone to tele-op your robot,
and they ever found themselves in the same state
and made slightly different decisions,
decided to go left one time and right another time,
then you've got an optimization problem
where you're trying to fit a function to something that's
not described by a function.
So this is the problem of having sort
of multimodal demonstrations.
And there's a few ways that people address it.
So you can have your network can output a multimodal--
a full distribution.
Right?
For instance, a mixture of Gaussians or something
like that.
I would say that's the standard thing that people try to do.
It gets to be a harder optimization problem,
of course, but oftentimes, if your policy--
you actually output a full distribution,
you can hopefully capture that full multimodal demonstration.
There are other approaches, too.
Pete has gone on and recently-- in fact,
he's at Coral right now.
The conference on robot learning is happening right now.
So it's a good time for me to be talking about this stuff.
He's got a new paper that he just presented,
which is, I think, really nice, called
"Implicit Behavior Cloning," which
is using energy-based methods.
I'm going to show you the videos.
It's pretty awesome.
So instead of u equals pi of y, he's
using a Yan-Lacoon-style energy-based method.
He tried to say u is argmin of u prime some energy u prime y.
So you learn a function that you have
to optimize in order to make your control decision.
And he's got some fantastic examples of making this work.
I encourage you, actually, to read the paper.
But it was released today.
He's got the same kind of examples,
but things that wouldn't have worked with the original.
For instance, trying to get this into a tight area.
You see-- I think he's got a bigger view of that.
Yeah, here we go.
So his argument here is that this was a very hard policy
to capture because of sharp discontinuities
and possibly multimodal demonstrations.
Did you see right there how the demonstrator
had a very similar state of the block and the hand?
And they took a very different corrective action
in order to nudge the thing here.
I think we're going to see it right here.
Watch right as it comes in here.
Very similar state.
Oh, that was not the one.
OK, right there.
That little corrective action is like a super small difference
in the controller, but to a very large difference in the policy.
And those things can really wreak havoc
on an existing supervised learning pipeline.
So roughly, they tried to learn the functions differently
so that they could represent discontinuities better
and potentially multimodal behaviors better.
OK, this is my favorite sort of generalization
that I've seen in a while of it's basically
just the blocks pushing task.
But it's brilliant because it's got
all kinds of logical components.
These things are going to get mixed up and be--
it's got the physics of the basic pushing a block around,
but the logic of trying to have to separate things by color
and potentially move the blue ones first out of the way
and then the yellow ones.
I think it's a really, really nice example.
I'd love to code it up myself.
But this is just continuing to show the power, I'd say,
of these kind of approaches.
A few other ideas here.
So people talk about a major limitation of behavior cloning
is that it's only as good as its demonstrators.
Now, that's-- I'll turn this down here a little bit.
OK, it's actually interesting.
The first behavior cloning papers argued differently.
They actually said that because of a robot's steady hand,
you basically, you filter, you have no feedback delays,
you can be better than your demonstrator.
OK, maybe a little bit.
Roughly speaking, people feel, I think,
bottlenecked by the quality of their demonstrations.
And that's a major motivation for the inverse optimal
control, to say somehow that the behavior cloning is doing
the dumb thing, that it's just trying to copy the demonstrator
without any understanding of its intent.
And I think that if you can try to, from demonstrations,
extract something higher level and put it through a planner,
you could potentially do much better.
And these things produce amazing demos,
but they really can be very narrow demos.
I think this is a big question of how--
if you can put the right features in or out in order
to get broader generalization.
But a lot of times, these demos look incredibly good,
work incredibly well inside the training data,
but then they fall down as soon as you go anywhere
off the training data.
OK, so that leads me to maybe the last point
I want to make here, which is where
do you get the training data?
[TAPPING]
There's some really clever ideas out there
about how to sort of scale this stuff up.
One of them is this Form2Fit project.
Kevin Zaka is a friend, and I think this is just so clever.
So they wanted to do a kidding task.
And there's more to the paper than what I'm mentioning now,
but they wanted to basically solve this problem of putting
objects into the bin.
And that's a very hard thing to--
you could take a long time to demonstrate
a lot of careful assemblies.
So what they did is they had basically the clutter clearing
kind of example we had.
They just had it disassemble all day long, automatically.
And then they just said, well, the opposite of that,
that if I time reverse the disassembly,
that's a pretty good demonstration of the assembly.
And they generated a bunch of supervision-based data
that just inverted time.
Super clever idea.
This is the paper, the Learning from Play paper,
which I think is also pretty compelling.
So they're saying that asking humans
to demonstrate one task at a time is maybe unnecessary
and potentially gives very narrow demonstration data.
So I think they gave a system, but they also
gave a pretty compelling argument
that if you just give people a robot simulator to play with,
they're going to do all kinds of crazy stuff.
If there's a button in the simulator,
they're totally going to make the robot press the button.
And actually, if you just go through and then effectively
label all--
similar to the form to fit, but basically,
if you take every trajectory that's rolling out,
anytime it visited a state in the simulator,
you have a trajectory that the human chose to execute
that got to that state in the world.
And if you wanted to use that as now demonstrations
to achieve that particular state,
you've got a trajectory that takes you to that state.
And they argue pretty convincingly, I think,
that it's not arbitrary-- that these are very
goal-directed behaviors.
It's not somehow random exploration
that you'd get if you were doing just random search
in the control inputs.
But it's got a very directed--
humans are choosing sub-goals.
They're executing them, and that you can actually just leverage
a pretty broad distribution of data
that way to train a more general agent.
And then there are people that are trying
to scale things up.
So this is the RoboTurk project, which
is on-- has gotten more mature now.
But this is one of their early versions,
where they're basically saying, let's
make it possible for people to tele-op with their iPhone.
You've got an IMU in your iPhone.
What if you use-- so if everybody who's got an iPhone
has a tele-op device, and we put a simulator in front of them,
then we can basically crowdsource tele-op.
And now they have these pretty massive data sets
that have come out of online demonstration data.
So I think it's a big question of whether you--
how far you really need to go--
how far you can go with human-based demonstrations
for the more dexterous manipulation.
All right, how does it fit with--
we talked about force control, impedance control.
We've talked about a couple of different approaches here.
The output of the network I wrote is just u so far, right?
In an arbitrary way.
But what is u?
In most of these tasks, people--
they will choose, for instance, an end-effector velocity,
let's say, or end-effector position or delta position.
[TAPPING]
And that means you're running a differential IK
or something-- this controller on top of that,
or an impedance controller or something on top of that
to do that, right?
So I think it's pretty rare that people actually
try to put torques out of the bottom of this thing, right?
It's often putting some clever controller,
whether it's an impedance controller or a force
controller-- if you had a task that was more assembly or more
welding or more handwriting or something like this,
you'd probably want to do some sort of force or stiffness
control down here, OK?
So I don't think this technology replaces
the sort of mechanics-based low-level, high-gain feedback
control that we know how to do well.
But it can send very interesting, rich commands
down inside of them, right?
All right.
So I think behavior cloning is this very clever way
to, like I said, separate out the question of,
how do you train the weights?
And is the representation of the policy
sufficient to do incredible tasks, right?
And we see over and over again-- this
has really been happening in the last few years--
people have incredible results of neural networks
solving really hard, dexterous tasks from vision, right?
So I think we've really made a lot of progress
in understanding the representational power
of these controllers.
The big question now is, if you don't
have to have everybody demonstrate,
how do you actually train those controllers?
So we'll take the RL approach next week.
Good, happy Veterans Day.