Hi, everybody.
OK.
Today we're back to-- I'm trying to give you kind of a-- not
a ping pong, but maybe a smoothly swinging pendulum
back and forth between deep networks and mechanics
and forces and stuff like this.
So today the pendulum swings back towards forces,
all the way to force control.
Let me just start quickly by giving you
an update on the projects on the administrative side.
So thank you for submitting your project proposals.
Those of you in 6.800, you're going
to do the peer review on Friday.
And we are trying to get our feedback to you this weekend
also.
So basically, take a breather.
Around the end of this weekend, you'll
get all of the feedback from your peers and from us.
And then a week from this Friday,
you'll be submitting the final project proposal.
So I hope you're continuing to think about it,
but no urgent items until we give you feedback
at the end of the week.
OK, so today is about force control.
Now, a lot of people today do manipulation
without thinking as much about force control.
And like I said, there's a lot of useful tasks
where really pick and place does a lot of work.
But it doesn't solve everything.
And even for the situations we've already given you,
there's a need, I think, for force control.
So I don't know if you saw the notes.
I sort of cracked myself up because I just randomly--
I generated like 10,000 random images.
And it just happens that random image number 9,964
or something like this looks like this.
And I just happened to have it open on my screen one day.
I was like, how the heck are you going
to pick that up, that Cheez-It box,
with your two-fingered gripper?
You can't do an enveloping grasp.
You'll never get an over-the-head,
antipodal grasp on the Cheez-It box.
And you can't get under it to pick it up antipodally.
You've got to do something more clever
if you want to get that Cheez-It box out of the bin.
So I kind of by accident had generated a bunch of examples
that I think you really need something
more than what we've given you so far to do.
So I asked my daughter, I said, OK, get the box--
this is the two-fingered gripper I had in my kitchen.
And she starts doing all this clever stuff
to get the pasta out of the bin.
And it's not what we've been doing before.
It's like using environmental contacts.
It's using very clever strategies,
multi-part strategies.
She's older now.
Well, she's in middle school now.
But that was cheating.
I said, no, no, put that back.
That didn't count.
But people are amazing.
We do things so naturally.
And I'll try to make that point a few times when we're
thinking about free body diagrams
and exactly what's going on.
Some of the things she did in there are actually amazing.
Writing the equations to make that happen with your robot
is amazing.
It would be hard.
So that's kind of what we're going to try to do today.
And I want to give a few good examples, I hope,
of what force control is and simple enough
that we can think through the equations,
think through the implications.
So there's some canonical examples of force control.
Right.
That was it.
That was my example.
Did you see that?
Right?
There's another good one.
This is actually really good.
That's really good.
If I didn't do force control there,
that just wouldn't have worked very well.
If I had my arm rigidly following some position
trajectory, you would have gotten something like this.
If I estimated the orientation of the board just a little bit
wrong, it would have looked like this.
And if you've ever tried to write something with a robot,
you've seen things like that probably.
Or worse, you'd have like broken chalk on the bottom of the--
because it went a little bit into the board.
And same thing for the force control of a racing.
You're really doing something pretty subtle
about sort of pushing into the board
and regulating those forces.
Now, whether we're regulating them to the micro-Newton level,
probably not.
It can be fairly approximate.
But I think there's some level of trying
to sort of regulate forces that really does matter.
So more seriously, if I think about force control
versus position control, I don't think
it's strictly one or the other.
So versus is kind of a straw man.
But the impression I want-- so sometimes you
will hear people talk about force control
as in it's just this completely different thing.
And it has these completely different concepts
about impedance and admittance and other things
that you'll understand a bit today.
And that it's just completely divorced from position control.
And I've never liked that.
You can take a low level force controller
and basically wrap it up and do position control
through your force control loop.
And if you have a lower level position controller,
you can act like a force controller on top of it.
It's a matter of what do you want your core controller
to be, the thing that's running at the highest bandwidth
down at your robot.
What is your robot trying to act like given the tightest
loop between your controller, your amp, and your physics.
And there are times where choosing
to act like a force down at the lower level,
to close a loop on a force sensor,
can be a better choice than trying to be like a position.
And there are some tasks at the higher level
where it's more natural to describe
the controller in terms of desired forces
than in terms of desired positions.
You can get more robust performance
without worrying about the exact location of the board
by specifying your task with force commands instead
of with position commands.
And we'll see ways that you can walk back and forth
between them.
But it's really-- it's an addition.
It plays nicely with position control.
And we'll see ways that they can all be put together.
So the organization-- we've got two lectures on control,
if you will, of your robots.
Today, if you'll permit me, I'm going to basically assume
the robot is a point.
So we're going to-- a point finger, assume a spherical
robot.
Actually, spheres are too hard.
We're the point robot.
And then we're going to think of that as,
what if I could control perfectly
the end effector of my robot?
And the end effector is a point.
And we'll add the robot back in on Thursday
and all the details of making that abstraction that we're
trying to create at the point, at the contact point,
be good for the robot.
So today, we'll do the point finger approximation.
And I basically like to use this sort of flipping up
the Cheez-It box as a running example.
I think that there's a lot we can
do on that pretty simple problem.
So I'm going to show you graphics and draw
on the board this basic problem.
I've got a box.
Maybe I'll make it even pink since I've got enough colors.
And that would make sense.
I've got my Cheez-It box.
We're going to think a bit about the way
that the-- we've already talked a bit about the way
the forces of the Cheez-It box can
be modeled with the ground.
If I'm being careful, which I was in my examples,
I put some specific little contact points here just
to make sure that when I'm running the simulation,
the solver doesn't have to arbitrarily pick some place
on the square to choose its forces.
It's going to have a force here that it computes
and a force here that it computes.
And those forces are going to have some friction
cone that are a response to when the thing's at rest.
I've got gravity pulling down on this.
And those forces are going to balance.
There's actually-- everything I'm simulating is in 3D.
I'm just drawing it in 2D.
And then we're going to add in our--
let's make it blue here--
our point finger.
OK?
And the task is to do something like my daughter did there.
Let's try to flip up the Cheez-It box
so that we can come in with our two-finger gripper next.
And that's a task that I think is natively described naturally
in the language of forces.
[SCOFFS]
I'll just give one more example because it's a good one,
I think.
But this is another good example of something
that's native in forces.
OK?
So you want to push the book to the edge of the table.
If you can rely on the assumption
that the forces-- the friction between the hand and the book
is larger than the forces between the book and the table,
then that's a kind of strategy where you need to put yourself
in a regime where you're not pushing too hard,
such that the book sticks on the table,
but you're not pushing too softly, that you're
in this nice regime where moving the hand
moves the book on the table.
OK?
That's another example of how you pick up
one of these big things, move it to the side.
All right.
So this is roughly the regime that we're going to be in here.
Point finger, contact forces between the box and the sphere,
right?
Again, with the sphere, the small point finger,
then I know exactly where my contact forces are.
I don't have to worry about all the complicated geometry.
And once I've tilted up, I know exactly
that I'm going to have contact forces on that back corner.
OK?
So let's think about the way to work through sort of that.
so the entire configuration space
of this system, my Q vector, right?
It has elements for both the sphere geometry,
you know, the finger, and it has elements for the Cheez-It box,
right?
Since the sphere is-- we're modeling as a point here,
not worrying about its rotation at all,
I'll just write x double dot of the finger, z double dot--
sorry, just writing the cubes first-- z of the finger.
And then I've got x of the box, z of the box,
theta of the box, OK?
Because I've pinned the box.
I added an artificial joint just so it can only
move in 2D, a planar joint, OK?
So if I were to write-- the simulator
is implementing these equations we've
showed you many times before.
All right, we've got some equations of motion.
Some of them are due to the finger.
Some of them are due to the box.
In these equations, if you've come
to be a little bit more comfortable with them, right?
If you were to write out these equations,
you would see that this is-- there's
two systems here that are only connected
through the contact forces.
So you would see the mass matrix, for instance,
would have entries here for the finger,
entries down here for the box.
They don't have any coupling terms.
They're only coupled through the forces, right?
If they're not touching, wiggling the finger around
doesn't do anything to the box.
It doesn't cause any accelerations on the box.
OK, so let's just write the top two equations out, OK?
So I'll do-- there's also-- there's a mass of the finger,
and there's a mass of the box, OK?
But I'll try to remember to put my subscripts in there.
OK, so it's chosen intentionally to be particularly simple.
I'm going to assume that I have this perfect torque
source or force source on the coordinates of the box--
or of the finger, rather.
So I can basically just do this plus any contact forces.
There's only one contact, so I'll just leave it like this.
And it's only the x component here.
OK, so this is just the first row of this, OK,
in the x-coordinate.
It just happens that gravity doesn't affect me
at all in the x direction, so this term didn't contribute.
It's a point mass, so there's no Coriolis terms, OK?
And the Jacobian is the identity matrix, right?
So it's intentionally chosen to-- and of course,
you know this is just a free body, f equals ma, right?
But it fits-- it's just the first row of that.
OK, and similarly, mz--
sorry, mf z double dot f is going to be uz z.
And then I've got minus mg.
I do have gravity terms there, OK?
And the way I've parametrized f here, since f is positive here,
it is actually the way this arrow is looking here.
So it's-- although that's only because the arrow is
hidden inside there, but this direction.
So the force here, the coordinate frame,
is that positive forces are the box--
it's the box pushing on the sphere, OK?
All right, so our goal is going to be
to come up with a strategy to flip up the box,
reasoning about forces, reasoning
about the contact forces.
And we're writing a controller, right,
which means we're going to write some equations to be implemented
as u right here, or in the system's view.
Got my plant here with u coming in.
These equations are inside the plant, right?
And I'm going to write a force controller here, which
is going to take in q and q dot, potentially.
It might take in other things.
For instance, it could take in a desired force.
And then there's a really interesting question here
of what else do you give it, OK?
So these are sort of-- you'd expect
to know your position and velocity, x and z,
of the finger, so that's fine to give this, OK?
You could give it the box or not.
If we're only doing force control on the finger,
you can actually just have this be the subset
that is the finger.
But there's a big question of what else do you
hand your force controller, OK?
And some natural choices would be a force sensor.
And if you see a lot of robots that
are trying to do force control type tasks,
have some interesting arm, but they put a force torque
sensor at the wrist, right?
So they're only touching the world and controlling forces
through a specific force torque sensor.
If you don't have a force torque sensor,
you can potentially do some of the same work
by giving accelerations.
You know, q double dot.
That's always a little bit risky business,
because we've said it a few times,
but you kind of expect to be able to measure your joint
angles.
You kind of expect to be able to measure your joint velocities.
When you start trying to get joint accelerations,
that tends to be noisy signals, unless you're
measuring them very directly.
You don't try to inject too noisy of signals into here.
Some people do it.
You can also do a lot of interesting things
if you assume--
if you are in the mode of trying to think about it
as you're putting in accelerations,
but I'm not going to measure the accelerations.
I'm going to assume everything's moving pretty slowly
and that accelerations are effectively zero,
that the any terms that are being contributed
by the inertial dynamics are small compared
to the contact forces and my applied forces.
So there's also an idea of trying
to do quasi-static approximations, which
I'll use to start, because it's easier, which
is-- this is a little less precise than I'd like.
Maybe I should be a little bit--
actually, that inertial terms are small relative
to the other terms, to gravity, fc, and u.
What really matters is the mass times acceleration.
So let's say our goal of our force controller
is to take a desired force in, command a u
to achieve a desired force out.
That's a pretty-- algebraically, we
can do something that looks pretty natural
and see if we decide it makes sense.
OK.
If we assume that our accelerations are small
and those terms are small, then a pretty reasonable strategy
would be to say, I'm going to just command in the x command,
in my x force, something that looks like that.
And I'll command in my z, plus mg.
So if you were to assume these terms are small,
stick those into the equation, not think at all about
where force is coming from, you'd be pretty happy.
You could write down something that says,
well, force of contact is going to look
like force contact desired.
Now, of course, you can't just make force out of nowhere.
Those force of contact are actually
coming from the interaction forces.
The physics engine's going to solve
for some complicated relation to decide that.
But let's see what happens when we do this.
OK.
So let's think about the case of a constant force.
So let's say that fc of d, I'll just
let it be 0 in the z direction, and some constant,
some positive constant greater than 0 in the x direction.
And let's say I start off in my configuration--
yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
I'm going to-- actually, that's exactly what
I'm asking about right now.
So the question was, are we assuming
breaking or breaking contact?
So great question.
Let's suss that out.
So let's start away from contact and just apply this controller.
So if I use this as my controller,
this would be my first instance of a direct force control,
where I'm directly trying to command a force.
What's going to happen?
So if fc desired, my desired-- I'm
hoping that I'm going to get a force here,
using this equation, which made up--
and just assumed I could get arbitrary forces algebraically.
Uz is going to be 0--
it's going to be mg, so the total acceleration
is going to be 0.
I'm going to get z double dot equals 0.
And x double dot, if I stick it all in,
in actuality, the contact forces are 0.
So I'm commanding as if I expect it
to be a gulp against a wall or something like this,
but I'm not actually touching it at all.
The interesting thing is that it'll actually--
in order to try to get a force, it's
actually going to push me this way.
I'm going to apply a force this way.
So when I'm off the wall here, I'll
get something like mx double dot equals a constant.
That's just putting this into those equations
and seeing what comes out.
So Charles asked the question, so what
happens if I'm off contact and I'm
trying to do force control?
In many cases-- this is a particularly simple example--
in many cases, if you command a force
and you're not actually making contact,
your controller is sort of unjustified,
but it tends to do the right-- you can analyze it,
and it tends to often do the right thing.
So this will actually, when I'm off contact,
will drive me into contact.
Once I'm in contact, then this is a more reasonable attempt
to try to regulate the contact force.
That's a super important point.
So this is, I think, a hallmark of force control.
So I worked on walking robots for many years,
and oftentimes, you would program your legs,
the robot's legs, to be in position control mode
when you're swinging, because you'd
like to get your foot to be at whatever foothold you've
been thinking about.
So maybe when you're in swing, you actually
put yourself roughly in a position control mode.
But then when you go to step, and when you're in stance,
you're often in a force control mode,
but especially that first step.
Because what happens is if you have any--
just like my board being a little bit off calibration,
if my feet are at all uncertain about the terrain,
if I start asking for a force and my foot
is a little above the ground, then it
has the property that it's going to try to drive
my robot into the ground.
In the DARPA robotics challenge, where
we had this humanoid that was walking around,
and we really didn't want it to fall down,
so we had this way to make it a little bit more conservative.
If we didn't trust our sensor estimates of the terrain,
we would put it in stompy mode, where it would actually--
we would just aim a little high on the terrain
and then lean into the force controller.
And you could watch from--
I mean, probably most people would never notice.
I know Scott Kindersma and I, we were watching that.
It's stomping like crazy.
And Robin Dietz, all these guys, we were on the sideline.
Like, it's stomping right now.
So it's confused about where the terrain is.
But it would go like this, just a little bit harder.
And we'd be like, oh my gosh, don't fall down.
But that is also the reason why we love the force control,
just because asking for force when there's no force to give
tends to drive you into contact.
I mean, locally, of course.
If I was up here, it's just going to miss.
But if you're close to contact, it'll get you there.
OK, so what's going to happen now if I--
so if I choose some c that's greater than 0,
what are all the things that could possibly happen?
And I'm going to accelerate.
We agree that for a reasonable set of initial conditions,
I'm going to accelerate into the box.
OK, what happens then?
Let's think about small c, think about big C.
What are the different things that could possibly happen?
It's pretty subtle.
I mean, there's some things that are not subtle.
And there's some things that are subtle.
Let me make this a little farther away just
to get you to think about it.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
OK, good.
So you said-- so first of all, maybe if c is very small
and your finger is light, it didn't have enough time
to build up a lot of momentum, it could just get there
and the box might just sit there, sit still.
That's like the lowest regime.
It's going to move a little bit, right, because of the collision.
But basically, just sit still.
And there's going to be some momentum effect, of course,
from the collision.
But really, we know that there's going
to be some amount of horizontal force from friction.
It's going to be maybe even just equal to-- in this case,
it's going to be equal to mu times mg, where m of the box.
So I've got my friction cones here.
I've got normal forces that must match mg.
And I'm allowed to put as much force as I can here.
So it's going to be less than or equal to mg.
So if c is small and the collision is small,
then it could just sit there, sit still.
If c is a bit larger--
well, sorry, if c is very large, it's
just going to move the box.
It'll be above this friction threshold.
It'll start moving the box until it slams
into the wall on the other side.
And then it's going to stop, in this particular example.
What's interesting is that you can also see--
if you just run the simulation, you can also
see a pretty big regime in c, where the impact's enough
to start it moving, but the drag is enough
that it's slowly decelerating into the point
where it'll just kind of come to rest,
move a nontrivial amount, and then come to rest.
So I actually just made that plot here.
There it is here.
I can make that bigger.
Can I make that bigger?
So this is different commanded forces,
from small, the blue one, to large.
When it's small, it takes a while in time
to even make contact with the box.
See, the contact with the box is always
going to happen at the same vertical place.
This is time versus x.
So there's an actual location of the box.
Horizontally, things are happening
all at the same location.
If you're accelerating slowly, it'll
take a while to get there.
And then it'll basically just stop.
You go a little-- hit it a little faster,
moves just a little bit more, but it's basically
a stiction regime.
But there's this regime where you hit it,
and it'll start sliding, but it'll come to rest.
And then there's a regime where you just
slam it into the back wall.
And that's the collision with the back wall that happens.
And there's lots of different forces that'll get you there.
Bigger and bigger will just hit that wall.
But it's a pretty rich--
it's a super simple system, but it's
pretty rich for all the things it can do.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question is, am I assuming inelastic?
I'm not rigorously making that assumption.
In fact, the bouncing you see is a little bit of plasticity,
if you will, in that.
It's subtle.
This is coming from a time-stepping method that
allows a little bit of--
a soft contact model, those things together
can allow some bouncing.
But if you think about it, if I do bounce,
I'm going to push right back into myself immediately.
So you're not going to see a boing.
It's going to be shoved right back in there.
You're kind of pushing in.
It might bounce for a second, but it'll go right back in.
Good question.
And to some extent, only when you've
gotten all the way to the--
I didn't plot the force on that.
But only when the box really isn't moving
am I going to get the force that I expect out.
But it can still attempt to regulate the force
and do interesting things when it's doing that.
This model assumes that I'm sort of pushing up against the wall
and it's not moving.
And if I push more, I'll get more force.
And that's only true in the limit.
But the controller we got out of a very simple derivation
is still useful.
Now, but this picture I like very much.
I want to flip up the box.
Now, I originally was like, OK, I'm going to shove it
to the side and I'll flip it up there.
But my daughter, she just flipped it up
in the middle all the time.
I was like, OK, now I've got to figure out
how do we flip it up in the middle.
And it's pretty tough.
So I actually brought a box.
I brought some friction because I need friction
to make this work.
And I've got some variational principles and mechanics
inside the box, which is a great book, Cornelius Lenk shows,
if you haven't read it.
Good stuff.
OK, so if I'm pushing, it's not hard to make this thing go.
How do I make it flip up?
It's actually super hard to make it flip up.
OK, like I can just barely-- oh, no, I could do it upstairs.
Oh, man, I might have to take Lenk shows out.
Shoot.
You'd think that would be worse, but let me just try.
Oh, man, it's too slippery here.
Well, this is totally cheating.
But maybe I made my point, right?
It's pretty subtle to get this thing into a regime
where you're controlling the contact forces enough
to sort of flip it up.
If I have a lot of friction, my friction cone is bigger,
then that allows me to have a bigger range of forces
I can apply here to tip it up.
Interestingly, I want you to really appreciate,
like if nothing else, at the end of this class,
I hope you watch yourself loading the dishwasher,
because it's super impressive.
Like if I were to pick this up at the end of lecture,
I'm going to do something like this.
And I'm going to put my hand down here and provide exactly--
like on the free body diagram, that's
exactly the right thing to do.
I'm going to make that--
I'm going to help out the friction
by with a little bit of force here, tip it up.
I do it all the time.
People do it all the time.
We're so good at these things.
And if you think about all the subtle physics that
happens to make that happen, it's really, really impressive.
And I think it's a gap between what our robots are doing
and what we're doing.
OK.
But if I'm in the land of knowing the friction
coefficient, being able to regulate contact forces,
and I have a robot that can apply contact forces more
accurately than my hand, then I can
try to do this thing that I failed to do experimentally
right here.
So what's that going to look like?
What I'd like to do is think about having only friction
here.
So I'm allowed to have friction here and the normal force
I'm going to apply a force here.
I also have a friction cone here based on my normal forces,
right?
Equal and opposite force.
So I'm only allowed to apply-- that's partly what happens.
This box is a little slippery.
I'm only allowed to apply forces inside this friction cone.
Otherwise, my finger will slip right up the box.
So the game becomes, can you find
a force in this friction cone that
stays inside that friction cone--
so there's enough force to keep my point from slipping--
that will rotate up the box?
OK.
Now, you're not going to be surprised.
And I wrote the whole derivation out in the notes.
But I like doing that with constrained least squares.
That's a good-- locally, it looks like a least squares
problem.
And this friction cone constraint
can be locally approximated as a linear constraint.
And I basically wrote a little controller
that sort of flips up the box.
OK?
I hope you run these yourselves, because they're fun
and they're good to think about, too.
But-- oops.
Oh, nice.
That happened last time, too.
Sorry.
OK.
[CLICKS TONGUE]
Um-- it's worth it.
I promise.
OK.
Why would that not work?
Hm.
I'll just do it again.
I'm going to run out of NGROC licenses.
So I shouldn't do that.
[CLEARS THROAT]
I have an idea.
[CLICKS TONGUE]
Darn it.
Would you guys try to click on it, maybe, for a second,
if I keep talking?
Well, I guess I can just-- I'll just restart the notebook
and talk, and then I'll redo it here.
That's the bad one, but I'll do it.
OK.
Suspend your disbelief for a second.
That'll work in, like, 3 and 1/2 minutes or something.
But-- OK.
So, I mean, the controller that I wrote for this
is effectively thinking about a virtual angle like this.
I can parameterize the orientation of the box
however I like.
But if I do it relative to vertical,
I basically implemented a small PID controller
that tries to say, I'm going to apply a force that is making--
I made theta desired be some slow from the initial angle
up to the top.
And then I followed theta desired.
I wrote a controller that was thinking about tracking theta
desired with my torque about theta
is like k theta desired minus theta actual estimated,
plus b theta dot desired minus theta dot,
in this, like, simplified coordinates.
I took that as a command, asked for the closest
I could do to executing this, subject to the friction cone
constraints.
And I give myself something that I can actually just sort of
follow, almost prescribe the theta trajectory up
to some friction limits.
If you start-- and I hope you do play with the notebook, right?
So if you start making mu small, then it's
going to, at some point, say, I can't find you a solution.
I can't execute that controller.
Even zero force would violate something.
But in the regime where that is happy and good,
it's pretty fun.
It works pretty well.
OK, almost there.
Ask some questions for a second, because I really
don't want to-- I want to show you that before I go on too
much.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Great question.
So the question was, isn't it always
going to be the case that I should
be applying a force that's on the boundary of the friction
cone?
Yes, but the question is how hard--
so the direction of the force, I would expect,
would always want to be on the friction cone.
Or certainly, there's a solution that would always
want to be on the friction cone.
But if you push too hard there, when
you're on that friction cone, you're
pushing both this way and that way.
So there's some limit based on the geometry
of that friction cone for which you can achieve some rate.
And the faster you go here, the faster you turn up.
But at some point, you'll slip.
So you're right.
Yep, I think you're right.
I might have even done that.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: When you set it up like this,
can you account for the fact that increasing
the force of the push will change the friction cone
at the bottom?
It'll reduce the normal force?
PROFESSOR: Yeah, yes, good.
So the total force here, the force balance,
is that this is also contributing to vertical.
That's a super good point.
So that's also contributing to vertical,
which is then fighting against mg, which reduces
the total friction here.
And I think all those are in the equations.
These are all simple enough that the free body diagram is just
completely written out.
OK, back in business.
Kind of takes the oomph out of my demo,
but the next one is also important.
So yay.
OK, oops, other side's better.
Look at that.
Beautiful contact forces, little sphere finger,
moving up the Cheez-It box.
Always staying right on the boundary of the--
let's watch, actually.
I mean, I think that force you're
going to see is always sort of on that margin.
It's kind of funny, though.
If you keep running the controller
after it goes up to the top--
I did make one linearization assumption there,
which goes bad when you're all the way at the top.
But yeah, you get this beautiful control that I must say
would be very hard to implement with position control.
So it's explicitly reasoning about--
like all these terms you guys mentioned,
the vertical force, what's the total amount
admissible friction in the corner in order
to command that trajectory.
Now, once the finger left the Cheez-It box,
it did something ridiculous, because it's
commanding forces, and that's not
so good for moving around the position of the world.
But OK, so that is strategy one, inspired by my daughter.
But it's just a simple example of a general principle,
of directly commanding forces, direct force control.
Now, direct force control, you can do that, again,
with the force sensor, or with this quasi-static assumption,
or by actually using the accelerations
and including them in the equation.
OK, there are lots of details, basically,
about how you derive that actual controller when
it's the full robot.
And those details really matter, like the difference
between a sensor that's high bandwidth and super clean,
implemented well at a high frequency,
compared to something that's not, is night and day.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yep.
I mean, I could ask for something
that would be too fast, I think, and it would just
refuse to execute faster than it could,
because of the thresholds from the friction cones.
I didn't repeat that.
She asked if the speed it rotated up
was given by theta desired, or something more subtle.
And it's mostly theta desired, up to some limit.
OK, so that ridiculousness of the finger afterwards,
I think, is something we can address.
And in general, commanding forces only
is potentially a slightly limiting view of the world.
And there's a generalization, which
tends to be called indirect force control.
There's a class of models, indirect force control,
that where you program the force,
but you do it indirectly, so by a surrogate objective.
So the simplest and one of the most powerful examples
would be stiffness control.
So it's an example of indirect force control.
All right, we've still got our equations up there,
the mx double dot equals ux fc, whatever.
If instead of saying my goal is to regulate this fictitious
force, if we said instead, I would
like that if you came up and pushed on my finger,
my little red circular finger, that the response you would get
would be like it was a spring.
And the rest length of that spring
is going to become the input to my control system.
So if I want the finger to come into contact with the box
and then potentially move the box around,
I can do that by just making my finger act like a spring
and then moving the rest position of that spring
into the box.
And it'll start pulling me, just like with the spring's dynamics,
So if the rest length was inside the box,
it would be applying a force to the box.
The force it would apply is proportional to how far
into the box my rest length is.
That's a sort of indirect way to command a force,
but it turns out to be super useful.
So if I want my new mechanical system
to look like my sort of textbook spring mass damper system,
OK?
And I think of this now as the virtual positions,
or the rest length is like the input to my stiffness control.
OK?
In general, actually, I've added-- this
is the stiffness component, right,
where I'm acting like a spring.
This is a damping element I've added here.
If you really look-- if you want to be careful,
then there's this thing called stiffness control.
There's a thing called damping control.
If you put them together, maybe you're
technically doing compliance control.
Doesn't really matter.
This is the idea, right?
Call it what you will.
Right?
So the model is, if the world is pushing on me,
whatever the world is pushing on me,
I have a well-defined response.
I'm going to act like a mechanical spring.
I'm going to replace the dynamics of my robot
with the dynamics of a spring.
That's a very important intuitive idea.
One of the things that's very nice about it
is that springs are well-behaved for any reasonable forces.
Right?
If the world is not--
I mean, you can--
if the world were to come up and try
to hit your resonant frequency or something,
maybe that's bad.
But if the world is sort of like passive, energy-conserving,
right, and you are energy-conserving,
then you have some guarantees that even
if you don't know exactly what's happening
on with your contact forces, you can
guarantee that things aren't going to go too bad.
Right?
And in general, there's a deep literature
on this about passivity-based control,
where you try to say that each of my elements of my control
system, including the world-- if I say the world is
energy-conserving and my system is energy-conserving,
it's passive or potentially even dissipative.
Right?
There's friction in it, or damping.
Then you can make guarantees about the stability
of the entire system, even when they're in complex composition.
So that's a very powerful idea.
And there's a couple of references in the notes
about it.
There's also Hamiltonian-- Port Hamiltonian theory
is like this taken to an extreme.
So there's a lot-- there's a deep literature there.
OK, but this is just an intuitive idea.
Let's try to act like a spring.
And it turns out to be way useful.
OK, so I put in here, assuming I'm--
I think it should definitely not have disconnected yet.
So I didn't do teleop with force control,
because if I put a little slider and commanded the force,
the demo would be very short, because my finger would just
either slam into something, or it would just
kind of off the screen, and I'd be kind of done.
But with stiffness control, I can
move that set point of the spring around
and do totally reasonable things.
So I give myself a little desired position of the--
wakey, wakey.
It's a little scary, but let's--
there we go.
OK.
That's got like an old mesh cat talking to me.
Oh, I hit play.
Stop.
OK, let's try that again.
Dang.
These things went so well in my head.
OK, good.
Now I'm in a mode where I have my robot.
I've got my finger.
I can teleop the set point of the finger.
I made the box transparent.
Jeez, too many boxes.
OK.
The box is more transparent, because we're going to stick
our set point inside it.
There's the red finger, but there's also
a little gold finger here.
So the gold finger is my set point,
and it's going to track it around.
And I've got yesterday's finger there, too.
I'll ignore the finger at the top there.
OK.
All right, so now this is a pretty intuitive interface.
So I can move this thing around.
It does good position control.
It doesn't do crazy things.
But I can also generate forces.
I'm up against the static friction,
but I'm not yet exceeding the static friction.
If I push a little bit harder by moving it farther into the box,
I can start moving the box around.
If I try to do what we did a minute ago,
it's not going to go super well.
I'm a human.
Oh, man, look at that.
OK, but you get the point.
So this is actually a pretty nice interface for me.
It's also a pretty nice interface for the robot,
in the sense that a large number of choices for this,
and this, and this give very reasonable behaviors.
So you don't have to dial it in too carefully.
OK, but it gives me the sort of, I think, the best part--
hopefully it runs on the first try.
Let's try a different flip-up strategy.
That I think really captures the idea
that if you program the mechanics of your interaction,
you can do something just way better
than if you're trying to program the forces or the positions
slowly.
So here's a different flip-up strategy.
I'm going to drive the box like I was doing there,
but I'm going to drive it all the way to the edge here.
Then I'm going to start pushing up.
Rather than-- it can't rotate around here anymore.
It's going to rotate around here.
So it's going to start tipping up like this.
If I'm successful, it's going to start tipping up like this.
I can do that just by having my set point of my spring
so it's pushing in here, and then just lifting that up
a little bit.
That will cause a vertical component of my spring force,
because it's trying to go here.
So exactly what we did before.
But here's what's really cool.
What happens when I get to the top,
when I start getting high up here?
At some point, this is going to exceed its friction cone.
So I'm going to have no ability to push here and stay
inside the friction cone.
You just can't do that.
So this is going to slip.
In the previous model, if I was monitoring the forces,
monitoring the accelerations, trying to estimate
the moment of that slip, that's not a good way to go.
So if you have to wait for slip, detect slip instantaneously,
and then make a control decision,
you're not going to be successful in life.
People try that.
It's very, very hard to do.
The moment of slip is hard.
They call it incipient slip.
It's like the signals right before slip.
But that's a hard way to go.
Here's the cool thing.
If I can program my interaction in the right way
with enough colors of chalk, so that I'm here pulling on this,
and I've got virtual set point in some reasonably chosen
configuration, then it's going to push me into the wall.
It's going to tip me up.
But the moment this slips, I don't
have to change my controller.
It's going to be pushing down.
And it's still going to just try to pull itself here.
But I will convince you, I hope, that it
does exactly the right thing.
I have to stop and tell you.
OK.
Here we go.
See that?
Watch the set point here.
All I'm doing is moving straight here.
And I'm moving straight up.
Watch what happens.
Boom.
OK.
So at the moment of getting near the top,
it's still doing exactly the right thing.
All it's going to do is going to push me so
that the box is in the corner.
Push me so that the box is in the corner.
Solves the entire task.
No detailed reasoning about forces.
No detailed estimation of friction contacts,
friction cones, or whatever.
Easy solution.
That's not the one my daughter took.
But if she had a point finger, maybe.
This strategy is like a narrow example of the big concept.
But I think the concept of programming your interactions
instead of programming the forces directly, I think,
does work for a lot of different shapes, objects, tasks.
There are some classic ones.
People talk about wall following or welding or painting.
These kind of tasks that are done by traditional robotic
arms are well suited to these kind of controllers.
Does that make sense?
Yeah?
There's a paradigm shift of instead
of programming the forces directly,
you program the dynamics.
And what's interesting is when we go away-- on Thursday,
when we talk about going away from just assuming
you're a point contact, the controller that implemented
this, if we had to think about how
to take the equations of motion and implement this controller,
it's not hard.
It's going to be like if I just write the u, z component,
it's basically-- these terms have to go on the other side.
I get like a b z dot f minus k z minus z desired, which
looks a lot like a PD controller.
But I also have this gravity compensation.
So the way that this got implemented
was something that looks like a PD control for the point
finger case plus a gravity compensation.
And more generally, it's going to look
like a bunch of terms that are trying to cancel out
the dynamics of your robot and replace them, typically
in an end effector coordinates, with the dynamics
of a spring.
So if I had to do this with joints and make myself
act like a spring at the end point,
it's not going to be just a simple PD controller.
It's going to be mapped through some transformation
to the joints.
But I can still-- if I master my own robot's dynamics,
then I can control the contact forces, the contact
interactions.
Do people know what impedance control is?
I know there's a few people that had better
know what impedance control is if you're
working in Neville's lab, yeah?
So how does impedance control relate to this,
if anybody knows?
Impedance control is basically a generalization of this.
In fact, I would call this an impedance controller.
So it's only a generalization.
So the thing I did here is I just
changed the stiffness and damping.
And I didn't try to change the effective mass of the sphere.
So I can, with a pretty simple controller that
doesn't have to know too much, I can make my sphere
act like a spring mass damper with the same mass
it originally had, and just act as if it's
got a spring attached to it.
More generally, if you have a real mastery of your dynamics,
you can even change the effective mass.
So if someone were to push on me,
even if my robot's very heavy, you
can make it act very light.
That's a harder thing to implement.
And depending on how you implement it,
with acceleration terms or force terms or anything like this,
it can be subtle to get right.
And it's also subtle in the bandwidth
of your controller sense.
So I think impedance control is the right--
you could use impedance control for the stiffness control
and be completely OK.
You could talk to your friends at conferences,
say impedance control, and mean that.
It would be OK.
People do that.
Strictly, the full glory of impedance control
is realized if you're also trying to change your mass.
And I think that's less common, actually.
The full glory of impedance control, I think,
is maybe less realized, just because changing
masses is nasty business.
I think IWA doesn't do that.
I think they went-- you could sort of watch
the series of progression of their papers.
And there were times where they were really
trying to cancel that mass.
And the final controller just didn't do it.
OK, so you know what impedance control is, right?
I hope.
I mean, there is a very different way to teach that.
This is maybe a much more intuitive--
trying to appeal to your intuition way to do it.
But I think that is the core idea.
OK, let me just move to remote-centered compliance.
OK, so one of the best--
this is a line of work, all this force control and impedance
control.
Neville Hogan wrote the famous impedance control papers
in the early '80s, up to like '85.
This is core robotics wisdom.
It's also super relevant today.
If you're programming-- if you're
trying to train an RL controller,
and you have a choice, given your task,
about choosing a position command, an impedance command,
a torque command, those are going
to work very differently in your training procedures.
Knowing a few things about impedance control
is going to serve you well for a lot of tasks
that are contact-rich.
You have to understand when they work
and when they don't work.
But this is really core foundational knowledge.
And I would say, in that spirit of the '80s, where everybody
was trying to figure out all the different ways to think
about force control and do rich tasks,
there was a canonical task, which
was this peg-and-hole task.
Right?
It actually motivated some great work in motion planning,
in addition to great work in control.
OK?
So you've got a hole in the world,
and you've got a peg that's roughly the same size
as the hole in the world.
And you've got to get this in here.
Right?
And if you try to do that with pure position control mode,
it can be nasty.
Nasty things happen.
OK?
So how do we think about how to do this?
Well, first off, if you're actually
trying to do peg-and-hole, then it's
OK to cheat a little bit.
You kind of chamfer the corners, because that's just worth--
it doesn't take any effort, really,
and it's going to make everything better.
You might do it up here, too.
OK, that's fine.
But still, all this weird stuff happens.
In particular, the bad case--
if I'm coming down and I'm just a little bit out of alignment,
I might make contact here early.
Right?
Get some contact forces here.
If I were to continue to push down
without paying much attention, I'm
going to get very large forces out.
OK?
Even worse is if I get myself in this configuration,
where I'm making contact here.
I'm getting potentially large contact forces here.
You can actually get the peg jammed in the hole.
Just absolutely-- it's also in a place
where Coulomb friction isn't going to give you--
it's going to sort of be in the underdetermined problem
for Coulomb friction.
And in practice, your peg's going to get stuck.
OK?
So it was decided early on that it
pays to be compliant when you're doing this,
to try to be in a forced control mode or a compliant control
mode.
And in particular, you can do stiffness control
in orientation, too.
So you can program a rotational stiffness of the hand.
OK?
So in position, you'd like for the case--
you've estimated things just a little bit wrong,
and you're coming down like this.
OK?
You'd like to have some stiffness--
a spring sort of in the horizontal stiffness
so that the controller is OK with sliding a little bit
in order to go in.
That's the translational version.
And then up here, you'd like in that initial contact
to have some ability to have some rotational stiffness
so that the peg will align itself and go in.
But if you think for a few minutes
about how that rotational stiffness needs to look,
it needs to-- you need to have some center of your rotation,
some coordinate frame to represent the rotation about.
OK?
If you choose a rotational stiffness around here
and say that if I'm deviating from this,
I will pull myself back, that's going to do the wrong thing.
When I come down and go like this,
it's going to allow me to go to bend more this way.
That's not what you want.
What you need instead is to have an effective center
of compliance that's over here.
OK?
Typically at the end point, I've got too many pegs
lying around here.
Pegs coming in a little bit out of alignment.
OK?
Typically at the end or even beyond the end,
I want to think about having a stiffness programmed like this
so that if I were to push here, it will actually
cause the peg to rotate this way in order to come down and in.
OK?
So that concept is called a remote centered compliance,
often RCC.
It's really just the choice of where you parameterized
your orientation.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
So let me draw it in.
Let's say that-- yeah, let me draw it more carefully.
Thank you for asking.
The question was, what the heck are you drawing?
So let's say I've got a desired orientation like this.
OK?
Now I come down, and I get some deviation from that position.
OK, so I'm getting some forces here.
That could cause me to deviate like this.
OK?
So I want to basically pull myself in this direction.
So if I get a force that's shoving me in that way,
I want it to act like a spring that's
pulling me towards that configuration.
OK?
And that'll align me and bring me down in.
OK.
So you can program that with stiffness control
and have some success.
But I would say one of the best things that happened
in all of this work is that people went through
and realized, actually, I don't even have to program that.
I can build a mechanical device that
acts like a spring that has a center of rotation
off the end of the tip.
OK?
So this is a passive remote center compliance.
And I just have to show you some of these old videos.
They're so good.
First of all, I was super--
I had forgotten, but it's totally
done by a guy named Drake, which is--
OK, so yeah, this is a thesis.
A lot of this work was done at MIT for some reason.
A lot of the Pagan-Hall early work on impedance control
was at MIT.
All the motion planning stuff was done at MIT.
And Pagan-Halls were big at MIT in the '70s and '80s.
OK?
And these are the pictures I was trying to show you.
So the horizontal stiffness, it looks like this.
It allows me to change my translational position.
This is right out of Drake's 1978 thesis.
OK?
And you have an orientational stiffness
that looks like this that allows me to align.
OK?
This is the device he built. OK?
It's crazy.
How do you make springs that are up here
act like the center of the spring is down here?
Right?
You can do it.
It's just a-- it's a geometric puzzle, roughly,
of how do you align the springs and counterweight this
and counterbalance this and whatever.
And you can build a device purely
in the end effector of the robot that
acts like it had its center of its rotation down here.
Remote-centered compliance.
OK?
The instant center side beam deflections are down here.
And this is kind of what they look like today.
If you were to go-- you can buy these devices still,
and they're still super useful to buy
a device that's got these sort of lined up springs like this.
And even-- I love these older videos.
OK?
This is the ATI, the company that will sell you one, right?
One of these devices.
And in parts assembly, right?
This is a case where--
I won't play the audio, but it's great.
But they have some mating--
they've got some small holes in the part that's
in the robot's hand, some small stand-ups right there
that they have to--
and they just sort of jam it down and just
rely on the passive compliance, remote-centered compliance
of this to do all that alignment,
both the horizontal and the rotational.
And they can do that--
all the controllers, especially then,
had bandwidth limitations.
Like, implementing that in software
is going to get you only so far, right?
You can only be so fast.
But the physical springs are instantaneous,
continuous time, right?
So for high-speed assembly operations,
these physical devices made the difference.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Are the ligaments in my fingers doing remote-centered
compliance?
Is that--
[INAUDIBLE]
Right?
There's pretty complicated stuff going on there.
I don't know if they're really tuned up
to be remote-centered, right?
And they're also, of course--
I have an example.
OK.
There is actually a great example, maybe.
So it's one of my--
throughout the years, I've watched for cool animal tricks,
and eagles pulling mountain goats off the side of a mountain
and stuff like that.
I've got all those videos.
OK.
Have you ever thought about how a bird sits on a perch
and falls asleep and doesn't fall off?
It's actually really awesome.
OK.
So it's a little bit like this, right?
So they have a tendon that wraps around their talon,
up around--
it looks like the knee, but it's actually kind of their heel--
up into their torso, right?
So when they relax, it clamps their hands, right?
And provides all the clamping force they need,
so they don't fall off the perch.
That's kind of like a remote center compliance.
It's like a grasp thing.
So I have learned over the years--
there's other examples.
The reason that a horse can run faster than us
is because they have this huge tendon running down
the backside of their hip.
Typically, the understanding of how fast
you can swing your leg forward if you're a runner
is based on your muscle dynamics, and that's limiting.
You can only accelerate so fast.
But if you load up a catapult tendon during stance,
and you're basically winding up the catapult,
and then you lift it up and it goes and shoots it forward,
then you can run faster than a human, obviously.
So that's how horses do it.
And over and over and over, I've seen examples in animals
where there's very clever mechanical designs
and wirings of the tendons that make these things just amazing.
So I totally believe it.
Is it remote center compliance?
Something like that.
OK, I'm going to not mention hybrid force position control
now just because it's another thing,
but I think that's a pretty good place.
I mean, I just talked about birds on perches.
What else can you do beyond that?
So let's call it for today, and we will see you on Thursday.