Deep note and wanted GPUs we might ask and they might you know see what they
can do and they might offer us some compute. Those are the best options I
have in terms of you know be needing a big GPU if you want to train something
deep. I mean unless you have a big graphics card at home that's that's kind
of how it goes. That's a good question. I would say ask us early just so if I can
get that conversation started but maybe like in your project proposal if you're
thinking I might be compute limited for this you know call that out earlier. I
have seen RL projects that sort of run out of time. Right you know like my
learning curves aren't going down and things are due and it just takes a long
time to run simulations so that is a risk with RL. We're good to go? Okay.
Thank you for figuring that out under pressure. That was great. Okay so
there's a important I think thing that I you know so we've been talking through a
lot of a couple different almost complete solutions but I feel like
there's an important piece of the puzzle that I haven't given you a good solution
to yet and I want to talk through that today. So you know we've been talking
this week about clutter clearing as just an example right and I would say the
quick summary of our simplified bin picking strategy has been first you
maybe get the hand out of the way use your cameras acquire and pre-process all
the point clouds from the candidate bin right you sample and score those
candidate possible candidate grasps using our antipodal metric but we have I
said antipodal plus plus because it also the one I implemented threw in some
preference for reaching down from above and some other things like that so it
had a few other terms in the cost. Okay and then we then you would complete with
the you know the recipe from from before you turn that into like a gripper
trajectory that's going to go down from my current hand position to the grasp
right and then you're gonna bring that over to the other bin drop it off and
you'll probably you'll execute that trajectory with diff IK that's what
we've given you so far there are other ways to do it but that's what that's the
toolchain so far and then you're gonna you know repeat until some termination
criteria or whatever and maybe at some point you start start picking up things
from the other bin and putting it back so you have a closed system that can run
for a long time. Now the thing that's happening here that didn't really happen
given our previous assumptions is that a lot of those steps can just fail right
for sometimes good reasons sometimes less good reasons but you know let's
just list a little bit of what are the what are the things that could fail in
that pipeline what are the steps that are sort of not guaranteed yeah yeah the
grasp could just fail right so I could I could go down I mean maybe the maybe I
just I closed my hand there and it slipped right out right so like a failed
grasp right so it might be that right at the moment of closing the hand I could
show to check if I've got something if my hand closed all the way and there's
nothing you know fingers are touching each other that's a failed grasp you
know the so there are sensors that will allow us to detect that you know but you
can also have a tenuous grasp right and then once you start lifting or moving
it slips right out right and we also talked about you know maybe I picked up
the hammer by the very corner and it just sort of torqued itself out right
it's not just okay that's definitely one what else can fail yeah right it could
be that there's there's a good grasp that exists and I just didn't find it
with my antipodal strategy because antipodal is not absolutely guaranteed
to exist in in some metric or it could be that I just sampled not enough right
what else could fail yeah right right so bad point clouds right reflections or
transparent objects or other you know all kinds of stuff can screw up your
point clouds there's another big one yeah
yeah that's that's close to the one I was thinking so he says differential IK
might fail right so the fact that we've separated the grasp planning from the
arm limitations right if there's any workspace limitations on your arm or you
know which could get subtle right if it if I have to get down and reach you know
it might be that's that an over the overhead gris grasp in the back corner
of the bin would be fine but if I went like this it wouldn't be fine because of
the reachability of the arm and somehow because I've decoupled those two
problems I could fail downstream right
and the arm has additional geometry it could be I mean I could tell you it
happens a lot actually that that kooka if it wants to get into the sink it's
got this big old elbow right so you know you think about just the gripper getting
in there but then you're gonna have a constraint coming from the elbow that
you didn't reason about so so those really do happen for just joint limits
but also collisions right and we could go on right so there's there's a bunch
of things that that could break in this system and I think that's just a reality
of having perception in there and having a relatively simple pipeline even the
logic of deciding when you're done it's kind of not clear exactly when you're
done you could have points still you know objects still in the bin that you
just have to decide I'm never gonna get that one right it's kind of stuck in the
corner my hands not gonna fit I gotta give up move on to the next one right
now the full on the the TRI clutter clearing has additional skills like we've
talked about sort of push things out in the corner to try to really get to zero
but but if you don't have all those extra layers of you know band-aids
around it that even just understanding when to give up right is something so
the big thing that's changing now that I feel like I haven't given you a good
solution to yet is that we can't just sort of run through a script and be
happy right we're gonna have a lot of branches right okay did my scoring
candidate find a good solution if not maybe I resample maybe if I've resampled
ten times I give up and I move on to the next you know so there's gonna be a lot
more branching a lot more checking and the like in here and even even given
that I haven't told you really how to go from this sort of script into the
simulation framework right so we're going to talk about you know what it
means to execute that sort of a plan in a situation where you're a dynamical
system and somebody's asking for an answer at 200 Hertz this is sort of
procedural script the way you'd write a you know write a standard code but
that's not the way we tend to write systems and that's not the way it's not
the framework that sort of guarantees that you're gonna have a message ready
to send to your robot every 200 Hertz so somehow somewhere there's got to be a
contract which tells me how I'm gonna go from you know that kind of logic into
this into this sort of tell the robot something all the time some robots will
actually just power down if they haven't heard from you in five milliseconds
right so okay a lot of times that contract is a little ambiguous right
maybe it's if you've got a multi X you know multi process system sending
message passes passing you know maybe your low-level controller is just
sending a keep alive and if it doesn't hear from you for a while it'll just
keep sending the last command and so you're not really worried about that
contract as much and you just every once in a while send a plan over but you know
when you get down into trying to make these things understand these things
completely I think that contract needs to be made more explicit so we'll talk
about that today I mean honestly this is a lecture I would say that I'm still
getting my head around right I'm trying to decide exactly what pieces to cut out
and and it's an interesting conflation of like what people like to do in AI what
people like to do in control theory what programmers like to do right somehow
it's like in the Venn diagram of those things and I don't actually think so you
might look at this list and think oh that's kind of like a software
engineering problem not a fundamental problem but I actually think it is
squarely in the you know the place where AI type planning methods and the like
are coming together with systems theory and I think it's really important in
fundamental okay so to start off I thought I'd I do like a bit of a case
study here this is I mean you've seen this before but but we can sort of dig
in now and say how did we organize the behaviors on this system right I've
never actually really presented that to anybody and there's some some details
that I think aren't going to surprise you but maybe we'll clarify something
that looks it's complicated complicated and this system I think notably was
taken to a very high level of maturity so it's a fairly complex task but it's a
task that worked very nearly all the time by the time we were done hammering
on it okay so it's a there's a statement just of you know the way we typed it in
this way is something that you can take to high levels of maturity and if you
guys have done you know internships at companies that are doing this kind of
work you'll see you know you might some of this stuff might look familiar it's a
okay so you know the scripts that I should the script that I showed you for
for bin picking you know has these different components that we've broken
off and that's a common strategy so in the dish loading there are a handful of
different you know primitives actions so we really decompose the big task into
these notion of many primitives okay so this was like picking up a I can play
them again real quick but this is picking up silverware that was pulling
the silverware rack out you know and picking up the silverware opening the
door is a primitive you know picking up mugs is a primitive this is the nudging
it out of the out of the corner because the hands too big to pick it up when it
was in the corner you know these are all composed with as different primitives
okay so the language that we use behind the scenes is not strips but I think if
you understand strips which is the which originally you know was the Stanford
Research Institute problem solver was the originally was the name of the
algorithm okay and became known for the sort of specific formal language
specification which was the input format to that solver is now what people often
refer to as the strips language okay this is an early sort of way to an AI
approach to planning that allows you to compose multiple motion primitive or
well let's say primitives we won't include the word motion yet okay and try
to compose multiple behaviors in a way that's a very natural sort of planning
framework okay when you think about AI planning you might think about graph
search right you should think about graph search that's a star algorithms
and and other kind of algorithms like this and the specification languages in
strips and its successors I think bridge the gap between those sort of search
algorithms and a specification language which is more about named actions with
preconditions and post conditions and the like okay and it just it's a
specification language that makes those planners good so the specification
languages most notably here you know you itemize a set of actions okay for each
each action you you talk about you know when am I allowed to take that action so
it's if it's the I'm gonna pick up a silverware this time but silverware is
my action right then the preconditions might be that I've got some detections
of a fork right and you probably won't get detections of a fork unless the fork
is exposed in press in practice actually we don't pick up forks until all the
plates and all the mugs are gone because well things go weird if you you can you
can find yourself in all kinds of crazy situations if you drop a fork in a mug
or something like this so we we just decided to prioritize you know get the
mugs and plates out and leave the forks and everything at the bottom okay the
inaction causes some change in the state in the in the state of the world okay
with some post conditions now this is interesting you know this is what allows
you to do prediction into the future so if I were to say I currently have a
detection of the of the fork in the sink after I run my fork pickup I'm gonna say
that there's no fork in the sink right it's in my other the fork in my hand for
instance okay and then you can specify a long-term objective like clear the bin
okay as saying like there are no objects or you know the point cloud is of
sufficiently sparse or something in my bin okay we're gonna see a couple
examples of this but but I want to just sort of introduce this like high-level
notion of separating your task into actions and using a traditional planning
system to sequence those actions okay the newer versions of this are I mean
not even that new right but potato is like the generalization of strips so if
you hear but it'll which you will hear around campus right you may hear potato
stream right but this is an active well there's there's a there's a lot of good
work about this kind of planning even taken to the next level you know
upstairs and listening to Masa's group for instance okay so but it'll just is a
richer form of the same idea I would say it kind of generalized strips and a few
of the other early programming language sort of planning specifications and in
particular it allowed you to sort of factor you could there's this notion of
objects that come in and instead of having just individual state variables
that get listed one by one there's a little bit of a object orientedness of
it the detail I don't need you to understand but basically it's the same
specification same type of specification of strips generalized to be more
efficient and more general you'll see the same initial state and goal
specifications and the same sort of actions that are around okay and in
practice you know you write these little you know specification files that that
just define your predicates maybe there there's a robot in a room there's balls
there's grippers okay you define actions that have preconditions and effects okay
different types of pick actions preconditions and effects and these are
all written as logical operators on these kind of variables and then
similarly your that would be like a that would be your domain definition and then
similarly you can write a planning instance where you say I need this is a
new problem I have some initial conditions where I have no two rooms and
four balls I have a gripper you know and I have to plan from the start to the
goal okay so that's a technology that's out there and I think it it becomes
essential when you're trying to compose much you know more and more complicated
tasks where your decisions about what I should execute right now are conditioned
on multi-step reasoning right where the reason I should pick up a fork right now
is because well maybe if I the reason I pick up a mug right now is because I've
already you know I want to get the rack open I'll open the rack now because I'm
gonna pick up a mug next maybe that's a better example okay when your decision
right now depends on multiple steps of reasoning this allows you to write that
sort of branching logic in a much more compact form and leverage a planner to
make those decisions for you okay so how does that look in the in the TRI
disloading system okay now in fact it's it's a little unfair to say to describe
it as pivotal I'm using that to simplify it it's actually a the the task planner
is actually a task in motion planner that's capable of more but I think the
bulk of the example here I can tell you without telling you that the full glory
of that okay so it's kind of fun to like look through the code and see that
actually those concepts really you know they they appear in your in your c++
classes and stuff like this okay so we really do define all of the actions all
of those those controls in terms of this you know action primitive interface
similar to biddle right there's there's a check that's like the is candidate is
like the precondition check right so you can tell it the current state you know
it's I'll show you what the state is in these cases this sort of subsampled
state of the world grounded state of the world if you will and it just answers
the question you know each skill each primitive action answers the question
yes can I run this now or not right just a Boolean outcome and then sorry the
the outcomes would be if I did run this what would I what would I expect to
change about the state right you can associate costs you can associate
rankings with each of those that's it those are generalizations of the basic
potato idea there's potato variants that include that for sure but if you want to
solve you know optimize and try to pick the best action instead of just having a
lot of feasible actions that those can be very important and then there's just
this notion of like I'm gonna now run the skill right so each of these sort
of actions has the ability to say when you can run it say what's gonna happen
if you run it and run roughly and if you look through the code there's just a
bunch of actions that are at this level of like you know pull out the lower rack
pull out the upper rack right and this decomposition was done by humans this is
a manual step this is something that is an active you know lots of people are
thinking about how do you get those to come out automatically but I think a lot
of people are still manually typing in those those decompositions okay and it's
also sort of interesting to see the level at which these are written right
so they're not the details of like twist my gripper at this you know and to this
angle and then push I'll show you what those details too but you know they're
more at the strategy level of like should I do this first should I do this
next right the high the task level
part of the reason for that is because you know the preconditions for these and
even the outcomes can be written in terms of a pretty simple and abstract
state of the world okay so just pulling into the code right the the state of the
dish task right is a combination of disk dish washer state and dish state okay
but they're basically what I want you to see here is that they're like number of
times I've put them away an integer okay the number of dirty items available
right they are Boolean you know is the dishwasher state known is the door open
is the lower rack out okay this is us grounding some symbols into our
perception there's a there's a step required to do this right is to have a
perception system that can tell me if the lower rack is out or in but if we
can ground that perception into a into just a Boolean classifier that we're
happy with then we can start writing this higher level procedural logic and
using the more sophisticated planning framework to make our decisions right
even the the dish types you know are enumerated if you throw in something
random it becomes unknown unless it's mug like and they might get grabbed as a
mug and put in the top rack right and some of the some of the different
objects have a requested location in the dishwasher right they all have like
relative status as you're trying to to move through that stack so so the the
decision-making there is you know it when you first turn the robot on it
looks at what you know it uses its perception system to decide the current
state and it will make a multi plan action using that very simple
representation of state using an optimistic plan that basically says I'm
gonna you know the outcome I get is success roughly and the you know it's
it's a yeah it's optimistic and it's deterministic so it also assumes that
you know I get what I with probability one the action is succeeds right so the
way to make that that's a common assumption it's not a there are people
that do belief space planning probabilistic planning planning with
uncertainty and the like but this is not doing that yet and the way you then
handle each outcome is that you're constantly watching if you've deviated
from your plan you just replan okay works fairly well right so if you start
putting your mug in and then you someone comes in this is like not as cool as
kicking the robot at Boston Dynamics but it's kind of kind of similar I guess you
know it will decide mid mid mid place that it needs to set down the mug
reopen the dish rack pick up the mug again you know it's got this layers of
complexity that come from that task level planner and it's infinitely
patient right because you know you can sit there do that all day and you think
about the robots gonna throw the mug at me but it never never does we didn't we
didn't program that skill
is that clear I mean is that there's a lot of details hidden behind there I
want to give you the sense anybody have questions about yeah
all right
the question is how far ahead do you plan right how do you have to plan like
20 steps ahead you have to plan till like the dishwasher is clean there's
there the dish the sink is clean a dishwasher is full right so we
definitely don't do that because perception isn't capable of telling us
the full state of the sink so we have to sort of have an incremental approach
you can't sort of reason all the way to the end but the the answer to your
question about how far do you look ahead is actually very subtle I'd say so you
know these preconditions that say when a skill is good if they are very weak if
they're like loose approximations of when you should execute that skill then
then looking ahead farther will will make those stronger this is a standard
thing in planning right so if you if I had for instance you know the conditions
that are exactly narrowly defined which says this is you know if I were to run
the plan these are the only conditions for which I would choose this skill then
I would never need to run the plan I could just if it's if you know
reinforcement learning like if I had the value function for instance as my
precondition check then I wouldn't have to do any planning if you write weak
preconditions then planning will make them stronger looking ahead will make
them stronger so in practice I think we're somewhere in the middle here we
take that we do plan ahead I would guess most of the time we take we take the
action that we would have taken if we hadn't looked ahead but we always look
ahead multiple steps in many steps just to make sure yeah
yeah so if these planners were a computational burden I think we'd be
playing more games about incremental replanning and the like and just you
know but the discrete level planning is lightning fast and we just go ahead and
plan to the end there's no reason not to for us when you start adding more of the
task and motion planning features which we'll hopefully talk about in one of the
boutique lectures later then then those planners can slow way down but for the
simple high-level logical planning that's fine yes
you are very wise so so the question was when does it actually check I do
think there are a few magical places in the trajectory where it's checking where
it's where it's transitioning between the lower level skills where those are
the discrete times where it checks so if we had pushed at a different time it
might have still gone to the top of that trajectory before setting it down right
so you're absolutely right the checking well I mean the perceptions running at a
higher relatively higher rate the replanning is happening at our between
the macro actions now if we I think we probably could do it faster but I think
for this this task that was sufficient those are good questions yeah and I'm
happy to take them okay I want to make this point super clear okay which is
that most of those states there was a po there were poses and a few things in
there that were continuous values but most of the planning there was actually
on discrete states the planner that we use is actually capable of much more but
that instance that I'm telling you about was mostly discrete state integer number
of times I've done things Boolean is my mug in my hand those kind of things okay
planning is fast in that case when you start including continuous state then
it's going to be a harder problem right and we will we will talk about that but
in general things get harder fast however the notion that's a little faint
on my screen but the notion of preconditions and post conditions of low
level skills I think transitions very well into the continuous domain and any
of you that have taken under actuated with me or will take under actuated with
me know that I'm a big fan of thinking about feedback controllers in a low
level even continuous state task in terms of their preconditions and their
post conditions that's a you know and there's connections to Lyapunov
functions from control as ways to think about those preconditions and the like
so the general notion of decomposing your task into skills is I think very
general reasoning about the multi-step effect of those skills and making a plan
gets much more expensive okay people do it right there's something called
feedback motion planning which talks about okay well if I was in this the
inside of this skill this funnel so that I maybe didn't say clearly enough so I'm
thinking of this imagine this is like q1 in this axis and q2 right the joint
angles or the continuous pose of my object right and the preconditions I
could draw as a subset a continuous subset of state space saying these in
these continuous values when q1 is and you know q1 q2 are less than you know
are in some ellipse for instance then I'm gonna say yes I can run the skill in
that case and you say after I've run the skill they're gonna come out hopefully
in a smaller set because oftentimes controllers are good and stabilizing okay
and if the the continuous set that I expect to be the effect of my action
fits completely inside the precondition of another set then you can imagine
sequentially composing these things into more dexterous behaviors okay now this
this idea is I think powering I mean so al Rizzi is now you know way up in
Boston Dynamics they don't want to get his title wrong but it's very near the
top of Boston Dynamics and spot is you know is under I'lls organization or
well it's a complicated organization but there's I think there's a lot of funnels
going around on spot okay so so I think that this this idea you know I think is
making real robots do amazing things okay so so I really think this notion of
programming by breaking up into small pieces and then using some level of
planning to compose them is a good idea
okay so let's dig in a little bit more to like what those individual skills
look like okay there are some which are more like our you know just sample the
point cloud there are some that are just sensing but the low-level skills for
that are doing the work that I showed you are maybe the more interesting ones
and we can step through them right so I should have started this from the top
right so you can watch we're gonna approach such them that the mug is in
view of the wrist camera now the wrist cameras got a good view now you see a
little bit of adjustment that's the visual servoing using ICP right the
iterative closest point to make sure your your scan matches the data and
you're gonna get the pose you expected to get then you insert to grasp close
your hand retract move to pre place when you drop it down you see that the force
is you know there's force thresholds to determinate do it one more time here
sorry ICP move move in retract move to pre place which is a big motion
planning system there and then when it actually set it down to it sets it down
and by touch right based on based on a force sensor right because if you didn't
get the pose exactly what you don't want to rely on your estimation of the
geometry to set it down that's how you break mugs we've broken a few okay this
is my favorite one right so the the plate pickup and it is similarly I would
say I should be clear that these were the original versions that we wrote we
wrote handcrafted versions and now we've been doing more and more automatically
learned or synthesized versions of all these tasks but I think it's important
to understand the first handcrafted versions of these okay so that plate
pickup is a pretty subtle one you have to potentially get your fingers between
different plates in order to get it up okay lots of different thresholds okay
and it is a similar but more complicated plan about approaching the plate so it's
roughly in view for the wrist camera visual servo for alignment now we start
stick our finger you know close our fingers to roughly the right amount
insert one fingertip between the plates you know and so on and so forth right so
this type of reasoning actually gets to pretty robust pretty sophisticated
behaviors in fact so I like to call see one actually called there - you know
there's a there's a sort of a type of person there's an attribute that people
can have I have no very few of them but I would call see one a robot whisperer
right it's like yeah I think different than a horse whisperer but but sort of
similar in principle like the robots don't work and then see one enters the
room and the robots work and they do magical things and you can't believe
that someone could make a robot do that and I think it's it's a lot of intuition
about what signals matter and good debugging skills and all these
incredible things but as much as many cool things as we've seen from from
learning these days I think I would put see one up against any of them in terms
of like you show me a complicated task for a robot and I think someone a robot
whisperer out there could make it work
we will talk later about the learning version of it this is one that we did
upstairs in robot locomotion group was a kind of a we didn't buy the sink but we
did a similar task on the on the tabletop and this is a neural network
controller that's doing a similar thing and one of the big differences of this
controller is that it's it's going based on directly from perception so it's
there's no explicit estimation of the pose or location of the plate there's
even really not an explicit notion of plate anywhere it's just trained to go
straight from a refined visual representation directly into the actions
of the hand but it still fits into this box of thinking of it as a primitive
that takes things from one set of initial conditions to another I actually
will in the RL section I'm hoping to use this as a simple this is the simplest
version we've done of sort of the same kind of task that you can just hammer on
in simulation it's all it's even in 2d and you can just do direct policy search
on that so we'll play with that later
okay so I think one of the big challenges of thinking of programming
the task level is that you know because there's failure conditions there's all
there's all these different things that can happen you know you end up writing
much more complicated code for the clutter clearing you don't actually need
a full-on task planner you could just write a script with a handful of
branches and you'd probably get pretty far but for something like the
disloading that breaks the stack and you don't want to write that one out by hand
you want to write these modular you know I think three conditions folks post
conditions and use it an AI style planner to handle all that branching okay
one of the challenges with that although I said that the discrete is fast it's
not 200 Hertz fast necessarily so so taking these sort of long-running
computations and putting them into a simulation loop I think is the next to
sort of I want to I want to start bridging that gap gap how do you how do
you write code sort of in the simulation loop that transition clear yeah okay so
the examples I just showed you still looked like scripts right the move until
you touch kind of scripts and they went down a procedural script now that's what
programmers like right that's good for rapid prototyping whatever but if you're
a controller a control theorist or applied controls person you don't like
that representation right that's there's like bad things going on from the similar
version of that that you'd see in controls are this is an original Mark
Raybert hopping robot MIT leg lab hopping robot sort of the precursor to a
lot of the Boston Dynamics robots now if you will and one of the things I
absolutely love about it is that although it was like the most dynamic
locomotion legged thing ever you know certainly in the 80s you know it was
just far more dynamic and interesting than a lot of its predecessors the
controller fit on a single page I could if you come into my office I'll like
show you the page which has this at the top and then like the four PD
controllers on the bottom half of the page it's like a small book with one
page and it's and it's a beautiful description of a controller that to this
day using all of the tools we have from optimization that I have from
optimization theory and the like I don't have I can't make a better controller
really than that it's just a beautiful like yeah very simple architecture very
simple design leverages a lot of mechanical intuition a lot of you know
physics based intuition but what you see over and over again when you see one or
or the folks at Boston Dynamics or whoever's doing these you know these
robot whispering right controllers they are very often right things that are can
be spelled like a finite state machine controller okay so
I would let's contrast procedural logic versus finite state machine controllers
okay so do people understand what I mean by procedural logic this is like I'm
gonna say you know Wow something it's something I'm gonna write sort of my
standard Python C++ code I might have branches I might have whatever this is
sort of the procedural logic view of the world is our sort of standard
programming interface it doesn't have explicit notions of time okay it has
it's just marching procedurally down and an exit and following branches and
you're always on one line at a time okay it's the state way we typically write
code now a finite state machine is a dynamical system you know it fits inside
a mathematical or a computational framework that is different than this
right it fits inside a simulation loop where you can have there's a multiple
ways to write it but I might say a discrete time one would be something
like my dynamical system okay but I might have multiple equations that
govern me one for each state which let me call it mode so in the on the board
here there's a flight mode there's a landing mode there's a compression where
the leg spring is compressing there's a thrust there's an unloading mode right
each one of those is implementing some sort of a differential equation or
difference equation okay and then we have the edges of a finite state machine
are conditioned which say I'm going to my next mode you know my I n plus one is
some branching logic so it could be the same as I n or follow an edge
that's not
that's not the point I'm trying to make is that these are really they live in
a time stepping of a dynamical system right they have a discreet miss about
them where it says I'm only in one mode at a time but when I'm inside a mode
I'm just a different set of dynamical dynamical system equations they can have
inputs they can have outputs they could be an entire system in the way we've
talked about in class okay but I'm going to transition to which one's active a
way to think about this is that the total state of that controller is the
states of all the individual modes plus an integer state for the mode
I
so when I look at this sort of a procedural recipe that is written like
this but that you could potentially be written like this or it could actually
be written like this where we really have a different dynamical system for
approach the plate for visual servoing for us you know for closing the hand
those could differ be different states in the diagram you could write it either
way the reason I mean you can imagine that that if I wanted to say something
formal about what's happening in the system this representation is going to
give me more power to sort of analyze the dynamics of the system say something
about stability say something about robustness you know use all of our
stronger tools right this system is easier this is the programmers the light
right if you just want to hack something together and prototype this is way way
better okay now if you think about programming languages at all if you this
system they if they could be mathematically equivalent then then you
know the state of this system which is declared very explicitly potentially if
you use something like the systems framework we use in Drake or you
simulink or anything like that right you're explicitly say what X is you know
you explicitly enumerate the mode that you're in and you've declared all your
state and your function your your dynamics are just a function of the
state and input the notion of state is much messier in a procedural code it's
somehow like the entire stack of your thread you know you feel like if you're
to hit your debugger and you do DB stack right like that somehow that's your
state okay and it's a it's a useful state for programming but it's a messy
state for analysis okay so I do think this is one of the big things that that
is a gap is if you know taking code like this and translating it into this is a
sort of a an interesting enterprise and an important one if you if you need to
somehow write your system in a way that it will always talk to your robot at 200
Hertz but like I said there are you know people can take that kind of a an
approach this is Andy who's the video you've seen before but you know the task
level behaviors here I don't know the details I know Andy I like Andy a lot
but I don't know what code he wrote exactly my impression is that it is you
know finite state machine like and it is extremely robust even if you know
people pull the back of the robot and the like right right there's no learning
at the task level here there's probably learning at the perception level this
was a few years ago but you can make these things incredibly robust by
writing them in this sort of like the the framework of these finite state
machines success at the end right
okay so you know and and this is something that people use more generally
I don't think I'm not sure this package is super popular anymore but they're good
in the raw stack you can find things like s Mac which is state machine right
and you know this is this is a tool chain that people do use okay but you
know this problem that it's trying to solve of taking something that's like a
procedural code and giving it an explicit contract about having an output
or a state updated every time step bridging that gap that's something that
that people have dealt with for a long time so that you get one what is this
picture here right so like game developers have known about this problem
forever when I was a year up many years ago and I when I was an intern many
years ago when I was a year up I worked at with Miss at University of Michigan
with a guy who was doing AI for computer games and when I went for the summer to
Microsoft Research at the time I worked on this game which was a project at
Microsoft Research because it was one of the first massively distributed action
games gaming zone was new and they're like you know they were doing sort of
character stuff but nothing that had real-time action over the internet so it
was like it was a research project I wrote the drone code so if you were like
ever to play this game and you saw like a mining drones or turrets shooting at
you or whatever like that yeah I was I was trying I had permission to do like
an Easter egg that would like spell my name in the sky or something but I ran
out of time so I don't I can't say that but the way people program these kind of
things in in games is similar to what more advanced tools that people have
used in robotics also right the problem with writing code in finite state
machine is that as the tasks get more complicated the state machines explode
they absolutely don't scale right you can get if you start you want to add
just one new behavior maybe that behavior has to touch has to work in all
of those different different situations all these different skills maybe you
know in all of the different sequences of the robot picking something up I still
want to be able to like stop and go home if something goes very wrong right and
so that might mean taking every one of my states and blowing it up and blowing
it up and you get these like exponential growth of number of states and it became
untenable so through some amount of like you know research in academia and just
hacking in game industries or something a new form of you know a new format for
specifying finite state machine like things was born and that was called
behavior trees right people know about behavior trees yeah there was another I
guess the part of the theme there was Rod Brooks colleague here for many years
and you know he was part of this sort of this push I would say from the academic
side you know this was the time where Tomas and other people here Tomas was
Rod's postdoc advisor so they were you know they were close but I think a lot
of people were talking about AI style planning planning planning planning and
Rod starts writing a series of papers like elephants don't play chess you know
and intelligence without reason intelligence without representation and
he started arguing that robots real robots should be programmed with like
small state machines and he built this subsumption architecture it was his
version at the time and that was used to program legged robots probably program
Roomba right I tried to find a subsumption architecture for Roomba I
didn't didn't find it but I think the early versions of Roomba were running
these you know state machine like but programmed slightly differently versions
of low-level controls as opposed to big planners it's interesting that his his
critique of why you know the traditional approach has emphasized the abstract
manipulation of symbols which whose grounding in physical reality has rarely
been achieved which is totally true and at the time and whatever but it kind of
has been achieved now right I mean perception kind of works I mean like
completely there's abstract symbols that are still very hard but like I can find
a mug you know I can ground that I could tell you if the dishwasher doors open or
not right it's interesting that that I in my view is it's not solved but it's
it's moved okay so behavior trees we're gonna actually have you work through a
version on for the for our task on the problem set but they are they are
similar in spirit to state machines but are better been designed with
composition and a factor representation in mind okay so you'll see these these
basic operators it's a graphical programming language effectively that
that composes different so the way a behavior tree works is roughly you go
down you walk down the tree on every execution you ask you know should you
there's a there's basically logical ors and logical ands okay you say is this
true if yes execute the action and it doesn't succeed and this is an or so
maybe if it didn't succeed I'll walk down this train this chain in practice
it's a simple programming language for these types of behaviors which people
have had much success building libraries of behaviors if I had like a new you
know way that the robot should go recharge its batteries then I could
bring that recharges batteries and somehow stick it in here on my existing
someone else programmed you know Roomba sort of program and it can just sort of
tack into the main tree you get this logical specification that is finite
state machine like but much more factored and easier to compose and I'm
totally serious that people in computer games you know do this right so I wanted
to you know like if you go to the Unreal Engine 4 behavior tree quick start guide
right you can see how to like what was the thing here is create an enemy AI
that responds to seeing the player and proceeds to chase them down right so
that's got to be useful right and there's like a whole GUI in Unreal
Engine for programming behavior trees right so people build pretty complicated
systems out of this and they they are designed around this this fact that the
game engines are stepping along at a simulation loop you have to tell me what
to do at every step so how does that connect back to like the systems
framework and our dynamical systems view of the world right you could just stick
a behavior tree here's an example of it from a early version of the class that
we did you can you can take your favorite Python behavior tree library for
instance and tuck it inside a system and have the the what do they call it the
blackboard of the of the behavior tree basically be declared as the state of
your system and every time your dynamical system is evaluated it just
walks down the behavior tree and runs the action and it fits right into the
systems framework it's not in Drake master it's one of the places where I
feel that we could make the full stack easier if we implemented a few of these
these algorithms and made them available for people okay so there's a thing that
happens here that I want to kind of land and I'm people disagree with me on this
by the way this is now you know squarely on Russ's opinion of the world not what
is absolute and correct but despite the knowledge and utility of writing of
writing behavior trees and computer games and stuff like this a lot of
people when they're writing robots don't don't use finite state machines don't
use decision trees don't even necessarily use the full planning stack
they will still write procedural code and I think that happened a lot because
of the sort of multi-process message passing so let's say it's Ross or some
other message passing it's happening inside here okay so maybe over here I
have a simulation with a simulation time step and something that's working on
every you know five millisecond clock okay that's going around over here maybe
I have my while dirty sink right and then along the way I just sprinkle in
my decisions to send and receive messages so this can work and I think
the fact that the message passing and the separate multi-process view of the
world has become so easy with all the you know with the way that we've
architected our robotic systems these days this has become common again what I
think people what I worry about we've lost that maybe most people don't worry
about we've lost is that it's it it is possible but it's very difficult to get
deterministic evaluations in these kind of systems okay so as soon as you start
getting multiple processes that have you know arbitrary delay in message time
arrival and stuff like this even just your CPU scheduling things at different
times I think you don't typically run the same Ross simulation twice right I
mean I think that's just not what it's built for there are message passing
systems that can do extra work to enforce timing and and and give some
sort of guarantees there but it's very hard actually to run the same simulation
twice in that kind of a framework and I think that doesn't hurt you when you're
just prototyping but when you start taking things to the next level of
maturity it really starts to hurt you I think a lot of you know I think a lot of
advanced users stop using some of those message passing systems because of that
it's just very hard to get very repeatable very reliable you know when
something doesn't work did it not work because I dropped the message or
whatever you know so it was interesting to watch sort of the the process of
taking and you know to work on the process of taking that dish example to
maturity so it was a there was a system that was constantly running Monte Carlo
tests so making random initial conditions random mugs random plates
you know generating random we have like procedural dishes that would make
different size but but mug like things and generates spit out CAD models right
we changed lighting conditions we change all kinds of stuff okay and it was just
be running over and over and over again and it got to the point where well first
of all that failures in reality would match the rare failures in simulation
which was pretty awesome but you'd occasionally find a failure and and then
you'd have to go track it down and if it was not deterministic oh my gosh right
and there's still not some number to terminate some in that particular system
but we're still fighting it down because it's a it's a every bit you can get out
it gets more valuable and a lot of the most subtle bugs actually happen at this
behavior level I would say so this is kind of a fun one that we that we found
okay so there was a piece of the initiation set the preconditions for the
should I put the mug down that had an arbitrary threshold of 0.45 on the rack
position of the mug of the you know somehow we have a perception system
that's estimating the location of the rack and and if it's if it's out enough
from 0.45 I'll continue to execute and if it was too little I would stop and set
it down exactly what you were asking about before okay and then we started
adding there was like the night when somebody decided oh I'm gonna add
randomness to the rack perception that that matches the statistics of the
randomness we got from reality it was this it's this constant battle between
the people trying to make the simulator harder and those people making the robot
better right so someone added rack noise okay and almost always it was fine every
once in a while it would be such that the robot would start moving somewhere
along the cycle it would it would trip this thing saying it was less than 0.45
you go I'm gonna set it down okay but then by the time it went to decide again
it's like okay the racks there so and it would basically get in this like
infinite loop of going like this yeah you know like this man and it like we
never would have found that without extreme testing and to be able to
reproduce it you know it's just very very hard to get deterministic results
out of a system that's that's doing this kind of stuff so part of the mission in
getting things more things locked in in the systems framework is to just be able
to run completely reliable deterministic simulations of including the whole stack
to be fair the noise that was the added was a little bit crazy so it was like
you know yeah the dish rack was going like that or something like this but it
but so so everybody's kind of like oh yeah that's great you found me found a
bug but that's never gonna happen in reality and then it happened in reality
it was like one day there were someone how the the rack got a little bit stuck
right around the threshold and there was very good like infinite looping and we're
okay there you go it really did happen
okay so yeah please yeah so so I think that gets to the question of how do you
put long-running computation into like a behavior tree or a finite state machine
for instance so finite state machines behavior trees will address that need
but they're asked to give an answer at every time step so so the so it takes
some thought right the proposal the thing we've implemented in the proposal to do
more generally inside Drake is to have a system where if you have a long-running
computation it just spawns a thread does that long-running computation and comes
back but the the system that wraps it has the ability to you specify a
distribution of possible running times okay so when you're running in
simulation and you don't worry about wall clock you can allow the run you
could you can have two options right you can basically let the thing return
whenever it's done and then you keep executing or I can basically block and
pick a random number of my of my runtime wait that long in the simulation and
simulation clock and then block arbitrarily waiting for that to return
and that would turn a you know you could model a stochastic amount of evaluation
time in a perfectly deterministic way they might be less performant at in
simulation but it would be determined deterministic so those are the kind of
games that we're trying to play to get to that extra level of reliability did I
say that I said that a bit complicated right so here's my main thread it's
giving an answer every time step so at time this is my main thread okay now I'm
gonna launch my worker thread here okay and it's a long-running computation that
will ultimately change the output of my system okay so you know when it
whenever it returns then the net from now on I'll have a different output from
my main thread okay and here I'm just returning I'm sending the last possible
output and the problem is that if I put a worker thread on a you know and I'm
relying on CPU processing or CPU scheduling to let this thing sort of go
and return whenever it does then it might return here it might return here
might return here I don't know okay so what we do is we flip a coin you know
say I've got a distribution of possible things I've ever run times I've ever
seen okay I will pick a priori that this on this rollout I'm gonna say it landed
at this it returned at this time okay and I will go ahead and do the worker
thread but if it if it took longer than I expected I will block my main
simulation thread pretend the time stopped waiting for that to return so
that it returns here if it returned early that's no problem okay that way I
can still have a distribution of possible return times but everything's
clocked off my random seed so if someone caught me with a you know that if I just
happen to run too long it's gonna hit this sort of a weird corner case I can
reproduce it perfectly okay but it allow it permits for things to have long run
times those are the type of games you have to play I think if there's better
suggestions I'm happy okay so that was a bit of a potpourri of like how do I mix
high-level behavior planning with low-level systems I would say for me
there when I'm implementing a new complicated system I think if I'm
rapidly prototyping something I will do procedural code wrap it up quickly and
and not worry about the extra burden of specifying finite state machines or
behavior trees or whatever and for simple branching logics I wouldn't even
use a task planner okay if the task complexity goes up and the multi-step
reasoning happens then I would bring in a task planner for that and still maybe
just write it in a procedural case but not worry about all this extra stuff
okay but when I start trying to get higher levels of reliability that's when
I think the extra burden of going to state you know to make the explicit
contract between your planning your behavior level computation and the
dynamical system time step becomes essential and doing that right I think
can can take you to the next level so I wish I had like you know here's the
fight in most of the most of the topics we've talked about I'll be like you know
here's the function you call in Drake you know here's the function most of
these are not in in Drake right now they're not in many libraries one of the
I mean some of even the planning stuff is GPL in most places so so finding a
right you know a good like PDDL library to that if we could bring into Drake is
actually non-trivial so you know this is a this is for me a still a work in
progress of trying to get that so you can actually like play with the full
powerful systems but I hope the concepts kind of land good okay so please do
reach out with us if you have questions and you're not sure what's going on with
your project you know reach out to us and next week we'll start learning