That wasn't weird at all.
All right.
So today is the second of our boutique lectures and actually the third to last lecture.
So we've spent the last four or five lectures, I think, on RL and learning.
And today we're going to take a slightly different perspective.
We've been working on how to generate more short-term behavior from scratch.
And today we're going to think more about multi-step manipulation and long horizon planning
and work that is general.
And so to set the stage, I want to give a couple of videos of examples, kind of giving
the motivation of the type of behavior that we're interested in producing.
So the kinds of things that I would like my robots to do-- this is a very simplified kitchen
example.
Here, a green block is supposed to be food.
Just believe with me.
And what we want our robots to do is it's doing what I'll argue is a complex series
of manipulation tasks.
It's placing things.
It's picking things.
It's sequencing the series of actions.
It's making a lot of different choices based off geometry.
It's doing all of that important motion planning stuff.
And this is a video you all have seen before.
Here again, we're doing multi-step manipulation.
And in addition to reasoning over all of the motion constraints here-- and we'll return
back to this example-- we're reasoning over force constraints as well.
And this is to open the bottle.
And the last example I'll give-- I believe so far every robot we've seen has been bolted
to a table.
I don't think we've seen a robot move.
But in the general sense, we have robots that move around.
And so you might imagine I have this robot that can move around and perceive the world.
And in this case, the goal of the robot is to escape the lab.
This is when we used to be on the fourth floor.
And so it's doing this kind of complex series of manipulations that it's planning.
How do I escape the lab?
Oh, there's chairs in the way.
Oh, I need to pick up and move the chairs out of the way.
I feel like often professors are showing off their students' videos.
And I have the joy of I am a student.
And this is showing off the professor's video.
This is by Leslie and Tomas.
They're actually coding in the background.
And at one point, you can see students come in and watch their advisors do work, which
is fun.
So I want my robot to do these kinds of things.
I want my robot to cook.
I want it to open bottles.
I want it to escape the lab.
And you might imagine we've talked about composing high-level behavior before.
If we go way back to lecture 10, we talked about you could script things.
You could do behavior trees, decision trees, finite state machines.
But I think you all got a taste for how complex finite state machines can blow up.
And if we think about accomplishing any one of these tasks, like having to write out the
finite state machine for what these robots do, it gets kind of intractable pretty fast.
So we want to do better.
And that's kind of what motivates what we're talking about today, which is task and motion
planning, which pretty much everyone abbreviates to the word TAMP.
So you're just going to hear the word TAMP over and over again today.
And the highest order bit is that TAMP is a computational mechanism for composing pieces.
Most of what we're going to talk about is planning.
But towards the end, we'll show how you can kind of bring in all of the pieces and that
TAMP overall is a framework.
So we're going to start off with a couple of building blocks of what is background knowledge
necessary.
Oh, I told Danny I wouldn't use this part of the board.
I'm so sorry.
We're going to go over some building blocks.
Then we're going to formalize.
I'm going to actually kind of go on a mini rant about how I like to define TAMP, talk
about the algorithmic components.
And then once we've had that established, I think to make things a little bit more concrete,
we're going to go through a case study example.
We're going to return to that bottle and think about if I wanted to actually code things
up, how would I do it?
And then we're going to end by returning to this idea of TAMP as a computational framework
and show kind of a bunch of different examples of how you can put different pieces in.
This is also a fun way for me to end by just showing you lots of videos of robots doing
cool stuff.
Any questions about where we're going today?
I will front that a lot of what we're going to be talking about today has basis in the
survey paper that our lab wrote last year.
So if you want to look into things further or get deep insight into how this lecture
was structured, I would very highly encourage you to look at our survey paper, which is
only slightly self-promotional.
But it's good work.
So let's dive into the building blocks.
I would argue task and motion planning builds off of kind of three key areas in terms of
where it pulls from.
It is perhaps not surprising that task and motion planning pulls from motion planning
and task planning.
And we're actually going to go through those very quickly because you all are super experienced
in motion planning and you've seen task planning in lecture 10.
And we're going to spend a little bit more time on multimodal motion planning.
Because this is a review in some parts, we can go through it a little bit quicker.
I'm going to actually ask you all to do half the work in terms of answering things.
So to walk through all of these, I'm going to set up a concrete example.
And this is a very, very simple TAMP problem.
Let's say that we have our little yellow robot.
And the red disk is a pizza.
Bear with me.
It's on a green plate.
And we have an oven, which is an orange box.
You could think of it as a hot plate.
And our goal is that we want our robot to cook pizza.
That is the task.
And for right now, we'll say the robot cooks pizza if it moves the pizza onto the hot plate.
That is about as simple as we can get tasks.
Check out.
So let's work through each of our three kind of building blocks.
So you all know motion planning.
It's lectures 15 and 16.
And I'm going to say in the most vanilla form that motion planning is if we have a start
configuration and a set of goal configurations, even our most basic motion planners that give
you the RRT from homework 9, that you're going to find a path from your start to your goal
such that you're collision free.
I'm reintroducing a little bit of notation because it'll help us later.
And so if I give you this RRT, the question I will pose to you all is, have we already
solved the problem?
Can the robot cook pizza if all I give you is an RRT?
Some people are shaking their heads no.
Why not?
You can just shout out.
You do not have to raise your hand.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So Yang is arguing that you have two different-- that the problem changes if you enact with
the state.
So it's an excellent point.
What you cannot do with motion planning in its most basic sense is that you cannot capture
changes in the world.
And so right to Yang's point, you cannot capture the fact that now you are grasping that plate.
So that is going to motivate that in order to capture that kind of structure in the world,
what we want to-- what we use is multimodal motion planning.
By the end of this, you will understand and deeply appreciate the beauty of this figure.
We will get there.
So what we want to do is that we need to introduce modal structure into the problem.
This is where multimodal motion planning gets its name.
What does modal structure mean?
So let's say we have our scene from before.
And we're going to describe this scene with something called a kinematic graph.
And so a kinematic graph is going to represent the state of our world.
It's going to encode the dependencies.
So the-- oh, I'm not tall enough.
Each of our nodes corresponds to an object.
So we have nodes for our world and then attached to our world is our table, attached on top
of our table is our plate, on top of our plate is our pizza.
And the edges represent some level of dependencies, whether it's being supported by or rigidly
attached.
And we're going to call what's represented by this that this is mode sigma, that what
the state of the world as represented by this kinematic graph is mode sigma.
And I would argue that within mode sigma, we can do motion planning, that we can control
the state of our robot joints.
Now if we were to do motion planning and kind of plan for a new configuration queue, would
our kinematic graph change?
If we just do motion planning and we move, basically change our configuration queue,
we move our robot.
Why?
Because I guess the relationship is all the objects want to interact with them, so the
objects [INAUDIBLE]
Yep.
There are no relationships between the objects changed.
That's exactly correct.
So let's say something happens in the world, something mysterious, we'll get back to what
it is.
Something happens in the world and now the robot is holding the plate.
Same question.
Does the kinematic graph change in this case?
Why?
Anyone?
[INAUDIBLE]
Right.
So our kinematic graph changes such that our pizza is still supported by our plate, but
our plate, instead of being supported by a table, is now supported by our robot hand.
Now Yang actually alluded to this earlier, is that we can do motion planning within this
new mode, this mode sigma prime, but it is a different motion planning problem.
In this case, it's a constrained motion planning problem where you maybe have the constraint
that I want to keep my-- you have an orientation constraint and you want to keep your plate
upright, which we know how to do.
But you can do motion planning in both, but they are perhaps two different motion planning
problems.
Now if we have mode sigma and we go to mode sigma prime, how do we go from one to the
other?
So transforming to one to the other is what's called a mode switch.
It's also called a kinematic switch, and that's the instantaneous change in our kinematic
graph.
In this case, what action is represented-- what happened during our mode switch in this
case?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
None of these are trick questions.
So what our robot had to do in order to switch from not holding the plate to holding the
plate is it had to hold the plate.
It had to grasp the plate, and it switched modes.
And there's a neat point in that in order to be able to switch from one mode to the
other, it had to be in a particular configuration where it can grasp, because that is a configuration
where it can switch to being in that next mode.
So if we take away our kinematic graphs, we can now understand one of my favorite figures
of all time, which is that this is the heart of multimodal motion planning, is that you're
basically sequencing planning within modes, switching to a new mode at an intersection
point, and planning within different modes.
And so if we connect that back to our example, we can do single mode motion planning where
we do not change mode, but we change our configuration.
You can imagine that as moving along that green manifold from one configuration to another
until you plan for a point where you can switch.
You have to find a point that's at the intersection of your two manifolds.
That's your mode switch.
Instantaneously-- we're dealing with discrete time-- you're going to not change configuration,
but you're going to instantaneously change mode.
And then you can go along your happy way in your new mode doing more single mode motion
planning.
So to summarize, what the robot's doing here is it has to plan for a sequence of modes.
It has to plan for single mode motion, and it has to plan for mode switches.
So if we return to our question from before, but slightly modified, if I were to give you
kind of a start configuration and a start mode, a goal configuration, a goal mode, and
a multimodal motion planner that does what we just described, can you cook the pizza?
Can the robot now accomplish the task?
I'm going to give everyone like 15 or 20 seconds to really think this one through.
If it can, why?
If it can't, why not?
Any thoughts?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE] Can you explain what you mean?
[INAUDIBLE] So the assumption in normal-- sorry, I should
have mentioned this-- is that we know the set of possible mode transitions.
So we know how we can transition from one mode to another.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE] That is exactly correct.
So you can actually solve this problem with multimodal motion planning.
This is enough.
Our robot could go home.
But in its most basic form, multimodal motion planning is kind of going to do a brute force
search.
So it's going to be horribly inefficient.
Actually for this problem, this problem is so simple enough that it'll be able to solve
it.
But if we wanted the robot to be able to escape the lab, then it's going to become quite a
problem.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE] This is my favorite question.
So there are two multimodal motion planning papers.
And the second one deals exactly with what you're talking about.
And so what it does is rather than having a mode for each grasp, which as you mentioned
could be infinite, they formalize it as that you have a mode family.
And there's a parameter for that family.
So the family is defined as grasping that object.
And the parameter for that is what is your actual grasp.
[INAUDIBLE] Yeah.
It has the-- wait, what do you mean by changing?
[INAUDIBLE] You would have a different manifold for each
grasp.
In picking the mode switch, it is picking up what grasp to do.
And the description of it being a little bit off would be if you were trying to do online
re-planning in the loop.
Other questions?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE] Yeah.
Sorry.
Oh, dear.
My bad.
So the question is, could you deal with basically not sticking contact is, I think, a way to
summarize that.
Generally in multi-modal motion planning, the assumption is made is that you have sticking
contact.
But you can imagine because the representation is like you are doing a single-mode motion
planning that if your mode was I do not have sticking contact, you would need a more complex
planner to handle that.
But you could.
OK.
So multi-modal motion planning might not be efficient enough.
This is where what we're going to do to get around that is we're going to leverage the
representational power that comes from task planning.
And I'm going to go through this part a little bit faster because you all have seen this
to an extent.
So for the next few slides, we're going to be in discrete world.
So you might imagine we have a discrete set of states.
You have some transition function that says what is your legal changes between states.
You have some start states, some goal states.
And your goal is to find a path from start state to goal state following your transitions.
This is the normal setup in task planning.
And you can imagine this as a graph where your nodes are your states and your transition
function just defines your possible, in this case, directed edges.
And so you could just apply graph search if you want to solve this.
So we take this formalism and we're going to apply it to a version of our pizza problem.
But I'm going to switch to making everything discrete for a minute.
And apologies for the icons.
But let's imagine that we have some set of movable bodies.
We have our robot got cuter, our pizza got prettier.
And we have some discrete set of locations that we could be at.
If this is the state of our world, there's a question of how do we define state and how
do we define transitions.
And so for state, we're going to leverage an idea that is critical but seems so obvious
that it's sometimes difficult to understand how critical it is.
And this is the idea called factoring, which is that I'm going to represent the state of
the world by different state variables.
And then I'm going to compose that by taking the Cartesian product of it.
That is to say, I'm going to actually break down what the state is and say, my robot is
at, in this case, the plate.
My pizza is at the box.
My book is at the sofa.
My pizza is not cooked.
And my robot is not holding anything.
And there are like-- we did up math-- like 600 possible states that the state of the
world could be at.
And by factoring things down very nicely, you can represent that super sparsely.
It's very obvious but super critical to being efficient.
So we're going to represent our states in this way.
How are we going to represent our transitions?
This is something you all have actually seen before.
This was in lecture 10, if people recall, preconditions and effects.
Does that vaguely ring a bell?
So preconditions is what needs to be true about our states in order to take some action.
And our effect is, what are the changes in our state once we take that action?
And so if I want to pick up an object at some location, we're going to say that the robot
has to be at that location.
You have to not already be holding something.
The object has to be at that location.
And then the effect, once I've actually done the pick action, is that now the object is
not at that location and I am holding the object.
That is what it means to define our pick operator.
So you can imagine defining a series of operators-- move, move holding, pick, place, cook.
In this case, cook is just going to be a discrete action of being on the oven.
And so if our plan was that we wanted our pizza to be cooked and our pizza to be at
the plate, does someone want to pretend to be a task planner for a minute and give a
feasible plan?
Yeah?
Yes.
You are an excellent task planner.
So that is that we can now find a plan for our task planning.
So that covers all of the preliminaries, all of the building blocks of that we have motion
planning, multimodal motion planning, and task planning.
And with that, I can give the definition of TAMP that I prefer, which is that TAMP is
an extension of multimodal motion planning that leverages the representational efficiency
of task planning.
Multimodal motion planning is abbreviated as MMMP, or you can just add arbitrary M's
as you say it.
OK.
TAMP is an extension of multimodal motion planning that uses the compact representational
strategies from task planning.
So if we have our representations from task planning, and now we want to bring it into
MMMP, we want to bring it into our robot, the question is, what has to change?
I would argue there are two things that we now have to account for, and that is continuous
parameters and constraints on those continuous parameters.
What does that mean?
So we have our pick action from before that we spent some time understanding.
And now if instead of being in a discrete world, you want it to be a real robot, what
has to change?
So now instead of being I have an object, and it's at a discrete location, now we're
going to be dealing with continuous variables.
And so in this case, we're going to have that we have some object.
Our robot is at a configuration Q. Q is a continuous variable.
Our object, instead of being at some discrete location, now we can describe our object as
being at a pose.
Pick your favorite pose representation.
And that we have some grasp.
And so we have a mix of possibly discrete and continuous parameters.
So this makes it a hybrid problem.
Additionally, we have some of the same preconditions and effects that we had before.
In order to pick something up, we assume that our robot is not already holding something.
But now we have to have constraints on our continuous parameters.
For example, the grasp operator-- sorry, Danny, I'm going to go horribly off screen-- is that
it's a constraint that our grasp G is a valid grasp on our object obj.
And we have the constraint that our pose P must be a stable pose for our object obj.
And Ken is that we have some constraint that if our robot is at configuration Q and our
object is at pose P, that is a valid grasp G on our object.
Questions about this?
We've transformed into now dealing with hybrid spaces.
[INAUDIBLE]
Ken is just a grasp.
It's just is that a valid grasp on the object?
And Ken relates in the robot as well.
So Ken is-- notice that grasp is just is that a valid grasp on the object relative to the
object versus Ken is like is your robot in a position where it can now use that grasp.
So we went through a little bit of detail for PIC.
You could do all of this for the same actions we described before.
Now we have to deal with trajectories.
We have to deal with poses and configurations.
And there's continuous but also discrete because we have objects.
So we have this set of operators.
So now we have discrete and continuous operators.
If we were to return to our goal, like our goal is to cook the pizza, I would argue that
a valid solution-- if we run our planner from before, a valid solution would be to move,
pick up the pizza, move, holding it, place it, and cook it.
And the difference here is that now these are over-- we have continuous parameters to
deal with.
It's that you move given a certain trajectory.
There's a reason that I like putting the solution in front of you.
And that is because to me it outlines what are the two things that you need to solve
for.
So I would argue that if we are leveraging all of this in order to find a solution like
this, what we have to do is search over action sequences.
So searching over action sequences is what is the strategy that I'm using.
Here the one that we find is move, pick, move, place, cook.
And then the other thing that we have to do is solve for those continuous parameters.
If that is the strategy that I'm taking, what are valid configurations and poses and grasps?
And you have the constraint that the pose that-- the grasp that you pick at is going
to be the grasp that you're move, holding, and that you're picking with.
And so there's constraints between the different actions.
Does it make sense that the-- sorry.
HDSP is hybrid constraint satisfaction problem.
We are hybrid because we have discrete and continuous parameters.
We're basically trying to find what is a set of variables that satisfies our constraints.
So it's a constraint satisfaction problem.
Yeah?
Which hybrid parameters are considered during the search and which are considered during
the HDSP?
Can you repeat the question?
Yeah.
So it's which parameters are considered during the search and which are considered during
the HDSP.
The exact ones may vary depending on implementation.
But in general, if it is a-- the parameters of the actions are going to be what you have
to find satisfying values for in the HDSP.
And so in this case, it would be q0, all the trajectories, but also a, in this case, object
that's found over.
Yeah?
So to compare this with the most naive level of the MMMT, would you do something like randomly
sample-- because in MMMT, you still need the discrete symbols to specify the goal.
You still need that--
You do not have access to those discrete symbols in the same way.
So then how can you then set the path?
How can you say, cook the food?
So you can define the mode where being cooked is true, but you do not have this ability
to describe this discrete notion of an object being cooked.
You do not have access to that representation.
That is what some of the representational power that we get.
So does that mean you just-- like in MMMT, if you wanted to do the figure, you would
have to specify the exact goal as well, if you're going to do the optional?
You would-- let's see.
You could specify the mode in a set of valid configurations.
You might not have to give the specific configuration.
I see.
So in MMMT, basically, you're trying to chain together these subsets of configurations.
So the idea is you-- so you have a bunch of subsets.
And I guess the thing that the PAMP is doing is replacing-- I guess it's kind of hard to
decide what order you would give the subset.
Which is why MMMT often ends up doing a brute force search.
OK.
So they just randomly sample the order of the subset.
Well, yeah.
We'll get back to what TAMP does instead in like two minutes.
OK.
Good question.
Which I'm probably not repeating.
So this is the mini rant that I promised.
My preferred way to think about what is task in motion planning is that your goal is that
you want to search over a set of action sequences.
And then you want to solve for those resulting parameters.
You have these two components.
And the reason that I prefer that is that, to me, it gets at the heart of what you actually
need to do and gives a point towards what algorithmically are going to be the components.
A lot of times people-- I understand why people do this.
They explain task in motion planning as there's some high level, symbolic, discrete task planning.
And then there's some low level, continuous motion planning.
And you just put them together.
And the more I work on TAMP, the more that deeply frustrates me.
And the problem is that it's not entirely wrong.
But the reason why I find it frustrating is that I don't think it's a helpful framing.
Because it leads you to be like, what is a task?
And what is high level versus low level?
And what do you mean by symbolic?
Jokingly, Leslie banned us from using the word symbolic when we were writing the TAMP
survey.
And I was like, what does it mean anyway?
And I think a lot of misconceptions people often have come from people thinking of it
as these two separate things, when actually what you need to do is you're finding a strategy,
a sequence of actions.
And then you're finding the parameters for those actions.
And you can't decompose high level and low level, because your continuous parameters
have an impact on what strategy you're doing.
And they're deeply intertwined.
So that is my-- you cannot think of these as two separate things.
And although we pull from motion planning and task planning, TAMP is not simply gluing
those two together.
There's a lot more deeper going on.
OK, thank you for listening to my rant.
So the two components that we've outlined is that you have to search over action sequences
and that you have to solve the constraint satisfaction problem.
Searching over action sequences, as we mentioned before, you can think of this as graph search.
And in the very simplest form, you could actually frame searching over the set of possible action
sequences as just A* search.
Luckily, the AI planning community, this is their bread and butter.
And they've developed really awesome planners that take advantage of domain independent
heuristics.
So something called fast forward or fast downward that are really great at doing this search.
So Richard, this goes back to your point of we can now leverage all of the awesome planners
from the AI planning community.
Fortunately, they're not open source, but that's a whole other thing.
So that's how we're going to deal with searching over action sequences.
For searching over hybrid-- for solving constraint satisfaction problems, it's actually a similar
story to the one we told in motion planning, which is that some people do it with sampling
base and some people do it with optimization.
And there are pros and cons between them.
But I don't think we're-- we can talk about that if we have extra time.
But the idea is that there are different ways that you can solve for constraining these
values.
OK, questions?
OK, these are our two components.
What we actually did, if I go back to our survey paper, is that you can actually group
most of the state of the art TAMP methodologies by how they order these components.
And so there's some category that primarily they first focus on.
I want to generate possible values that could be satisfying values for my constraint satisfaction.
And then I'm going to use those values to try to find possible action sequences.
And if I can't do that, I'm going to repeat.
That's like I'm going to try to satisfy my constraints and then sequence them into a
valid plan.
FF Robb, which is work done by my lab mate, is a good example of this.
On the other end of the spectrum, you can imagine, first I'm going to try to find my
action sequences.
And then once I have my action sequences, I'm going to try to find satisfying values
to those constraints.
And a great example of a work that does basically this, but using optimization, is Mark Toussaint's
Planner that he published a couple years back.
Those are two ends of the spectrum.
It will perhaps not surprise you that the majority of work is people who do interleaved,
that you more tightly couple searching over action sequences and solving for your hybrid
constraint satisfaction problems.
So we're going to look at one example to go into a little bit more detail of how this
actually ends up working out.
And specifically, again, this is work done by my lab mate, which is this planner called
Pitital Stream.
We're going to understand it graphically at a somewhat high level.
So what Pitital Stream does-- and again, this is a planner for solving TAMP problems-- is
that it's going to take in a domain, and you have a series of what's called streams.
This is why it's called Pitital Stream.
And those streams basically work to sample possible values.
So this is handling the solving the CSP.
We are sampling possible values.
So that might mean I am sampling possible graphs.
I am sampling possible poses, possible trajectories, possible wrenches, all my possible values.
Once I have that set of variables that I've sampled, I'm going to take my operators, start
state and a goal state, and I'm going to search over my action sequences.
In this case, we're going to use something from the AI planning community.
In this specific case, fast downward.
And it's going to search over possible action sequences using those sampled values from
our streams.
If it can't find something, it's going to use that information to kind of sample for
more values.
It's going to keep doing that until we find a possible plan.
Now one way to think about this is that if we think back to lecture 16, we talked about
PRMs.
People remember PRMs?
So PRMs sample configurations.
Then they build that graph and configuration space, and you search over for a plan.
Pitital Stream is the PRM of TAMP.
And that you can think of it in that it is sampling values, again, which may be discrete
and may be continuous.
It's going to use that to build a pitital search problem, which is then searched through
using an AI planner.
Sample values, search, repeat.
Set check out.
OK.
I'm going to skip over one part.
Not everything is perfect.
There are computational issues.
If we have time, we will come back to this at the very end.
Does the algorithmic components and then Pitital Stream as a specific example make sense to
people?
Are there questions so far?
Yeah.
Isn't the guidance for sampling required?
That was the part I was going to skip.
So the question for guidance for sampling in the shortest form, which you should go
read the paper if you want to know more, or you should already know, is that it's basically
going to use lazy instantiations.
And so it's going to delay sampling for as long as possible and use the information from
the search in order to be more specific about how it picks those samples.
Yes.
This is maybe going back a little bit, but the definition you wrote up there of sampling
and extension of MMMT, representational power of pathfinding, it seems like we not only
get representational power from pathfinding, but also computational efficiency.
Is that accurate?
Yes.
I would say that the representational power is what enables you to leverage that computational
efficiency.
But yeah, that's it.
But yeah, that's correct.
OK.
So what I want to do, we're kind of moving into the third segment, is that to make this
all a little bit concrete and kind of give you all a sense for like, if you had a problem
and you wanted to apply task and motion planning to it, what would that concretely look like?
And kind of give you a flavor of what it is like to use those systems.
So we're going to return-- and this is my bias, due to my work-- we're going to return
to an example that we presented earlier when we were dealing with the case study.
If you all remember, this is when we were talking about impedance control and hybrid
position control.
I introduced this problem.
I'll reintroduce it here.
But you might imagine that I want my robot to get me medicine when I am sick and old,
or either.
And so I want my robot to be able to open childproof bottles.
I'll argue that specifically for a push-twist childproof bottle, what the robot needs to
do in order to open it is that it has to both push down on the cap while twisting.
And that if we are exerting this kind of wrench onto our object, we also have to fixture in
place.
We have to hold it still.
My goal is I want my robot to be able to push-twist the lid and then be able to pull it off so
that it can then, I don't know, give me my vitamins.
Does the context for this problem make sense?
We're going to spend the next, I don't know, 15 minutes with it.
So in thinking through, if I think first about that push-twist operation, there are a lot
of different ways that we could get our robot to do that.
And so the way we brainstormed up is that we wrote out four different ways you can imagine
using the robot's hand or fingers in order to actually exert that push-twist.
I think we only talked about one of them in the context of the control before.
The exact details of them are not terribly important at the moment, but you can imagine
using your grasping it and twisting it, or using your fingers, or using what we call
the palm of the robot, or grasping it.
It could pick up and use a tool.
So these are a couple of different ways that the robot could do that.
If we think about the fixturing side of things, the robot has to hold the bottle still.
There are a couple of different ways that it could do that.
You could get another robot to actually hold the bottle still.
You could put the-- if you have a vice in your kitchen, which maybe you do, the robot
could put the bottle in a vice, or it could use frictional contact in order to hold the
bottle still.
So these are the different components of the different ways that I want to get my robot
to do things.
From this, we can think of is, what is the set of operators concretely for our task?
Before in our pizza example, we had pick, place, and move.
And we do have those same examples, because moving, picking, and placing is almost always
helpful.
We almost always need our robots to move, and pick, and place things.
But then we're going to define a series of operators that are those push-twist actions.
And for our fixturing methods, you don't actually have to-- some of this is just picking and
placing, so you don't have to find new operators.
All you have to do is define opening and closing the vice.
And then we're going to define a special operator, which is removing the cap.
Yeah?
So for these operators, you just define them ahead of time, and then you learn individual
skills, like with whatever type of controller you want ahead of time?
So we will define them.
In this case, we are also going to write the controller.
But later on, I'll show you a method that actually does learn the controllers.
Can you repeat the question?
Yes.
Sorry.
The question was, do you write down these controllers and then learn them?
And the answer is, you do write down the operators.
Whether you learn the controllers or you write them down is kind of a design choice.
But I promise we will get back to it.
So yeah, what you concretely do in this case is that-- what I did as the programmer is
I wrote down this set of operators and the samplers that go with it.
And so to make that a little bit more concrete, I'm going to look at, what does it mean to
actually write one of these operators?
If you had to think through for your problem, what does it mean to write an operator?
Because we've only worked through pick, and pick is one of the simpler ones.
So let's say that this action that we want to do is that the robot grasps the cap, and
it does this push twist.
And if we recall, what we talked about in the previous case study is that the controller
that's actually running to do that push twist is the impedance controller.
So we actually know how to write down that impedance controller, and we're not going
to do any learning in this case.
We're going to use the impedance controller we already wrote down.
So if I'm sitting in my computer, and I want to define the operator, I'm going to define
it over what are the parameters to this action.
In this case, I'm sorry, there are a lot of parameters.
We'll kind of walk through each one.
But we have the parameters.
Some of these are continuous, and some of these are discrete.
A in this case stands for arm, because I have two robots.
And so one of the discrete things that the planner has to reason over is which robot
arm do I use?
And it has two objects, and it has poses for those objects, P0, P1, a relative pose between
them, a grasp that it needs to choose, a wrench that it needs to decide to exert, and then
it needs to decide what is the actual trajectory.
These are the parameters of our action.
What are the preconditions?
What needs to be true?
I also say that before I showed that a thing that needs to happen is that you need to define
constraints.
We're going to actually represent those constraints on the continuous parameters by shoving them
inside our precondition.
And so we're only going to have preconditions of effects and not a separate kind of constraints.
Does that make sense?
So what are our preconditions?
I'm a programmer.
I'm going to write it down.
What I'm going to define is that our object that we're operating on has to be of type
cap, and the other one has to be of type bottle.
This is because in this particular framework, I have specific things that are true about
that object type, and so I want to give that object a particular type.
I'll then specify a constraint that I want to have on my continuous parameters is that
I want P0 to be the pose of the cap and P1 to be the pose of the bottle, and I have some
relative pose defined between them.
So these so far are kind of obvious constraints.
I want my robot to be at a certain starting configuration, Q0, and before I do all this,
I want the hand of my robot arm to be empty because it needs to be able to do this operation.
People following so far?
I know we're getting a little bit into the weeds.
The next two things-- first one is that I want my graph to be stable.
Now, I didn't do a mini lecture on mechanics, so in this case, we'll just say that this
grasp is stable with respect to some wrench.
Honestly, if you want to know more details about grasp stability and mechanics, come
talk to me after.
I love to talk about it.
In this case, we want a grasp such that our grasp is stable, and we want to make sure
that our bottle is stabilized.
And so that is that one of those things from before is true.
Either another robot is holding our bottle, or our bottle is in our vice, or we have enough
frictional contact in order to stabilize that bottle, and this is with respect to a given
wrench.
Wrench is a force and a torque.
Then comes the biggest and most powerful sampler, which is that we now want to define a relation
over all of our objects, and this is the sampler that's actually going to generate the trajectory.
And if we remember that this is the trajectory that it's generating, it's generating that
impedance controls parameters.
Does that stop me if that doesn't make sense?
So what this is generating is it's going to take in the object that is the cap and the
bottle in those poses, and it's going to say, what is the motion that the robot has to achieve
in order to, in this case, do this twisting motion?
So when we talked about the control parameters before, because of the impedance control,
it's generating a series of set points and a series of stiffnesses for what are our impedances.
And so what you can think of is that this is a sampler that basically takes in information
about our current state and outputs what our robot should do, in this case, Cartesian set
points and impedances.
Yeah?
So where do you encode the fact that how much of rotation it needs to have a [INAUDIBLE]
So the question is, where do I actually encode what it means to do this motion?
In this case, it's how much do I twist.
In this case, that is a predefined thing within the sampler, but you could also imagine that
being a parameter.
It could be yet another continuous parameter.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
It takes in, what is my robot, what are my objects, and where are those objects, and
what is the wrench that I want to be exerting as I do that push twist?
And it is going to return you the trajectory, which in this case is your Cartesian impedances
and your set points.
[INAUDIBLE]
Those are the outputs of your sampler.
Some of these are inputs, and some of these are outputs, because it is simply defining
a relation over all of them.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
So this is-- yeah, that's an excellent question.
How do I go from-- you notice that there is an and on top, and so this is the precondition
has to be true.
And so what's happening here is that twist hand can is a relation over all of these parameters
and connected to that relation is a sampler that is generating satisfying values of those
parameters.
And so basically, if the sampler is able to return values, then that constraint is satisfied.
If it can't return things, then there isn't satisfying solutions, so it isn't satisfied,
and this thing would render as false.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Don't believe I understand your question.
It will also return the trajectory.
So what it does is it returns where there's true, and it populates that variable t with
the solution.
[INAUDIBLE]
Gets stored.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
It is just enough to loosen the cap.
We made the design choice that there is another operator which actually pops it off.
Actually the reason why we wanted to separate the twisting motion from the removing motion
is because I gave that picture that there are four different ways that you could do
the twisting, and so I want to separate twisting from removing it.
Because I'd have to copy the removing it into all four of those.
Good.
OK.
We're actually not done.
There's one other thing, which is that we want to check that our trajectory is collision-free.
So those are all of our preconditions.
These are the things that need to be true, and we built it together.
These are the things that need to be true, and these are the variables that we're basically
solving for that satisfy these constraints.
In order to fully characterize this, we also have to define what is the effect of this
action.
And so the effect of our action, the main thing is that we're going to say that the
cap is now twisted off, and that we are not at the configuration that we started at, and
we are now at the configuration that's basically at the end of our trajectory.
Our robot has moved as a result of this action.
Constraints are almost always easier to specify than preconditions.
That is a deep dive into what is it like to actually specify one operator.
And so that hopefully gives you all a sense for what it is like to write these operators,
is that you write what is the specification in terms of preconditions and effects, specifically
in this framework in Prediddle, and then you write all of those samplers that actually
does the controller generation.
In this case, we write it in Python.
So now you've done that work.
You've written all of your operators.
We're going to tape our operators, and we're going to put it in Prediddle stream, and we
can now actually appreciate the video that I showed from before, which is that the goal
of our robot is that we want to uncap.
So the robot is going to first do a move, pick, and then place it in the vice.
It's then going to do that push-twist that we just spent a while discussing before removing
that cap.
So it searched over to find that action sequence of move, pick, move, place, and it solved
for all of the continuous parameters.
What are the trajectories?
What are the paths?
What are the actual configurations and the grasps?
Yeah?
It has the on-flip, and then it's just dividing, so it's just going to do a--
It did.
Can you repeat the question?
So the question is, did it have all of the operators possible?
Could it have picked-- yes.
In that case, it chose to do a grasp twist.
And the beautiful thing is that if I give my robot the list of operators, there are
many, many different ways that it can solve the same task.
I've learned I can't talk while this video is playing because everyone just watches the
video.
Let it play.
I was asking it to do the same task.
The environment was different in each one in that the bottle was in different starting
locations and the objects were in different starting locations.
And in some cases, there was the tool, and in some cases, there was the mat, and there
was only a vice in one of them.
And the robot is essentially doing the planning of how do I sequence those set of actions
to accomplish this task?
And the really beautiful thing about this is that it is searching over a space that
is combinatorial.
This is showing not even all the possibilities, but I put all the possible push twists versus
all the possible fixturings.
And the beautiful thing is what I love so much about this is I gave my robot-- here
is a list of operators.
Here are the different things that you can do.
And then it does the work to find all of the different possibilities.
It does the combinatorial search to find how can I compose these operators to find a satisfying
plan to achieve my goal.
Yeah?
Is it possible to use the first two different levels?
I can imagine one of the steps would be like, I'm Captain Medicine Bottle, and then the
next thing would be like, do a bunch of other tasks.
Can you superimpose multiple levels of this?
Yeah.
So the question is, can you have hierarchy?
So the famous task in motion planners is hierarchical planning in the now.
It is actually Leslie and Tomas's task in motion planner is built upon this idea that
if you want to do truly long horizon tasks, then you have to have notions of hierarchy.
So yes, and a lot of people have thought about it.
Yeah?
It says a point of reference.
How long does it take to find a process in wall process?
You mean for each individual one?
If I wanted to find a plan?
A plan.
So I have the results of that in the paper that this work is based off of.
But if you want to do order of magnitude, sometimes under a minute or up to two to three
minutes in this case.
Part of that is because there are two reasons why it takes-- well, I don't know whether
you think a few minutes is a long time or not.
But there are a few reasons.
One is that I don't optimize any of my code for speed.
And so it almost certainly could be faster.
And I just don't care.
And the second is that there are actually-- and this is something that's good-- computational
bottlenecks that can make this search difficult.
And that you can imagine-- if you were solving a constraint satisfaction problem, and the
space of satisfying solutions is rather small, then-- and especially given that we, in this
case, are taking a sampling-based approach-- that it's going to take a while to sample
satisfying solutions.
So sometimes I can set up this problem such that it's like if I require exerting a lot
of force, such as there are only a few configurations that actually can achieve that, then I've
basically made my constraint satisfaction problem very hard.
And so the planer struggles.
And it takes longer.
OK.
So this is hopefully a little bit of an example of what it is like to use a task in motion
planer.
And in this case, although I did not emphasize it too terribly, this is a task in motion
planer instance where we are also bringing in aspects of control, leveraging impedance
control, and different mechanics.
I want to expand upon that point-- this is going to bring us to our last section-- about
TAMP as a computational framework.
And I want to hammer this home by showing-- I've been showing mainly kinematic things
and taking a very planning-based approach.
And I want to show you that a lot of the pieces that we've learned in this class so far fit
within this framework and that you can integrate them in.
And this enables you to do super awesome things.
Admittedly, this is also just going to be me showing off a lot of the work that our
lab has done.
Because nothing is more fun than bragging about your friends.
And so we're going to show a lot of videos of awesome stuff that task in motion planning
can do, which maybe hopefully gets you excited about things that you could do with task in
motion planning.
OK.
A valid complaint you can make about what I've shown you so far is that there is no
perception involved.
And personally, in my work, I do not deal with perception.
But that is not a limitation of task in motion planning.
So we've had people in the lab who wanted to integrate perception in to task in motion
planning.
And so you have your task in motion planner from before.
But instead of a priori assuming you know where everything in the world is, which is
what I do, is that we're actually going to use all the perception tools that we've learned
throughout this class.
In this case, they're going to take an image and operate on point clouds.
And in this work, they used a lot of pre-trained models and a lot of awesome stuff.
We talked about math, RCNN, in lecture 9, maybe?
No, I don't remember.
In this case, instead of operating on known poses and known objects, that your task in
motion planner is operating on the output of these pre-trained perception models.
And that allows you to do super cool stuff, like instead of having to have a notion of
object state, what you can do is I want to put everything that's red in the red bowl
and everything that is green in the green bowl.
Notice that bananas are green, which is-- I don't know what perception system did that,
but it's the decision made.
And right here, it's putting all of the objects in the opposite color regions.
And to go into a little bit of detail, the different perception elements that are getting
used is that it is segmenting out the table, and then it's segmenting out all of the objects.
In this case, for a lot of these, doing color detection and is operating directly on those
point clouds.
The other thing that it's doing is to specify a set of graphs that is using GDP, which is
the learning-based method, to generate those graphs as opposed to those graphs being generated
a priority.
So this gets back a little bit to the question of are things learned?
In this case, for this system, some elements are learned.
For each of these, I'm going to have to say, if you want to learn more, I've listed the
paper down below.
So this is just a little bit of a sampling.
There was a question before, which is you write out all of these things, and do you
learn your controllers, or do you specify your controllers?
This was your question.
And in the case that I showed, we wrote down our controllers.
But maybe you don't want to write down controllers all day.
And so there's a project in the lab that was, what if we want to acquire new skills by actually
assuming that we have the controller, and we want to learn the parameters of our controller
in order to use it?
Let's make that a little bit more concrete.
Let's say that I would like my robot to learn how to pour.
And I have some specification for what it's like to pour, and I want to learn how do I
have to move my arm such that I can have a successful pour?
And I do not want to have to write down this controller from scratch.
So what they did, step one of learning is we need to collect data.
And oh, man, I hope this video loads.
So our robot needs to learn how to scoop, how to pour.
And so we're going to first collect a lot of data.
I will point out that it is times 40x.
And we're going to have our robot collect a lot of data.
Z is the lovely grad student running around in the background.
The nice thing about this is that what we're going to do is it's going to pour over and
over again.
And this is actually labeled data for whether the pour is successful, because you can measure
that's actually a scale.
It's what is the weight of the amount that I've poured.
And so you can imagine if the weight is very high, then I've had a successful pour, because
most of-- those are chickpeas.
So the chickpeas went in the bowl.
And if the weight is very low, then that's an unsuccessful pour.
And so we ask our robot to do this over and over again.
And we collect a lot of labeled data about what are the control parameters that lead
to a successful pour.
Does the data collection make sense?
If you were worried about what happened during COVID, what did the statum mice eat?
They ate all of our chickpeas.
It was gross.
So you have some grad student, in this case, Z, collect a lot of data.
And it's labeled training data, which is super awesome.
And what they did in this case is given the kind of specification of our action and given
a lot of labeled data, what we're going to do is we're going to learn a constraint, which
defines what are the valid control parameters that lead to a successful pour.
In this case, they use a Gaussian process regression.
Their argument, which again, they make more beautifully in the paper, is that this is
useful for sampling and that it is great for data efficiency.
And having watched the video from before, you might imagine why they really cared about
data efficiency in this context.
So to summarize, they gathered a lot of data.
And they used learning method in order to characterize what are the control parameters
that lead to a successful pour.
I will say they use Gaussian process regression.
You could swap in any learning method that you wanted to if you wanted to learn the control
parameters.
But the nice thing is that they gathered enough data.
We cleaned up the chickpeas.
And that now our robot has effectively acquired a new skill, and that it can now do pouring.
There's nothing in the cup, the first pour, which I find super weird.
But there is stuff in the second pour.
So we'll wait for the second pour.
We'll notice the goal is to pour.
But because we've added a new skill, we haven't lost what we've had before.
And so we still have all of-- yeah, there it goes.
Is it still doing all of that geometric reasoning?
I'll pause it for a minute.
We've added a new skill of how to do pouring.
But we haven't lost the fact that we know how to do pick and place.
We know how to do all of these other things.
We've just added something in into our existing repertoire of skills.
And once we've added in our skill, we can now search over action sequences that involve
that new skill.
And you can imagine maybe you use a different method.
You learn a new skill.
You add it in.
Now your robot has more capability.
You just keep building.
Cool.
This is one way to integrate learning.
And there's a lot of different ways.
But one other way that I'll mention that's just skipping is that something that we talked
about that Charles asked about is like-- OK, you didn't ask why things are slow.
But that's an interpretation of what your question could be-- is that you can imagine
also using learning to speed up your search, that can we use prior experience to speed
up this search over action sequences?
And there was some work done by our lab.
This again shows off mobile robot manipulation in the PR2 style of moving.
And now what this does is actually, if you're searching over action sequences, it learns
a Q function in order to bias what action sequences you want to explore.
We mentioned that you get computational efficiency from task planning.
The question is, what if I'm planning really long horizon stuff and I want to move even
faster?
And what they showed with this work is that you can basically learn this Q function that
speeds up your planning by a couple of factors.
Cool.
Those are two ways to integrate learning.
Those are not all of the possible ways.
But I hope it gives you a flavor of the ways so far of how you can integrate perception,
how you can integrate control, and how you can integrate learning into task and motion
planning.
OK.
There's one more thing that I want to cover.
And to be honest, I'm sneaking a special topic inside a special topic.
Something that we haven't talked about so far that I'd be remiss if I didn't mention
is uncertainty.
If we think about what we've dealt with so far, we've kind of assumed that the world
is observable, that things are deterministic, that we know how the world is going to act.
I wrote out those operators and I said, this is what's going to happen in the world.
And it's making kind of a strong assumption, like I know what's going to happen.
Because the world is not deterministic.
The world is not observable.
The world is stochastic.
The world is partially observable.
The cabling is correct.
The world is a POMDP.
So how can we get our-- if we want to use this framework, how can we have a framework
that still deals with uncertainty?
Does the setup of what we want to do make sense?
OK.
So I don't know if this was mentioned previously, but we're going to introduce-- instead of
saying I know what the state of the world is, we're going to introduce this notion of
belief space.
And instead of saying the pose of the object is here, we're going to have a probability
distribution over your underlying world states.
Instead of saying the object poses here, I'm going to say I have a probability distribution
of where my object could be.
And what this means is I have a belief over where my object is.
So the robot, in now planning, has to maintain what is its belief over where things are.
And you might imagine that if I am a robot, I have some belief that my computer is on
the table.
But maybe I do not know exactly where it is because I'm not facing it.
And that if I use my perception system and I observe that I can update my belief on where
I believe the pose of my computer to be.
And so our system now needs to-- instead of saying this is the state of our world and
updating our state, we have a belief over our world.
And we may need to take actions that allow us to update what is the belief of our world.
And now instead of our effects being on state, our effects are going to be on our belief.
That setup makes sense.
Now, there's been a couple of different ways that people have done belief space planning.
This is perhaps one of the earlier ones.
This is actually-- the robot escaping the lab from earlier comes from this paper.
But the example I specifically want to show is a bit more recent and actually uses that
podidal stream planner that we discussed from before.
So this is going to keep track of belief specifically using particle filter.
If it doesn't mean anything to you, that is OK.
It is a representation for how we're going to represent our belief.
And what our robot's going to do is I'm going to show this by example.
That our robot's goal-- our robot's goal is to cook spam.
It's not for me, but it's cooking spam for someone.
And it doesn't know where the spam is at the beginning.
And so what it starts off is that we say that the robot has a prior that there is a uniform
distribution of where the spam could be on the table.
It does not know initially where it is.
It just knows that there's a uniform prior over positions on the table.
And so what the robot decides to do is it says, well, the sugar box is in the way.
And so I'm going to make a plan to pick up the sugar box to see if I can perceive the
spam and update my belief on where the spam is.
It's going to pick up the sugar box.
It does an observation.
It updates its belief that the spam is not behind the sugar box.
And so it says, OK, where else could it be?
Maybe it's behind the Cheez-It box.
This is the same Cheez-It box from the YCB object.
Everyone uses Cheez-It boxes.
And so it moves the Cheez-It box.
And the first times it moves it, it still can't perceive that the spam is there.
It cannot update its belief.
And so it tries again.
And it actually moves it further away.
And now it can finally perceive the spam.
It updates its belief about where it believes the spam to be.
And now it can cook the spam.
It cooks the spam.
But what we saw is that the robot had some belief on where things were.
And it had to do what's called information gathering actions in terms of, well, I can't
see it now.
I should-- this is a very weird set of videos to pause on.
And it's going to take information gathering actions in order to update its belief in order
to basically be sure of where things are before it acts.
This is the same Predictable Stream Planner that we had before.
And it has basically a few extensions.
One is that instead of operating on states, it's going to be operating on belief.
There's some notion of replanning, that as soon as you get an update about your belief,
you have to replan and pick what is my new sequence of actions and new satisfying values
based off that new belief.
And those are the two key elements that we need to do in order to enable belief-based
planning.
I'll show one other video just because it's super neat.
Our goal is that we want to have the spam in the bottom drawer.
And we have a uniform distribution on where our spam could be.
It could be either in the top drawer or the bottom drawer.
Our goal is for the spam to be in the bottom drawer.
And we do not know where it is initially.
So what the robot does is it first opens the bottom drawer.
Because if the spam were there, we would already be done.
And so it observes-- I will say, in this case, the camera is overhead.
And so it observes.
It says, the spam is not there.
Therefore, I update my belief.
Because it was not in the top drawer, it must be in the bottom drawer.
So I will go open the bottom drawer.
I will observe.
Sure enough, my spam container is there.
In this case, it actually has to put the spam on the tabletop in order to have its hand
free.
So it can close the drawer.
Then it uses its open hand to open the bottom drawer.
And now it can place the spam there and observe that we've achieved our goal, which is that
our spam is safely stored away in our bottom drawer.
Yes?
You said you pick the bottom drawer first.
But there's no optimization in that pattern, right?
No.
So there is actually two versions of this video.
One is that it picks the top drawer first.
Yeah.
So Russ's-- sorry, Russ's question is, there's no optimization happening.
So why would it pick the bottom drawer first?
And that actually gets to a point-- we've been talking about solving constraint satisfaction
problems.
But in this case, all of what we've been talking about is finding satisfying values and not
necessarily optimal values.
You can imagine having a constraint satisfaction solver that leverages optimization such that
you actually do get optimal values.
But in this case, it's not.
Another question?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
The most general form of phrasing Richard's question is, why is all of this worth it?
And what is it value?
And so you could script this behavior.
If I gave you this environment and I said, hey, I want you to get the spam in the bottom
drawer and the spam is either in the top drawer or the bottom drawer, I have full belief that--
OK, pun not intended.
I think that you all could write a script where the robot does exactly that.
You could recreate this behavior.
It'd be kind of a weird final product, but you could do it.
If the environment changes at all, you have to re-script it out.
If I gave you a new robot or if I gave you a different object or if I said, now there
are three drawers or now my probability distribution is that I believe my prior is that the spam
is on the tabletop, you would have to re-script out that behavior.
And so the generality that this gets is that I have defined each of my operators and that
the task and motion planning element composes that in order to solve my problem.
And if I give you a new environment or new objects or a new robot or new settings, you
can still kind of throw all of this power at it.
You do not need to re-script out robot trajectory, then grasp, and then move, and then pick.
The robot is doing that sequencing for you.
One of the reasons I love task and motion planning is it allows me to be lazy.
I do not want to have to tell my robot what to do.
I want it to figure it out for itself.
And when you're scripting, you are telling it, do this and then this and then this.
Task and motion planning, it is figuring out what is my valid sequence of actions given
you've told me what I can do.
Yeah?
Is there any problem with the-- when you have the expectation part, is it a problem that
you get something that is resulted in a task?
So that you're--
Yeah.
So what about the deterministic part of each task?
So let's say like it drops a can or something.
Yeah.
So the question is, what if things are not deterministic and something changes midway?
So the case study that we walked through with the bottle, it would absolutely be a problem
because there is no replanning there.
It plans everything ahead of time.
And the robot basically closes its eyes and tries to do it.
And so if you, as like a pesky human, ran into the middle of my experiments, the robot
would not know what to do.
In this case, because it is perceiving and continuously updating its belief, it is doing
replanning.
It is replanning based off its belief.
And so if you were to kind of walk in and like steal the spam, it would update its belief
and replan accordingly.
OK.
So we are exactly at time.
I'll just leave with-- this is the list of kind of all of the papers in about rough order
of the things we covered.
We actually didn't cover some middle part of this.
But I think they're really cool.
And so if you're kind of interested in explaining this more, again, highest priority probably
goes to the survey paper, which kind of summarizes all of this.
But these are kind of neat extensions of things you can do with task and motion planning.
Yeah.
If there are no final questions, this has been the special topic on TAMP.
Thanks, everybody.
[APPLAUSE]