A lot of people are already traveling,
but I'm happy to be here.
So we're going to do sort of the last of our three RL lectures,
although maybe we'll do a little bit
of the model-based version of RL in one of the boutique lectures.
But I want to--
first of all, especially since there's a few less of us,
I think if you guys have any questions whatsoever about RL,
you can ask me anything, any time.
But Abhishek, in particular, promised
that I would fill in a few details,
and I fully intend to do that, connecting
some of the ideas we talked about already,
from policy search and BlackBock optimization
to the actor-critic kind of ideas that he talked about
and why that can help with sample efficiency.
But I also want to talk through just a couple
of specific examples and maybe even discuss
some of the ongoing work to understand when RL works
and why it works when it does work.
OK, so let's start.
Of course, having said that, I should
wait to see if there's any questions.
Anybody have general questions on what
we've talked about so far or Abhi's lecture?
Well, any time.
Please say anything.
OK, so let's just think about what we've said about RL so far.
So I started off with a picture of RL as BlackBox optimization.
And I tried to draw some pictures of how
zero-order methods, methods that don't
rely on any analytical gradient calculations of the plant,
or they just rely on samples of the--
or rollouts from your simulator, have different properties.
Some of them can be desirable, right?
So if we think about some general cost landscape,
but maybe it's got lots of jagged stuff right here,
and I want to do an optimization on it,
then my gradients might be locally not very informative.
But sample-based algorithms could potentially
take samples and estimate the local curvature very nicely
and very robustly.
So that's one of the ideas we've put out there.
We talked about, very quickly--
I want to connect the dots again a little bit--
the policy gradient idea.
So I think of this as doing, let's say, direct policy
search.
So I'm going to search directly in the parameters
of the policy.
For instance, if I have some policy with parameters theta,
and I want to search directly in theta,
I could do it with these kind of tools, right?
Even if theta is buried in a long-term optimization
where I want to try to minimize the sum
over some long-term rewards where
these are the rollouts of some simulation, right?
So if I write it more carefully here,
these are the fundamental equations of optimal control
and certainly of RL.
Now, the way I've written it, that
looks like a constrained optimization.
If I want to minimize this over theta, for instance,
that looks like some constrained optimization.
But because these equations are easily
solved away by just forward simulating
from some initial conditions, you
can do this with an unconstrained optimization
and black box methods.
The policy gradient family of algorithms, in particular,
combines some sample-based optimization
with analytical gradients of the policy.
[TYPING]
Which makes total sense, right?
If you have a neural network in the middle as your policy,
and we know very well how to-- we
have very efficient implementations of backprop
that run on GPUs.
So we should be able to leverage those gradients.
But if we don't know f, and we don't maybe
know the loss function, then it might
make sense to do some sort of black box optimization
to take care of these things and some analytical gradients
for the policy.
And that's the type of algorithms that you
explored on your homework and that Abhi
was starting to talk about in his lectures
in the policy gradient and actor-critic space.
[TYPING]
These are the reminders so far, right?
Abhi talked about a couple big ideas.
I mean, he talked about how to specify objectives
in the real world, right?
The imitation learning side of--
or sorry, the inverse reinforcement learning
side of imitation learning.
He talked about multitask RL, how
you can keep the data collection going if you learn--
don't just train it to open a door.
Train it to open a door and close a door,
and then you can get this continuous cycle of learning.
And even if you can't open a door yet,
you can make systems that do that very well.
But he talked about data efficiency, too,
as a major challenge for getting RL to work in the real world.
And there were a couple ideas that he brought up
that we want to follow up on today, right?
So he talked about actor-critic variance of policy gradient,
which can optimize faster.
They can be lower--
can provide lower variance estimates of the gradient.
And he also talked about Q-learning,
and in particular, off-policy and experience replay
kind of ideas.
And I think he actually said on his slide--
Russ will fill in the details on some of these things.
So there we go.
Thank you.
So to talk through this, I want to use a running example.
So you remember this example that I cooked up
from the force control lecture, where we had first a force
controller that did this very careful.
And I could put it on a tele-op, and I could have it-- oh,
stay inside the friction cone, rotate the Cheez-It box
up on the corner.
Right?
And then we talked about stiffness control
and how once we had the stiffness control,
there was actually an open-loop trajectory.
You could just close your eyes and move the finger
through this cycle, and it would very robustly flip that box up
with the thinking of the programming the virtual spring.
Right?
So what I was doing last night, I decided to code up
with stiffness control, this as an RL problem,
and throw some of the popular algorithms at it,
PPO and SAC and the like.
And you would think--
I even said, the control parameterization
of stiffness control should help RL, too.
So I want to work through that as an example here.
This is, I think, a good example for today.
So the first question is, which RL algorithm should we use?
And if you look down the list--
so we are in the space of--
this is what our algorithms are available in the main stable
baselines 3 repo.
So the categories here are your action space.
So we're in the box place where we have continuous actions.
All these other ones are discrete actions,
but we have continuous actions if we want to have a--
let me even write it down here.
So my box flip up example, B0 in the standard RL case.
So I'll set up my actions to be the xy position
for stiffness control, the virtual finger.
All right.
Now, if you remember, the stiffness control
in its full glory, when your robot is a point finger,
it looks almost like PD control.
It's PD control plus gravity comp.
So that sounds fancy.
It is fancy in its generality, but for a point finger,
it's kind of just PD control.
So we're not doing anything super special there.
My observations-- we can have a couple
of different variants of it, but let's start with just
the full state feedback.
So that's got the box state plus the finger state.
So that's in the plane xy theta x dot y dot theta dot.
The finger state is just-- since it's a sphere,
I've only given it the two degrees of freedom.
But it adds up.
Even though it's a super simplified problem,
it's still got a lot of state variables.
And it's not approachable by our brute force
gridding the state space kind of approaches.
So we need some sort of neural network kind
of function approximators in the middle.
My reward now is going to be something about the box angle.
I want the box to be flipped up.
And then I'll have something about low effort
to try to discourage the finger from going totally nuts.
And there's actually a few other please
don't go totally nuts terms that I put in.
Nothing's scary.
It's just like damping.
In general, I'm allergic to trying to tune cost functions,
possibly to a fault. But my videos look more janky.
And then in the OpenAI Gym case, I'm
just going to terminate if time is greater than 10
or my multibody plant crashed, which
I don't feel bad about that because this
is a game about trying to-- I mean,
I could set the time step of the simulator small enough
that it would never crash.
But I would be paying a price for simulations
that are reasonable.
And I actually want to discourage simulations
that are unreasonable.
So I think aggressively want to choose my step size
to be large, put myself in a regime
where some of the rollouts will crash,
and tell it it's bad to crash.
Yeah?
So when you're trying to do a continuous simulation
in a framework like RL where you want to have steps
and you get a reward in each step,
how do you set the RL step size versus your Euler condition
step size?
That's awesome.
So the question is, there's a subtlety
if you've got your RL step size.
The gym step function takes some amount of step,
has some step size.
And then I have a continuous dynamical system underneath
that I'm using integration for.
I think those are often very different.
In general, the step that you need in your gym
is like your control frequency.
I chose it to be large, like 0.1,
even though I'm going to simulate under the hood
at a millisecond or something like this.
I started cheating it up to be a few milliseconds.
But it's down in the physics dynamics regime
in order to do proper time stepping.
But I'm-- and in general, the Drake gym end
will just call the integrator.
So whatever systems you have, continuous or discrete
or whatever, it will simulate them
with whatever resolution you care about for whatever
the gym time step is, which is typically high.
Great question.
OK, so given we have these continuous actions,
I mean, that's an action space that's small enough
that I could discretize.
So I could use a few of the other algorithms
if we chose to discretize the action space.
But I think in the spirit of making
it work for non-point fingers, let's
stick to the continuous action space.
That's where we normally are for robotics.
So there aren't that many choices.
It rules out a lot of the--
well, let's see.
The combination of wanting to do continuous actions
and multiprocessing rules out a lot of the algorithms.
And that's, I think, true.
I think there are a few algorithms that
tend to be very popular because they
can handle continuous actions and handle multiprocessing.
In particular, PPO is a very popular choice,
I think, for those reasons.
So if you look at, for instance, the OpenAI learning dexterity
paper, PPO has become the default reinforcement learning
algorithm at OpenAI because of its ease of use
and good performance.
I think in particular in the multiprocessing case.
So when you don't care about data,
you're going to do massive multithreaded stuff.
Then PPO tends to be the tool of choice.
I think if you care about data and you're
doing it on a real robot, people will
tend to prefer SAC or one of the other variants that
is using replay and experience in order
to be more data efficient.
But we're in simulation world right now,
so we're going to continue to see this trend.
This is recent.
I meant to show this last week.
This is the recent result from Pulkit and his group,
which won the best paper award at Coral.
Congratulations to them.
And it's a nice generalization of the original OpenAI work,
where it's doing maybe more general, if you will,
in-hand reorientation.
But it also does it upside down in unstable configurations.
So I would encourage you to read that paper,
but that's not really what we're talking about yet.
I just wanted to emphasize that it's also using PPO.
And you see, in the context of the last lecture,
I was going to point out the impressive evaluations
that they did.
OK, so I told you packages like stable baselines
have gotten pretty good.
Stable baselines 3, it's really pretty darn easy
to implement these algorithms now,
to try a suite of these algorithms on the simulator.
So I made a little box flip up environment
with the Drake Gym environment wrapper.
And it's like three lines, really,
to start running PPO on it.
Admittedly, you can probably do better
than picking the absolute default
arguments of everything.
But I'm making a point here, right?
So I'm really just going to use the default MLP policy, which,
by the way, is this--
the fact that that is even a thing is interesting, right?
That almost every paper that uses MLP policies
has the same architecture always.
And it's a small network.
So when people talk about deep RL,
and then they always use a three-layer network
with 255 hidden units, it's like, that doesn't match.
OK, and then it's only, again, a few steps
to run the actual simulation once you get it out.
You can just ask the model for the--
this is the policy coming out.
It's very simple and very clean.
My cost function is, like I said, it's the box angle.
I put a little disincentive to have a large box velocity,
angular velocity, disincentive for effort,
and finger velocity.
And then I'll show you why there's a 10 there in a minute.
OK, so I put this in there.
My machine at home is bigger than my little laptop here.
It's got, like, 56 effective cores.
So I'm like, I'll run it on 48 of them.
That way, I can still tell it to stop if it goes badly,
or leave a few cores for the cursor.
OK, so I ran it last night.
And I woke up this morning to see what it did.
And this is what it does.
So it's going to reset every 10 seconds.
Sorry.
It kind of solves the problem.
The box always ends up in a configuration
that I guess I asked for.
But this is also--
it's sort of classic RL, right?
I mean, this is what you expect and what you see.
I immediately thought, I could make that better.
And I definitely can.
But like I said, I'm kind of allergic to cost function
tuning.
And it takes a lot of time, actually,
I think, to go from this step to, like, it looks beautiful.
I think there's a lot of cost for lower returns.
But it's awesome.
I mean, it solved this problem with very little handholding.
I could tell you, I had three bugs
that I had to work through, which are kind of funny.
But I'll tell you about them in a second.
OK, and it's got a very robust, if terrifying,
to run on a real robot policy.
OK?
Question?
Yeah.
When you see RL policy jittering like that,
do you worry that it's exploiting
hard facts and simulations that show up
in terms of high velocity impact?
Yeah, so it ran to convergence.
I mean, so this is what--
the curves kind of go up.
And then they flutter around a lot.
It'll get confused for a little while to come back, right?
So I don't claim that this is terminated exactly
at the best policy that PPO ever saw.
This is just whatever was at when I woke up this morning.
OK.
And so let me just--
so why the heck is the finger kind of going around like this
after the box is up, right?
My cost function was clearly said,
don't move if you don't need to, right?
So in any sense of doing a good job of optimization,
it's clearly not even at a local minimum.
I mean, there shouldn't be any problem with it
having to do the same policy, but then once the box is up,
just set the velocity to zero.
So there's something weird kind of going on there.
Maybe it's just entering states that weren't trained enough
or whatever, right?
It just didn't visit enough.
And your question-- sorry to get a roundabout answer here.
So do I worry about it exploiting?
I think there's a very explicit way it started exploiting,
which I'm going to tell you in a second.
But in general, I think--
I mean, there's two features.
There's one thing, which is that because we haven't put
any biases on our policy, right?
We haven't sort of put any priors, let me call it,
on the policy.
It's easy to be in a place where it's never visited before
and take an insane action.
I do worry about that a lot, right?
We haven't said what you should do everywhere
in any rigorous way.
The other thing, which is people often
talk about in terms of value alignment, for instance,
is that I think it's very hard to write a cost
function that fully captures--
if it did optimize the cost function.
But I think there's a lot of things
that we encode in our robot solutions, which are subtle
and they're implied, like don't move your finger
at incredible velocities.
It's somehow implied in most of my optimizations
in a way that maybe I've parameterized myself out
of that.
And by virtue of having not specifically specified it
in these problems, it will find those solutions,
unless you tell it not to.
So yeah, Leslie Kelbling talks about the-- what did she call
it--
background utilities, for instance.
She says, you can tell the robot to put the dishes from the sink
into the dishwasher, but you also
have to tell it, like, never throw a mug through the window
and never stick your finger in a light socket.
There's all these things that we have in our head
from common sense that we haven't told the robot not
to do them.
And if you just let it go in the simulator,
it's going to do those things.
And when you see real robot videos saying
they learned to do something and they never threw their fist
through the door or whatever, then you have to ask,
why didn't it happen?
And how much reward engineering did you
do in order to make that not happen?
This code is all--
I'm trying to make it run better in notebooks,
but otherwise it's going to be pushed.
OK, so yeah, use the stiffness control.
You'll see, if you look at the code,
that we do have some mechanisms right inside multi-body plant
to set random distribution so that it is easy to do.
It's doing multiprocessing using subprocesses.
If this was my research project and I
wanted to make it run faster or whatever,
there's lots of things I could do, for instance.
Right now, it's very, very many of the 10-second simulations
sort of do something interesting for a second
and then find themselves in some sort of fixed point.
And I just keep simulating for nine more seconds.
And I should not do that.
I should just truncate the simulation.
But I'm just-- let it go.
There's some funny bugs, right?
So the first one, which is just classic for me,
was I wrote down all my functions.
And I wrote them down as cost functions
because I'm an optimal control person, not a reinforcement
learning person.
And it's like, wow, this looks like it's
doing exactly the opposite of what I wanted to do.
And in fact, it was doing exactly the opposite
of what I wanted it to do.
So now you'll see my code says reward equals negative cost
on the last line.
OK, that's just my bad.
When I did that, there was kind of a funny subtle thing,
which was I had this early termination.
If the simulation went unstable, I would stop the simulation.
And that made sense when I had costs and I was minimizing.
But when I flipped the cost upside down,
now if it got an early termination,
it would receive less cost.
So it did a very good thing for a while.
It started learning how to flip the box up or whatever.
But it slowly started discovering that if I crash,
I don't incur much cost.
So I woke up or I came back after dinner or whatever,
and it's like, it's crashing all the time.
Why is it every time--
it's reporting so many crashes.
And it had explicitly been told by me to crash.
So it's pretty good at finding the bugs in your simulator
if that's what you wanted to do.
But to be clear, that cost function is not tuned.
It's really just-- that's what I--
so I added the 10 just so that every step
got some positive reward.
And then it subtracted from 10 any costs.
But as long as it was encouraged to keep taking steps,
then that resolved that problem.
But these are just not tuned at all.
Like, those are the first numbers I typed in, always.
And you could do much better.
OK, yeah?
You mentioned about how sometimes, like,
if you enter a state where, like, the system
has to go through all this medicine before,
like, you use that wacky action.
Do you know of any ways of fixing that?
So the question is, how do you fix
the problem of getting wacky actions when you enter a state?
Right.
I mean, Abhi did mention one idea.
So I think there's a couple ideas there.
First of all, you could try to somehow put a prior
on your policy so that it does reasonable things.
And then maybe the neural network only learns something
in addition to a reasonable controller.
That would be one way to do it.
The one that Abhi talked about was
about restricting your policy to take actions that
would keep you near your data.
So if you say, I've seen some amount of--
there's states that I've seen, there's
states that I know I haven't seen.
You can either keep track of them explicitly,
or you can keep track of them implicitly
with a couple different approaches.
Ensemble networks is one way people do that.
And you could try to ask your controller
to stay near the data in safe territory,
even if that could be conservative.
But that comes up-- there's a lot of different--
I've seen that from the very control side.
I've seen that from the talk last Thursday.
And that's another idea.
I mean, the other one, I think, would
be to try to visit aggressively all the states,
somehow to try to--
I mean, there's a good sense of what these distributions are.
They're very hard to write down, of course.
But there's the distribution that you're exploring.
There's the distribution that you would have
under the optimal policy.
And your goal in learning should be
to try to sample from the distribution that's
relevant to the optimal policy.
So there are various ways to try to do that quickly.
The default way would just be you get some distribution
from your bad policy, and it extremely slowly
walks towards your good policy.
Anything you can do to try to get the relevant data faster
can also address this problem.
So that's-- sorry, three big things.
But in the extreme case, so if I'm
trying to do swing up for a cart pole or an acrobat
or something like this, the random policy
always visits these states for a really long time.
It takes a long, long time with random exploration
to ever finally decide to get up here.
But if you can do something like start it up here a bunch,
then you can skew the distribution
to be the relevant states more quickly.
I hope I don't discourage questions
by being long-winded in my answers.
OK.
So let's just look a little under the hood of PPO.
I don't want to give the full derivation.
But this is right from the PPO paper,
since I picked PPO and used it for that.
The first thing you'll see is effectively
the equation you saw in the talk last Thursday
and in your problem set.
This is the advantage function.
This is the log probability of the gradient,
the gradient of the log probabilities, which
is the reinforce idea, roughly.
OK.
There's also some sort of complicated-looking KL
divergence-type terms that come from TRPO.
But if you look, there's actually--
despite that being emphasized in the paper, in the end,
they say there's two versions of the algorithm.
One of them uses that complicated KL divergence-type
thing, and one of them doesn't.
It just does standard actor-critic and clips.
And that's actually what people use.
So actually, PPO, I think, in the end,
is very much like the old-school actor-critic algorithm, which
I know best from--
the original actor-critic papers were back in '99
by Condon and Tsiklis.
And they did beautiful analysis of the convergence
of those algorithms.
OK.
So that's an example that I hope motivates
us to understand a little bit more about actor-critic
algorithms.
And the actor in actor-critic algorithms is a policy,
and the critic is a value function.
So we need to learn a little bit more about value functions.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
[SOUND OF WATER RUNNING]
[TAPPING ON BOARD]
OK.
So I want you to have the mathematical understanding
of a value function, but I also just
want you to have a very intuitive understanding
of a value function.
For manipulation, these things should be very, very intuitive.
I almost wish-- so when Abhishek was showing the dexterous hand
opening the door, I wish I had some magic AR goggles that
would somehow show me, as it was progressing,
the value function estimate.
What you would expect to see is if the value function is
the expected cost to go, or expected--
I have to watch my cost versus reward--
expected long-term cost or reward,
depending on if you're a positive person
or a negative person.
I'm a negative person, apparently.
OK.
So basically, it tells me-- my value estimate
says if I'm in this state right now
and I continue to execute my policy,
then what reward should I expect to receive?
So what I would like to see for the robot opening the door
is that I would expect to see some future rewards.
And if I were to move the hand in the direction of the door,
I would expect to see the reward staying high.
Let's say I only got a reward when I actually successfully
turned the door knob.
So I would expect to roughly see in the direction of the door
that I'd get-- there's a high reward prediction if I'm doing
the right thing.
If I deviate, I would expect to see my expected long-term
reward go down.
There's directions that I should not move.
It's taking me farther from my possible goal.
But if I'm moving in the direction,
depending on if there's a discount or shaping
or anything like this, but I would roughly
like to see that my rewards are predicting--
there's a path that this function is roughly
telling me a path of where I should move through space
in order to accomplish the task.
And to make that a little bit more concrete,
the simplest example that I always have to use,
I think, just to make that concrete,
is imagine you're a robot in a grid world.
I'm sorry for those of you that know this well.
Just take a second on it.
Imagine I'm a little robot living on a grid.
And my action space is to move up, down, left, right.
And let's say I have a goal that's down here,
and I have some bad regions, pits of despair,
or something like this over here.
And let's say I get a reward of a million
when I get to the goal, and I get some penalty
when I fall in the pit.
And maybe I have a cost of taking an action.
The reward function in this task is very simple.
Everywhere here, the reward might be just a small penalty
for taking an action.
And it's not until I get to the goal
that I actually get some big one-step reward.
But the value function captures the long-term expected reward.
So it can tell me if I have an optimal policy,
then this is a pretty good state to be in.
And this is almost as good state to be in.
And it can start backing up the long-term reward
into a map that tells the system where to go.
So here's my goal.
Here's my pit of despair.
And if I start solving from the reward function to the value
function, then it's going to find this function now,
which you see the height of the function.
This is my cost formulation, sorry.
This being in the pit is a very bad place to be.
Being at the goal is a great place to be.
But it goes through the entire state space.
And basically, it figures out how much cost
I would expect to incur over the long run.
And it provides effectively a map that gets me to the goal.
So we'll work through the basic mechanics of it.
But basically, if I'm in some state
here, rather than solving some long path planning problem,
I can use my value function to just say,
if I'm going downhill on the value function,
then it's going to take me where I need to be to the goal.
It turns a long-term delayed reward problem
into a one-step decision-making problem.
So if this is my value function here,
then the features of it that make the algorithms like you
just saw possible and that Avi was using in his lecture
is that it has this beautiful property, which
is my value function at state x is
equivalent to my one-step cost plus my value
function at the next state.
And if I'm going to do this for a particular set of parameters,
then this is a sum over many rewards
from the current time up to n steps into the future.
And it has a beautiful recursive property
that says my value function I can compute by saying,
I'll take the one-step cost plus the cost
to go from the next step, from wherever I get to.
This idea of a value function or cost-to-go function
underlies all of the fundamental results in optimal control.
It's the reason that we have good solutions
to the linear quadratic regulator problem.
It is the thing that underlies all of the deep results
in robust control.
And it is certainly a mainstay for reinforcement learning,
too.
What reinforcement learning has particularly emphasized
is when you can't solve these value functions perfectly,
but you're going to use approximation methods
to estimate the value function.
OK.
I'll make one more point here.
So if I were to somehow find the optimal value function--
and our notation is typically something like this--
which is the cost-to-go that I would get if I was following
the optimal policy.
That also has a beautiful recursive structure.
It turns out that, like I said, if someone's
computed the value function, the cost-to-go function,
then it turns my long-term path planning problem
into a short-term.
I just need to figure out what's the best thing to do in one
step, plus given this map that someone gave me
of the long-term cost-to-go.
OK.
I really think value functions are
a fundamental property of control,
of reinforcement learning, of all these things.
There's evidence from the brain that there are signals that--
there are neurons in your dopaminergic system
that light up when you anticipate
you're going to get reward.
There's like-- I don't think this
is some arbitrary concept.
This is deeply embedded in the fabric of control,
of making long-term decisions.
OK.
And I really do think it's very intuitive.
It's a way to capture the roadmap to the goal.
So how do we use some concept of value functions
in a deep learning setting?
The first thing is that we need to think about the approximation
version of this.
RL is, if you approximate dynamic programming--
in fact, one of the conferences, the few conferences that
really focused on RL all the way through,
was a conference called ADP RL.
It's still alive, but approximate dynamic
programming in RL.
This was one of the places you could continue
to publish RL works, even when it was not super popular.
And it's asking the question of, if I
want to store or represent v hat with a function approximator,
let's say, then there's the objective
that's sort of natural, given the sort of recursive
structure.
You'd like to have v hat given some-- let
me call it alpha, the parameters of my function approximator--
minus--
, minus.
So this now becomes like a supervised learning loss.
This is called the Bellman residual.
[TYPING]
You can similarly-- you can do this on policy,
or you can do it for the optimal policy, if you can compute it.
So it turns out that learning cost-to-go functions--
it's not surprising, I guess--
can be done mostly with supervised learning.
So it makes sense that you could try to train a neural network
to try to represent a value function.
One thing that doesn't make sense--
I don't know if people have caught up on this.
So I write this down.
Abhishek wrote this down, too, roughly.
He did it for the Q functions.
This isn't actually what people do.
I don't know if people know that.
So every once in a while, you'll see people talk
about solving this exactly.
But actually, this doesn't work as well as you would expect.
Anybody know the catch, the subtlety that's written here,
but often not done in practice?
The way you would think to do this with supervised learning--
if you wrote this as your loss function,
and then you would try to take the gradient
of this whole thing with respect to alpha.
People don't do that.
They almost always fix this and only take the gradient
with respect to this.
There's a bunch of ways that people talk about that.
But certainly, the TD updates do that.
Sometimes they'll talk about this as the target network.
But empirically, it seems to work better
to fix this side, this right-hand side,
and only update this side.
There's some theory about why that is.
But it's always struck me as frustrating.
There's some notion that it backs up better.
You want to encourage it going backwards in time,
and maybe this is the way to do it or something like this.
But this is already one place where I think
it's a little unsatisfying.
Our theoretical understanding of that is a little unsatisfying.
But mostly, this is supervised learning, throw it in PyTorch,
take your gradients, lock those parameters,
and then take your gradients, and you
can train your value function.
If you look at the code in stable baselines,
it almost doesn't even call out the--
so my code said MLP policy.
So the inputs in stable baselines
that a lot of the algorithms, basically, you
have x coming in, you get your big neural network here,
and you have your actions coming out.
That's what you have your pi.
And they just will add one extra output
to the same architecture for v hat.
So it's actually plus value all hidden in this.
So it's very common to use the same architectures
for your policy and just throw one extra output on
for your value function.
Value functions are intuitive.
Value functions are essential.
There are reasonable approaches to train a value function.
Now, here's where there's a lot more options that open up.
So what do you do with your value function
once you have it?
In the classic dynamic programming world,
you'd say, once I have my value function,
I've solved the problem.
I'm done.
Because if I have a value function,
then I can say my optimal policy--
if I found the optimal value function,
then my optimal policy really, like I said,
should just be the one step I should minimize over u,
my one step cost plus my value function.
So if I know the value function, I know the policy mostly.
The problem with this is that it assumes I know the dynamics
and I know the cost.
I don't fault anybody for assuming
they know the cost most of the time.
I mean, there are settings.
But in robotics, I always say we know the cost.
But knowing you know the dynamics,
if you need to know the dynamics in order to make your decision,
then this is hard to use in a setting where I'm
like got a robot making salad.
So the alternatives here--
one is a Q-learning, and the second one is actor-critic.
The Q-learning roughly says, why don't I just
take this whole function here, and I'll just
learn that instead.
So I'll just call this thing Q. If I learn that whole thing,
then my optimal policy is just looking up Q.
I don't need to know something.
I don't have some other hidden terms that I have to know.
It has other benefits like off-policy,
which is a big deal.
I'm not trying to make that a small deal.
That's a huge deal, and other benefits.
I think the first idea, the first reason
you might need a Q function is because you
don't have the model.
So having just the value function by itself
isn't enough to tell me what control action I should take.
But having just the Q function is enough,
because I can just minimize directly on the Q.
The actor-critic thing is make an explicit policy
parameterization.
So you're basically trying to learn this function,
the minimizer, as well as V simultaneously.
Those are two solutions to the same--
they have different aspects, but I'd say first and foremost,
two solutions to this problem of having the value function
alone is not enough.
Now, it's interesting.
This min over U for Q is a non-trivial problem
to solve, potentially.
If Q is a deep network and U is a continuous action space,
then that amounts to solving some potentially very
non-convex problem in order to even take your actions here.
So as a result, for continuous action spaces,
people often prefer actor-critic.
There are a few examples of people
that stay in the Q-learning domain
and try to just solve this optimization.
That's an approach being pushed hard at Google,
where they're saying, we're going
to just learn the Q function.
We'll just solve that optimization on the fly.
That's what the opt part is.
They also-- Qt opt is more than that.
It talks about how to do decentralized Q-learning also.
But I think there's a group at DeepMind also that's quite
still thinking about the advantages of Q-learning
from experience replay kind of perspective.
And that started with Martin a long time ago.
He was maybe the first to talk about fitted Q-learning
with a neural network.
And he did a big series of experiments.
2005 was right when I was getting my PhD.
We were at the same conferences.
And he was talking about neural Q-learning at the time.
And I remember that well.
So this is a big idea, a big branch of work.
But it tends to be more popular in the discrete actions.
And if you look at the stable baselines,
and you look at all the DQN and other methods that are
explicitly Q-learning, they're optimized
for discrete action spaces.
And Actor-Critic is the version that
works really well with continuous action spaces.
All right, so now let's come back to the view
we had of policy gradient, where we have a policy.
We're doing black box optimization on it.
Why would we need a value function?
Why would that help?
Can we connect those dots?
Why is it useful?
So it makes sense if you have a value function,
that's not enough.
But now let's flip back from the other perspective.
If I've got a policy, why isn't that enough?
Why is-- if I've got a policy, why do I also
use a value function?
Why is it helpful to do both simultaneously?
Because you might start with some place where the policy's
not trained well.
You might start in a place where the policy is not trained well.
And so how does the value function help you with that?
So you can know how to act whenever you [INAUDIBLE]
OK, so you're leveraging this fact
that the value function provides a map, roughly tells you
where to go from a long way out.
Yes, OK, good.
So I'm with you on that.
So I think the value function, if you
can learn it simultaneously, can give you
the ability to train your policy more locally.
There's a very specific role it plays, too,
in the policy gradient world, which
I wonder if we can capture.
If anybody knows.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It provides a baseline.
ERIK DEMAINE: Yeah, it provides a baseline.
We did it-- we just did a problem set on this.
The advantages functions in your problem set
were exactly this idea.
So what does that baseline provide
for the reinforced algorithms?
If I'm doing my long-term optimization,
and I'm getting noisy random samples
of the objective function, then if I'm
trying to estimate a gradient locally,
I'm going to have maybe noisy estimates of my gradients.
I think the pictures in the problem set
were actually better, right?
Were that you'd like to be going straight downhill,
but in practice, the reinforced algorithm is taking you
all over the place, sometimes uphill, sometimes downhill,
whatever.
And the reason for that is you don't know,
from a single rollout of my robot, I get a score of 42.
Was that a good score or a bad score?
And if I ran almost the same policy
from almost the same initial conditions,
and I got a 38, was that a difference in noise,
or was that a difference in actual cost?
So distinguishing between noisy samples from a rollout
and true signal is a hard problem, OK?
And if you know that my expected return with my current policy
was 40, because I've been in this vicinity before,
and I've learned the value of my current policy,
then that gives you this sharp tool to distinguish,
but that 38 was a good thing to do.
I should try to make that happen more often,
and 42 was not such a good thing to do, right?
The particular role it plays is--
let me think how I want to say this.
The value estimate is a baseline in policy gradient
and can dramatically reduce the variance.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
The amount of random walking you do as you descend the landscape
can go down a lot with a good baseline.
I hope you saw that in your problem sets.
OK.
So in practice, the actor-critic methods
are winning for these continuous control
for all these reasons, right?
They're better than the policy search
because they can make the policy search much more effective.
In the case of you have a multi-step problem,
if you have a single-step problem,
then the concept of value function--
the general black box optimization world
doesn't think about value functions
because it doesn't assume anything
about the long-term multi-step problem.
But if you do have a multi-step problem,
then this notion of a value function
becomes an important one.
OK.
That's sort of the rough taxonomy of these methods.
Let's dig into just a few more specific details.
,
So the actor-critic algorithms actually, and even the value
estimate algorithms, I should say
there's good work, including that Kanda and Sinsiklis
work from early 2000s, or '99 actually,
that understand some rigorous statements about what
actor-critic or value function learning does,
even with function approximators.
Typically, the statements are if you
can represent your value function perfectly,
then you can-- many of these algorithms
enjoy strict convergence to the true value function.
That's a super powerful thing to say.
The fact that if I--
I will eventually learn the true cost to go.
That's a very powerful thing to say.
There's a next tier of value methods
that use linear function approximators, where
we can say rigorously that it will find the--
that it will converge to the closest value
function in the class that is close to your data.
There's some really strong convergence results
for linear function approximators.
OK.
Most of those are based on this notion of value functions
being a function of x.
I mean, even the modern analysis of what's--
trying to people-- people trying to understand why is deep RL
working.
There's people trying to connect ideas
from deep learning and supervised learning
with these old results from linear function approximators.
But they're all based on--
all of the good theory says that the cost to go
is a function of my state.
If you look at the code in stable baselines,
or in-- you name any of these RL algorithms,
almost always the gem just has actions coming in,
has observations coming out.
And the critic and the policy takes observations in,
takes my actions out, and my value estimate.
OK, so there, where I think of--
my notation is that my dynamics are f of xn, un.
My observations are some other function.
This value function is not v of x.
It's v of y.
Let me write in big letters here.
Observations are not states.
This is like one of my big gripes, I guess,
with just the sloppiness, I guess,
of people writing code and the like.
Let me just make that point.
I've got a box here.
I've got some money here.
Do you want to open the box?
There's a lot of money in that box, right?
OK.
I've got something you probably don't want.
I mean, you could have it if you want.
[LAUGHTER]
OK, my observations are the same.
I know this is a silly trick.
But my observations are exactly the same, right?
But my value, how much I want to open that box,
has changed completely.
Observations are not states, especially the biggest culprit
here.
You'll see people saying, like, images are our states.
And that can be true if you have partial observability
and you have quasi-static dynamics and all these things.
But beware of this, please.
Observations in general are not states.
Partial observability is the easiest example for that.
But dynamics already is enough that a single image
doesn't tell me the velocity that my cheetah is running at
or something like that.
OK, so there's this big important idea here,
which is either your observations,
you need to take a history of observations,
you need to have a recurrent network,
all this discussion we talked about before.
There are ways to make this OK.
Or there are places where, if you think about this
as just a very approximate version of the true value
function, v of x, the actor-critic algorithms
can still flourish.
Even if your value function doesn't
have the information it's required to estimate
the true cost to go, it can still
do good things in terms of improving
the convergence of your actor-critic algorithm.
But I think any analysis or even just debugging of these tools
needs to be aware that all the foundations of RL
are based--
and of actor-critic algorithms--
are based on some analysis of the potential convergence
of the value function to the true value function.
And if you stick in a deprived state representation,
then I think there's really nothing that tells--
I don't know how to tell you if it's doing a good job or not.
Because you're asking it to solve a different problem.
And I think we're lacking the tools.
And I would say, in general, when--
even just playing with the box flip up last night,
I think that--
or if we have student projects.
If you have a project, and you're working away,
and your trajectory optimization isn't doing what you expected,
or your dynamics isn't doing what it's expected,
or your differential IK isn't doing what's expected,
I can almost always tell you.
You can come up with yourself.
But there's almost always something like, OK,
it should definitely do x.
There's theorems that say it should have this property.
Make sure it has this property, otherwise you have a bug.
And you can go down the list.
And you can vet these very complex algorithms.
You can debug, I think, very effectively.
Because there's a deep theory behind many
of those algorithms.
RL's theory is deep, but it's harder.
I really think RL is in this place where it's starting
to work incredibly well, but it's
missing some of the fundamental theory that would even help
you-- not just if you care about theory, just like if you want
to debug your algorithm.
It went downhill.
And I could feel myself making stories like, oh,
it wanted to do x, so my cost might be--
but no, it might have just gone downhill,
because it's a random algorithm going in a random direction
with 50 random rollouts.
So I think there's a big role for the theory
to play to talk about-- there's lots of good work
already on approximate value functions.
But I think there's a big push that
needs to happen in terms of closing
the gap between theory and practice for this stuff
to work better.
So let me try to say a few things about the ongoing theory
of RL, of deep RL.
And I think this is just such a vibrant area right now,
because empirically, it's working so well.
Right?
Maybe it even starts with some results
from deep supervised learning.
There's only a few--
I mean, there's lots of ideas out there,
but there's a few sort of really big dominant ideas
about maybe why supervised learning seems to work now.
You've probably heard of double descent curves and all
these different ideas.
But the arguments roughly go into two parts.
So the first argument is that if you're doing well,
your training error, your training loss, goes to 0.
And the argument there-- there's a handful
of different sort of pieces of work on this.
But why does your training loss go
to 0 for arbitrarily complicated nonlinear objectives,
it seems?
There's a very simple argument that people make.
One of them is called the neural tangent kernel.
The argument is that if you are in the massive over
parameterization regime, you've got a big deep network
and a relatively smaller set of data,
then even a random initialization
of your deep network produces some outputs
in your last layer.
And it produces a rich enough basis of possible outputs
that the last layer can effectively just do
least squares.
So you can get-- so basically, if your second to last layer
spans all of the possible space and your last layer is just
a linear layer, then you actually
have a least squares problem in the last layer.
And then all of the other stuff in the beginning
can just be left-- you'll get to 0 training loss almost
trivially if you have an ultra wide last layer.
OK?
And that's sort of in the massive over parameterization
regime.
That's an explanation for maybe why your training
loss might go to 0.
OK?
And the second part then is then sort
of this implicit regularization.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
Stochastic gradient descent.
OK, so if I'm able to fit my training data by just having
a really wide second to last layer,
the last layer is just solving a least squares problem.
Then I get to-- in the null space of my solutions,
of 0 training loss, I get to move,
walk around inside the parameters of my earlier
layers of the network.
And there's a lot of ideas about why stochastic gradient descent
will continue to walk around even after you've got 0
training loss and will find a solution that generalizes well
to new examples.
That's sort of the simplest brush pass
of what people are talking about in deep supervised learning.
OK?
And there's-- I think it's not quite what happens in practice,
but there's this massive overparameterization regime
that's happening in practice.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
There's a lot of ideas about it.
But it seems that of the solutions which
fit my data perfectly, I mean, SGD
tends to walk around and find them that have a--
they minimize particular norms of the parameters and stuff
like this that tend to give you nice smooth functions
around your data.
And even do ridiculous things around noisy data,
like fit the generalizing curve, but still explain noisy data
with 0 training loss.
It's a big topic that I don't mean to go into,
but thank you for asking.
The point I want to make, though,
is that the theory we have for deep supervised learning, which
assumes massive overparameterization
and ultra-wide last layers, simply
doesn't explain why we're having success in deep RL
with a 255 layer, three layer network.
It's just not the same regime at all.
So I don't see how this--
there's more gap to close in understanding
the connections between why supervised learning--
it's not enough, I think, to just say,
supervised learning works, so RL starts working.
I do think some of the black box optimization
that we talked about maybe is part of the--
I should-- I think the story I told you a little bit about,
about black box optimization working fairly well, even
in noisy landscapes, I do think that's part of the story that's
emerging, is that some of the--
what sounded to me as very naive algorithms
for gradient descent in RL might be getting around
some of the fundamental complexity of the landscape
in a nice, smart way.
So I think that's part of the emerging story,
is the black box optimization, both in its--
sort of its local robustness to bad landscapes,
and some of its global optimization aspects.
I think both of those have a role
to play to understanding when and why RL works.
I think the stochastic objectives that we talked about
is an important part of the story.
It connects to the idea of randomized smoothing.
Remember I said if you have a discontinuous loss
function like this, but then you take the expected value
over some kernel, you might smooth the loss function out
beautifully just by having a stochastic formulation instead
of a deterministic formulation.
I think this is a big part of it.
In fact, I would go so far as to hypothesize.
So I have a couple of versions of my box flipping code.
The one I showed you that I trained last night
was the box has random initial conditions,
but it's the same box all the time
because I'm using full state feedback.
The next version that I just haven't run yet
takes key points from the box.
And then I can take and make different sized boxes
and different masses of boxes.
You would think that that would be a harder optimization
problem.
But I'll go out on a limb, and I would say--
when I run it tonight or whatever--
that it's probably going to be an easier optimization problem,
or let's say a better optimization problem.
I would actually expect to say that the policies we would get
out of that optimization might be less ridiculous.
And I would guess that it learns faster,
learns reasonable policies faster.
And my intuition for that is that I
think when you ask too narrow of a problem,
then there are many quirky solutions that
almost solve the problem.
But when you ask that the same policy solves
a whole distribution of problems, like all the boxes,
then all the quirky solutions where you just
happen to throw your finger into the back corner
and knock it up and the box happened to land on it,
whatever, that just doesn't happen
if you have arbitrary boxes.
It's just not a good solution.
The solution that works for all boxes of all sizes,
whatever it is you got, you put your finger on
and you twist it up, I would think.
I'll find out.
I'll run tonight.
And I think there's something important
that we need to understand in that space.
Here's the thing.
RL can't solve every problem.
We know that.
You can write any optimization problem as an RL problem,
as a one-step RL problem.
There are NP-hard optimization problems.
We just know there's problems.
I would be mining Bitcoin now if RL solved every problem.
Because it just doesn't do that.
There's something about the types of problems
that we're asking which RL is solving well.
And it's something about the distribution of problems
that we're asking.
Roughly, I would say that maybe the biggest thing maybe
is manipulation is easy if we formulate it this way.
I think that's maybe my number one takeaway.
I'll say a few more of the existing work stuff.
But I think deeply that there's something
about the distribution of problems
that the real world gives us.
My human intelligence is limited also.
And somehow, I'm pretty effective in my kitchen.
I mean, not great.
But I can get around my kitchen without throwing boxes
through the window.
So there's something about the distribution of kitchens
in the world that doesn't have the crazy scenarios.
And I think somehow that makes the optimization problems
better that I can learn.
There's something about the distribution of the world
and the distribution of our problems
that I don't know how to capture yet.
But it seems important.
There's a bunch of good work on controlled parameterizations.
[WRITING]
That make-- or value function parameterizations
that aren't super present in the neural network deep RL
community.
But they're sort of coming.
They're coming behind.
And they're taking even classic control problems--
LQR, LQG, some of these classic control problems--
asking, does stochastic gradient descent work for them?
What about robust control formulations?
Some of the formulations that we really
understand well from an optimization perspective,
can stochastic gradient descent--
how do we understand stochastic gradient descent
on those problems?
And there's some really deep things happening there.
And while it's still a long way from the neural network case,
I feel like that's the theory community chasing.
And if we can even catch up a little bit more,
then I think it's going to give good dividends.
So as an example, for instance, some of the work
that Jack and others in my group have been thinking about,
if you have a convex reparameterization--
[WRITING]
--e.g. from robust control--
If you look at my underactuated notes,
there's a bunch of cases where it's like,
here's a crazy hard problem.
But if you change coordinates into this new set of decision
variables, then you can write it as an optimization problem
that's convex.
The fact that those tricks even exist actually
implies something topologically.
If they have certain properties, those reparameterizations,
like if they're smooth and other things like this--
[WRITING]
--about, let's say, policy gradient.
And there's a stream of results from the theory community
saying, well, actually, LQR, we know how to solve it in MATLAB.
But actually, that means that we can solve it
with stochastic gradient descent, too.
Even though the cost function is not
convex in the control parameters and the policy parameters,
it can't have local minima because
of the existence of these reparameterizations.
And even some pretty hard--
increasingly harder problems, we're actually saying, oh,
that would have worked with SGD also.
And I think as we grow that body of knowledge,
we'll get closer and closer to understanding
why these things work.
But there is some limits.
Right?
I guess I said Bitcoin.
That's not what I wrote in my notes, but here we go.
Yeah.
Someone's got to do that next week now that I wrote it.
But it doesn't solve-- there's problems that are just
fundamentally hard.
We have hardness results, hardness theories.
You can write all of them as an RL problem.
Like I said, it's hopelessly generic.
And you're not going to run PPO and suddenly solve that.
So there's something more going on between our RL algorithms
and our RL formulations.
There's some structure that's hidden there
in the cases where it's working that's not visible yet.
But we have to discover it.
That should be our mission.
OK, so that was a whirlwind tour of RL in a couple lectures.
And Happy Thanksgiving.
I'm happy to keep helping with projects.
And we'll transition into some like the boutique lectures
that you guys picked starting next week.