Let's do it.
So last time, we did our sort of lightning introduction
to deep learning for manipulation.
We talked a little bit more detail
about the deep version of pose estimation
and some of the nuances of asking a neural network
to spit out in orientation.
If you choose Euler angles, you might be sad.
If you choose quaternions, there's
some evidence that you might be sad.
And thinking more about the exact output
that you ask the network to give can make a big difference.
And I guess the last big point I made last time
was that for the types of shapes we often
manipulate in manipulation, we have
to accept that there's going to be potentially
ambiguity in pose.
And so outputting an entire distribution over pose
can be a much richer specification than asking
for just a single pose.
But I already forecasted.
I actually think asking for a pose out of the network
is probably the wrong thing to ask for.
It pigeonholes you into a world where you have CAD models,
for instance, of your objects.
And you're trying to find a specific object in the world
where you can describe that object by the CAD model
and the pose, for instance.
And I want to think today with you about a little bit more
general question of object representations.
And I think what object representations
support manipulation?
[WRITING ON BOARD]
And it's a subtle thing.
But we've sort of already given--
we have pipelines that work for two extremes.
At one extreme, we have known objects.
Say we have a CAD model or something
that we can throw in a simulator and generate a bunch of data.
We can do pose.
We can do our grasp.
We could do pose estimation, grasp planning.
We can specify the goals of manipulation
in terms of pose of objects.
That's a pretty good pipeline.
But its limitation, I think, really
comes from having to do only known objects.
At the other extreme, we said unknown objects, anything goes.
I would say arbitrary unknown objects.
And we did even just geometric estimation.
We did antipodal grasping.
And for simple objectives, where you just
want to do things like move all the points in that bin
over to that bin, then that's actually
a fairly useful pipeline.
You'll see if you combine this with a deep segmentation
network, even an instance level segmentation and recognition,
then that gets already pretty useful.
And we're going to have you do this on the problem set.
You could say, pick the mustard bottle out of the bin,
or pick the Cheez-It box.
There is a world outside of Cheez-It boxes and Spam cans
and mustard bottles, but we're pretty
happy in our little world.
So that is already a pretty good pipeline.
But at some point, manipulation is about more than just picking
things up and dropping them off.
That's not a very rich specification for a task.
So what I want to think about with you today
is this middle ground of how can we relax
the assumption of known objects.
We're going to have to give up, I think,
doing arbitrary unknown objects, because I don't even
know how to specify-- if you just tell me
the object is anything, then I don't really even know how
to specify the task anymore.
So I need something in the middle here
that is usefully general, but allows
me to still specify the task.
And I think what the computer vision world has
been calling it, and what we've been starting to call it
in manipulation, there's a nice spot--
it's probably a little bit closer
to the known objects than the full arbitrary--
that I want to explore today, which is this category level.
Category level perception and category level manipulation.
And I think that the trick is going
to be finding representations of objects that
allow us to specify the task, but aren't tied to having just
a single--
a single category.
It doesn't have to be a pose, for instance.
And there's a few canonical categories
that all the roboticists like to use.
So here's the task, roughly.
I've got mugs.
Everybody uses mugs.
You've seen mugs in our slides already.
But there's normal mugs you wouldn't be surprised by.
And they get pretty ridiculous pretty fast.
They get all shapes and sizes, all sorts of materials.
We've got cat mugs that are completely weird shaped.
There's one you'll see in the slides that has udders.
Like it's-- if you go to the Disney store,
you're going to come back with all kinds of weird gnome mugs
and stuff like this.
This is a small fraction of the collection
we've acquired in our lab here.
There's actually-- I walked over to the side,
and I saw like eight boxes of test mugs.
And there's the training mugs I didn't even see,
which were over somewhere else.
But it's interesting to just stop and think for a minute.
Like, how do I write a goal?
How do I even tell the manipulation system
what I need to do?
If I want to do something to mugs more generally,
what is the representation that would support thinking
about all of these things?
I mean, clearly I can talk about them.
I could say, put your finger through the handle,
and that's going to work.
I could tell you, and you'd do it fine.
Or I could even say, just set them upright, line them up.
Those are kind of reasonable tasks
to ask a manipulation system.
You don't get it out of this.
So we need something in the middle.
The other canonical category has become shoes.
There's a ridiculous number of shoes and diversity of shoes.
That one was a surprise when we first grabbed that one.
But there's also flip-flops, the types of things.
And the other one we discovered is
that for a while we were running these experiments where
we basically said, anybody who comes in the lab,
take off your shoe.
We're going to put it on the rack and line it up,
and we're going to do a good job of it.
People have ridiculous shoes.
We did really well, but we'd still
get stumped by a shiny Italian shoe or something,
which I didn't know if my robot should be touching
in the first place.
But are there like--
the high heels can be impressively high.
And we've seen them all, I think, at this point.
But just think for a second.
How do you write a manipulation specification, let alone
the implementation, that would sort of ingest that level of--
it's totally reasonable to say, I
want them to be on the shoe rack in the store.
They should all be pointing roughly like this.
I could tell you that, but how do I tell my manipulation
system that?
And by the way, I always have this camera in my pocket.
I got to do it all from this.
So this is what I'm working with.
This point cloud's in, maybe some untold amount of data
behind the scenes, maybe some human annotations.
That's to be determined.
But I need to even specify the task.
So that's the basic setup.
So James was asking the other day.
He said, pose feels like kind of almost too much to ask.
For a lot of these tasks, I actually probably
don't need to estimate the pose very accurately
to accomplish the task.
I mean, it's actually probably there's
a representation out there that are easier
than estimating the pose that would still get the job done.
I don't have to have accuracy in this dimension
to be able to set it down on the plane.
So that's the basic setup.
This is-- let's see, there's the udders right there.
Look at that.
Who gets cow udder mugs?
But you'd like to be able to do something like--
this is one of the canonical tasks now, I guess,
is just take those mugs, put them on a rack.
And why is that a good task?
That's because it requires some understanding, if you will,
of the mug.
You have to understand where the handle is,
and the handles are all over the place.
This handle is so different than this one or whatever.
But somehow, there's something about them that we understand,
and you have to understand it fairly well to be able to
thread the--
I mean, not thread the needle, but stick the big peg
through the bigger hole, much bigger hole.
So that's an interesting balance of a task that requires
some kinematic accuracy.
It actually doesn't require much dynamic understanding,
which is another key thing.
We'll get to more dynamic stuff later.
But it's a nice, I think, useful skill
that you might want to program.
OK, so there's a couple of different broad approaches
with it.
And rather than--
I mean, last time, I felt like I kind of had to mention
a bunch of things, but I don't really like doing that.
So I'd rather go into one or two ideas a little bit more
specifically, dig into some of the details.
So I'm not going to mention every category level
representation.
Well, I'll cite a few extras that we
won't talk about in detail.
But let me go into a few that we thought a lot about
that I think are representative.
So it's actually possible to do a lot of this kind of thinking
even in simulation.
One of the nice tools about that is this-- you
see this parametric--
there's a bunch of basically spline parameters
here that if you move them around continuously,
you get a continuous set of mugs that
represented everything we found in the cabinet at TRI.
And you can, in simulation, generate a huge diversity.
Never touch the same mug twice.
There's an infinite number of mugs there.
We also would texture map every mug differently.
So you just take your favorite images off the web,
slap them on there, throw them in your renderer,
and you can generate a lot of data.
So this is not an exploration that's restricted to reality.
You can do it in simulation.
In fact, we have this kind of nice pipeline now
where you can take a new mug in, scan it super fast,
take any image off the web or whatever,
and very quickly generate a new simulation asset
for mugs of some quality.
It's interesting to just say the path
from a mug on the table to a mug in simulation,
it's still hard to go all the way to--
so there's different things you might want to get right.
You might want to get the physical properties right.
You might want to get the rendering properties right.
Getting a quick asset that you can manipulate
is actually not that hard anymore.
We have really nice 3D scanners, effectively.
We can take pictures.
We can do texture maps.
But if you want to get the material properties--
this is a super shiny mug for some reason,
and this one's completely matte over here.
So that's hard.
Nerf is looking exciting.
There are ideas out there that make
it look like we're getting better at it,
but that's still hard.
And even the physical properties,
like the frictional properties, the inertias,
we have some capabilities for that.
But we don't really have mature pipelines
to go from this pile of junk into sim yet.
It's a good standing challenge.
OK.
So this is an example of the task of take the shoes,
any shoe, and just put it on the rack.
So that's a different task that we looked at.
Shen, in particular, was in the group at the time,
and she had all kinds of small, cute shoes
that were hard to grab.
There's some high heels that came in there.
That was from-- yeah.
OK.
So here's the first idea that we'll talk about.
I listed two.
One of them is going to be based on key points.
And to some extent, that was an example
that was suggested last time, I think.
The way Charles proposed, maybe we think about even pose
estimation might be through finding key points.
But I want to talk through why that could be a good idea
and solve something on this spectrum.
It's not going to be only key points.
If you just knew where a few key points were on the object,
you might not be able to grab it.
So I'm going to say key points plus plus.
So what do I mean by key points?
Some of you know this well, but there
was a thing that happened in the computer vision world.
It was motivated initially by human pose estimation.
So if you've seen the videos of people dancing,
and they're being tracked amazingly well
by a neural network, that is a thing that has a capability that
has gotten better and better.
Open pose was the first one in 2014, I believe, around then,
like pretty early in the revolution.
And they've just gotten increasingly impressive,
where you can see gymnasts that are basically
folding themselves in half, but it's tracking them fairly well.
And they can be made to work for household object types,
different categories, not just humans.
But the original push-- and actually,
a lot of the architectures and even notation
in the open source codes all have some like--
you could tell that the code base started working only
for humans.
But the basic notion is that you'd like to have some--
I mean, you can just attach them directly to the object,
but some points that are identified.
They need not to be--
if you have enough of them, they probably
are sufficient to estimate the pose for any one instance.
But they are different than a pose estimation,
because if I want to say maybe there's
a key point for the back left leg of the table,
or the chair, sorry, and I've got
a bunch of different chairs, and I can sort of put
a consistent key point across the category.
So while the distance, possibly even the relative positions
of the green key point versus the red key point
or something like this, this is not
a rigid transformation between the different objects.
But it can be a consistent representation
of a diversity of objects.
For the mugs, we chose to put one
on the bottom of the mug, which is interesting,
because you don't even have to see necessarily the key point
where you want to put it.
But we wanted to put something in the bottom
so that we could set it down, something in the handle
so we could grab it, something in the top,
not that we ever poured anything into it,
but we at least want to know which way is up.
For the shoes, we picked the toe, the heel, the top.
This one was very different than these tops and the tongue.
But just a few key points actually
tell you a lot about the object.
And they can morph across the category,
but still be a consistent representation.
So that's why it lives in this nice category-level space,
is that that representation is more flexible.
What's interesting, and still I think
there's a lot of things you can do with this representation.
So I said to some extent, the representation we need
is we need it to be sufficient to specify tasks.
So certainly a pose in a CAD model
is sufficient to specify a task.
I said this is limiting in terms of specifying a task.
But it turns out if you just label a handful of points
and allow them to shift along the category,
there's still a lot of pretty useful things
you can do, like the ones I showed you.
Put the shoe on the rack, put the mug on the rack.
In particular, if you assume that the objects are nearly
rigid, for instance, and I assume
that when I grab the objects, the key points, wherever
they may be, they are in a very different relative location
on that mug versus this mug.
But when I start moving them, they
go through only rigid transformations.
Then I can write pretty--
I can just turn it into an inverse kinematics problem.
I can do all of my original thinking
that we've already done in the kinematics parts
of the lectures to talk about relative transformations
of mugs.
Maybe I can put a constraint saying
that the point on the bottom of the mug must be on the table.
The handle must be to the right.
These are things that you can write directly
as kinematic constraints.
Throw it into your optimization problem
and solve for across a category of objects.
So like label fusion, which we had talked about using ICP,
there are different ways to get key points.
We'll talk a little bit in a minute
about self-supervised key points,
where you just try to have the perception system discover
key points, meaningful key points by itself.
But I actually think there's a lot of value
in human-labeled key points.
Because at some point, there's some information
that the geometry doesn't give you.
There's some semantic information about the object,
the fact that this is a handle.
People know the word affordance.
Yeah.
From psychology, I guess, Gibsonian, right?
I think it's this notion of the handle is something
that I can affect change with or something.
The definition of the properties of the object that I care about
are the things that afford me the ability
to change something about the object or the world.
And you can't get that, I think, easily out
of a self-supervised pipeline unless you're
trying to go all the way to an end-to-end task, maybe
a deep reinforcement learning.
But just looking at the geometry, it's hard.
So we started off by saying, let's hand design
the notion of the toe key point, the heel key point, the tongue,
the back of the opening, and use our same kind of tricks
to make a GUI that would allow you to quickly label
lots of key points and generate a big data set.
So it was important to us to have no requirement on CAD
models.
So that is a shoe that was just scanned
by the robot doing its quick thing with a depth sensor
and doing one of these dense reconstructions
just on the point cloud.
So that's a mesh that came out right out of a point cloud that
was fused together by multiple views on the robot.
And that was enough to throw it in the GUI, click a few times,
and you can label lots of images.
So I want to dig in a little bit to the details,
and I'll go through a couple of examples here.
So it's interesting to think about how do you actually
set up this key point detection algorithm,
and how do you train a key point detector?
So the first question is, how do we formulate the problem here?
Let me impose that we're going to start
from an image coming in.
And let's start off with the simpler maybe form
where we just have an RGB image coming in, which
has got-- it's just my width times height times RGB coming
in.
And I'm going to put it into a big deep network.
I won't talk in detail about the architectures,
but there's a bunch of canonical architectures
for key point detection I can mention.
And again, the first question is, what representation
should we put out?
What do you think?
What's the natural representation to put out?
Yeah, totally, right?
I mean, you should just put potentially--
let's even, like you said, it's easier
to think first about just 2D key points.
You can potentially project them back into 3D later.
But yeah, so maybe if I have a handful of them
that I want to spit out, one for each of the key points,
you'd think I could just put the xy position out.
And OpenPose, I believe, did this.
Certainly, the early key point networks definitely did this.
But people don't do that anymore.
And for me, it's somewhere between a--
I think we can generalize it.
We can think about uncertainty distributions and the like.
There's also something about what neural networks
like to do that's hiding in there, which is frustrating.
That I think we don't, as a field,
completely understand what works and what doesn't work.
And people have found that other representations can work better
for a key point estimation.
People know what the more common one these days is?
Someone knows.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So you could say, maybe I would just
draw in the 2D image the locations of the points.
That is close to what it is.
But what they end up doing is for each key point i,
we actually put out a 2D heat map.
So the desired image, if you're making training data
from this or from something else,
would be actually an image that basically
is drawn as a probability distribution, rendered
as an image, if you will, where the pixel value i is the,
let's say, the probability that the point is at this--
that key point at x, y.
So you see these little Gaussian heat maps
that people will render as the output of the neural network,
an entire image for each distinct key point.
It is meant-- I think it is satisfying to think of it
as trying to represent the uncertainty of your key point
estimator.
That is a very satisfying explanation
for why this would work.
But it still feels a little--
like there's no real notion of people
taking that to fruition.
It's kind of like--
I think the recipe right now is try a few covariances
until you find one that works well.
It's kind of like the official recipe I hear
from people who do it a lot.
And I think people don't tend to use--
they tend to say that the desired image is
this entire probability map.
They don't tend to use maximum likelihood or other sort
of losses that might account for more interesting uncertainty
distributions.
It's really almost-- it feels to me almost a trick to just--
it's a neural network's like the output image.
Image is in, the image is out.
So let's write it like that.
And you can make these smooth loss functions
by, depending on how you infer the true key point
location from the rendered image.
If you take the expected value of this distribution,
then that's a smooth function, which
people do in the integral-posed networks.
So for every one of these, we take a 2D heat map coming out.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question is, is this for a single category
or for many categories?
So I think the sweet spot seems to be for a single category.
We're going to learn one set of representations.
If you wanted to manipulate multiple categories
simultaneously, I would think of it
as a separate set of networks.
Yeah?
And how you define category is ambiguous.
I gave you two examples.
But is your system going to perform better
if I called that a boot and distinguish it
from the flip-flop and the other ones?
For some tasks, yes.
So I think the notion of a category
is very vague at this point.
But I think it depends on your task.
So a reasonable loss function here
would be like a heat map regression loss people use.
What do I mean by that?
I mean the output of my network is an entire image.
And I will use the L2 distance between that image
and the desired image, which is a hallucinated heat
map with a small Gaussian.
It's basically neural network out--
let me call it neural network of the image
minus hallucinated heat map with a Gaussian
at the labeled key point.
And that seems to work fairly well.
I mean, people have different ways exactly to train it.
So you said, do I mean taking a Gaussian blurring kernel?
And if I made a 0, 1 image, and then I did a Gaussian kernel,
I would get effectively a rendered image
that looked like if I printed a Gaussian.
So I think yes to both of them.
Yeah.
So again, there are modifiers to this
that I think can make a big difference in practice.
The ones we used in our work were
from the integral pose machine line, which
did have one other term there.
But conceptually, this is, I think, the workhorse.
Yeah.
OK.
So a couple of nice points to make.
So depending on how you generate the training data,
whether it's synthetic training data or human labels
through a GUI like this--
so I made some of these points before.
But the fact that it is a fundamentally different
representation than pose, it has interesting properties
like I can put a key point that I'm predicting right
in the smack in the middle of the handle of the mug.
It doesn't have to actually be geometrically
connected to the mug.
It's somehow an affordance of the mug
that I have semantically labeled by a human annotation.
But it need not be actually part of the mug.
It could be the top of the mug in the free space here.
You can have them be very sparse.
You could have them be more dense.
Right?
And they're good for different things
depending on how sparse or dense they are.
But there's a lot of subtleties, I think,
about how this works through.
And I thought the place where I've
seen the subtleties pop up in sort of the simplest
to reason about fashion, we did this sort of thought
experiment.
Greg was doing this thought experiment
with Maggie Wang of just what would it
look like to use key points as a way to reason about boxes.
I think he had a bunch of boxes in his apartment during COVID
and was inspired to--
he was pointing his depth camera at the piles of boxes
and asking, could I estimate shapes and pose
and everything in boxes given a key point type network?
So let's just work through that as an example.
The boxes-- the key points that he identified here on the board
are in the picture.
He put some yellow boxes at each of the corners.
Maybe you want to know where the label is or something
like that.
Seems like a totally reasonable thing
to output from the network.
But it starts to get into some subtleties.
So first question is, how many key points do we want per box?
An important question.
There's only a couple of sort of--
well, sorry.
It gets subtle if you start thinking about it.
So let me ask you, how many key points do we want per box?
You say three.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
So let's say I just want to move them to the next--
I'm going to pile the boxes over here
to the piles of boxes over here.
Maybe I want to do a--
pack a trailer or something like that.
Something a lot of people want to do.
What do you think?
Other answers besides three.
So let me ask you why you say three first.
I can--
[INAUDIBLE]
Right.
So from three, we can get the height, the depth.
Maybe we need four to get the width also.
Yeah.
Maybe four.
So if I were to just get those four.
But how do I know that they're those four?
And what if I'm looking at it straight on from the side
or something like that?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
Yeah.
So you could try to predict all eight.
And maybe that would give you some robustness even.
If it's already just--
think of it as a more robust version of the four key point
thing.
And yeah, for consistent tracking.
So these are good questions, good examples.
Yeah.
Oh.
[INAUDIBLE]
Right.
So that is a key point.
I can't believe I was about to say that.
I just-- that was like just association, not humor.
So right.
So you said it is an important thing
to observe, which is that the orientation at which you're
viewing the box, you might have a different number
of key points available.
Also, you can see there's an occlusion up here.
If your box are piled up, it might cover up
some of your corners.
So occlusions are also a reason why you might-- your key points
might appear or disappear.
So are the key points unique?
I think this is an important decision that one
has to make when they're training a perception system.
Do you expect to have--
if I were to rotate the box by 180 degrees,
and let's say I--
you said the tracking example, which is a good example.
But what if I wasn't tracking?
I just showed two images with no context connecting the two
of this box and this box rotated 180 degrees.
Should I try to train something that
is canonical orientation of the box,
and maybe the only signal I have there
is just where the label is, or there's a few small asymmetries?
Most things are asymmetric a little bit.
Maybe the mugs aren't so much.
Or do I try to have something that
is in whatever orientation gives the canonical key point
locations?
There's no right answer to any of these, really.
These are-- it depends on the task, I think,
is actually the right--
the truth.
But they get subtle pretty fast about the choices
you make there.
I like eight, myself.
That's what I've always advocated for, eight.
But I wish it was as simple as that.
Because what if the box is--
if my picture of the box--
part of it's a little bit off the screen.
I think occlusions are something that we can potentially
deal with.
You can actually estimate occluded key points.
In synthetic data, it's very easy
to label the location of the key points,
even if they're occluded.
There's nothing that would stop my simulation
from putting xy locations, even the ones that
are behind another box.
In real world data, it might be hard to label occluded key
points.
But yeah, even if it's not occlusions,
if it's just clipping or partial view or whatever,
there might be reasons why you shouldn't expect
to get exactly eight every time.
So you have to have some sort of estimation pipeline that's
OK with getting eight, but doesn't demand getting eight.
I wish, because things would get easier if it was--
if you could demand getting eight.
The symmetries, I think, are an important issue.
Do you try to make a representation that
allows for the symmetries?
In which case, how do you generate that synthetic data?
Carefully, right?
Or not?
These all come up.
So how would we output a system that didn't have--
what would be the output of my network for a system that
didn't try to identify any of the symmetries or anything
like that?
I mean, to some extent, this image
is kind of an example of that.
If I were to just draw a heat map that really just had
a Gaussian in all the places I thought I had--
single heat map, I could say these are the places where
I have my Gaussians.
And the desired image is to put a dot in every one of those.
That would be a representation that
would allow you to say, I don't care about which corner it is.
They're all the same.
And I want to generate a bunch of training data
that would just find all the corner key points,
and possibly the occluded corner key points, too.
I could have the ones in the back.
[INAUDIBLE]
Say it again?
Do you want to know what to tell it
if it tries to go into the same box?
So the question is, do you need to be
able to identify the same box reliably from frame to frame,
let's say.
I think in a lot of these cases, that's
not the stated requirement in the category level.
It would be just, given I have some instances in front of me,
be able to reason about them as one of the family of boxes.
I think you can use object detection on top of this
to do labels of particular boxes.
If you want to have the shoeboxes different than
whatever, I think the object detection pipeline
would help you more with that.
Maybe if the size was a strong indicator,
and you could estimate the size more explicitly with this,
maybe that would help.
But oftentimes, I would just think
of the perception front end.
The object detection front end.
So this would be all corners are the same.
If I trained the bottom left corner, the top right corner,
defined maybe in my camera frame, for instance,
or something like that, and I trained each of those
as being somehow a different Gaussian,
then I could try to learn a more orientation-specific
representation.
And these are all possible.
And I think the heat map progression loss
would support any of those.
Some of the other losses people use
where you are kind of baking in the assumption
that you have only one Gaussian, and you
try to find the peak of that Gaussian.
But the expected value interpolations
in the integral pose machine would not do well
on this kind of representation.
There is an important point.
So if you have multiple instances,
then how do you deal with that?
This gets a little bit to your point.
How do you deal with multiple instances?
[INAUDIBLE]
That's really what people do.
So she says, do instant segmentation at the same time.
It is, to me, a major success story.
That mask-rcnn pipeline just works so well
that almost every other downstream perception task
says, step one, get my crop around a particular object,
and only worry about finding a single instance
inside that crop.
So typically, you take the bounding box approximation out
of something like a mask-rcnn and just
apply these algorithms directly inside that tighter bounding
box.
This is a pretty tight bounding box already,
and you have corners from other places.
But you can say, in this bounding box,
I expect to find eight or less if it's going off to the side.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So I don't claim--
I'm not trying to claim this is the state-of-the-art box
detection.
I'm using it as a thought experiment for key points
more than that.
But I think I will show later a different--
I was going to use this as the example for both this
and the dense descriptors, which would be a little bit-- it's
going to show you you can pretty reliably get
the centers of the box, too.
Yeah, absolutely.
But the corners are appealing, I think,
in the sense that if you wanted to estimate the shape of the box
and that had some canonical values,
then that might be the signal you most want.
There's another interesting step,
which I think connects back to what we've already
learned in the class.
So if I do have estimates in, let's say,
2D of my eight key points, then how do I get that back
to something like a shape and a pose?
So somehow, people want to do 3D key points, probably.
So you can try to make a heat map in 3D.
That's a standard approach.
So think of it as a voxelized--
so you have images at each possible depth.
And you really put your Gaussian-desired kernel,
a heat map in that big object, in that big space.
I mean, like I said, it's shocking to me
how many outputs people put on the output of a network.
I mean, it seems hopelessly inefficient to do that.
But it works.
And we have hardware to support, right?
A lot of people will do something like 2D key points
plus depth per pixel.
So you'd have the heat map for the 2D key points.
And then you have one extra channel, which says--
at every pixel, I think the depth is some number.
And that is, I think, justified like this monocular stereo
kind of workflow I mentioned to you before.
And there's a handful-- some people
will try to take 2D key points projected onto a point cloud,
projected onto a depth measurement.
That's not going to work for occluded key points.
But at least for the key points you can see,
if you have a depth image, it might be enough
to just do a 2D key points and then project directly
onto the depth, which is kind of--
you could imagine this being the attempt to learn roughly that.
If you can get 3D key point estimates out,
then you can imagine trying to estimate
the shape and the pose using basically
the middle of our ICP step, that pose regression.
It's an SVD problem when you have known correspondences
and you're trying to estimate a given rigid rotation.
It's actually easier in some sense,
where it has less constraints.
If you're allowed your box to shrink and stretch,
then that is actually taking away some of the constraints
on the transform.
So it's actually an easier problem.
But that pipeline can work well.
Imagine doing ICP that's allowed to stretch and shrink in order
to go from the key point coming out of your heat map
into an estimation of this box's shape and relative pose.
So that whole workflow can work pretty well.
So this is how Greg played it out.
It played out for Greg and Maggie.
Those are rendered images.
So this is just rendered boxes.
He took some texture maps of Amazon boxes
off the web or something.
I think the way--
I remember I was standing with Greg.
I'm like, is that one rendered or real?
I'd always ask him.
And the tell is the background.
He wasn't upside down in the forest when he had those boxes.
So that's probably a render.
That's a Blender rendered image, something like that.
But they look really good.
They can look really, really good.
So you generate all your procedural training data.
You can train your mask R-CNN front end
with a perfect image pixel-wise labels
for the instant segmentation.
And then you can start making your synthetic desired key
points either occluded or not.
Actually, generating the unoccluded key points
is harder in simulation.
But then you generate a bunch of ground truth data.
The performance in synthetic images,
again, like random person sideways in the background,
is an indication that that was a Blender image.
But in real world data, it transfers surprisingly well
or not surprising anymore.
But you get these beautiful instance crops
from the real data.
And you can get pretty good predicted key points
with just the standard machinery pushed through that.
I do think that the subtleties of this--
I don't know that we know the right answer.
This was something we did for fun,
but haven't taken all the way to fruition yet of how exactly we
want to--
what's the best way to represent these 3D key points.
And I think it's driven partly, I think,
by how you'd want to reconstruct and, like you say,
what the task is, exactly what the--
I think my preference has been for occluded key points,
hoping for eight of them, a strong ICP type
loss to reconstruct, which means we need our heat map in 3D.
But who knows if that's the best.
Questions on that?
I can see how that's more than pose.
It's more than pose even for boxes where there's not
a lot more semantic information available.
It still allows you to do things of boxes of all sizes.
OK, so for manipulation of more interesting things,
where we've labeled just a handful of key points,
I think the key points alone are not enough.
That's what I meant when I wrote key points
plus plus over there.
They are often enough to specify the task.
So say I want these key points to move
through this reg and transform over to this location.
That's a nice way to specify the task.
But if you actually want to grab the mug,
then you need a little bit more.
But it seems-- so we felt that there's
a lot of interesting manipulation tasks
that you can do with sort of an online geometry
estimation of the geometry of the mug,
the task specified in terms of key points,
and then you do basically your antipodal.
You can do something fancier in there.
But if you just reason about the point cloud
and you have the crop from the instant segmentation,
then that's enough.
The sort of the local instantaneous point cloud,
maybe with a little bit of reconstruction,
plus this idea that once I grab the object,
it stays rigid in my hand and moves
through the same rigid transforms,
was enough to program a pretty interesting broader
amount of tasks than we could do with the pose-based known
object pipeline.
Does that make sense?
Right, so we have manipulated lots of shoes and lots of mugs,
just to say it's statistically strong.
So what are the limitations of that?
That's just one recommendation of a pipeline.
One of the things that it struggles with,
if I only use the instantaneous point cloud that I'm getting,
then I don't have any sense of what's the back of the object.
Right, so if I wanted to grasp something that
involved me picking up the back of the object,
or if I'm moving it through space
and I wanted to avoid collisions,
if I pretended that my mug was only the front side that I
could see, then I'm going to bash things in as I
move through the world.
But neural networks are good at predicting hard things.
Shape completion is a thing.
You can make shape completion networks
that will hallucinate the back of an object.
A lot of the tools we use in manipulation
do this implicitly, but you can do it explicitly
by just trying to have-- training a different network
to take a partial view and hallucinate
the backside, for instance.
And if you put that into this pipeline,
you can do even more.
You can do collision avoidance constraints
as you move through the world at a class general level.
And we'll talk more about force control later,
but I was just very surprised when
Wei Gao, who was working on this,
showed that with basically that same pipeline,
just knowing where key points were,
he could do a lot of tasks that would have seemed
to require more information.
So like peg and hole type tasks or force-based tasks.
And basically, for those of you that know impedance control,
and hopefully you all will in a few lectures,
basically you just--
if I wanted to apply an impedance
between the mug and the world, if I grab the mug in my hand
and I just start regulating the impedance down here,
then I can do a lot of interesting tasks.
So just to say that this pipeline supports
relatively advanced things.
I'll show you a couple of fun examples.
Peg and hole type stuff.
Erasing with arbitrary erasers.
Like to have a reasonable eraser,
that means some sort of force control type task.
But how do you do force control if you don't even
know the geometry of the thing you're controlling through?
Well, you put a key point at the bottom,
you regulate the force at the end of the key point,
and you can do sort of a category level force control
type task.
Peg and hole kind of tasks work surprisingly well.
It's plugging in USB cables, putting Legos together.
Big Legos, admittedly.
But yeah, plugging things into the USB charger.
And it's mostly a question of what tasks
can be sufficiently specified, and where
this sort of very simple representation of the object
is somehow sufficient.
And for tasks like this, knowing where the end of the USB thing
is once it's in your hand is most of what you need to know.
Yeah.
That make sense?
So key points better than pose, I think.
To the point-- so I mean, here's what happens.
You have a team that's working on perception,
you have a team that's working on planning and control.
You agree early on that the message you're
going to send me from your perception system
is like the pose of the object or whatever,
and I'm going to build my whole planning and control
stack around pose.
And then I've got my state estimation stack around pose,
and I've got my simulation stack around pose.
And then someone says, oh, you know what?
Pose is really a bad thing for us to estimate for perception.
And then it takes a very long time
to sort of go through and make all of the systems
stop thinking about pose, because it's so
baked into everything we do.
So if you're starting up and you haven't already baked it in,
just don't--
you start typing pose, you know, whatever, just say,
wait a second, not in my message, not in the API.
Those things should not communicate with pose.
It's restrictive.
OK, so that pipeline, I think it is--
we'll talk about its limitations.
It's very geometric.
It does have the ability to capture semantics,
because it had human labels.
So the question really, I think, is, can you do similar things
to that, but get rid of the human labels?
What kind of tasks can you enable
without that semantic level of labeling?
Can we do some of this self-supervision kind of work
in this representation?
So people have taken key point type representations
and done tool use.
That's something that your TAs work on.
And there's hammering tasks and other tasks.
So it does, I think, extend potentially.
But at some point, it is a limited representation.
So let me tell you about a generalization of that, which
is another, I think, proposal for a category-level object
representation, which goes through dense correspondences.
And the version we did was called dense object nets.
But the core technology was done before--
not specific to manipulation, but was
done by Tanner Schmidt and Richard Dukum and Dieter Fox,
for instance.
So here's the basic plot that you have to understand
to get the gist of this.
So this is a new camera image of a hat.
This is real-time observations of the hat.
Pete, I believe, in this particular case,
had his mouse over the left image at this part of the hat.
And the correspondence problem you know well--
the correspondence problem would be given
two very different images of the hat,
try to find the same point in the other image of the hat.
So let me just start from the beginning.
So there's some at the beginning here.
This is the proposed-- this is what
the network is predicting is the same point in the hat.
And it's getting it in very different orientations.
Whatever the hat is deformed completely,
but it's still giving reliable representations of what's
the same point of the hat.
And in the middle, we have the same heat map
kind of rendering of the output of the network, which is saying,
what is it scoring all of the different possible points
in the image as being potentially
the best correspondence?
So let me tell you how this works.
I think it's another good example
of these kind of representations.
I mean, the basic--
I'll even just show you the pipeline first.
So the basic pipeline is, again, this 3D reconstruction.
So you put a brand new object.
That's another thing.
So we have shoes.
We have mugs.
We have a lot of baby toys around lab, too,
which is kind of hard to explain to fiscal.
But yeah, it's good for robots, I think.
So soft, plush toys with buckles and zippers and stuff
are great for robots.
OK, so you've got a baby toy.
You put it on your table.
You do your dense reconstruction.
So this is something that I think in a future term
deserves a lecture on just dense reconstruction.
It's basically simultaneous localization for manipulation.
But we've said over and over again
that you have this ability to fuse point clouds
into a consistent representation using sine distance functions.
And you get these beautiful meshes out just
by scanning with your 3D scanner.
So that, as an intermediate signal,
allows you to train this representation, which
is these dense descriptors.
So how do I train dense descriptors?
the formulation here is I'm going
to take an image in-- again, it'll
be my RGB image width, height by 3.
I'm going to pour it into my neural network.
You could call it your latent representation
or intermediate representation or whatever
you want to think of it as.
But I'm going to project the pixels in the image
into some descriptor space.
And the thing you get out when you do that
is hopefully-- not that, but yeah, that's too bad.
You get nice colorful images.
We'll see different examples.
But you'll see if you choose d to be 3,
then you can actually just render it again as an RGB image.
And what you'd like to see is somehow
that if I show many different poses of the object,
that it will have a consistent--
the same color will be associated
with the same parts of the objects
and you can move it through many different lighting conditions,
many different poses, many different deformations,
and stuff like that.
So it's just some intermediate latent representation
that should be better than working with RGB.
We're going to put it into some descriptor space, some light
pose invariant space.
And the way that we train them is
with a pixel-wise contrastive loss.
So we train this by putting in image A, image B.
It's a Siamese training.
You get two dense descriptor images out.
But you have a data set already where
you've taken many images of the same object.
You've done your dense reconstruction.
And now you can go back and say, in this image,
this pixel should be the same as, in this image,
some other pixel.
So you have matching pixels just based on your 3D reconstruction.
So from here, we have descriptor images A and B.
And then we have a list of matches
for 3D reconstruction.
And we also just make a bunch of non-matches.
So basically, for every one match
that we have in our data set, we'll
throw in a bunch of non-matches.
I think 150 is the default number.
150 non-matches, roughly, for every one match.
And it's to the point where our lost function has got,
I think, order of a million samples per image pair.
So we're just pumping through a pretty dense version
of these two images, milking them for everything
that we can to write a lot of different--
a rich objective function for this.
And then we'd write a loss function, which basically
looks like this.
So the loss of the matches is like 1
over the number of matches of the--
you want those two to be the same.
So I'll say the neural network of image A at the match image
minus the neural network function at the image B
at the--
whatever the match pixel should be at B.
That whole thing squared.
And then you have some negative score
for non-matches, which you can write
in a bunch of different ways.
But the way in practice it gets--
it was done in that work was the non-matches.
And the idea is to only penalize--
you want to saturate your penalization.
So you don't want-- if they're too close to the same point,
that's OK.
But you want to--
let me just write it.
And I'm going to do max of 0 and some threshold
minus the neural network scores.
OK.
So I'm going to--
I want these things to be different.
So I'm going to penalize now if they're similar.
But I'm only going to penalize if they're
beyond some threshold.
I want to rule out nearby points.
And you basically add these two objectives together
to get this pixel-wise contrastive loss.
, OK?
So that's it.
Find some intermediate representation
so that two views are the same.
They get the same value in this d space
when the pixels should be the same and a different value
when they should be different.
OK.
And it works surprisingly well.
OK, so you get these--
you can get potentially very sharp.
This was an old version.
This is a new version.
I've got the--
you know, Pete's mouse or whatever moving,
maybe Lucas's mouse moving over the object here.
And you can get very sharp responses
to pretty non-trivial objects.
And they're arbitrary objects.
OK, so yeah?
Did you train the network to perform this in scratch
or were you using, like, tags to train them?
Almost always ResNet backbones and stuff like this, yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah, big ResNet backbone, yeah.
Sorry, the question was, were we training from scratch?
And the answer is almost always no.
Yeah, we generate-- again, it's sort of like your point
last time.
We generate a lot of data, but in a pretty narrow band.
We do try to do things like lighting changes
and getting lots of different poses of the same object
and deform it if it's deformable and stuff like that.
But it's still very narrow compared to ImageNet, right?
And do you get a different network
for each type of object that you're using?
So this is the mystical, magical, and ad hoc,
I'd say, maybe, thing.
So we can do either class general objects.
See, these are the kind of images I was talking about.
If you choose D to be 3 and you render it as RGB,
these are different shoes, but they all
light up the same colors in the same places on the shoes.
So how did you train that?
So that was the case where you trained each shoe
independently.
So each shoe was scanned independently.
And just something out of the capacity of the network
or something, it chose to reuse the same D value.
It didn't have any incentive to use or not
use the same values, but it tends
to find representations where it uses the same color
values for the same parts of the shoes.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
So it is explicitly, for any one view of the object,
saying that these things are distinct.
Whatever pose you're scanning, whatever,
it's saying every point is distinct.
So if you had repeated buckles or whatever like that,
those are distinct.
There's a canonical frame where I'm
going to say where I am in that frame
gets a distinct descriptor.
That's the objective explicitly.
It doesn't try to find repeated structure inside it.
What's interesting is that if you train them--
in this example, we train different hats
at different times.
So if you actually train all of the same--
if you put multiple hats in the test data at the same time,
then it will distinguish--
it must learn a different representation for each hat.
So it will actually learn an instance specific.
All you have to do is throw multiple hats in
at the same scan.
If you train one hat at a time, then it somehow--
this is unfortunately black magic--
it somehow chooses to use the same representation
for the same parts of the object,
and you get these class general descriptors out.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
It's impressively good.
Yeah.
I mean, you want your training data
to include those sort of deformations, but if it does,
it's impressively good.
Yeah.
So that is a pretty--
so that's a completely self-super--
I didn't have to-- anybody had-- nobody had to go in and label
anything.
Right?
So you could think of it as just having
very dense but self-supervised key points, which
is super useful.
It doesn't give me the language to say,
you know, hang the handle on the rack.
There's nothing-- I haven't attached enough semantics
to do some of those richer specifications,
but it's sort of just sufficient to specify some tasks.
And so it lives somewhere else in that spectrum of, like,
what can I specify?
So for instance, if you just wanted to, say,
pick up the object from the tail,
the caterpillar from the tail, then
clicking in the dense descriptor image
says, I want you to grab at this descriptor value.
And that's enough to partly to specify a pick task relative
to the points of the object.
Did you have a question?
Yeah?
Yeah.
So when you say self-supervised, but you
have a known list of matches?
But the robot is doing all the data collection for itself.
There's an algorithm which does this dense reconstruction,
and it's just--
you just go through that list of data and point--
you know, saying this point projected back.
All that data is constructed automatically,
no human touching it.
So there's some tasks you can do with that representation alone.
Right?
Yeah?
So in these exchanges, do you see the robot kind
of moving around before it's [INAUDIBLE]
during a reconstruction of the object,
but can pass the [INAUDIBLE]
Good.
So it's doing significant scanning
when it's learning the dense descriptors.
Even when it's picking, you can get a--
we're doing reconstruction so you can just--
you don't have to.
If you had a partial view, and you did the dense descriptor,
and you went and grabbed, you'd be able to do something.
But if you want to have less partial views,
then that initial scan can make it more robust.
OK, and so this is to answer your question
about the centers of the boxes, right?
So you can totally do this for boxes,
and it sort of lights up, and there's
a canonical sort of dense descriptor frame for boxes,
too.
Right?
And it works pretty well in reality.
Yeah?
If you can do a 3D reconstruction
to get a 3D model of an object, and you
have a [INAUDIBLE]
So you'd like to be able-- so the question
is, if you can do a dense reconstruction in ICP,
then why are you not done?
And the point is, I'd like to, for instance,
specify the task on one model of the shoe.
So I'll scan one shoe, and I'll say, pick it up here,
and then transfer that to new shoes
that I haven't seen before.
So I want my specification and my manipulation
to generalize across the category.
So I agree with you.
For any one instance of the shoe, we could do this,
and then you could move the shoe.
I could try to reconstruct it with ICP.
But if I want the task to generalize across the shoes.
[INAUDIBLE]
I might mention them at the end.
But if you know more, that's great to know, too.
Yeah?
Yes?
So what exactly is the descriptor dimension
of how many shoes, how many you want to use?
Is it just like a-- it finds something
that's consistent across the category?
Good.
So the question is, how do you choose D?
Is there any intuition about that?
The answer might not be super satisfying.
I think even since the first paper came out,
we've had more tricks that we use for training.
They're all in the public repositories.
But it used to be that actually we
would use 3 for visualization.
And you could increase it, and you'd hope it would do better.
But it didn't do a lot better.
With a normalization trick, we basically
would push all the descriptors to be on the unit sphere.
Then we did see that as you increased D,
you'd get better and better, meaning sharper
receptive fields in the dense descriptors.
And I think 10 or 12 or something
is probably what we would be using at the end.
But it is not like analyze your system,
go through some procedure, decide what D is going to be.
It's really kind of--
maybe it's not bad.
It's a model reduction in classical system
identification.
Also, even for linear system identification,
you try a number of different--
principal component analysis.
You kind of see how many different modes
you need to describe your data.
And I think the same sort of thinking is happening here.
As I increase the dimension of my representation,
I can do more.
But at some cost, I don't have enough data to fill that space.
It's that kind of thinking.
You would like to think, given infinite data, as I increase D,
I would have only sharper images.
And I think the only thing pushing down on that
is computation time and data time, so you find a balance.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
They are projected-- so it is not
that the pixel 32 in this image and pixel 32 in this image.
It's pixel 32 in this image plus whatever pixel
that same thing in my 3D maps to in this other image.
So that's match A, match B. Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
OK, that's a good question.
So could I do mass properties or other physical quantities
inside the dense script?
So one thing you can definitely do
is you could just take your RGB image,
turn it into the descriptor dimension.
I mean, really, even in this picture,
you could sort of think, this is an ugly space.
I turn the lights on or whatever.
The same points change color values a lot,
whereas this gives a very consistent representation.
So using this as features for something like ICP
totally makes sense.
And then if you get in the space of you've
got features that you want to correspond masses
or other things to, it could make sense.
But I do think that the dense descriptor object by itself
becomes a useful quantity for the object,
but it's trained purely on a geometric understanding
of the object.
So in fact, that is, I'd say, the limitations
of the dense descriptors is that they are completely geometric.
So Pete used to say--
what did he say?
He won't tell you when you've done frying your egg
or something like that.
You can come up with silly examples.
But even-- I mean, there's other places.
We know that there's limitations to this.
So if your object doesn't have a canonical pose,
then there's not a right answer for the dense descriptors.
So like we were playing with peeling potatoes.
Want a robot to peel potatoes, right?
There's no canonical pose for a potato.
You can rotate the potato or whatever,
and there's no reason that the dense descriptor should
have a consistently put-- like at the 43rd i,
it should be descriptor value, whatever.
And it just doesn't work for that.
It's not a good representation for something
like that, or peeling carrots, or anything that doesn't have
a canonical reference frame.
If you can't go down and say, I would put the reference frame
like this, then it's not going to be able to do it either.
It's also very just--
it's not going to capture anything about the dynamics,
really, or anything like that.
All right, let me just close out by mentioning--
these are the representations we used in the video
I showed you before.
And we'll talk more about that later.
There are a couple other really good, interesting object
representations that--
this is an early version of the Knox family,
which is normalized object coordinate
space for category level 60 object pose and size
estimation.
So this one is more explicitly saying,
take all of your CAD models, snap them
into some canonical frame.
We're going to still think about poses,
but poses plus the transformation,
the warping from the original geometry across the class
into this canonical frame.
And I can't help but see dense descriptors
when I look at these pictures, because they're
rendered in sort of the same way.
But you make-- the value that you give this,
it's not discovered by gradient descent.
It's imposed as saying, this pixel
in the squished, scaled, canonical frame
would have color value whatever.
And you can use that representation
in a lot of similar ways.
The Knox line of papers talked about doing pose estimation
even by taking your canonical frame
and basically trying to warp the images in your renderer.
That's what analysis by synthesis
is, to try to estimate the pose.
So this is a good one.
Watch right here.
You see you've got some different pose,
and you basically try to warp it through rendering
into the canonical frame.
And that gives you-- that estimates your rotation
and translation and does pose estimation.
So I didn't say much of anything about that, but Knox is--
if you think about object category level,
object representations, Knox is one of the first ones
you think about.
And there's just a lot of other good examples of people doing,
for instance, using a kind of geometry inference engine.
Let me see if I can find the right pictures here
in the middle.
Yeah, so you get some point cloud,
and you try to basically fill it in with a shape completion.
And maybe shape is just enough to do
a lot of good manipulation.
So if you have from point cloud to shape completion
to writing objectives just on shape,
that can work pretty well too.
So it's a super rich class of space
of what is the right level to represent
objects for manipulation.
I'll say again, I think it's mostly about how
do you specify the task.
That's what defines these things.
And these are insufficient for the tasks I love most
that have more dynamics.
If I wanted to tie the laces on those shoes,
it's probably going to fall short.
We've tried a little bit.
So but I hope you guys can all be contributing it.
I think this is an active area of research.
Good.
That was part two.
I guess we'll see you next time.
Sorry that the PSET's not released.
It's going to be released as soon
as I get back to my computer.
So.