[INAUDIBLE]
All right.
OK, we're good.
Let me list a few administrative things just to kick off,
since there's a lot of things going on.
We know that the drop date is Thursday,
so people are thinking about their grades.
We've done our best.
I would say Rachel and Danny have done their best.
Thank you to grade as many of the p-sets
as we could possibly do.
They should be-- all the grades should be available to you
on Gradescope.
You get emails, I guess, most of the time that they're released.
And the rubric is on the website,
and the percentages should line up.
There's no intention to curve.
So you should have a good sense of where you're at.
If you have questions, of course, you can ask.
We have our project face-to-face meetings this week.
I'm excited to see your faces and talk about the project.
That's my number one goal.
I mean, I sent in the post just some basic instructions.
Come and tell us--
show us a few pictures, talk us through them,
and tell us how things are going.
Use it as a chance to ask us questions.
If you're stuck on anything, we want
to make sure we're helping you as much as possible
and that you're still on track.
If you have a big team and you want
to help us understand if everybody's
able to contribute, I think that's an important thing that I
would like to look out for.
In general, I think some of you are
asking lots of good questions on Stack Overflow.
I think a lot of them are private.
You guys don't realize how many questions
are getting answered all, but there's lots of good questions.
Keep them coming.
Some of you are asking them on Stack Overflow, which I actually
really appreciate and love.
I mean, I think--
and some of them have gotten-- some of those
have gotten extremely good answers.
So don't be shy asking on the main Drake forum.
I think that's incredibly good for, in general, just
having more open documentation and community
building for that.
And you also get more people answering questions
because they're on--
someone's there answering most of the time.
And the last thing that I guess we haven't said,
but we sort of decided, is that logistically,
with 50-some groups, we're going to do the videos again
for the final project presentation
rather than the live presentation.
I think it's actually worked incredibly well.
It was one of the good things that came out of Zoom semesters,
I think, is being able to have something-- an artifact
that you can look back at and share and other things
is a great thing.
And also, avoiding the switching laptop conundrum is nice.
So we're going to go for that again.
We still have the last day allocated for it.
I've actually reserved the room for longer.
We'll have a viewing session.
So it counts as one lecture from the time we get together,
but we'll watch as many of them as we can.
And we'll give you all the details on the website
about exactly the time durations and how to post
and everything like that.
Lots of small things, but any questions
about the administrative stuff?
OK.
So we started-- I kind of gave the prelude last week
to reinforcement learning, talking about visual motor.
And this week, we'll squarely focus on reinforcement
learning in two parts.
So part one today, we're going to talk about mostly
sort of the policy gradient view of reinforcement learning.
And then I'm going to talk--
I'm going to emphasize sort of a few of the core ideas, I think,
and maybe not even the most commonly discussed ideas,
but the ones that I think are most relevant to manipulation
and that are coming up in our research.
Some of the important ideas of thinking about it
as a black box optimization, some
of the important things that happen when we add
stochasticity to the formulation.
We'll talk through those.
Thursday, we're actually going to have a guest lecture
from Abhishek Gupta, who's fantastic.
He's a recent graduate from Peter Abbeel and Sergey
Levine's group.
He's done lots of reinforcement learning on real robots
doing manipulation.
So he's going to give you a very sort of applied RL view
and what does it take to do RL with real data
in the real world on Thursday.
So I think that'll be very good.
And he'll build off this, talk about the actor critic
and the Q-learning varieties.
Good.
OK, so let's start talking about RL.
What is reinforcement learning?
It means a lot of things to a lot of people.
The scope of what you might call a reinforcement learning
algorithm is a dynamic object.
And it grows aggressively, I would say.
For me, RL is a set of methods that
are trying to solve the control problem.
So the diagram you will always see here
in every sort of RL talk or book or whatever
is that you have an environment.
You have an agent.
Sometimes that's agent.
And we're just trying to close the loop with the environment.
But I think what defines RL for me, which
is maybe slightly narrower than it's broadly used these days,
is the idea that we're going to assume
that the environment, the world, the plant, is a black box.
So you get to run experiments on the environment.
You get to send in actions and get observations out.
But you don't get to know the full detailed equations
of the environment.
You don't get to explicitly take gradients of it.
You don't get to know its convex.
You don't get to do any of the stuff
that we've been trying to emphasize.
And there's a couple of key ideas about policy gradient
and Q functions and value functions
that are, I would say, defining in the sense of RL.
But this, I think, first idea is treating
the world as a black box.
And I think another key idea is that RL almost always
leverages stochastic optimal control as opposed
to the deterministic formulations
for algorithmic reasons.
And we'll see, I think, important reasons
for the success of the algorithms.
So last time, we started talking about the visual motor
policies, which is just so good and so awesome
that we can finally take a full camera input
and think about possibly blocking it off a little bit
and having a smaller pipe that comes down to a controller
that we think about with our RL tools,
but still this pipeline that takes images straight
through to actions and in a feedback loop
is just so good and so powerful.
And I really became completely convinced
when we were doing these experiments, this very, very,
I think, compelling, robust behavior, at least
local to the demonstrations, but where you could prod and push
and watch the robot interact with the world
in a much more reasonable way.
But last time, we did visual motor policies
with behavior cloning.
And today, we'll try to talk about some
of the underpinnings.
Can we find those policies with RL?
, OK.
So I actually want to start.
It's been very fun for all of us,
I think, to read the feedback that you
give on the problem sets.
Those of you that are continuing to give good feedback,
we appreciate it.
Many of you keep asking about, don't
forget to throw in some software examples and the like.
So I actually want to start a little bit with this--
talk a little bit about RL software.
And it's actually progressed quite a bit
since this time last year.
So this time last year, I was looking around
at all the possible RL packages that I would recommend or not
recommend for the class.
And I was torn, because a lot of them
were in an intermediate state or something.
But I think there's some pretty good, more mature offerings
this time.
And I'm pretty excited about that.
So I feel more confident recommending
one or two specific things.
OK, so the first--
I guess I've forgotten my intro order,
but let me forward pass that for a second.
OK, the first bit of RL software that
has become the winning format, I think,
for specifying the environment half of this
is the OpenAI gem.
Many of you know this.
So there's a standard Python interface, the gem environment,
which asks you to define your RL problem--
not the algorithm, but the problem--
just by filling in a few simple callbacks.
You have a basic init method, a step method,
which takes your action, outputs the observations
at the next step, advances your simulator,
however you want to do that, a basic reset method, something
to render just for the human or for making
videos, which could be separate from the observations.
These are all, of course, very analogous to the things
we have been using in Drake.
This picture is not so different than a sort of systems
view of the world.
So every one of those things has sort
of an analogy in the tools we've been using.
We have-- we put our diagram builder inside the init,
and our--
not just the diagram, but the simulator.
Our step function is equivalent to advance to in Drake speak,
but it also has to return the evaluated observation,
the evaluated reward.
Reset just means start over, create a new context, probably
a random context, actually.
And those sort of all--
I think it's pretty--
this is what's been great about the OpenAI gem,
is that this is asks very little of the interface,
and it's very easy to populate, whether it's
from a game engine or from an Atari game,
or all kinds of problems are easy to sort
of cast in that framework.
But I also think it's very telling, maybe,
to think about just the difference, the different sort
of view.
And maybe it's one of the best ways
to express my mixed feelings about RL,
is that this picture of the world
is general enough to be used for everything.
And that API, you can put sort of anything behind it.
But if you contrast that with sort of the Drake systems
framework that I've been advocating,
where the goal in Drake has been to expose everything,
not to bottle up everything.
I mean, this is really a sort of a philosophical difference.
And it's not clear if one's better or worse yet, right?
But there's a philosophical difference,
where I believe that the systems are very structured.
I think our mechanics is very structured.
I think our controllers are very structured.
I think you should do everything in your power
to express that structure in a clean way,
and allow your algorithms to dig in and exploit
the structure when they can, and make that as glass box,
clear box as possible.
And the RL approach is more general,
but it's weaker in the sense that it doesn't ask
you to declare those things.
It only assumes a black box.
And that's a philosophical difference.
And so I actually, this week, have
been trying to make sure there's a nice interface available
for you to--
if you have a Drake system, you can use the open AI tools
and things like this.
So it's easy to go back and forth,
and I'll show you that in a second.
But it sort of pains me to do it.
I mean, of course, I want to be able to enable both.
But I feel like we've tried to expose
all this beautiful structure, write
all the diagrams and all the systems in a way that's
sort of like, if they're convex, they're convex, whatever.
And then it's kind of like, we're
going to let you look at them through a little drinking
straw in order to do the algorithms.
And it's not leveraging the extra work that
has happened behind the scenes.
So I would say that's the only--
I actually love--
I do really like RL.
I think RL is clearly the most exciting thing that's
happening, I think, right now.
It's generating the most excitement right now.
And even my thesis-- that's what this funny slide was before--
my thesis was actually in RL, right?
So this was in 2003, probably, this one,
where I was in building E25, back when
the neuroscientists were in E25.
And because I was in a neuroscience lab
and I was trying to build robots,
I had to bring a CD rack shelf from home.
And someone needed a piece of rubber,
so I only had one piece of rubber.
I was working on a shoestring budget,
but this is a little walking robot
that just fell down a ramp.
There's no motors, no RL there.
And then my thesis was about making
a robot do RL in the wild, sort of,
and learn it quickly to learn how to walk.
And this was the actuated version of that simple robot.
And I spent a lot of hours watching
that thing do gradient descent with kind of a--
you're trying to write your thesis and you're hearing--
[TAPPING]
Everyone's over here.
But no, I mean, this was defining for me
to think about what you could do with online learning.
And I think-- and even in my job talk,
to get the job at--
when I went around giving my faculty candidate talks,
I was saying, even if we could solve the optimal control
problem perfectly for humanoid robots,
you would still need online learning
to adapt to all the changes that are
going to happen in the world.
And I still believe that.
OK.
So this little robot basically fell down a ramp
because of the mechanical design,
but then it learned how to walk using RL.
That was doing policy gradient-based--
actually, an actor-critic-based algorithm
that was learning to walk in real time.
It took only a few minutes to learn how to walk
because the design put it in a space
where it could tune only a very small policy at that time.
And it would adapt on the fly.
As it walked around, this was--
walking from E25 towards the Media Lab
was like the crowning achievement
because it wasn't a very big robot.
And right around that time when they were shooting that video,
Marvin Minsky walked by.
And he looked down at the robot, and he
looked at the camera crew that was behind the robot.
He's like, I think the camera is more impressive than the robot.
And I cried myself to sleep that night,
but I was still proud of the robot.
Anyway, so this was defining for me.
I really think a lot about RL, but I
think that there is a fundamental sample complexity
issue in the amount of training data
that you need to do the types of algorithms
we'll talk about today.
And so I have been trying to contribute
to trying to exploit the structure in the equations
more.
OK, so there's this OpenAI gem.
It exists.
I think you can use anything that's
sort of a system in Drake can be a system in OpenAI gem.
And similarly, you could take any OpenAI gem system
and use it in Drake.
You just won't be able to use all
of the gradient and other features in Drake
if you do that.
So I made this Drake gem.
Many people have done Drake wrappers around exposing
the gem interface around Drake, but I tried to make one
that you could build off of for your projects if you want this.
So it just goes through and defines all of those carefully.
It's actually-- I think it's important to do it right.
I mean, there's sort of right ways
to reinitialize the simulator to get everything seeded properly
off a single random seed and the like,
but it's all very easy to do.
So that's available if people want it.
OK, and like I said, back in the day-- so the OpenAI gem
is for the environments.
And this has been relatively convergent.
Most people are using the AI gem interface for some time now.
But for the algorithms, there are
lots of good tools out there.
And I'd say they're even more mature this year.
So the one that I will be using in the notes
as I write them up this week is the stable baselines
3 as an example.
We're using PyTorch in the class.
It uses PyTorch.
Some of the other baselines algorithms
are still using TensorFlow, and so harder for me
to use alongside the notes without having
more dependencies and the like.
It's got a lot of the famous algorithms implemented.
It strikes me that this isn't the best advertisement.
The particular lots of red that they put here
is a little scary, but there's still some good check marks.
And it's honest, right?
But there are a lot of the algorithms
that work for a lot of cases.
So this has got many of the RL algorithms.
I guess I already wrote algorithms.
And then there's one other tool that I think is incredibly
good that we've used a bunch, which is this NeverGrad tool.
Now my slides are not quite--
for some of the black box optimization,
which is not purely RL.
It's for a broader view of this.
NeverGrad has a bunch of good algorithms,
and we'll use that too.
NeverGrad meaning no gradients for black box optimization.
[TYPING]
OK, so let's dig in and talk a little bit
about the implications of black box optimization
and why it's good and why it's expensive in some ways.
OK?
OK, so I've been advocating many times
to think about our manipulation problems
through the lens of optimization.
The general form of that is something like this, right?
In many cases, many algorithms we've used,
like the solvers in SNOPT or if you've
used any of our MOSEC or Girobi sort of tools,
exploit some structure in f and g.
The weakest form, the sort of SNOPT
or the general nonlinear optimization,
maybe it's just asking for the gradients.
Some of the more advanced algorithms
from MOSEC and Girobi will ask if you
can say that this is quadratic or it's
convex in some structured convex form.
It's similar for these constraints
to be a convex set.
Then you can level even more advanced algorithms at it.
So what we're going to go to today is just a simpler form.
We're going to minimize f of x and assume almost nothing.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
About f.
We're not even going to assume it's a-- we'll
start off by assuming f is even a deterministic function,
but there's going to be versions of this where you won't even
assume that you get the same answer every time you
put an x in.
So when I think of this as a black box,
I'm saying that I give you an x, you give me f of x out,
and that's it.
I don't get to ask any more detailed questions.
Don't get to know anything about what's
happening behind the scenes.
It could be calling a game engine.
It could be playing Go.
Doesn't matter.
OK, so in this view of the world-- I'm
going to erase that just to stay on the same boards here.
In this view of the world, we had some really nice algorithms.
So for instance, if I had some complicated optimization
problem, the simplest versions would be gradient descent.
I get a point here.
I start moving down the landscape.
We talked about sort of Newton-like or quasi-Newton
algorithms or the quadratic programming
generalization of that, sequential quadratic
programming, which maybe if I have a sample point here, what
I would do would be use some of the gradient information
to make a local quadratic approximation of the function,
jump right down to the minimum, get a new sample point,
jump right down, and eventually converge on the minimum.
So if I tell you now that you can assume almost nothing
about f, we don't actually even want to assume it's smooth,
but I think our pictures will indicate it's smooth for now,
just to get our head around the problem.
Then what kind of optimization are you left with?
I mean, in a one-dimensional board example,
you could just sample until you find a good solution
and be done.
But in high dimensions, we're thinking that's probably not--
it's harder to draw, but it's important to think about this
as sort of a high-dimensional object.
And just trying every point until you find a good one,
brute force search isn't going to get the job done.
So how do you do something like gradient-based optimization
when you only have a black box?
And you can imagine that almost most of the ideas over here
have sort of a sampling-based analogy.
Right?
Which is, in many ways, not so different than what
we talked about with kinematic trajectory optimization
versus sample-based motion planning.
There's actually a lot of nice parallels
between those two worlds and the two worlds we're doing today.
But maybe the simplest algorithm,
gradient-like algorithm, would be if I take my random sample.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
Perturb it by some amount.
So let's say I have my guess that the i-th step is xi.
You have f of xi.
Try to go ahead and evaluate f of xi
plus some small perturbation.
So I'll make a little perturbation here, w.
I'll get a different point.
Maybe that's just drawn from some Gaussian.
I'll just make a small random change to my parameters, w,
in some direction.
And the simplest algorithm, I think,
would just be to say, if this value is less than this value,
keep it.
Use that as my new point.
And then we'll wash, rinse, and repeat.
If it went uphill, discard it.
Maybe a slightly more refined version of that
could be to say that I will move in the direction of this point
proportional to the reward I got, the relative reward.
So if this looked a lot better, I'll
move aggressively in the direction of that sample point.
And maybe even if it went up, I could move somehow
in the opposite direction based on this.
So there's a sort of a first order
sample-based approximation.
OK.
But there's also-- you can imagine second order methods
or richer methods that are doing sort of the same thing.
I'm highly positive about the SQP style optimization.
I think it's a very powerful, fast, converging
set of algorithms.
And you could imagine taking my initial sample point
and taking lots of random samples.
Again, the picture is not fully expressive in 2D on the board.
But you can imagine trying to take lots of samples
around here.
Maybe I explore broadly.
And then fit a-- I almost said covariance,
but let's call it a quadratic.
Fit a quadratic, fit to samples, and then
do sort of something like a quasi-Newton descent.
OK, and this turns out to be a very powerful class
of algorithms, this general idea of trying
to use samples to approximate some
of the other types of algorithms that we like.
There are other considerations, too,
that make sampling a nice choice.
Right?
[SIPPING]
All right.
So let's just think for a minute about what's
the relative merits of a sampling-based approach
versus the exact gradient-based approach.
I mean, first of all, the sampling only requires--
that's easy, right?
f of x.
Doesn't require the actual gradient.
I think there's a question of how expensive is evaluating
f of x versus partial f of x if you have it.
That's definitely a consideration.
Sometimes it can be so much faster to implement--
if taking gradients is quite slow,
then it might actually be better to just run f
a bunch of times separately.
I remember Mo Todorov going back and forth with this from Majoko.
He was like-- one day I would talk to him.
He's like, oh, yeah, I wrote all the analytical gradients.
And then he's like, oh, no, I realized this is just faster.
Because I could put it on a GPU.
And he went back and forth.
So there was a time where he had all the analytical gradients.
And I think he's mostly gotten rid of them.
Another sort of important consideration,
like how many GPUs--
how big is your GPU, right?
How many threads, how many GPUs?
Because doing lots of samples of f
can be sort of trivially parallelized.
And if that is expensive but not as expensive as--
if it's free to make this in parallel,
then maybe it's cheaper, again, than the partial f partial x.
And that's a big one.
I think the success of these methods
is tied, I think, very closely with the fact
that we've got good GPUs and the like now.
But there is more subtle reasons that I really
want to think about, more, I think, robustness reasons.
So what if your cost function looks like something like this?
Right?
If there's a lot of sort of local, noisy structure
that happens in your optimization.
OK?
The gradient is a beautiful object, of course.
But it's-- for better or for worse,
it's an extremely local object.
If I happen to sample this point,
I might get instantaneously a gradient
that looks like that just because
of the high frequency components of my landscape.
And that could be a very poor representation of what I
actually-- the direction I actually want to move in.
So I think there is some robustness in actually
taking multiple samples.
Of course, it could still be susceptible to noisy
evaluations, but somehow the sampling-based thing
can potentially power through some noisy--
locally noisy observations.
So I think there's a very deep question that I don't
have an answer for you for.
I've seen examples that look a lot like this.
And I've seen examples that look more
like those simple pictures coming out of manipulation.
But I think there's a deep question, which
is, do our manipulation problems look like this or not?
Do the problems we care about solving and control,
more generally, look like this or not?
I think for the low-dimensional problems where
it's easy to plot these things, I don't worry too much
that it does.
But in the higher-dimensional, much richer sort of contact
kind of configurations, it's hard to know.
It's hard to know what those look like.
Like I said, I've seen examples where we're like, oh,
clearly the performance of our algorithm
is suffering because of something like this.
And then you plot them, and they're actually pretty smooth.
I think that there's other examples like people
tend to use these sampling-based methods sometimes
to optimize neural network-based models.
And so you think, well, maybe the neural network
is capturing the function correctly,
but it's locally not very smooth.
And I think that is probably true in some cases.
But we've seen other cases where we do our best to visualize
them, and they look pretty smooth.
Yes?
For higher-dimensional problems,
how do you check whether it's a normal shape or more
like a 2D shape?
Good question.
So when I say we've checked sometimes
and have looked at this in higher dimensions,
what do you do?
The tools are not as strong as I would like.
But a standard heuristic would be take your sample point,
pick a random direction, and make a 2D plot.
And if you do that a few times, you
can sort of convince yourself of the local shape,
even if you can't say anything rigorously about it.
I think in general, the sense of taking small probes
into the neural network, for instance.
And as a follow-up to that, is it common for the whole function
to have a similar level of local minima?
Or is it possible that it's just pockets
and really simply 2D?
Yeah, OK.
So the question is, do you expect
to see this uniformly everywhere,
like this high-frequency stuff, or just in pockets?
I think it's completely problem-dependent.
And I would suspect, in a lot of our manipulation formulations,
if I've got a huge swath of parameter space
where I don't even touch an object,
and then there's some parts where
the detailed mechanics are coming in
and it's much more complicated, that it's probably
going to be smooth sailing but maybe uninformative
for a lot of places, and then a lot of activity
in other places.
I would definitely think that's true,
which makes it hard to set global learning rate
parameters and the like.
So this is, I think, a very important point.
And I really do think that this number
of parallel executions is a very important point, too.
But of course, the most naive version
of this, of a sampling algorithm,
would say that every time I want to make
a local approximation of my gradient,
I'll take n samples, where n is the dimensionality
of my parameter space.
So basically, I'll change--
I'll perturb the decision variables
in every possible direction at least once.
That'd be like a finite difference type method.
And if you're doing that, then you'd
expect potentially the number of possible evaluations
that you have to do in f, in parallel,
to grow very badly if your number of x's
is like the weights of a neural network.
You would expect that to start getting bad.
So there's ways to try to fight against that.
And then the question is, do you have a super good gradient
based--
for neural networks, we do have very good gradient algorithms.
So these two do fight each other.
And they fight each other in interesting ways
as the dimensionality goes high.
Now, there's another name for these sort of black box
sampling based algorithms, which for a while
was sort of a bad thing, a bad word, or something like that.
I don't know.
But these are really the genetic algorithms.
They were not as popular before, or swarm-based optimization,
let's say.
But I think, like I said, because of the ability
to do these things in parallel, and I
think because of these nice robustness properties,
they've come back into fashion.
So the one that is most similar to this picture
that I said of trying to make a local quadratic approximation
of my data and then doing a quasi-Newton update
is an algorithm called CMAES.
I mean, all these algorithms are pretty similar.
There's many algorithms that are small variations
on each other.
So cross-entropy methods are pretty similar to this, too.
But I'll highlight CMAES here.
So CMA stands for covariant matrix adaptation.
It's often with an ES, evolutionary strategy.
OK.
As we've said before, the probabilistic interpretation
would be that you're trying to fit the covariance
matrix of a Gaussian kernel.
But that's the same as fitting a quadratic form
for a quasi-Newton method.
And this is just sort of a picture
if you actually do try to do a simple optimization,
if you're on a simple quadratic landscape
and you start with a swarm of particles,
you'd expect the-- in fact, in the simple case of it
being a quadratic, you actually expect
that the local covariance matrix approximation will indeed
reproduce the Hessian of the quadratic form.
So it's an accurate second order approximation
of the quadratic form.
You get a new covariance matrix.
You have a new Gaussian to sample from,
which tells you where I should draw samples
on the next update, wash, rinse, and repeat.
And it will converge to some local--
there's an additional scheduling and other sort of heuristics
inside there about the path that it takes
given these approximations.
But roughly, it's what we say.
It's a quasi-Newton method that's
trying to use swarms of particles
to estimate the local curvature and move down the hill.
Is that clear?
There's another feature of these algorithms
that I think is important, often sort of mixed in
with this local convergence analysis.
So in a quadratic form, you can really sort of focus in
on the convergence rate.
You can talk about all the things we would like
to talk about with gradient descent
or other optimization algorithms.
You can talk-- it's just converging to a local minima.
If you're in the vicinity of a local minima,
you'd like it to behave roughly like this.
But there's also some sort of global aspect
to the sampling-based algorithms,
some sort of global optimization interpretation.
And this is, I think, harder to appreciate rigorously.
Even in my simple picture, where I've--
if I were to do even the completely deterministic
quadratic approximation of my Hessian
and make a quasi-Newton update, it could be--
if I'm sorry to be a screw over here--
it could be that as I'm walking down here,
I get a quasi-Newton step that jumps me all the way across
and finds this better local minima.
That can absolutely-- it can even
happen with gradient descent if I'm taking big steps.
But it's maybe more likely to happen in a quasi-Newton
algorithm, which is intentionally taking
potentially very big steps.
It could have gotten lucky and gotten here.
That can absolutely happen for the same reason
in the evolutionary algorithms, in the CMA-style algorithms.
But these algorithms, because they're doing samples,
will often have some extra layers of heuristics
that try to add a global aspect to their optimization.
They'll cast off far-ranging samples, maybe, for instance,
and just explore.
It costs little to throw out a few Hail Marys out there
to see if they can find another possible minima.
And so they do tend to have a more global success.
I'd say they can find global optima in a stronger way
than a method that's dedicated itself
to myopically looking at the local curvature.
So there's, I think, a somewhat confusing but important
global optimization aspect to the sample-based planning
algorithms.
And I think there's a big discussion about,
should we be using these algorithms
to do planning with a neural network or whatever?
And I think there's a, why does it work?
I often see people going back and forth
between these kind of justifications,
the parallel execution type of justifications,
the global optimization aspect.
They're all mixed together in some way.
But if you put them all together, this has now
come back into fashion as a good set of algorithms to use.
Just to say that one more possible way,
if I have a gradient descent type algorithm that's
using local gradients, we said that there's--
I'm just trying to be like I'm a vehicle flying
around some obstacles and going from the start to the goal,
or I'm reaching around some obstacle,
and this is the current path that I'm considering,
it seems very unlikely with gradient-based methods
that it'll suddenly find a completely different solution.
That's the same picture.
This is just a geometric version of the same picture,
but in a trajectory optimization sort of case,
you really don't expect gradient descent, any information
over here, to ever tell you to jump over here.
Because at some point, you're going
to do worse for a long time before you get better
and go to the other side.
And I think these algorithms will occasionally
send flyers out there and find an ultimately better solution
in ways that you don't expect your gradient-based methods
to do.
Yeah, of course.
Would you expect an algorithm of this type
to be more robust to--
I'm imagining a case where you are
trying to optimize the policy, and it
finds a very deep but very shallow or very narrow
optimum.
But then if you try to run that on a real robot,
the odds that actually you think that's going to be
[INAUDIBLE]
Would an algorithm like this be more robust
to find an optimum like that?
Awesome question.
So the question was, what if I have these sort of landscapes
that maybe have a small, narrow optimization?
I mean, you could do the same thing where you could have
a narrow local minima that's maybe a trap, for instance.
That's not the one you want to end up in.
I think the case of the good solution being narrow
is one case, and the case of a suboptimal solution being
narrow is another case.
I think these algorithms, they are both
subject to possibly getting stuck there.
In practice, the algorithm is just like a learning rate.
They have a handful of parameters
that control how much exploration
versus how fast they converge and how fast they settle.
And when you feel like your algorithm is getting
stuck in these, you dial up the heat in a sort of entropy
kind of way and try to explore a little bit more.
And you end up finding a balance there.
But that is, again, very problem specific.
Did you have some intuition about whether you'd expect one
to be better or worse than the other?
My intuition is that if you're sampling,
then you're more robust because you have a very narrow value
of good cost.
Yes.
And then sampling around the rim of that
and then ignoring it more.
Right, so I think what could happen
with an algorithm like this, he says,
for the same reason I said, if it's sending out
flyers, maybe if it starts converging
with a local quadratic approximation that's
very narrow in here, then that's where-- at some point,
it will actually get in convergence mode
and try to efficiently-- but if it occasionally throws out
these sort of extra samples, it might
discover that it's made a mistake and jump out.
And I agree with you on that.
But that's going to be subject-- the amount of exploration
versus exploitation it does is subject to these sort
of temperature kind of parameters.
Did you have a question?
Yeah.
Yeah, I was wondering what it was like.
I think I've seen some results that say that it seems to be
[INAUDIBLE]
And so is that just a matter of [INAUDIBLE]
So why is it, for example, using a window or something
like [INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, I think-- so there are many variants of it.
It'd be interesting-- if you have that paper,
if you want to track down the reference,
I'd actually be interested in that.
Yes.
Some of them keep multiple populations around
and can be more explicitly multimodal.
Some of them really do just have more feelers
out there in some sense.
But I think the inner loop CMAES is really
this sort of covariance-- makes local Gaussians
and will shrink into a minimized necessary.
The cross-entropy methods, which are, I think, known to some
of you, are very similar to CMAES.
They make a slightly different-- they
take a slightly different path.
And the way they update their local Hessian approximations
is slightly different.
But these are all very similar algorithms.
So that is a very important first big thing that's
happening, I think, when you give up on the structure in f,
you open the door to these algorithms
making a lot more sense.
And maybe they make sense even if you have structured f,
but you just have a really big GPU.
And that's the way the cost-benefit trade-off falls.
I'm pretty sure I had the Nevergrad list of solvers
here, too.
Nevergrad is a toolbox that just has a bunch of these solvers
implemented, super easy to use in Python.
And it's got a whole list of these sort of optimization
algorithms that are all based on no gradients, hence Nevergrad.
I think it's a very--
I have no qualms recommending this as a tool to play with.
We've used it often.
So I think that's the first sort of major shift in thinking.
Well, I should say one thing we didn't talk about yet
is when I went from the left side of the board
to the right side of the board, I dropped my constraints.
So that is an important thing that I left out.
I think that the structured solvers I've always advocated
using fairly simple objectives and rich constraints.
That's, I think, a much more robust way to sort of live.
[LAUGHS]
I've always said, keep this simple.
In our kinematic optimization, our IK problems, for instance,
I was just saying, just do Q minus desired squared,
something like this.
Keep that simple, and then add all your rich constraints.
Not everybody agrees with me on that,
but I've seen lots of people go down--
so spend a lot of time tuning cost functions
when everything's up in the cost function.
And the constraints are just, I think, a much more--
it's a stronger way to say what you actually require,
and then a lot of the tuning goes away.
Nevergrande explicitly says you can only do--
it's actually better than many sort of sample-based methods.
But it says, we're only going to let
you give us computationally very cheap constraints.
It's like, the method is actually, like,
add cheap constraints to your solver,
because the only thing it will do is do rejection sampling.
So if it's walking around and you give it an x,
it'll just evaluate g.
If it's less than--
if it violates the constraints, it throws that sample out.
That's the only method of constraint reasoning
that these solvers typically do.
And there is not--
these algorithms do not typically
embrace the rich constraints.
You end up playing the game where you say,
I'm going to minimize f of x plus, like,
lambda times g of x, for instance.
I want g of x, maybe minus, or something,
whatever my sign should be.
And you start putting a penalty approximation
of a true constraint.
I guess I do want that to be plus.
And there are good ways to schedule this,
that penalty parameter.
But it becomes a harder game, because really, what you're
doing is something that looks a lot more like this.
And you've got lots of knobs to tune,
and they all kind of compete.
Some people worry a lot about RL not embracing
the full constraint view of the world
and being only in this jam everything
into the cost function.
Some people think it's not a big deal.
I'm somewhere in the middle, I'd say.
Let's talk about, I think, another essential aspect,
which goes together with the black box optimization.
By virtue of feeling like we're going to do sampling anyways,
it's natural to couple that with stochastic formulations
of the optimal control problem.
Yeah, sure.
[INAUDIBLE]
In terms of the black box solvers?
So I'll repeat the question.
So it's certainly true that you can take any optimization
problem here, and I could write that as s f of x less than
or equal to s g of x less than or equal to 0.
You just try to push down on s.
This is a scalar, and then maybe you have to--
so those are equivalent.
But that's putting things more from the objective
down into the constraint, not going the other way, right?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK, so you're not worried about the penalty method.
You're just worried about the basic statement about-- yeah,
yeah.
Yeah, I think these ways do not embrace
what I'm trying to say here.
You can hide your objective, of course, in the constraints.
I mean, this comes down, I think,
to what your solver likes, whether you prefer
to write it like this or prefer to write it like this.
And some solvers do actually really like this.
Many times, they require you to-- a lot of the convex
solvers you know require you to write it like this in order
to write something as a semi-definite--
if you have a quadratic objective
in a semi-definite program, then you
have to do something like this, for instance.
But I think this is more of a--
you could defeat this heuristic by writing constraints
in such a way that you had a very simple cost function,
and you still jammed all your penalties and stuff
in the constraints.
That's not what I mean.
I'm saying, if you don't want to collide with the mug,
say you don't want to collide with the mugs, not say,
well, I'd be kind of sad if I collided a bit with the mug.
I think this is a stronger thing to tell the solver.
That's a good question.
Another really big important thing
is this sort of stochastic formulation of control.
So stochastic optimal control is as old as optimal control.
It's not an RL thing.
But RL has embraced those formulations.
And let me just try to--
I'd say I think this is inspired in RL probably first
by the practical, right?
On a real robot, frankly, I mean,
even if you think of your robot as a black box
that you can set your control parameters,
run an experiment, measure the outcome,
wash, rinse, and repeat, you can never
run the same experiment twice.
I was acutely aware of that during my thesis.
It was very hard to get the same--
the robot to be the same initial conditions.
It was very hard to get repeatable data,
even in the load regime.
This is what experimental science is all about.
I've had a little bit of--
I've had some really, really good collaborators
in experimental fluid dynamics.
And the amount of effort that they
put into making experiments as repeatable as possible.
I can only imagine what the condensed matter
folks do and the like, right?
And the roboticists just don't do that.
You just expect every time I run the robot,
it's going to be different.
My actuator's heated up.
I didn't put it in the same initial conditions.
It stepped on a pebble this time, whatever it is, right?
And I think we've just embraced it in RL more than in most
other cases.
So let's think about what the implication for that is, right?
So how would I write this in the simplest
form of a stochastic optimization?
So I wrote min of x, f of x before.
But now if f of x is some sort of random evaluation,
there's a couple different ways I could write that.
I'll choose to write it like this.
I'll make the randomness explicit.
So w is, for instance, drawn from some random distribution.
It doesn't have to be Gaussian, but let's just say--
make that explicit.
And if w is a random variable and f depends on w,
then my cost is a random variable also.
I need to take the expected value.
I need to take some statistic of that random variable
in order to make a scalar cost.
And this is the one we almost always
choose in stochastic optimal control,
because the expected value plays well with the additive cost
formulations.
And this is very consistent with what
I've said before about the modeling choices in the systems
framework, where we very explicitly--
and throughout robust control, I'd
say you'll see pictures that look like this, where
you have your control inputs coming in here,
and you have an explicit disturbance
port, or something like this.
Disturbance input.
So don't call rand in the middle of your plant dynamics function.
Make it very explicit.
And then you can start thinking about it more carefully
like this.
Stochastic optimal control is a more specific version
of this big picture, where I know
that I have a dynamical system.
So this f is actually a rollout of a long-term dynamical
system.
So stochastic optimal control is just
narrowing in on the stochastic optimization problem, where
I want to maybe minimize over, let's say,
my policy of my controller now of some long-term cost that's
over time.
So I'll just write it out like this.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
And probably I have to choose where
I want the randomness to come in.
There's a couple different choices.
It might be that there's randomness in the dynamics.
We'll see that there's going to be choices we make,
where we might add randomness explicitly to the policy.
But we still have a random disturbance input.
Random noise or disturbance.
And I'll take some expected value over those.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
So there's a lot of work specific in stochastic optimal
control to exploiting this sort of important structure.
But let's start by thinking of it
just as now a stochastic optimization problem.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
I mean, there's lots of places that people put in randomness
in our actual manipulation RL experiments.
So you can name them, I'm sure.
What are the ones you see in all the videos?
Like, what are the crazy things people do to add randomness
to the simulations?
Yeah.
OK, good.
So you get the random disturbances
where you're jamming something.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, right.
So the robot's getting hit from all sides.
I mean, in Boston Dynamics, I guess they actually
do it for real.
Yeah.
I mean, I think the one that I always laugh at
is the domain randomization, where
they will put the most ridiculous patterns
for the vision, for robustness in the perception system.
The fact that you might have an elephant
on the side of your coffee mug or something like that,
or a giraffe or whatever, just cracks me up.
But these can all be interpreted in some squinty way
as adding some sort of randomness, random parameters
to my system.
If I'm allowing w to be an entire rich signal,
it would be fine if it's just a constant.
That would still fit in the class.
OK, so let's think through how it changes the optimization
problem to now have these stochastic objectives.
And as a thought experiment, imagine
I've got some manipuland on the table
here that I'm trying to pick up.
Something on the table here.
I've got my shunk coming down from above.
Let me just consider, so I can plot things,
a very simple policy.
We'll just move straight down to height alpha,
and then close the hand and then lift.
Right?
And let's say that the cost function, or the reward,
is just the height of the center of mass of the object,
manipuland.
What is that going to look like?
[INAUDIBLE]
Maybe if I set my height of my controller too low,
then maybe I have a collision or something down here.
Or maybe I just give a bad score if I
have a collision with the hand.
[WRITING]
And then maybe if I'm too high, the height of the mug
is somewhere over here, let's say I don't get any point.
I don't get any reward, because the center of mass
just stayed where it was.
And somewhere in the middle here,
I've got a plateau where I've made successful contact
with my cylindrical mug, and I lift up.
Just a toy example of a kind of reward function
that we might get when we have manipulation.
We have the possibility of making contact,
of colliding dramatically, of completely missing the object.
You can often get these sort of pretty ugly--
this does not look like these nice pictures
that I showed before.
It's not the kind of landscape you'd
want to do sort of gradient descent on by default.
OK, so this is often not the problem
that we try to formulate in RL.
I'm going to draw giraffes on here and stuff, right?
But I'm also probably going to change the shape of the mug,
maybe change the initial positions of the hand, right?
And that can do good things, right?
So if I ended up with even just a richer shaped object, right?
Maybe it's a-- I don't know what that is, a chalice, right?
Then maybe I've got a slightly better cost function.
Maybe I'm still in collision for a bunch of the time,
but maybe there's some interesting times
where I can grasp successfully.
I fail in the middle.
I grasp-- I don't know.
I could get something by just having a more interesting
object.
I could potentially have more interesting cost functions,
OK?
But that doesn't sort of defeat the problem of if I just
airball, I've got nothing going on here.
Having lots of samples down here,
that's just not going to give me any gradient information
to base my search on.
I've got lots of samples over here.
I've got nothing good to do.
OK, so it's very interesting to think that-- I mean,
you might think that if you're asking
the same robot, the same policy, to pick up
a whole variety of objects, that that would be a harder
optimization problem.
I would think that, right?
That sounds like a harder optimization problem.
Tune a robot to pick up a single object versus pick up
an entire category of objects.
You'd think that would be a bigger ask.
But in sort of a gradient optimization landscape way,
it can actually make things better, right?
So imagine now that just I have a variety of different-- well,
let me even go back to an even simpler example here.
So the characteristic I care about here
is these rough discontinuities, right?
So what about if I just bottle that up
and think about a very simple case of this?
If I'm just trying to minimize some discontinuous function.
This is a function that is 1 if x is greater than 0,
negative 1 if x is less than 0.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
That's a nasty optimization problem for gradients, right?
It's also a boring one because I guess
there's a lot of uniquely good answers.
But just if we think about its gradient-based properties.
Randomness can make these problems better.
OK, so let's think of a small variation on that,
where I want to say min over x now.
And I'll add noise in sort of the way
I've indicated above here.
Let's just say we'll do it like this.
What does that optimization do?
OK.
What does that optimization look like?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
So what is your intuition for why that is?
Because the bigger x is, the smaller w
has to be for the sine of x plus w to be possible.
So it should be increasing x.
OK.
So the bigger x is, then this can get smaller.
So maybe if I were to plot this, somehow this
might be my probability of x plus w.
Yeah.
And so you're saying that as I make x bigger,
then I'm going to get more of my Gaussian on there.
And that's exactly the right picture.
So what I'll get, I think, I know,
is actually a beautiful sort of smooth version
of that original function.
That Gaussian-- you can think of this Gaussian
as actually acting as a smoothing function that
goes over your cost landscape and smooths things out.
OK.
And gradient descent here has a much better chance
of doing something interesting.
What's super interesting is that I
think a lot of the domain randomization
that we're doing in RL is having a similar effect on the cost
landscapes that we're generating.
So there's a more general interpretation of these ideas.
In stochastic optimization, there's
a field of randomized smoothing.
OK.
And in fact, many ways that you would
choose to add noise to your simulation,
or to your policy, or whatever--
a lot of different choices of w will have this interpretation
that it'll take potentially a complicated landscape.
I've got a fun one plotted up here from Terry, actually.
OK.
This is just a--
Terry's way of thinking about this was he's
trying to throw a ball over a wall.
OK.
And he's trying to maximize the distance,
the final distance of the ball.
And the only control decision to make
is sort of the angle at which you throw.
OK.
And for some small angles, you'll just land smoothly.
And you'll get better and better scores, less cost here.
At some point, you'll run into the wall.
All of these angles have exactly the same cost.
And then suddenly, you're over the wall.
So you drop down.
45 is sort of the optimal solution,
is to throw it 45 degrees.
At some point, you throw too steeply,
and you actually hit the wall again, because you went up
and on the way down.
But if you were to just add some randomness--
so if you took the policy parameters,
and you say, I'm going to throw the ball at theta,
plus or minus some Gaussian.
So every time I throw it, I'll just throw it
at theta plus some Gaussian.
And I'll take the expected value of that cost instead.
Then for sort of arbitrarily complicated landscapes,
you end up with things that look much more
amenable to gradient descent.
And I think this is an essential part
of what's making policy-based, gradient-based methods work
in RL.
OK, I've talked too slowly, I guess.
I'm sorry.
But let me see if I can at least indicate
one other important idea.
So I think those are maybe the two I really
wanted to land first.
One is that we're switched to black box optimization.
The second is that I think these stochastic formulations
really affect the success of a gradient-based method.
All right, let me just tell you what policy gradient is
in a way that Abhishek can build on here.
So policy gradient in RL is not quite black box optimization.
So imagine I have a function.
Imagine I'm trying to do this, minimize over x, f of x.
I'll leave the randomness out for just a moment
just to make this point simple.
Imagine I have a nested function.
I have two parts of my system, two parts of the cost
function.
Let's say this is something that is known,
and I know partial g, partial x.
So I have gradients on the inside.
And this is unknown, black box.
[WRITING]
OK, so not surprisingly, this is going to be my policy.
This is going to be my neural network.
[WRITING]
And this could be my dynamics and cost function.
There's a lot of parameters in a neural network.
You probably don't want to just randomly check
all the parameters of a neural network.
Well, we can talk about when you do
and when you don't want to do.
It's viable.
But it seems like you'd like to leverage the fact
that at least part of my gradients are known.
And this is the key idea in the policy gradient algorithms,
basically is to, instead of adding--
so there would be two approaches I
could do if I wanted to do the random version of this.
[WRITING]
I could try to minimize something like this.
I could add noise directly.
[WRITING]
Or I can add noise to the output of my neural network,
let's say.
[WRITING]
And if you do this second version, in both cases,
there's an interpretation where if x plus w was better than x,
then I would like to make x plus w more
likely to happen in the future.
That's the basic gradient descent sort of story.
If x plus w was better, make it more likely to happen.
In this case, you say I've got a neural network outputting
y equals g of x.
[WRITING]
If y plus w was better, I'd like to make y plus w more likely
to happen in the future.
And I can do that by using gradient descent on g.
So the policy gradient suite of algorithms in RL
is basically a combination of the black box optimization,
which is leveraging the gradient of just the policy,
hence the name.
It's often, I think, misused.
The word policy gradient is often misused.
But I think that, in my mind, that's the key idea,
is that you take the gradient of your policy,
the true gradient of your policy,
and you combine it with a noisy approximate gradient
from sampling for the part you don't know.
And you're actually-- I don't feel too bad.
I think we've got a problem on the problem set that
will help you explore the details of that
with enough instructions that it'll be OK.
But this is sort of the key idea in policy gradient.
You can imagine, if you have the additive structure
from stochastic optimal control, then you
can even be smarter about taking gradients
through the serial chain and leverage
the structure of the optimal control problem.
And the more advanced algorithms in RL do that.
That was a super-- it was like the three-minute version
of a complicated topic.
But is that OK?
At that level, does it make sense?
Yeah?
OK.
Good.
So I will see many of you in face-to-face this week.
Those of you that I'm going to meet in a few minutes,
I'm happy to-- I'm happy, in general, to meet in person.
It's just there's a logistical problem
of getting to the offices and stuff like that.
But most of you, I guess, I'll see on Zoom, just for logistics.