[SIDE CONVERSATION]
You guys ready to go?
Everything's good, right?
Already been going, I guess.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah, sure.
OK, welcome back, everybody.
So last time, we started doing perception.
We started the more geometric perception.
It connects, I think, nicely with the kinematics work
we had been doing, just thinking about the motion of the robot.
And I want to continue that today,
with the major theme being we're going to do estimation
and think a lot more about the consequences of having
very messy point clouds.
Now, there's a couple topics that I wanted--
there's lots of things to possibly say or know.
But I wanted, instead of listing all of them,
which I think the notes can be better about being a little bit
more encyclopedic, I want to go in a little bit deeper
and talk about a few cases that I think stand out
and are worthy of some attention here.
And I hope it will not only continue
thinking about geometry and perception,
but also it's going to dig a little deeper in the way
we're using optimization.
So this whole connection--
I know I've only introduced optimization
through a couple of pictures and examples,
but I'm hoping that I can continue
to build on that with build your intuition by working
through some of these examples and showing you how
powerful that framework can be.
So I'll start up on the slides here.
So remember that we started-- the setup
was we're using the soon-to-be-extinct D415
cameras, awesome cameras.
They've been a workhorse for robotics.
And we are simulating those cameras with basically
a rendering pipeline, where we've added our RGBD sensor,
so color and depth sensor.
And we're getting out images that
are of color image and a depth image that are the same size.
We can transform that into a point cloud.
And last time, what we started talking about
was the iterative closest point algorithm,
which we're going to build on today.
That was the foundation.
So roughly speaking, it looks like this.
So I've made a random shape.
I put it in original pose and some perturbed pose.
The blue is the model.
The red is the scene.
And the algorithm-- I mean, it's actually kind of worthwhile,
I think, to watch it and step through it
and see the choices it makes because
of that simple heuristic of distance.
But oftentimes, it will converge to something reasonable.
I also put in a few examples in the notes where it does not
converge to something reasonable.
It does something pretty ridiculous.
And that can be pretty frustrating
when you're trying to pick up a mug or something in the sink.
But this is the workhorse that we're going to start with.
Let me remind you of the basic equations there.
So it's iterative because we're alternating
between two different optimization problems.
In one of them, we assume the correspondences are known.
We optimize over a position and orientation
where this is actually a 3 by 3 matrix.
And we had to put in these extra constraints that--
so that was given the correspondences.
We did that.
And the other part of the algorithm
was given my guess at the pose, I
reconstruct by searching over possible correspondences.
And this one, since r is given, doesn't have those constraints.
This is just a distance, minimum distance problem.
It has good algorithms.
So it's important for today's conversation
to realize that this problem, when the correspondences are
given, we've decided that it has a good solution.
It has a globally optimal solution.
We showed you the pictures of that quadratic bowl.
This solution, once the correspondences are given,
it will find you the best p and r.
No worries about local minima or anything like this.
It will find the optimal p and r that minimizes this equation.
So that's an oracle that we can go to,
and we will go to, to ask, what was
the answer to this problem?
And separately, we can, either through brute force search
or clever nearest neighbor algorithms,
just search over all possible correspondences
and find, given the current pose,
what is the best correspondence?
What is the minimum distance?
So that we can also solve globally,
and we can do it efficiently with good data structures.
So we're going to alternate between two algorithms that
are independently global, but that alternation
can cause local minima.
So the problems where it gets stuck
and gets in this frustrating bad estimate of the solution,
alternating between two global solvers
does not mean that you're solving the joint problem
globally.
Yeah?
Are there known shape cases that are
harder than others, like stars versus compact bodies?
I haven't seen it broken in terms of shape.
It's possible that there's a dichotomy there.
But I think you can think about the global optima as--
basically, we're going to see a few of them do outliers.
But once you get a bad set of correspondences,
it doesn't take a star pattern or something.
You can get caught in the corner of a cube just fine
and get yourself pretty stuck.
I think it's highly dependent on both the shape
and the guess of the pose and the number of points
and all these different things.
I don't think it's as simple as that.
Now, it's interesting.
Oh, see.
Yeah, please.
I just want to confirm the objective functions.
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh my goodness.
I wrote subtract.
Thank you.
I appreciate you catching that.
Yeah, you definitely want to--
this is the points projected into the world frame.
This is the other point, so that we
want the distance between them.
Thank you for catching that.
Good, good.
OK, I mean, I want you to know that this is a general--
this is a common strategy in optimization.
When you have a problem that is non-convex,
but you can lock a few variables in and solve different pieces
of it optimally, these alternation strategies,
they come up over and over again.
You see them in bilinear optimization.
You see them-- if you've heard about the EM algorithm,
expectation maximization, that's an instance of this.
These are all the same kind of thing, where you're breaking up
a problem that is non-convex into two convex problems,
and you alternate.
But it can get stuck in local minima,
because the two halves are convex
is not enough to solve the original problem jointly.
OK, so yes, thank you for catching that.
Another good question that Jared asked at the end of class
last time was, sometimes I've written the model points here
and the scene points here in the notes
I have written in the other case.
So I think a question that I'd like to address here
is, do we want the model to match the scene points,
or the scene to match the model points?
If we're going to figure out correspondences,
which one's better?
Should we find for every model point a scene point
that it corresponds to?
Should we find for every scene point a model
And I think the complexity there starts
to reveal some of the challenges in the real problem.
And I made some pictures.
So there's a couple of things that--
the real point clouds are messy.
They're messy in terms of having dropouts.
They're messy in terms of having outliers.
Remember, this video was just showing the lumpiness.
So these things are messy.
And if you wanted to run ICP to find a LEGO block or a piece
of carrot or something, this is not
the picture I had drawn with the simple shape in 2D before.
It's a much messier proposition.
So there's outliers and noise.
And the other big thing that we saw
is that there's partial views, the fact
that the camera looking from one side
is only going to see half your object at best.
You can put multiple cameras, but still you're
never going to see the bottom of the object
if it's sitting on the table unless you pick it up.
So if you start with a CAD model, which
has points all over the geometry,
and you try to find--
correspond every model point to a scene point,
what's the problem with the model points to scene points?
This is-- the potential problem with this is partial views.
So if you have only half of your mustard generating the point
cloud, and you have model points for all of your mustard,
if you ask every one of your model points
to correspond to some scene point,
then you're asking for it to correspond to things
that just don't exist.
And that's going to pull it backwards.
It's going to try to pull your estimate
into the wrong location.
Is that clear?
OK.
So you think, OK, let's do scene to model.
But that has problems too.
OK.
That has problems-- more problems with the outliers.
OK, this is actually-- let me finish the partial view.
So this is a partial view case, right, where I just made that.
So this is actually solving the scene points to model.
It happens to get caught in a local minima this time.
But scene to model can do better with the partial views, right,
if I only take my scene points and try
to capture the model points.
That seems natural.
The problem with scene to model is outliers.
OK.
[WRITING]
One of the problems, right?
So I've taken my blue perfect scene points,
and I've just added three random outliers.
I got a speck of light or a speck of dust in the air,
happened to catch a return.
I've got a random point in the middle of the air.
It happens, right?
Now, those are still going to match
if I'm asking all of my scene points
to connect to some model point, right?
Then this, even when it wants to get close,
it's still getting pulled towards these points
because they're all trying to find their match.
OK.
So both of these problems have potential pitfalls.
Both of them have possible solutions.
But I think one of the things that could fix either of these
is if we had some way of identifying outliers
and ejecting them from the data set, right?
[WRITING]
And I hope you're already thinking about some reasonable
heuristics for that, right?
If the distance is too big, I can just crop it.
There's a bunch of things that we can go through.
But before we completely solve the problem,
let's try to make a little bit more understanding
about this sort of decision.
There is actually one thing.
I think in both of those cases, if you have partial views
and you can reject outliers, then you
can reject the model points that were
on the back of a mustard bottle, right?
If you have actual outliers and you have the ability
to pull them from the data set, then I
think this can work too.
Both of those can be made more robust
if you have some algorithm for removing the non-matches.
But there are more subtle reasons maybe
to prefer one or the other.
I tend to prefer finding scene to model
because I particularly like a generalization
of the point-to-point correspondence, which
is point-to-mesh correspondence.
And it's worth, I think, writing that down.
So presumably, your CAD model-- it's kind of weird, right,
that we started off-- we have this nice CAD model.
You think that's something I've got,
like a nice triangular mesh, for instance.
And I'm going to start by sampling points on it.
And then I'm treating it as a point registration.
That always felt weird to me, right?
There's applications where maybe you actually had a point.
But I don't know.
In my world, you start with a CAD model probably.
And you're going to go from there.
So let's say our model was not a set of points,
but maybe a triangular mesh, one of our other 3D
representations, 3D geometry representations.
Typically, a triangular mesh, you
end up with a list of vertices, not so different than a point
cloud, but a list of x, y, z locations in space.
They could be sparse now instead of a dense point cloud.
And then you have a list of faces
where each face has indices into the vertices.
Let me write vertex indices.
So if I have a triangular mesh and a bunch of triangles
building up my geometry, then these might just be--
for every face, I have three integers that reference
the big list of vertices.
And if you look at an OBJ file or an SDL file or whatever,
that's basically what's inside there, is those two lists.
Sometimes some normal information,
but that's a big part of it.
So just to spell it out here, let's
say I've got everything in 2D for now.
So maybe my vertices could be negative 1.5, 1.5.
Got a box of size 3, let's say.
So this is maybe my vertex 0, I guess.
And then I made this one 1, 2, 3.
And then these are my vertices.
And then my faces in 2D would just be a list.
I'm saying, oh, I've got a face that goes from 0 to 1.
I've got another one that goes from 0 to 2.
I've got one that goes from 1 to 3.
I've got one that goes from 2 to 3.
What I'd like to do--
this is a different representation
than what we did before, where we had--
somehow, if we had a big box, we somehow
wanted to sample points all over the place
with some dense geometry.
I would like to solve a better problem, I think.
If I have a point here that I'm trying
to register with the CAD model, I
don't want to find the closest random sample point on this.
I want to just do the distance to the actual face.
It seems it would be way better if we could do that.
So you should start thinking about,
how would I write the point to a plane or point to a face,
even, because a face is actually not a full plane.
It's a segment.
And I hope you're thinking in your head, OK, well, I know--
I can write the equation of a plane as somehow a linear
equation.
We would define a plane.
So maybe I can use that.
And you actually can use that.
You can derive things.
You can think about taking dot products of the normal vector.
And there's a bunch of geometry that you can do.
And they will get you various different formulations.
But there's a really slick way, now
that we're in the land of optimization,
that I think is worth you appreciating.
So how can I say--
I guess the first observation here
is that I can talk about the element.
I can define the set of points that are inside here
by writing some element, p, if I want to position p.
And I want to parameterize all of the positions that
are inside that face.
I can do that.
This is any face or a triangular face is a convex set.
So I can do that by just making an affine combination
of the vertices.
So if I take a sum of the vertices,
let's say alpha i vertex i.
Let me say p of vertex i.
And I say that all the i's alphas are greater than 1.
And sum of the alphas equals 1.
Then in the case, this would be, let's say,
inside some face f, all the vertices inside some face f.
So in this case, it would really just be alpha times this
plus alpha times this.
And if the sum of them has to equal 1,
then I would parameterize.
If I change my alpha 0 from being 1 and the other one being
0 to this one being 1 and the other one being 0,
I'm just going to walk along that face.
And that's true in higher dimensions, too.
If you have any convex polytope, you
can write a member of that convex polytope
by an affine combination of its vertices.
So why is that so useful?
Well, we're leaning more and more
on the power of optimization.
The game in optimization, the reason
we liked this sort of objective was
that that term, the inside of this,
is linear in the decision variables.
Therefore, when I take a squared,
it's quadratic in the decision variables, which
made it was convex in those decision variables.
So if I'm going to add any excitement to this,
any new things to this, I'd like to do it
in a way that is linear in the decision
variables on the inside, so it's quadratic for the whole thing.
You see where this is going?
So what if I do this for each of those points?
I'd like to say-- I guess I've got to flip my-- minus.
Now I'm going to do sum over j, alpha j, p of m,
j in the face that I know to be correspondent to.
Get that right?
So I'm going to do for all of my scene points,
i, I'm going to look up the face.
This time, my correspondence that I've given--
this is given correspondence.
I'll say fi, let's say.
Given correspondences fi.
I can just add in this alpha in a way that's
linear in the objective here.
I still have my more nasty constraints,
but I can do the same tricks I did before now
and actually solve in closed form for p and alpha
and r using my SPD trick.
So this is pretty slick, I would say.
Now you can have a much sparser representation.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, sorry, sorry.
Yes.
Oh, you're right.
So that makes it harder to do the SPD.
Alpha i and sum over i, i.
Yes, you do have to deal with those.
Right.
So yeah, you're right.
I misspoke when I said you can just call it the SPD
because you have to take those into account at the same time.
OK, but that's beautiful and good.
And now I can get closest point to a plane instead--
or to a face instead of point to point.
And I think it's so useful that that's maybe one thing
to break the tie between scene to model versus model to scene.
Is that good?
I'm hoping that you'll get increasingly
flexible with this sort of way of thinking about optimization
is that we can carve out these optimization problems
and doing a little extra work to sort of find the right way
to add your parameters into the model
can make a huge difference to the optimization landscape.
It's like if you make good choices here,
you are fundamentally reforming the landscape from something
that could be very non-convex to something that's non-convex
and an easy optimization to solve.
That is, I think, deep networks work so well that people
tend to not think about these kind of things as much anymore.
But it's still, even for deep networks,
if you make your landscape better,
it's going to work a lot better.
So make good choices.
I think that's the takeaway.
OK, so let's think about how do we reject outliers.
And let me distinguish between two cases.
One I would say is the easy case, which
would be inside the ICP loop where we've
got a pretty good solution, and we're just
trying to refine it.
We're kind of like in the last stages of convergence,
and we don't want these distant points to be screwing up
my optimization.
I would say good pose estimate near convergence.
And there's various heuristics that we'll use for that.
So for instance, let's say if I do my distance calculation
and the distance is greater than 3 centimeters,
I'll say just pick some threshold and distance.
And anything beyond some distance threshold
is just left as an outlier.
Threshold maximum distance.
There's another one that we put on the--
think about on your p-set, threshold
the number of inliers.
So is that language clear?
So if you have an optimization problem,
you're trying to fit all these points,
we're going to call the inliers the ones that
are agreeing with my model, and the outliers
the ones that are not agreeing with my model.
And we're trying to separate the inliers from the outliers.
So it might be that if you know a priori that you expect
to have exactly 10 points, then taking the 10 closest ones
could be a good one.
And that'll be something you'll look at in the p-set.
OK, but let's contrast that with the harder case, which
I think I put in the next slide here.
Yeah, so let's say I'm just looking
at some complicated scene, and I've
got a CAD model or a point cloud model of a drill.
And I'm trying to solve this much more global problem
of saying, find me the points that
match my drill in this scene that
has points all over the place.
And some of them are drill-ish shapes, but not a drill.
And you've got to find-- this is the more global registration
problem.
This global point registration problem, I think,
requires different tools.
You can't just somehow threshold max distance,
because you might not even latch on.
It might be that your initial guess, the max distance just
rules out the drill right away, and you'll never find it.
So there's a series of different ideas--
I'll tell you one or two of them in more detail--
that try to address this more global problem.
I'm OK going back and forth with these two.
[END PLAYBACK]
Do people know various ideas in this vein?
Anybody want to throw some buzzwords out?
What would you think of if you're
trying to search for the needle in the haystack here?
You've got a big point cloud, a little model.
You're trying to find the model in the point cloud.
What would you do?
Segmentation, awesome.
So in fact, the coloring there is
an example of a segmentation.
And these days, I think you're absolutely right.
The first thing I would do, I would train a deep network
to do some initial segmentation.
Nowadays, you can download deep networks
that are pre-trained, that you point them
at your environment, you're going
to get a fairly good segmentation right out
of the box.
But typically, you would try to throw
in some of the specific objects you're trying to segment
and at least fine tune a deep network model, which
we'll do in a few weeks.
So having an initial segmentation--
and I should say that there are geometric algorithms
for segmentation too.
Those have mostly been eclipsed, I would say.
I would say most of the time now,
it's deep networks for segmentation
for that part of the program.
What else would you do?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Awesome.
Good.
So just take some random crops.
Maybe take a bunch of random crops of the scene
and check those random crops.
I think that's a really good--
both of those are very good suggestions.
So I think the way you said it was very good.
You said that-- I mean, because we have our points in 3D,
we know that the points we're looking for
are localized in 3D.
We could use our geometric intuition to take subsamples.
There's a more generic way that people do this,
of this random subsampling.
If you just have a random data set,
you don't have that same geometric intuition,
then you might just take that data set
and just at random pick some subset of the pixels.
And that is called RANSAC.
That is-- which would be random sample consensus.
It's typically done-- it's a general tool for regression
given outliers, where you can sample a subset of your data,
try to fit everything that's an outlier you discard,
and then you just do that initial sample a bunch of times
and take the best one.
It's an algorithm that has some theoretical guarantees,
but they're only probabilistic.
It's like, if you sample enough times,
you will eventually get lucky and sample the right thing.
So these are probabilistic type algorithms.
They can be useful.
We're going to have you implement a simple RANSAC
algorithm for the problem set.
But I think your observation about it being geometric
is often not discussed in the generic RANSAC literature,
but very relevant here.
And I'm going to list one more, which I particularly like.
I think it's particularly clever for the--
and I think uses our understanding of geometry
with our optimization.
And that's the pairwise distance ideas.
So what do I mean by that?
So the pairwise distance between points
is a-- the pairwise distance is invariant to translation
and rotation.
OK.
So let me just make a super simple example here.
I'll do my-- my daughter's doing 3, 4, 5 triangles at home,
so I'll do a 3, 4, 5 triangle.
We've got nice numbers.
OK, so let's say I've got points just in the corners to start,
although I think that's artificial
and we'll fix it in a minute.
So the distance between those two points is 4, 3, 5.
Every distance here for every pair of points
is either 3, 4, or 5.
If I take another--
if I just change the pose of that,
I could perturb it arbitrarily in translation and rotation.
If I compute the distances in that new point cloud,
the distances are still going to be only 3, 4, or 5.
OK, so it's kind of cool if you're
willing to take a relative measurement between just--
that's a distance relative to the points,
then that actually metric doesn't--
you can-- it's completely invariant to pose.
So before I have any estimate of my pose,
I can just look at the pairwise distances
and start asking, is that a pairwise distance that could
possibly exist in my model?
If it's not, I can possibly reject it.
So if I have now this setting where
I have a bunch of point measurements,
it's potentially an expensive sounding approach.
But I'll take pairwise distances from every possible pair.
For every possible point, I'll take every possible pair.
And in this case, I'll just check.
Is it 3, 4, or 5?
If the number is not 3, 4, or 5, what does that tell you?
That tells you that if this edge is not 3, 4, or 5,
that tells you that one of those two points
must not be in the mesh.
It could be that one of them is, but the other one's not.
OK, so there's various ways to leverage that.
The one I like that I'll show you now-- anybody here
working with Luca Carlone?
Luca and Hank and folks have been
working on an algorithm called Teaser, which
has a piece of it that leverages this idea.
It's actually, I guess I should--
I've got some other collaborators too.
They're at MIT.
OK, so they actually recommend-- so you can immediately
rule out some points if a point does not
have any edges that could make it feasible.
Then you can just remove that point immediately.
But you can do more aggressive pruning
by actually looking at the whole graph that gets constructed out
of these things.
So let me try to say that carefully.
So if Psi minus Psj squared--
I'm going to just use my cartoon here.
It's either 3, 4, or 5.
Then we'll add an edge.
If Pij is not one of those things, we won't add an edge.
So if I have k over here and it wasn't part of that,
then I won't add an edge.
So I'll have a bunch of points out there.
Some of them have edges.
Some of them don't have edges.
If I have anybody that's not fully connected,
then we know it's an outlier.
So if I have something like this,
I better be fully connected.
This guy happens to be 5 away from something.
But because it's missing the other pairwise distances,
it can't possibly be an element of my object.
So the expensive version of this,
in an NP-hard kind of sense, is to try to find the largest
clique of the graph.
Now, depending on exactly what your point cloud looks like,
they talk about in the paper actually using max clique.
I think, depending on the numbers of points flying
around, that's a hard argument to make.
But let's look for large cliques in the graph.
Now, that is a computationally hard problem.
But there are approximations that
can find at least-- allow us to discard
large numbers of points that don't exist in a clique
over some size, for instance.
OK.
Kind of a neat idea, right?
Without having any notion of the pose whatsoever,
or the position, I can just look at pairs of points
and reject a bunch of things that couldn't possibly match.
Now, I actually don't fully know.
My mind is not made up about how powerful this is in practice.
Luca, I think, is extremely positive about it.
I think-- and I believe him.
I think he's-- so, you know.
But here's the question I have, right?
So I think I have-- there's no doubt in my mind
that if you have an existing point
cloud, like a perfect point cloud,
you perturb that point cloud with its exact 3, 4, 5
kind of numbers, and you add a bunch of outliers,
and you try to recover it, I think
it would work extremely well in that case.
If I have a box, and I'm approximating it
with whatever returns I get, and I'm
going to have all kinds of distances that are like--
anything, it could be--
I could have-- this is the case I'm worried about,
is that I've got my nice box, but I'm actually
getting sample returns like this, right?
So in some sense, the only thing I really know
is that my-- I kind of know it's going to be less than 5,
but probably it's going to be greater
than my minimum resolution of my camera and less than 5.
So if you have this weaker version, where you can't
really expect these to match perfectly,
or some noise threshold or whatever, I just don't know.
I mean, how far--
I mean, we've run the algorithm.
I've seen some results.
But I think this would be a great project.
This would be a great final project,
would be to dig in and understand,
in the same teaser, in some of these kind of settings,
how effective is that clique reduction for real--
for point clouds that come out of simulation,
where you just throw a CAD model in?
That's a great question.
What do you think?
[INAUDIBLE]
Like, can you even expect a pairwise [INAUDIBLE]
sort of similar in the first camera world
or in the model world?
Like, what if it's like scaled faster?
[INAUDIBLE]
Awesome.
OK, so the question was about the camera world
and the original world might have other artifacts.
I mean, the camera might have a little bit of distortion.
There could be some scaling effects.
Scaling actually can be treated very nicely
in the same kind of way.
So there are similarly metrics.
There are things like the pairwise distance effects,
just take the squared away, that you can figure out
the scale without solving for the translation and rotation
using similar ideas.
Scale, they address nicely in the teaser paper, for instance.
Distortions and things like that,
I think you've got to just calibrate your camera.
That one's going to be bad.
Do something to get rid of that, because that's always
going to screw things up.
But you're right that those do exist,
and they can affect your point clouds,
especially if you have like a--
people will knock into your camera,
or your robot ran into a wall, and now it's
camera's a little bit off or whatever.
These things really do happen.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Awesome.
So let me repeat the question.
So what if I had an occlusion?
Somehow this box was in front of me,
so I didn't get all these points.
I just got the partial view.
So if my camera is over here, I might have only
gotten these views, but not the ones
that were occluded by that box.
So I think this step is robust to that, in my mind.
It would basically-- so this is only excluding outliers.
So it's not going to--
in the later step, you've got just your inliers,
and you're going to do your pose estimation.
Now you have less points to do your pose estimation.
But I don't think this step would falsely
discard any points.
There might be-- you'll get some returns maybe on this front box.
If they don't match any of the expected distances,
they might even be discarded in a nice way.
But I would think the hazard there
is just that you have less points left,
rather than this would discard them artificially.
Yeah?
How many points do you expect to have [INAUDIBLE]??
That's a super good question.
So the question was, how many points do we expect to have?
So I think some of the initial point registration literature,
it was not that many points.
And then there's people that are trying
to apply it to big, raw point clouds that are coming straight
off the camera.
And I think some of the algorithms will scale to that.
Oftentimes, hidden inside the algorithm,
you'll see a subsampling step, where they're actually
using a small subset of the dense clouds.
And that can work.
In fact, I think the teaser picture I have here--
by the way, everybody uses that bunny.
Every paper I was looking at today,
there's at least one picture with a Stanford bunny.
So I'm going to have a series of pictures from bunnies here.
Oh, I didn't pick the one that had the--
did I?
No, I didn't pick the one that had this.
But oftentimes, if your algorithm
can't cope with the fully dense, then you'll just subsample.
And it tends to be fewer than you might think.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
If there's a lot of pairs of points,
then you can basically expect the distances
to have to be somewhat filling an entire range of what
the minimum distance is in the maximum distance.
And then if you also have some sort of [INAUDIBLE]
in terms of your period, then it's
basically any pairs of points that are within the certain
minimax are going to be [INAUDIBLE]
The question is, if you start having dense point clouds,
then don't you have pairs of points that are arbitrarily
close?
Yeah, so I think this is like noise floor almost zero.
This is what I worry about, is that if it really only tells me
a maximum distance, then it could
match the drill and the bucket and the whatever.
Everything that's roughly drill-sized could match.
And if you have a dense, cluttered scene
of similar objects, I would guess this heuristic
doesn't buy you as much.
It might form multiple cliques that
are all reasonable things to start searching for.
And that would be interesting to explore.
But I think as a global metric to find the biggest clique
or whatever, I feel like it's not as popular.
That would be my understanding without having
explored it deeply, waiting for someone's project to do it,
let's say.
Yes, Joe?
For the messy version of the algorithm,
is it productive to think about this
as like you have some sort of empirical probability
distribution on [INAUDIBLE] and you're
trying to match that by combining some [INAUDIBLE]
or is that a non-good [INAUDIBLE]??
Oh, I think that's probably an excellent way
to think about it.
So his question was, is there maybe a probabilistic way
to think about this, that you have some distribution
of possible pairwise distances, and you're trying to--
even the-- you'd like the statistics
of that distribution, for instance,
I think is what you're getting at to match your--
so I think that's an excellent way to think about that.
So this clique idea would be like a brute force version
of that.
And I think the probabilistic version would probably
be a softer statistical version of that, which
could be a very nice relaxation to make these NP-hard problems
less NP-hard.
So the idea of pairwise distances
has been around for a long time.
And there's lots of papers and computer graphics and the like
that have used it.
I'm guessing people have looked at it from that lens.
I can't think of one off the top of my head,
but I'm guessing that's--
so Justin Solomon teaches a great course
on computational geometry.
And he's done a lot of work in this over the last 10 years
or so.
But that's a great idea.
In fact, it leads in nicely to the next thing.
So let me just make sure that the story arc of the lectures
is good, right?
So we talked about more messy point clouds, the scene
versus model and the point to mesh.
And then we started talking about,
how do we actually reject outliers?
And in the hard case, pairwise distance
is a nice example of a geometrically inspired algorithm
that can do this.
And it's one of many examples, but it's one I think
is particularly insightful.
OK, but I think there's another way
to be more robust to messy point clouds, which
is to relax a little bit.
And not so different from Charles's question there
is to relax a little bit this super rigid notion
of correspondence.
Like this point corresponds to this point, period, right?
And it does not correspond to anything else or whatever.
So how do we slightly relax that notion of correspondence?
And how do we continue to flex our little optimization
toolkit?
So let's think about how do we generalize and make
softer versions of the correspondence.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
So far-- let me just use the shorthand here.
We've done P of O, M, or P i.
I guess I should have made one point early on, right?
So if I do switch this to be M and this to be S,
if I do switch this, that's not a big deal, right?
But what is it geometrically?
So algebraically, it doesn't look like a big deal.
I just move my decision variables
over to this side of the equation.
The math should still work, right?
What does it correspond to in terms of my frames?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
You get the inverse frame, right?
So geometrically, the version I've written here
is I'm taking my scene points and trying to--
sorry, I'm taking my model points
and trying to put them in world coordinates
so they match the scene points.
If I were to put the x over here, what I'm trying to do
is I'm trying to take my scene points
and warp them into my model coordinates.
So the difference is am I going--
am I trying to solve xow or am I trying to solve--
I said ow thinking that way, but yeah.
It's just the difference of which frame
you're doing the matching in.
And it doesn't matter.
You can do it in the object coordinates
or you can do it in the world coordinates.
So either one of those is OK.
But so far, our correspondence has entered the equations here,
right?
And that's a pretty limited way.
There's like-- that's just an integer
in an index of the data I'm putting into this equation.
There's not a way for me to make that less integer, right?
The way it's written right now.
So because this means that ci has to be j and only j and not
something else.
So let's write a different version
of this optimization that's just a little bit more flexible.
And then we can soften things, right?
So let's make a correspondence matrix where ci, j--
if we want to write the exact same rigid correspondence,
we could do something like this, right?
We say ci, j is 1 if i corresponds to j or 0 otherwise.
And then if I were to write this same objective as--
I mean, this I should have be--
this way I was summing over just the i's before.
Now I'll sum over both i and j.
I'll do my same objective now.
But I'll turn off all the ones that don't correspond.
I'll just multiply by 0 all the ones
that I don't consider to be corresponding.
Do we agree that algebraically or mathematically
that's the same as this?
This one, though, as you can see,
we could start being more flexible with our decision
about what's corresponding.
I could have some points that are--
I could have entire rows or columns of j
that are completely 0 if I want to have something that doesn't
correspond to anything.
Or I could even have multiple points from my model
correspond to my scene, or multiple points in my scene
correspond to my model.
There's just a lot more flexibility there.
I can also allow partial correspondences.
I could say that model point i kind of corresponds
with scene point j.
I could set c to be 0.5 or something, or 0.2.
So I can relax this hard constraint
to be-- let's say it doesn't even really
have to stay inside 1, but let's just say it stays inside there.
Similarly, only match model only matches one scene.
This looks like a constraint, like the sum over--
corresponds to-- depends on what I wrote here.
So if I say model j only corresponds to one scene,
so this would be sum over i, or model sum over i.
And if I wanted to say that the scene sum only matches
one model, I could put a constraint saying
that the sum of over j had to equal 1,
just the columns and rows of that.
But this is a pretty flexible representation.
I could add constraints to that if I
want to impose more rigid matching.
OK, so the same way that ICP goes through and tries
to compute the correspondences in an outer loop,
there's another well-known algorithm
called coherent point drift, CPD, which,
given my guess of my pose, will go through and compute
kind of a softer distance to compute these Cij's,
hold them constant, solve the x, same way we did before.
And then given x, solve for my Cij's,
but using just a softer version of that that gives me
values between 0 and 1.
OK.
[WHIRRING]
[CLATTERING]
So it's still an iterative algorithm.
It will go through, and given my current x, it will compute Cij.
And now, coherent point drift, the paper
is written completely in a Bayesian probabilistic
framework.
I'm translating-- I mean, you can write anything
as a Gaussian, and it's just a quadratic, and vice versa.
So I've converted it to stay in our notation,
to look just like the quadratic objectives
that we know and love.
But it's all the same.
You could take any of our quadratic forms
and give a probabilistic interpretation.
But because they have a probabilistic interpretation,
they choose a weighting function to say two points are not just
the distance, but I'm going to put a Gaussian kernel.
So I'm going to say that the points are corresponding based
on a Gaussian kernel that says how close they are to matching.
OK.
So I will just pick e to the distance, basically.
And this is a normalization constant
to get it all equal to 1.
OK.
So what does that look like?
Instead of in my-- I should make a nice little animation
of this, too, where I had my animations that
look like this, if I take one step,
you see the little green lines there?
This is actually-- that's a bad case,
because there's three scene points that
match to that one blue, but the blue only matches--
each scene point only matches to one blue.
Now, think of it as having a little Gaussian
around each of the points.
OK.
And based on the distance, I'm going
to score all of them, all of my neighbors,
as having some weight of correspondence that drops off
in the shape of a Gaussian.
Now, why is that more robust, potentially?
The word on the street is that it's more robust.
It tends to be more robust to outliers and everything.
First of all, the fact that it tails off nicely, right?
It's not just any arbitrary distance.
It's got an explicit tail, where the points that are far away
get zero correspondence, turning towards zero correspondence.
OK.
And it's a softer correspondence.
It doesn't have to have exactly a one-to-one matching when
that's an artificial thing, right?
So you're matching-- you can match up between two points
if you're just getting a different sample returns.
There's lots of reasons, maybe, to believe
that this is a slightly more robust version of the algorithm.
Because of the probabilistic interpretation,
they even have a way to schedule the covariance, right?
So you can look at your current fit
and tighten your covariance estimate
so that you're dialing in and converging to a good solution.
OK.
So this-- oops.
This paper also has bunnies all over the place.
Like, figures 1 through 6 are all bunnies, Stanford bunny.
And some people have been at Stanford before, right?
When you go running around Stanford,
the bunnies don't look like that, right?
They're hares.
They're like these big jackrabbits things.
So it's kind of funny that they have a New England
bunny or something that's the Stanford bunny.
Anyhow, bunnies everywhere.
And the evidence in the paper and the, I'd say,
consistent feedback from the community
is that these algorithms tend to be more robust to outliers
and noise in this, especially in the local convergence sense.
The downside is that they tend to be much more
expensive to compute.
You're looping through a lot more pairs of points,
as opposed to just picking for every scene point,
you just compute the distance for one.
Somehow you're computing this thing
for every possible pair of points,
and you're using it in your posed estimation
update, a lot more terms.
Wei Gao, who was a student with me not too long ago,
had a version of it that observed
that if you flip some of the terms around,
you can actually get a lot of the performance back.
And he has a CPD-like algorithm called
FilterReg that was a lot faster.
So CPD tends to be pretty slow but robust.
He had a version that was pretty fast and pretty robust.
Does that general idea of softening the correspondences
make sense?
No.
I feel that a lot of people get confused about CPD,
because the notation is so different.
But really, it's just that.
But if I think about that equation there--
I'll pull it back down.
I've been sort of preaching this make good choices,
I guess I said.
Did we make a good choice here?
It's fine for this implementation,
because we alternate between picking Cij and then
solving for the pose or whatever.
But what immediately jumps out to me
is that if I wanted to try to optimize C and x
at the same time, this gets me at least closer
to thinking about how I would do this.
There's two sets of decision variables
that look kind of similar.
I could potentially throw them into a solver.
But those things are being multiplied together.
So I'd have a term that would be quadratic in my terms
inside here, but multiply it again
by this set of decision variables
if I wanted to solve them jointly.
So that's not a good choice in terms of global optimization.
For the CPD, it's great.
So let me do one last optimization sort of idea
with you here, which would be, how do I massage
this equation one more time to try to get the Cij to enter
in a better way so that I could do joint optimization
on those things?
, There's a handful of methods
that try to solve those problems jointly.
Here's one formulation that is the most logical successor,
I guess, the closest to that set of equations.
Let's try to minimize over P, R, and C all at the same time.
And what if I did this?
Sum over i again here.
We do the Si here, and I'll do M.
OK.
So flex your optimization muscles for a minute here.
So what is this saying?
This is saying for every scene point,
I want it to, with my correspondence function,
match some combination of the model points.
Not so different than what we did with the faces.
But this is a version of the soft correspondences
that you see there, too.
You can add hard constraints on Cij,
or you can allow them to be more soft.
You can ask for them to be one to many match,
or many to one match, or in whichever direction
with constraints like this.
And it fits inside this nice framework.
The trick with this and the one that I wrote earlier
is that these constraints are still bad.
And once I add these other constraints here,
you can't just solve the SVD.
So there's various ways that people
have tried to work with these kind of equations.
OK.
There's a form of it where you try
to stick to binary correspondences.
And you can write this whole thing as a mixed integer
optimization.
Is it good?
I forget the relaxation here.
Is it still a QP?
It's definitely mixed integer convex.
OK.
There are versions of this that use semi-definite programming.
If I don't do this, there's also another version
that does semi-definite programming.
These are more advanced optimization algorithms,
but they're still optimization algorithms
that you expect to be able to solve globally.
And they require relaxing these constraints a bit
to fit them into that framework.
And there's various levels of success
for those different algorithms.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Right.
So that's what I was just saying is that it's also not
a semi-definite program by itself,
but you have to relax this to be-- yeah.
Both of these require relaxation.
Yeah.
We come up with some approximation
of those rotation constraints.
Yeah.
Just make sure I'm super clear about that.
And I won't cover the details.
I just want to get you to think about that equation
a little bit, because it's similar to what we've
been thinking about.
It's another way.
There's this kind of skill that you'll
pick up of how do you fit these harder formulations
into the same kind of toolkit.
This is a good, I think, way to think about that
and know that there are papers you can read, if you'd like,
to understand the details of how to try to do
more global optimization.
I'd say I would not call global optimization a technology
in really messy point clouds.
It's something that people are trying to do.
They're often very expensive.
They often don't work as well.
I mean, Luca is very keen on the teaser semi-definite programming
representation.
So maybe it's gotten a lot better.
The SDP relaxation in teaser and the like,
I think the way to think about it,
which I mumbled about last time, but it really
is 2D is not enough to show the picture that
would need to be shown.
But I think conceptually, thinking about this optimization
problem that we showed before and having that unit circle
constraint, saying that a squared plus b squared equals
1.
And we're going to change that to a squared plus b squared
less than or equal to 1.
This picture of trying to solve for these things
jointly by relaxing the non-convex unit circle
constraint to the convex unit disk constraint,
that's basically what's happening
in these SDP relaxations.
So you'll hear people saying things like, well, it's tight.
And that's in the case where there's no noise,
it's tight because the objective function actually
lands right on the unit disk.
And if you pull it outside, this constraint
will pull it back inside.
But if you're inside, it will be loose.
So if that's helpful, I know that's--
I haven't given you everything you need to appreciate that.
But if that is helpful, I hope it helps a few people.
So that was today's story about dealing with messy point
clouds and about doing a little bit of geometry
plus optimization, which I really
think is a beautiful combination of those ideas.
So we talked about three specific ones.
I hope you come away with this point to mesh registration
idea, with the pairwise distance idea,
that it's a translation and rotation invariant quantity,
and this idea of generalizing correspondence to make it soft,
paying an increased computational cost,
but potentially robust, getting robustness benefits.
Good choices, yeah?
OK, cool.
There's one last big set of ideas
that I want to make sure we cover in pose estimation,
and we'll do that next Tuesday.
Sorry that DeepNote was having troubles this week.
They were having, I think, bad actors attacking their servers.
They're super responsive, actually.
They told me when it happened, and they said,
as of last night, it's back up.
So if you have any troubles, let me know.