It's around the right time.
I'm just going to go for it.
OK.
So last time, we talked about force control.
I tried to give a couple examples about how sometimes
it's more natural to program using the language of forces
in your controllers instead of using the languages of positions.
But we mostly assumed that the robot was a point.
And so I promised that today we'd go through and add
the rest of the robot back in.
And that is exactly what we'll do.
It's a part of a bigger discussion
about manipulator control.
I'll mention again at the end, but there
are aspects of manipulator control
that might have you focus on executing trajectories
at high speeds with very high accuracy,
possibly with uncertain payloads.
But we're going to talk about the force control
aspects of manipulator control primarily today.
So I'll take you through a couple steps.
But I want to call out that at the end, we'll have--
Rachel actually does work on this regularly
with her Franca robots.
So she's going to show you some of her case studies
at the end, which will be an extra treat.
OK, so just to set it up and remember,
there are tasks like this one, for instance.
I gave a couple different examples last time,
where really, the task requires thinking
about something about forces.
You're trying to apply the right amount of force
to maintain frictional contact between the hand and the book.
And then between the book and the table,
you need to be in that sweet spot
where the book's still able to slide on the table,
but the hand isn't sliding on the book.
That extra part is-- actually, this is a pretty good example.
The video wasn't actually meant to show force control.
It was meant to show this cleverness at the end, which
even though there was some uncertainty,
having driven the book to the end,
if you choose the right kinematic strategies
at the end, you can reduce all the uncertainty
by just pushing to the end and then grabbing the book.
OK, but that's a good example, I think,
of something you'd like to do with force control,
writing on the board, erasing the board,
picking up the really big flat Cheez-It box.
These are all good examples, I think.
This was the one we spent time on last time,
was just actually trying to reason about what forces you
should apply at the finger in order
to stay in the friction cone on the end.
And this was a strong regulator on the forces
you would apply at your finger in order to not slide.
OK, so let's add the robot back in.
And I'm going to do it mostly--
of course, we want to apply this on the KUKA.
But I actually think for the board and for all the concepts,
it's totally fine for me to do everything
with a double pendulum for today.
And then we're going to use the general form
of the double pendulum.
But any time we want to get into the details,
I'll just choose two angles instead of seven to work with.
And I'm going to spend a little bit more time
on this part of the board today.
I realized I was always showing my backside to the camera.
So let's see if this works.
If you guys don't like that, you should tell me.
But let me try.
OK, let's spend our time today mostly thinking
about a double pendulum.
I actually will often call this the simple double pendulum
when I use point masses for the dynamics.
But we're going to stay mostly in the general form today.
All right, so a lot of times when I draw the pendulum,
I'll think of it as coming down from the top
as a hanging pendulum.
If you're a KUKA, maybe you're bolted on the bottom.
No big deal.
So importantly, I'm going to parameterize the double pendulum
with just the two angles.
I'm going to put my end effector here,
which I'll call the kinematics of this.
I'll have some point.
We'll potentially call it the contact point
if that's the places where we want to make contact.
We've got gravity coming down, of course.
I'm going to allow motors in both of these places.
So I have a torque here, torque here, masses distributed,
and the like.
So this fits right into the same equations
we've been using for the big, complicated EWA.
It's got the standard manipulator equation form,
plus potentially any contact forces, which we'll add later.
And in particular, it's nice because Q here is just
theta 1 and theta 2, super easy.
And U here is just tau 1, tau 2.
And the equations are derived in the notes,
well, the linked notes.
But if you care, it just comes up,
especially if you just do lumped masses,
then the terms come out particularly easy.
And we could write them on the board.
I won't, but they look like that.
OK, so what we want to do here is figure out
what torques to apply to achieve some sort of force control
or program the interaction here at the contact point.
That's the goal that we're trying to achieve.
And there's a really core idea that I
want to start with, which is this idea of feedback
canceling control.
So given the system as written, if I have U as an input,
so I can apply torques at both of those joints,
and if I know m, c, and tau g, the gravity forces,
then I can write a controller that
sort of changes the dynamics, the effective dynamics
of the robot, almost at will.
At some point, maybe I'll have torque limits
or other problems.
But let's just think about how I can already
change the dynamics of this to pretty much anything I want.
So as an example that I actually use typically
in underactuated to talk about how this approach is limiting
in the more general sense, but it's actually very useful here,
what if you had a goal of just replacing
the dynamics of your two-link pendulum
and make it act like a one-link pendulum?
Or, I mean, there's only two degrees of freedom,
so you can't make it act like a four-link pendulum.
You can sort of impose whatever two-link dynamics you'd like.
So what would that look like?
The equations of the single pendulum
are even simpler, right?
Maybe I have-- this would be equivalent to saying
I'd like the accelerations of my two-link pendulum.
It's deeper desired, right?
Let's say I'd like the first link to just swing around
as if the whole thing was just a one-link pendulum.
So maybe this gives me something like negative g
over l sine theta, maybe with some damping.
That would make this first thing act
like as if it had the dynamics of a single pendulum.
So if nothing else, it would be canceling
any effects that are coming from theta 2 moving around
so that theta 1 moves like a simple pendulum.
And there's a handful of things you could write here.
Let me just sort of cartoon it.
Let's just say I want the dynamic acceleration of that
to be 0.
In practice, if it doesn't start straight,
maybe I would put a little feedback control
to make it go straight.
But in general, I want to basically make this--
pretend that it's not there and not move.
And I'll just make the whole thing sort of swing
like a single pendulum.
So that's just a different desired acceleration for this.
It's not the one that naturally happens with the physics
of the double pendulum.
But as you can see sort of algebraically,
if I were to just choose to apply a controller which
goes in and exactly cancels out the terms in my equations
of motion, and then for this one I'm a little bit more clever.
I'll do this.
[AUDIO OUT]
Then if I were to run this as a controller--
this is my control, this one which looks very similar.
It is my plant, my equations of motion.
If I put them together into the closed loop dynamics,
then c cancels, tau cancels, and I get mq double dot
equals mq double dot desired.
And because we know--
I mean, the world knows.
We haven't spent time on it in this class,
but the world knows that mass is always positive.
Even in the mass matrix form, mass matrices
are always positive definite or semi-definite,
depending on the system.
But in general, we're going to say in these cases,
it's safe to do m inverse.
That exists, which implies that I get q double dot
equals q double dot desired.
So this kind of works, and I have a simple example
of that in a notebook.
I can take my original dynamics of the pendulum,
and if I run that, this is just the-- if u equals 0,
what happens with the double pendulum?
It just falls down with respect to gravity.
And if I write a simple controller that just does
almost exactly what I just said, and I
write that in a simple leaf system
here and put it in feedback with my plant--
[AUDIO OUT]
I wait for the first one to finish running.
I was just saying that somehow all of my computers
feel slow today.
I don't know what's happening.
Here we go.
All right.
So the double pendulum with that simple controller
suddenly just acts exactly like a single pendulum.
And that doesn't seem too surprising or whatever.
I can also just--
I mean, I don't even have to respect gravity.
I could just do the same thing but make gravity
be the negative of the true gravity,
and I could run that controller too.
And I just have a new system that--
because I've just overwritten the dynamics completely,
that new system can be whatever I want.
I could do it like I'm a pendulum in space
or a pendulum upside down or whatever.
So this is a powerful idea, which
is if you write the right controller
and you have enough control authority,
then you can basically overwrite the dynamics of your system.
Now, what can go wrong with that?
Yeah, please.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK, so he says it seems very dependent on your ability
to estimate the torques.
I mean, it also means estimating the masses accurately,
estimating Coriolis terms accurately,
the gravitational terms.
Absolutely.
So that's great.
I mean, people do things like this in practice.
And it's interesting to run the sensitivity analysis.
There's ways to sort of see how sensitive are you
to your mass matrix estimate and the like.
But to an extent, I mean, this works.
So it works in the case of a known robot arm.
Let's be super clear, actually, that if I
were to write the dynamics of a full manipulation problem,
where the equations of motion included
both the robot and the world, the manipulator
and the manipulate--
and the manipuland-- you guys know
the word-- I don't know if I've used the word manipuland a lot.
But that's what people often call
the thing you're manipulating.
It's kind of-- actually, props to Steffi if she's out there.
She made me laugh about how ridiculous this is.
It sounds like a place where everybody's happy
and manipulating, right?
But that's the word people use, right?
That's the object.
OK, if you had equations, what would
happen if you had equations that included
both the masses of the robot and the masses of the manipuland?
Well, I can't write this form anymore
because I don't have torque applied directly to the objects.
I only have seven actuators on my robot,
and I don't have actuators directly affecting.
So I can't directly overwrite the dynamics
of the objects in the world.
This B matrix becomes low rank.
And so that's why this is a lecture in underactuated
because the whole system is underactuated
if you consider the robot and the world.
And that's kind of what the other class I teach
on robotics is called underactuated robotics.
It's all about that.
So that's definitely a limitation.
But of course, like you said, these are also limitations.
You have to estimate this.
And also, if you ask your system to follow
some dynamics that just requires ridiculous amounts of torque,
and you have torque limits, there's
lots of things that could potentially interfere with this.
But locally, within reason, if you
want to change your dynamics a bit,
then it's an incredibly practical, powerful idea.
And this philosophy is going to underlie what we're going to do.
Basically, the goal is make my big, complicated robot
act like it's a point robot at the end.
And I can apply forces at the end,
or I can program the interaction at the end.
OK, so let's generalize that idea
or implement a version of that idea that
is going to act like a stiffness controller.
So if I want to program the interactions,
but I'll start by just programming them
at the joint level.
So instead of having my double pendulum
act like a simple pendulum, I'll make
it act like a system that, when I push it,
has some desired mechanical response.
OK?
So there's a bunch of different controllers
we could have written here.
We talked, even in lecture two, about the differences
in torque control and position control.
If I were to write a position controller for this,
I might write a PD control, something like this Q.
That's one controller I could write.
The philosophy in stiffness control, though,
is not to have somehow just a rigid position,
but to actually program the response.
If I were to-- I want my pendulum to act,
not like a simple pendulum, but like a different mechanical
system, which has a particular response to torque
perturbations.
So I'd like to act like it's a pendulum that's
hanging down that has some springs, some rotary springs,
here, that have a certain stiffness, and maybe
some damping.
So I'd like it to act a system like this.
.
This is the interaction that I would like.
I would like it to be that if my pendulum is sitting there,
and I were to go up and push on it--
now, the push, in this case, is written in the--
the coordinates of this equation is in torques.
But you can imagine coming in and just
giving a torque perturbation.
Or if I had a force that I pushed on the end,
I could transform that into the torque coordinates.
But if there's a perturbation in torque,
whether it's because someone actually pushed on me
or the robot's moving and it didn't realize
it ran into the dishwasher or whatever it is,
then I'd like it to respond gracefully as if it was
a mass spring damper system.
This is almost-- this is just the generalization of the mx
double dot equals kx plus bx dot equals--
this would be the simple mass spring damper
that you get from 18.03.
And this is just the joint version of that.
OK, so using the same philosophy from the feedback cancellation,
whatever is back here, I can write this controller
by canceling out the dynamics of the plant that I don't like
and inserting the dynamics I do like,
just like the pendulum example.
So the controller I write here, it's very simple.
It's going to look not so different than before.
I'll just choose u to cancel out pow g.
I'm going to leave-- see, I have this term
I don't have to cancel out.
I've left that alone for now.
We'll talk about that.
And then I'll just add in my-- this
looks almost identical to the PD controller I did--
we put as our strong end.
But it has one extra term.
It's got the PD control.
I made this point last time too, right?
So I'm going to add in my PD plus some gravity compensation.
Same thing I said for the point finger.
And in practice, when the EWA is doing this,
it's actually doing much more than just gravity compensation.
Did I get something wrong?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
Good.
Thank you.
Yep.
I have to flip it.
When I put it on this side and I want
to think of it as a stiffness, I get it like this.
And when it's on this side, I have to do this.
Thank you for catching that.
There was a high probability I was
going to get at least one of those signs wrong today.
There were so many of them that looked similar.
OK.
On EWA, they're doing gravity compensation.
But they're also doing friction compensation
and some pretty subtle stuff at the actuator level
to try to basically cancel out the effective dynamics
of the arm and replace it with this stiffness
kind of interaction when you run the EWA in joint stiffness
control or joint impedance control.
We'll say that in a second.
OK.
Now, again, so what's the big difference
in practice between having this versus having this?
It can make a huge difference in practice
because if you think about even the double pendulum,
if I need to choose a stiffness that allows me to work sort
of when I'm at a horizontal position where I've
got gravity pulling down and this term could be large,
if I want to have a small position error here,
I need to choose KP very big in the PD controller.
OK.
And here, KP could be excessive down here
to have that kind of KP that I would need here
just to get a reasonable.
So if you want reasonable performance all over the state
space, with the PD controller, you
have to choose KP very large, KP very large to damp that out.
OK.
If I subtract out gravity, then I
can write a smaller KP that has a similar response
all over the workspace.
That makes a big difference in practice.
It means you can choose these much lower
and you can be much more responsive.
So in practice, when people are running these controllers,
you bump into the robot and it's like,
and maybe it's a fault and powers down.
If you do it like this, then the EWA,
the way we typically operate it, will just kind of
be soft enough to get out of the way.
OK.
We chose our desired dynamics to use the initial mass.
So you should think of these things as always going together.
This one is just like the MA in F equals MA.
Those two really go together.
And we chose not to change them.
You can imagine the same kind of trick
where you go through and you try to cancel out M and C.
But it typically requires high bandwidth to achieve well,
good accuracy of your mass.
That would take you into a joint impedance control mode.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
And sometimes this stiffness control,
you might call it the simple impedance control.
I think impedance control is the more general term.
And it often gets used for the whole set of concepts.
EWA, actually, when you go into their settings,
it's like you're definitely choosing joint impedance mode.
And they are doing some amount of mass cancellation.
But actually, they're only compensating
for the masses of the rotors and not for the whole robot.
And it's actually a very subtle, I think,
well thought out, carefully designed control
that does exactly this kind of thing.
So they are technically changing this a little bit,
but not in the way of making a different effective mass.
Does that make sense?
It's really a lot like the feedback cancellation story.
But it's trying to do a little bit less.
And it's even more robust because of it.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
I had thought about possibly spending some time talking
in more detail about the EWA implementation.
I decided if most of you are not using EWA all your life
or care more about RL agents in simulation or whatever it is,
maybe that I shouldn't dig in too much to those details.
But I will recommend that the papers are totally fantastic.
Strongly recommend the papers, which
are linked from the notes by Albus Schaefer and Christian
Ott about the elastic control of elastic joint robots.
I would say impedance control.
Alessandro De Luca has some great notes, too,
if you're interested.
Mark Spong had some of the early work of it.
There's a lot.
There's a really good literature there
that I was tempted to talk about, but decided not to.
So let me remind you a point I made earlier when I was just
telling you the virtues of EWA is the fact that we do have
that kind of capability, and we exploit it often.
So in the pieces of the dish task, for instance,
opening that door.
So the joint trajectory that is programmed is a big part of it.
And it's a big part of the job.
So it's a really big part of the job.
The joint trajectory that is programmed
to follow during that opening motion
is actually deviating probably significantly,
depending on how accurately we modeled and actually
captured the location of the dishwasher,
and even the hinge of the dishwasher.
You can imagine that if you're trying to move down exactly
some kinematic constraint given by the door of the dishwasher,
if you're a little bit off, then it pays a lot
to be flexible enough to just follow whatever contour is
given by the actual position of the dishwasher
and not by your course approximation.
You can see that over and over again.
For the EWAs upstairs, we have a little IKEA cabinet
that you can open, and you'll see the same thing.
If you spend any time trying to open those IKEA cabinet doors,
your fingers will typically slip right off
if you're in too stiff of a mode and you have to get soft.
Similarly, when you push down here,
so it's still in a joint impedance mode there,
and it's not tracking the position trajectory
super accurately, but it's accomplishing the task.
Cool.
Does that make sense?
All right.
Now, the interesting part here is how we go from this basic--
I guess that's distracting.
So how do we take this idea now and implement it
at the end effector?
So instead of affecting the dynamics in Q,
we want to write the dynamics at the end effector.
So I want to go up, and I want to push
on the fingertip of the EWA and have
it act like a mass spring damper system in 3D or whatever.
So--
[WRITING ON BOARD]
So this is sometimes called Cartesian stiffness control,
end effector stiffness control.
OK, so how do you take those basic equations
and impose a dynamics in the end effector?
Now, we have the end position of the arm
given by some kinematic function of Q.
So this is the relationship we get to work with.
And I would like to impose something
like mp c double dot plus bc dot--
tell me if I get the sign wrong--
equals some-- this is my goal.
It's to achieve something like this.
The interesting thing is that the way that--
if I were to try to rewrite the original Q
coordinates in this form, I have to somehow change between Q
and P. OK?
It turns out you can take those initial equations.
I think it's very easy in the derivation
to end up at a dead end.
But I promise you that the proper change of coordinates
that gets you through is you have
to write your end effector mass.
This is the Jacobian here.
I use the Jacobian times mass inverse of the original system
Jacobian transpose.
Take the inverse of this whole thing.
And that's my new effective mass.
It's not surprising that you're going to use the Jacobian
to change coordinates.
What's maybe a little surprising is
that you can write the equations of motion in the end effector
frame as a function of the original coordinates
and the Jacobian.
So I can get a new set of equations
with an altered mass matrix, an altered Coriolis
matrix, which still depends on Q and Q dot,
an altered torque matrix-- I called it this in the notes--
plus my u in the new coordinates plus my external forces.
This transformation is often called operation space form
of the dynamics.
It's super useful.
OK?
Yes?
I was just about to ask you that.
It's not really fair.
If you ask me before I ask you, then do I still
get to ask you, right?
I'm going to ask you.
Is it obvious that this matrix is invertible?
What are the conditions that would require
that that matrix be invertible?
In general, you'd expect this to exist.
This would be like the right inverse of A
if A has full row rank.
OK?
So let's first ask, does the Jacobian have full row rank?
You can certainly find singular configurations
where it doesn't.
But in reasonable parts of the workspace,
J tends to be, for instance, could be like 3 by nQ,
for instance, if I'm trying to do n-defector.
It tends to be full row rank and low column rank
because it's a long, short matrix.
OK?
So this has every reason to work.
And then M is actually also positive definite.
So this thing is going to be well-conditioned, too.
So this thing, yes, will have an inverse,
as long as J doesn't go singular, which
is as it should be.
If you just try to start jamming J transpose
into your original equations of motion, like I said,
you'll find yourself stuck.
But I think it must be the case that if I
were to push on the n-defector of a physical contraption,
it will push back on me with some physical force.
That force that it pushes back on is configuration dependent.
There's some big, complicated set of mass.
I'll have more or less of it working against me
at each axis, depending on the configuration of that mass.
OK?
OK, but this was the magic step we need.
Now we can do, if we start working
in this, the dynamics in the operation space,
or the n-defector space, then we can just
do feedback cancellation in this lower space.
OK, yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
So we had a good question about this,
even when I was talking about singularities.
Like, what is your ability to produce force at this end point?
The controller can't produce force in that direction
instantaneously.
But it can produce a force dot.
So you have to be careful, if you
start writing these controllers in those singular
configurations, and you tend to either do
the kind of things we talked about with writing it
in a constrained least squares and put some boundaries on it,
or something like that.
Yeah, but I think, try not to do that, or be careful about it.
There's something else that's happening here, too, right?
So if I write a controller that tells
me to act like a certain dynamics in the xyz
configuration, but let's say I have
seven degrees of freedom of my robot,
then you've still got to do something else.
The same way in our Jacobian-based controller,
we talked about putting a secondary objective
in the null space, something, for instance,
just stay in a comfortable joint configuration.
You need to do something like this
to stabilize the null space of this controller, too.
So such that this basically almost equals this.
OK?
Plus null space stabilization.
OK.
So that has some implications.
The fact that we tend to not try to change m and c,
and the fact that it is configuration-dependent
means that instantaneously, you can make your robot act
like a mass-spring-damper system.
The mass that it acts like, though,
will be configuration-dependent, almost always.
So in the quasi-static analysis case,
if the accelerations are small, and you're just
trying to push and see how far does it deflect before it
stops, before you hit a new steady state,
the mass doesn't matter there.
The inertial terms don't matter in the static analysis.
But in the dynamic analysis, if you
start trying to understand the dynamics of your robot,
then it is going to be notable, maybe not hugely important.
Like I said, it would be beautiful and clean
to make them somehow constant a function of q,
but we tend to not do that.
There's theoretical limits on how much
you can change the mass to before you write
a controller that is unstable.
And Neville has some great surveys on that.
Neville Hogan has some great surveys on that kind of thing.
OK, so if you remember--
maybe I didn't show all of them before,
but this is end-effector impedance control.
And again, it's only barely impedance control.
It's really more of a stiffness control, I'd say.
And watch-- first of all, he's very happy, so it must be good.
And second of all, they're going to change the compliance,
the effect of compliance.
And he's going to show you that by changing the compliance
there, now it's a very low compliance.
A small force is allowing a big perturbation.
Again, the stiffness of that will not
change as a function of the position of the end-effector,
but the effective mass will.
There's no reason why you have to choose the same stiffness
in all three axes.
You can choose them differently, and that's
going to be important at the end of the lecture, I think.
That's probably fun to watch.
You can also write stiffness in orientation.
So I think this one is showing--
you can set a rotational compliance, too.
If you're now trying to control the whole parameterized
in terms of roll-bit-jaw, or however you parameterize
the end-effector stiffness, you can similarly
command an end-effector stiffness on this.
Make it very soft in rotation, very stiff in translation.
Pretty beautiful.
OK, one more point, a small point or detail
to call out here.
When you go to implement this controller,
one of the things you need is you actually
need to insert somehow the acceleration.
You need p double dot of c, right?
This is just kind of an aside here,
but we said p of c is f of kinematics of q.
We know p dot of c takes this form, the Jacobian.
You end up needing p double dot of c, too, in the derivation.
And it comes up in a lot of derivations,
so I just want to call it out here.
So what is p double dot of c?
We want to take one more time derivative of this equation.
So using the chain rule, I can write it
as jcq q double dot plus j dot cq q dot.
And there's a question that we get every couple of months
on Stack Overflow.
They're like, oh, how do you produce--
how do you get j dot in Drake?
Sorry, that's a specific version of the question.
But this comes up often.
And the answer is you don't, or you could,
but you really don't want that.
You probably don't want that.
And this is just a little window into a lot of smart thinking
that happens in the manipulator equations about how
to optimize different workflows.
But j of q is a matrix.
It's a-- I'll just even say a matrix.
I don't even care about its size right now.
J dot of q is going to be partial j, partial q.
I may have to be careful how I write this, q, q dot.
But that's a tensor somehow if I'm not careful.
So this thing is going to be a sum over i.
Maybe the simplest way for me to write this,
partial j, partial qi, qi dot.
Just take element by element gradient of this.
You definitely don't want to compute this.
You can compute it with autodiff if you want.
But we're not going to make that easy for you
because you almost never want that.
Because j dot q dot is a vector.
And pretty much every time you ever
want j dot anywhere in any of your controllers,
you actually want j dot q dot.
So in practice, when people say, oh, where's j dot?
You don't want j dot.
You want j dot q dot.
There's a function for that.
And you'll see that over and over.
You can compute that fast.
It doesn't have to allocate a lot of memory.
It's got this nice recursive form.
That's the term you always want.
And it becomes essential in implementing this controller.
Loads of details in there.
Everything good so far?
OK, so one last idea I want to land before I
let Rachel have the stage here.
So I've done stiffness control in end-effector coordinates.
I could have also done force control
in the end-effector coordinates.
And it's really pretty easy to do
if you make that same quasi-static assumption
that we did last time.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
The recipe is use the operations-based form.
A recipe would be to say, assume that q double dot--
approximately take the quasi-static assumption
like we did last time.
And choose your controller to cancel the terms such
that fc desired equals fc in the end-effector coordinates.
The equations would look almost the same as what I just wrote.
But do you remember what happened
when I was doing the pure force version of the Cheez-It box
flip-up?
Did this sort of beautiful force control.
It stayed inside the friction cone.
It got to the top of the box and sort of by all accounts
was done.
And then the finger went--
kind of shot off into nonsense.
That's real.
If you're only commanding force and you
have no other specification of the objective,
if there's not a world to push back on you
and the force you expect, then you can go away pretty fast.
I think it's relatively rare to do pure force
control in all six degrees of freedom.
There is a thing that people do do often,
which is hybrid force plus either position or stiffness
control.
So if I have my two-link arm here out in the world
and I've got my P contact.
And let's say there's a chalkboard over here
that I'm trying to write on or push the book.
The way we push the book there was very similar to this.
Then it's very common to do force control
in this direction.
And stiffness control in this direction.
That's sort of a natural specification of the task.
The natural way for me to specify my objective
on the board is that I'd like to be pushing into the board
with some amount of force.
Regulating that force is the primal--
the most natural way for me to specify
the goal of having white lines appear on the board.
Stiffness, of course, or somehow reasoning about the position
is what gets the job done in the other axis.
So this is a very standard setup to do hybrid force and position
control.
And there's no reason in the equations
why you can't set the dynamics in one axis
to be a force command and the other axis
to be a stiffness command.
This can have very nice properties.
If you're trying to do the wall following kind of behavior,
it'll do these.
The only challenge, I guess, is that you
have to estimate the coordinate frame well.
If you are a little bit off on your estimation,
then you could be applying forces
or just acting like a little bit of a stiffness into the board,
and you can confuse things a lot.
So it's a little bit dependent on the accuracy
of your coordinate estimation if the gains are
very different in this axis versus this axis.
But that's a strategy people use.
I think Rachel will give you an example of where it may work
or may not work as well.
You could also alternatively act like a stiffness
into the board too, right?
And the example that we just showed of the IWA acting
like a very different stiffness in the x direction
as in the y direction could be exactly what you'd like here.
In this case, then, maybe the goal
would be to put a set point of my spring
at some virtual wall just behind it,
have a carefully chosen stiffness in this axis,
and a different stiffness in this axis,
and that can get the job done too.
And there are differences in the way
those get implemented that can make
a big difference in practice.
But this notion of hybrid force position control
is an important piece of that.
OK.
OK, so I just want to mention what I think are the--
the beautiful thing about this is this idea
that I can really make my dynamics at my finger
act like whatever I want within reason.
The problem I have with all this,
and I think maybe the biggest limitation in my mind,
is that you're only talking about the dynamics
at your finger, right?
So in the case in the world where
you have an EWA with this beautiful point that
wants to stay perfectly there, and I'm
going to push on the point, that's all good.
If you're reaching into a toy box
and making contact all over the place,
then this doesn't give you a recipe yet.
There's something else that's missing.
Somehow you either need to estimate
the locations of contact, which is hard, by the way.
There's good papers on that, but it's not easy.
And typically, the sensors that you have,
joint sensors are impoverished for that estimation problem.
You might need a tactile skin.
And even if you did, if you have multiple points of contact,
you somehow would need to somehow program
the behavior of interaction at multiple points
simultaneously or whatever.
So how do you program a more general form of interaction?
So that's one big limitation.
There's another sort of silly, annoying limitation,
which is that if you want to change
the location of that end effector
or even change from joint stiffness to end effector
stiffness on the EWA, you have to stop the robot,
turn off the control software, change the mode,
and then power it back up.
And I can totally see why that makes sense,
because they don't want to worry--
reason about-- I mean, they work so
hard to guarantee the passivity properties and safety
specified-- safety steps or whatever.
And if someone starts flipping between controllers
in software, I can see that being something
you don't want to support.
But it's kind of annoying.
And it means that, in general, we
are operating primarily in the joint stiffness mode
in the work I've shown you.
I think Rachel will show you something that uses the end
effector modes.
But there are sort of problems, I think,
that go along with that.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
So good.
So the question is, why not work in torque control mode?
So you can send a feedforward torque.
Even with a stiffness controller,
often you can say, I want to act like KP plus KD
plus some feedforward torque.
It's typically-- just sending torques
puts an onus on you modeling the dynamics well enough
to cancel the gravity compensation out
and everything like this.
You're going to run your controller over some impoverished
interface at a lower bandwidth than what's
running on the robot.
So it really pays to let the EWA stack, or the Franca stack,
or whichever stack, do as much of the cancellation
at super high rates with super well-calibrated gains for you.
So we tend to do--
so actually, the way the book worked
is we were in a joint stiffness mode, which we tend to use.
And then we added an additional feedforward force
on top of that joint stiffness controller
in order to push into the book.
So it's a good question.
But for implementation reasons, we tend to not--
I mean, if we were working at KUKA,
maybe we'd go all the way to torque level.
But as a user of a commercial robot arm, you just can't.
So the transition here-- let me just call out.
So there's actually a fun project at TRI trying to build--
it's not Baymax.
It's Puno.
Puno means chubby and lovable and a little silly
in Japanese.
This is actually the Toyota THR robot, which is awesome,
if you haven't seen it.
And that's Baymax from Disney.
And we're slowly building Puno.
So this kind of makes the point, though.
I mean, we'll talk more about the tactile sensing later.
There's some really nice tactile sensors and soft bubble grippers
there that are all open source.
But the goal of this project is to make contact
all over the robot.
So this is just a kind of a fun video
that they had the robot grab a fish tank,
because you could put a camera in the fish tank.
People were a little worried about it dropping the fish
tank, so they were just checking.
But it's super fun.
So that impedance control, as I've written on the board
today, doesn't offer strategies for programming
interactions like that, because the location of the contact
is sort of not specified a priori.
So there's a different mode of operation, which I honestly,
I think we have to get to, is just a more general
make contact all over the system, instrument contact,
tactile sensors all over the robot that are constantly
measuring forces and pressures and everything.
So that's just a fun project going on.
Cool.
OK, let me turn it over to Rachel,
who's going to tell you about her work.
What do you need here?
Oh, it's just the--
OK.
I think it's good now.
All right, we'll need to save that.
Oh, yes.
Is this going to be annoying?
Yeah, it's going to be annoying.
OK.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and save it.
And I'm going to go ahead and save it.
Is this going to be annoying?
This is the first time you're all seeing the bottom of my face,
which is fun.
I do have the bottom of my face.
So we've been talking about control over the last two days.
And what I basically want to do for the rest of the course
is we're going to talk through a case study.
I'm going to introduce you to a new robot and a new task.
It is not with a dishwasher.
And we're going to walk through basically what
are the control options that you could do.
And then it's going to be specifically,
because this is based off work that I've done,
what are the control choices that I made.
So even more so than usual, this is not
objectively the correct answer.
This is the choices that we made.
And I will walk you through why we decided to make them.
So we've been working so far with Kuga.
This is the robot we've been dealing with.
I'm going to introduce you to a new robot, which
is the closest robot to the EWO while technically being
a different robot, which is the Franca Amica Panda.
Franca Amica is the name of the company.
Panda is the name of the robot.
They have a very cute story about why they call it a panda.
These robots are incredibly similar.
They are both 7 DoF.
They are made by the same people.
It is DLR, the German space agency.
The differences are that the Franca Amica is newer.
It is significantly cheaper.
And it has better documentation.
I think Russ's joke is that if you
know how something works in the Kuga,
you just go read the panda documentation,
because they are exceptionally similar.
So this is the robot that we're dealing with.
Sorry, I forgot to grab the notes.
One really neat thing about this robot
is that on the underlying system,
you can send either joint positions, joint velocities,
or joint torques.
That is the underlying controller interface.
And the really nice thing about that
is that allows you to build on top of it
a wide range of controllers.
So you can build, in joint space, position, velocity,
impedance, torque.
And in Cartesian space, position, velocity, impedance,
force, hybrid, anything you want.
To kind of echo the point we made on Tuesday
that these controllers are not so different
is that you can implement joint position control either
by sending positions at the lowest level
or by sending torques at the lowest level.
You can do position control either way.
One difference between the Kuga and the Panda
is that if you want to switch control modes
or if you want to switch stiffnesses for the Panda,
you do not have to turn off the robot and reboot.
You can just willy-nilly switch the controllers,
which is really nice and something
we're going to take advantage of.
OK.
So this is our robot.
It has lots of different control modes.
That's cool.
Let's meet our new task.
The task we are going to consider, which I will draw out,
but I also brought a prop, is that let's say
we have a childproof medicine bottle where
you have to exert a push twist.
You have to push down and twist in order to open it.
All of you have this in your medicine cabinet.
For me, it is nice that we could get a robot
to open a medicine bottle.
That's something I'd like my robot butler to do.
But the broader point is it's a very nice example
of a system where you want to both exert force and position
in order to accomplish this task.
So write this out.
If we want the robot to open this bottle,
it has to both exert a force downward on the lid
while twisting it, which you could
think of either as twisting it or exerting a torque.
Are we clear on the robot that we're using
and the task that we're achieving?
Cool.
OK.
So let's walk through the different ways
that we could approach this task.
We're going to walk through basically three different
control strategies.
Option one.
Now, I'm asking what control strategy
could we use given that we want to exert forces?
And not being creative at all, what's
the first thing that comes to mind?
Yes.
So we've talked about force control.
You could do force control to implement this task.
You could run a force controller.
You may guess by the fact that this is option one,
and I told you there are three, that we are not
going to go with this.
There are two main reasons.
One, force control scares me.
Force control can be pretty dangerous.
Russ mentioned force control is great if you are in contact.
And to illustrate that, if I have--
this is the Franconica Panda.
This is one specifically in Alberto's lab.
And if I ask it to just exert force down
while it's in contact, it doesn't care where that block
is, it's just going to keep exerting force down.
It's somewhat robust because it doesn't care about position.
It's just trying to exert force down.
And actually, we'll switch it back
that if you ask it to exert no force, then to echo the point,
it's actually going to run gravity comp.
But here, I'm not asking to exert anything down,
but it'll stay in place because it's
doing gravity compensation.
Cool.
Force control is well-defined.
If you are actually in contact.
But if you are not in contact and you ask force control
to exert force, you're kind of in an ill-defined state.
If you ask it to exert force and it's not in contact,
it's going to do its best to exert force, which means it's
just going to whip back at you.
Fun fact, I did this by accident the first time.
And it nearly cracked the back wall into Songbei's lab.
Sorry, Songbei.
And was very terrified.
I was, oh, god, I have to--
it's because I put something in the wrong sign.
I was, oh, god, I have to fix that.
Did it again.
And my nervousness did not recompile.
Did it a second time.
And then the third time, I was like, I should record it.
So that's what you're seeing here.
This is a toy example of where force control can be dangerous
because hopefully you will not be so dumb as to make a sign
error.
But in general, you have to ensure that you are in contact.
And force control is not well-defined
if you're not in contact.
So that's one thing that makes me nervous about force control.
The second reason that we did not go with force control
is you could argue, here, our goal is to exert a torque.
But specifying it as a torque could be kind of tricky.
And it arguably is not maybe the most intuitive way.
And so for that, our second option
that we could have taken, looking
at what we just covered, if I now want to do a force
and a position--
[INAUDIBLE]
Well, before that, force and position,
we're just going to talk about hybrid position force control.
One note is, as was mentioned, some people
call it hybrid position force control.
Some people call it hybrid force position control.
Some people call it hybrid velocity force control.
They're all effectively the same thing.
You just can't call it hybrid control
as another thing entirely.
So if you do hybrid position force control--
now, again, I told you there are three options.
So you may guess that we didn't go with option two either.
Why?
Hybrid position force control arguably
would be a great choice for this problem,
because it's very easy to specify.
We want to exert force in one direction.
And we want to control motion in another position.
Additionally, my advisor is the dude
who advised the person who invented hybrid position force
control.
So it would have been a very natural choice.
Why did we not do it?
So it actually comes back to this point
Russ made, which is that--
I'm sorry.
I'm moving a ton, which is what we tell Russ not to do.
In order to do hybrid position force control,
you are specifying in what directions
do I want to exert force and what directions
do I want to control motion.
And you define those constraints with respect to a frame.
And you turn it-- there's a lot of beautiful math.
And you specify it using Fafian constraints.
But it relies on being able to estimate that frame very
accurately.
And as Russ mentioned, if you get that frame wrong,
you're going to be exerting forces
in the wrong directions, which is just the same case of force
control being scary.
So one is that hybrid position force control is beautiful.
I love the math.
It is difficult to get it right in a system.
That's reason one.
The second reason is you might not actually
need it for this task.
So hybrid position force control works well
and is definitely needed if you're in the case
where you care very carefully about regulating force.
So the classic example is if you want to be writing
or you're doing welding or you're doing grinding or sanding,
where you really carefully care about regulating
what force you are exerting.
Oft less so.
We are in the case where we want to control how much force we're
exerting and we want to be able to exert enough force basically
to open the bottle.
But we are less concerned with regulating
like it has to be exactly this force
or we've messed up welding a part that goes on a plane.
So hybrid position force control, powerful,
hard to get right in some cases, maybe not needed for our task.
And so because of all of that, we opted--
and again, this is what we opted to do in our research.
You could definitely do this with hybrid position force
control and that would be an equally valid choice.
Also, if my board work becomes either too small or ugly,
someone please call me out on it.
So what we have to do is use Cartesian impedance mode.
To Russ's point that he made on Tuesday,
we'll use stiffness control and impedance control fairly
interchangeably.
In this case, it would be more accurate
to say that we're using stiffness control.
I'm going to call it impedance control.
Also, as Russ pointed out, some people say Cartesian,
some people say indefectors, some people say operation space
because that matches Osama Kati's seminal paper.
Some people say task space.
All of those words technically have
like slightly different meaning, but we're
going to use them interchangeably here.
Good so far?
OK.
So I want to open a bottle using Cartesian impedance control.
How am I going to do that?
Which Russ somewhat stole my punch line, but that's OK.
So let's say that we have a ground
and we have our indefector and we're
dealing in Cartesian impedance space.
So we have a spring.
This is a symbol for a damper, if that's unfamiliar to anyone.
OK.
So we specify a stiffness and a damping and a set point.
Technically, because we are in Cartesian impedance control,
in our full glory, our stiffness matrix is a 6 by 6.
So is our damping matrix.
And our set point is in SE3.
Everyone good with that notation?
OK.
So how do we, given a mass-spring damper system,
exert force?
For right now, I'm just going to focus on the fact
that we want to exert force down.
We'll get back to that twist part later.
How do I exert force down?
Russ already mentioned this.
If you basically move your set point further into the ground,
by let's say some d, this is going to cause your spring
to compress the decision.
Again, this is a decision we made.
It doesn't mean it's objectively the correct thing.
It's just the choice we made.
Because if I think about what stiffness and what damping
do I have to specify, that's a lot of numbers.
Those are big matrices and more than I want to deal with.
So what we're going to do is, instead
of specifying the entire matrix, we're
going to actually only consider the diagonal.
So what is our stiffness in x, in y, in z, in--
oh, I'm not going to remember the order correct--
roll, pitch, yaw.
Instead of 36 numbers, now I have 6.
And rather than controlling the damping matrix,
I'm just going to set it to be critically damped.
If that does not mean anything to you, that is OK.
It's basically a way of setting it
such that we minimize oscillations.
So that is-- to tie back to a point that was made on Tuesday,
I've seen a lot of people who do work now on learning impedance
parameters.
And there's an interesting thought of,
like, you can learn everything.
Or if you make these simplifying assumptions,
it's a lot smaller thing to learn, which obviously would
make your learning problem easier.
And so there's a thing to think of,
like, how much do you actually need?
Sometimes you will need the off-diagonal terms.
This is not a decision you can make unilaterally.
But it's just something to think about what assumptions
can you make about what you actually
need to get your controller.
Cool.
OK.
So we have our stiffness and our damping matrix.
We have a lot less to specify.
Let's think about what stiffness do
we want to exert in the z direction,
and what is this offset d?
If we want to-- what do I need my spring stiffness to be
and my offset to be if I want to exert force down?
Now, we have told you that we are getting the robot to act
like a mass spring damper.
And you might reasonably say, OK,
it acts like a mass spring damper, but is it actually?
And shockingly, with some back of the envelope calculations--
again, these were done kind of ad hoc,
so don't take them for granted--
is that the relationship between your offset in your d,
your offset into the ground, and the stiffness of your spring,
and the force that you exert is linear.
Like, how far I'm exerting, the force that I'm exerting.
And so it behaves exactly like a spring,
the fact where if you say, for a given stiffness,
I want to exert this force, I can pretty closely tell you
this is the d that exerts that.
And we actually did this across multiple stiffnesses.
And the fact that the robot behaves so amazingly well
is honestly both suspicious and a credit to the engineering
that it actually behaves like a mass spring damper.
No one is suspicious of this.
OK, you all believe me.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, r equals 1 for that last one, which--
I mean, it's not the densest point.
But when we say it acts like a mass spring damper,
at least for the panda, it actually
does an excellent job of acting like a mass spring damper.
So this is to say that if I want to exert a certain downward
force, I can pick a certain stiffness.
In my work, I have a heuristic for which stiffness,
effectively, I want to be as stiff as possible.
And that can directly tell me what d that I need to exert.
Does everyone follow on that?
This is how we can use Cartesian impedance
to exert a downward force, because we
have a super well-behaved mass spring damper.
So you said the Cartesian principle,
although it cannot go down actually--
Yes, you are asking it to do a thing that it cannot.
It gets very frustrated and exerts force at you,
which is what you want.
Cool.
Nishant, Willie, sorry.
[INAUDIBLE]
So here, I can be very confident that I can exert a force.
If this was less well-behaved, then you
would not be able to as directly control your force.
And that gets back to the point, like, if we needed
to control an exact force, you shouldn't
be using Cartesian impedance mode.
You should probably be using hybrid.
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, sorry.
The question was, what if this wasn't so well-behaved?
OK.
This covers what is my offset d and what is my stiffness in d.
We've right now only covered the pushing down part.
What about the twist?
So for the twist, what we basically need to do
is we need to generate set points at this d offset, which
move in a circle.
And luckily, all of you have done this,
because this is what was asked in the robot painter example.
And I wish I could claim this was all planned,
but it just works out very nicely.
None of you look happy at the fact that you had to do that.
So to review, what do we have to send our controller?
We're going to set our stiffness and our offset d based
of how much force we want to exert.
And then we're going to generate a series of set points
that basically trace out a circle,
choosing pretty high stiffnesses in the other dimensions
with our damping set to be critically damped.
Questions so far?
OK.
So that is essentially what we're going to ask our controller
to do.
That is not actually the complete picture.
So let's say that we have our robot here.
This is the same panda from before.
And what we're actually going to do in order to--
in my work, I call this a push twist--
is that we're not exclusively going
to run a Cartesian impedance controller.
We're going to leverage the fact that we
can switch between controllers.
So the first thing that we're going to do
is we're going to actually do what's called a garden move.
It's a move until touch.
It moves until it feels contact with something,
which allows us to be kind of invariant to what
the exact position is in d.
Once it moves until touch, it's going
to compute those set points based off
what that actual distance is.
It's going to go around and twist.
I don't run my robots very fast, to be fair.
And then once it's finished, it's
going to do what I call a move out of touch.
And so it's actually three controllers
that run as part of this-- move until touch,
Cartesian impedance to actually twist it,
and then move out of touch.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
You could just run this with Cartesian impedance control
direct down.
Yeah, it's an equally valid choice.
The practical answer is I have move
until touch implemented using position control instead
of Cartesian impedance control.
And so that's just what I call.
But there's no good reason for that.
Yeah?
Oh, I did not repeat the question.
Why don't I do move until touch with Cartesian impedance
control?
Because it's springy.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so the particular implementation-- sorry,
the question is, why does it look like it's not
moving continuously?
And that's because the implementation
that we're running there is that we are actually
sending a series of set points.
And it's checking that you hit each set point
before moving to the next one.
There's an interesting-- OK, I consider
an interesting implementation detail about how dense
do you want those set points.
First, we make them somewhat dense,
because particularly for this robot with the impedance
controller, it does not like doing large motions
in impedance mode.
It can be pretty dangerous and actually fault sometimes.
Yeah?
Why does it not like doing big motions in impedance control?
So the question is, why does it not like doing big motions
in impedance control?
Part of that is due to the gains that it said,
which you could change.
The other question-- the reason why I pause is because I
can answer this question with a lot of personal bias, which
is that doing large motions running Cartesian control,
I would argue, can be somewhat dangerous
for the instance of you are not collision checking.
If you are moving in an empty world, which
is what a lot of people do when they run Cartesian control,
and they're not collision checking, then it's fine.
But it's not terribly general, because you're not
collision checking against the world and checking things,
or often checking a lot of other things like that.
So it does not like it, for the gains perspective.
I do not like it, because it's not general and safe.
Hope that answers.
OK.
There is actually-- and due to time, we won't get into it--
there's a couple interesting points about--
this is a redundant manipulator.
And so there are design decisions
about what is the starting configuration before you
run that controller, and picking that such that you can control
things within an all space and do not run into a singularity.
And so we do some heuristics and checks
to make sure that that initial configuration allows
you to do that smooth motion pretty well.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
So I've showed you, for one case,
to zoom out a little bit with this work,
we actually implemented that same controller,
but four different ways, where the thing that changed
is what is the contact that you are making.
And all of these controllers were
defined as basically actions that you
could do that you could either open the bottle by using
your palm, by using a grasp, by using a finger,
by using a tool.
All of these have different kinematic properties,
as well as frictional properties.
And so these were different actions that you could take.
We're not going to talk about this yet.
But basically, we defined those actions in combination
with a lot of other actions.
And we used a task and motion planning system.
This is something that I think was mentioned four lectures ago.
In the decision-making lecture, we
mentioned that task and motion planning is a powerful tool.
Basically, using that to sequence
our set of controllers, we can search
through basically a combinatorial search
base of different ways to solve this problem.
So for the interest of today, this
is running different Cartesian impedance controllers,
as well as position controllers, in order
to accomplish this task.
If we do a task and motion planning kind of boutique
lecture at the end, then I will be
able to explain to you how it actually does the search in
order to be able to find these sequences
and understand what's truly going on in this video.
Questions?
Yeah.
So specifically for this task--
and this gets into a little bit about task and motion planning--
it's defined as a fluent where the lid is off of the bottle.
And we constrain it such that you cannot take the lid off
the bottle until you have exerted this forceful-- what
we call forceful operation, the push-twist operator.
And so it reasons through, OK, my goal
is that I want to remove the lid.
In order to remove the lid, I have
to exert this forceful operation.
You also have to fixture the bottle in place.
And it kind of reasons through what
is the sequence of actions that I need to take,
as well as what are the parameters of those actions
in order to achieve it.
So the planner is actually--
we walked through how you do this.
The planner actually is the one deciding what is that d.
It's the one computing all of that,
in addition to the sequence of actions.
Task and motion planning is really cool.
If you want a boutique lecture on this, please say so.
OK.
Yeah, any other questions before we--
we're just about at the end of time.
Sweet.
Thanks, everyone.
Pset 8 is out.
8 involves hybrid position force control.
so you'll be able to implement it.