doing it, then it might help you in case there's any weird thing happening.
So basically, on DeepNote, every time I post to DeepNote, I lock in a snapshot of both
Drake and the manipulation repo.
The idea is that you could return to DeepNote, if you make a duplicate of that notebook and
you return to it, in four years, it'll be rock solid.
Like, it'll still run.
You can still do your quadratic programming.
Okay.
And even though I'm going to move things ahead.
The only consequence is, if I'm updating, you know, sometimes I do while we're talking,
if I get a question, that's a good thing.
That means you might not see the absolute version.
If you ever feel that the textbook is saying, oh, you should see the X, and you're not seeing
it, you could just duplicate the notebook again.
Precious concept.
So you can still use your stuff in four years, you know, when you are starting your manipulation.
Okay.
So and finish our first journey through making robots move.
The basic picture place.
So we remember the sketch.
Let me just remind you of the sketch.
Our goal is just to get the first robot to be doing something fairly simple, but we're
going to go all the way through the controller, plan trajectories, execute this motion, think
about the right way to execute that motion.
The steps to achieve that started with understanding basic kinematics.
Kinematic trees.
And I tried to tell you about the spatial algebra version of that.
The second step was once we had this notion of thinking about frames, even, for instance,
talking about the position of the hand and the orientation of the hand relative to the
object, we could go through and just forget about the robot for a second and just say,
I want my hand to visit these places in space at these times.
We came across, we came up with trajectories for the hand motion, starting with a sketch
and then just filling it out with simple interpolation.
And then we talked through how you could connect the gripper position with the joint angles
of the robot.
And that was the kinematics problem.
We're going to get into that again as we launch into the full differential inverse kinematics
problem today.
Right.
So that's the last piece of this puzzle now is you've got your gripper sketch, your trajectory,
your desired gripper positions.
You understand something about the mapping, at least how I could recursively compute the
frames from the hand up to the, you know, each joint is just another multiplication
through my kinematics and my spatial transforms.
And the question now is, and we talked, we introduced the Jacobian.
I'll pick back up at the Jacobian here.
The question is, how do we robustly execute trajectories?
And we're going to even get into the issues of like joint limits and velocity limits or
what happens when things are going not according to plan.
Okay.
So Patrick Winston always used to give talks about how to speak.
And he said, "Start your lecture with promise."
So my promise here is that I'm going to, you're going to be moving this robot and understand
all the pieces now into this lecture to understand how to make a robot, at least in simulation,
you know, do the whole thing from my sketch all the way to joint commands.
Okay.
If there's any questions from last time, I'm happy to take them.
Always, by the way, sometimes we've had some really great questions right after class.
And I thought, "Oh, I should ask that during class," because everybody wants to do that.
And I'll tell you, some of the questions and answers I think are, I might mention as we
go here.
Okay.
So, I mean, if you'll remember the mechanics that we introduced last time and the spatial
algebra that we introduced last time, we talked about, you know, positions and use our fancy
notation with superscripts all over the place, subscripts all over the place, right?
And we had, that would be for a relative position.
We had rotations.
We also had our pose, which put them all together.
Now, actually, I want to say something about this.
So you guys asked a perfectly good question last time about whether we ever have the expressed
in frame for the transform.
And I think, so I had to think about it, right?
And I said, "Yeah, sure, you could do that."
I couldn't actually think of a case where you do do that.
So I actually went through all the code and everything and all the derivations.
You never need that.
It's not wrong to put that.
But all of our useful quantities and all of our useful multibody computations and stuff
like this, you can be fine having B in this.
And we actually, in the code, in the notation, we basically don't support putting an expressed
in frame there.
Okay.
So it's not wrong, but it's just not needed.
Now, that's not-- when we get to, for instance, the derivative of the pose, which would be
a spatial velocity-- I'll try to be careful and put some-- there's a lot of Vs flying
around.
The spatial velocity was our 6 by 1, which had omega, which is our angular velocity,
and our V without the lines, which is our translational velocity.
And this, we absolutely do end up finding places where we want to talk about that being
expressed in a different frame.
And that's just the derivative of this.
But it turns out, this all the time, this never.
So we have our spatial velocities, and we will soon have spatial forces and spatial
accelerations and things like this.
But this is how far we've gotten so far.
Right.
We talked about the strangeness of the fact that even maybe just even for rotations, there
are many possible representations of rotation.
We have, for instance, Euler angles, axis angles.
If you know this, quaternions and axis angles are quite similar.
Rotation matrices.
But in spatial velocity, or even angular velocity, we always just have a canonical angular velocity.
Someone asked a great question, which was, so why are rotations bad, but rotational rates
OK?
And that's a good question.
There's a lot of different ways to think about why that is.
I think probably the most fundamental way, the reason that that happens is because angles
wrap around in 2 pi.
And velocities don't wrap around at 2 pi.
So if I rotate by pi, and negative pi, I'll end up at the same place.
Or if I run 3 pi, that's the same as pi.
But 100 radians per second is still different than every other positive radian per second.
Now in two dimensions where you can represent everything with a scalar, a single rotation,
that turns out to not be OK.
You can always do the right thing to figure out-- maybe you flip back from polar coordinates
to rectangular coordinates.
And you can always figure out the angles between two locations, even around that weirdness
where they wrap.
When you're in 3D, you have to pick some point where your math goes wrong, basically.
At some point, there's angles-- there are rotations that you can get to from many paths.
And to sort of pick a unique inverse of that without having any degeneracies is bad.
But angular velocities don't have this wrapping problem.
And they seem to be fine.
You can also think of it about it as being just-- it's a differential quantity.
So if I think about-- let's see, even in 2D, if I think about a rotation taking me around
the unit sphere, I'm taking any point and moving it around the unit sphere, I mean the
angular velocity is just a tangent on that.
And it's sort of well-behaved.
It's the wrapping that gets it.
We actually put a-- it's not exactly about this, but we put a problem for the slurp on
your homework to get you thinking about it.
In practice, there are many different-- but in velocities, everything collapses to one.
Now there are classes you could take that would spend a long time talking about the
different transformations between these.
I don't think they're meant to be as essential.
I think you should understand that they exist.
You should understand that there are times where one is better than the other.
And you can understand that there's-- you can look up in a textbook to go between one
or the other.
But it's more important to me to stay at that-- for this to stay at the concept level and
not dig into all the-- especially quaternion math is beautiful if you-- once you own it,
and it's terrible until you do.
It's like all these weird symbols to make everything work.
So there's another question which is going to launch us off today.
So I said, for instance, if I wanted-- if I had the x of the body, we could call it
in the world, is some forward kinematics of that body, which depends on q.
q remember is my vector of positions.
And this is my pose of the body in the world.
OK.
So there is a limiting case where I have exactly one body in the world, right?
And therefore, q's representation must be enough to tell me where that body in the world
is.
Always, q should be sufficient to tell me what all the bodies in the world are, where
they are.
OK.
For an EWA that's bolted down, all I need is the joint angles, seven numbers of the
different rotations of the different joints.
But if I have a red brick on the table, I need my-- I need enough something in q to
be able to eventually pull out the pose.
So again, we can represent that orientation however we want in this side and this side.
In some sense, this is just a-- when I've written it like this, I think of it as a mathematical
statement.
OK.
But if I write it in code, then I have to make a choice between those different representations.
We tend in the code, almost always, and in our derivations, q, we want it to be a vector.
And we're going to combine orientations with joint angles and stuff like this.
So here, we're going to choose quaternions for a number of reasons that will be more
and more obvious as we develop algorithms against this.
The q is often a very-- the vector quaternion version is powerful for a lot of algorithms.
But when we get here, on disk, if you will, when we have to make a choice, we often choose
rotation matrices here.
So in the limiting case of just having a single object in the world, the kinematics actually
just change the quaternions to rotation matrices.
OK.
So we want to do the opposite of that.
We want to go from a ban of poses in the world into joint positions.
We talked just at the end about how that's not necessarily a unique mapping.
There can be multiple q's that give the same pose in the world.
So just taking an inverse doesn't seem quite right.
Probably I want to send smooth commands to my robot.
So making sure that what we're doing here is not jumping around to different solutions
is very important.
So what tends to be the winning approach here is to use the differential form of the kinematics
in order to say, actually, if I just want to take my current pose and make a relatively
small change in a certain direction, then what is the incremental change in q I need
to make?
And that is well defined everywhere.
Well, we're going to talk about when it's defined, perfectly defined.
But certainly the partial derivative exists everywhere.
And we're going to use that to then do the inverse.
In particular, because we're playing this game with different representations, if I
want the spatial velocity of b in the world, and I'm going to use my Jacobian, which is
a little bit more than the partial derivative of that f, because it's also doing the change
of variables.
I'm changing between body and gripper here.
So I can write this as my geometric Jacobian.
And the thing that I wrote on the board that I hate writing on the board, it's only a straw
man, it's only a placeholder, is what we would conceptually like to do is something like--
now this is a matrix.
It's a position-dependent matrix.
But if this is a matrix times a vector, so I could potentially do something like this
to try to make from a desired velocity to a desired joint angle of forces.
But let's just think if that's even a reasonable thing to write.
How big is Q dot for the EWA?
Right.
There's seven joints up and down, seven joints make a lot.
This thing is always 6.
So this is a 6 by 7 matrix.
You're not allowed to take inverse of non-square matrices.
So that's why I don't even like writing this on the board.
But conceptually, I want you to think about it that way.
But this is not OK.
Now there's a generalization of that, many of you know, of where I can-- people use different
symbols for it, sometimes just plus, sometimes sharp, sometimes-- I'll just do that to make
it clear on the board.
A pseudo-inverse-- maybe I'll just do the plus, that looks good.
I hope that's clear enough.
So the inverse is not OK, but this is the pseudo-inverse.
How many people are comfortable with pseudo-inverse?
Yeah, good, some of both, right?
So you can think of the pseudo-inverse at one level.
So I used to call inverse "inv" in MATLAB.
Now I'm going to call "p-inv."
It's like a standard linear algebra tool.
It exists everywhere.
It actually has magical properties.
So well, first and foremost, it works even if your matrix isn't square.
So it's well-defined if it's not square.
But it's better than that.
So when things are not square, you could have infinitely many solutions.
You could have no solutions.
So this sort of does the right thing, but we'll define exactly what the right thing
is.
But in the case where you have infinitely many solutions, it will pick one, and it will
pick the one that's minimum norm and the least squares norm.
So it'll find the smallest solution.
In this case, it'd be the smallest joint velocity, which sounds pretty good, that achieves the
desired velocity.
That's good.
If there are no solutions, then it doesn't just fail.
It actually does its best effort and tries to find a dot that is as close to matching
this equality as possible.
The pseudo-inverse is awesome.
Yeah?
So is pseudo-inverse solving for an actual matrix, or is it solving for a 2 dot given
to you?
You can just call it this.
OK.
And is it-- or is it just going to call it a least square solver?
That's going to be the topic for today.
And generalizations of least squares.
Yeah.
You're--
OK.
I didn't--
[INAUDIBLE]
Can you call pn-- is pn solving the entire--
--systems of equations, and just an operation on the matrix, and gives me a new matrix.
And the answer is pn-- pseudo-inverse just gives me a new matrix.
We can think about its size and everything, but it's the size that's required to make
that transition.
OK.
But this is actually enough to get us going.
So without thinking any more about it, we can actually build our control system using
the pseudo-inverse.
OK?
So let's just think about wiring this thing up.
I'm going to go over here.
We've got a lot of components flying around, but we've got a new one, which is our first
controller, which is a pseudo-inverse controller, which would be-- so this thing is going to
spit out-- I think of it as q dot, the EWA velocities.
But I'm going to think about it as the desired EWA velocities.
I'll just put a superscript e, so I remember that's not what's actually happening on the
robot right now.
That's what I hope to have happen on the robot.
OK?
In order to do this computation, I need the model of the robot inside here.
That's OK.
I need the current positions of the robot.
So I need EWA position coming in.
And I need my commanded V spatial velocities.
I can think of it as a desired again, so spatial velocity.
Now downstream, I have my wrapped up manipulation station, which takes in q desired, not q dot
desired, for reasons that are subtle, I think, but we talked about a little bit before.
So somewhere in here, I need one other step, which is to integrate out my desired velocities
and turn them into desired position commands.
This is some initial conditions that must be carefully
to match your original initial conditions of the robot.
Common mistake, you wire this all up, you forget to set the initial conditions of your
integrator, and your robot goes, whoa, at time 0, and then tries to do something reasonable.
But it's already-- the game is over, pretty much.
So we have the actual EWA positions coming out.
Think of it as measured EWA positions.
And then we have one other component that we hinted at last time, but didn't actually
use in the last lecture, which is the trajectory source, we call it.
So I'm going to do my plan sketch, come up with a spatial velocity trajectory, and put
that into my source.
That's going to feed my pseudo-inverse controller, which is going to feed an integrator, which
is going to feed the manipulation station.
Now there's one subtlety, which actually goes to one of the questions Charles asked last
time, what do I want to use for this?
Because there's two choices, natural choices.
I could try to take my hypothetical commanded positions, or I could use the actual positions
to wire that over.
I would think my inclination is not the real thing.
Why would I take a substitute?
But actually, most of our code is going to do this.
It turns out that even in simulation-- so this could be a noisy measurement.
There might be a reason.
That might be one reason.
But even in simulation, it's more stable to use the desired.
And just think of your trajectory as playing out this integrated-- I think of this thing
as a big system that has to happen to go through velocities in order to use this controller.
And really, I think of commanded poses in, commanded joints out.
Interestingly, you could think about this if you want.
But the phenomenon that you get if you wire it up to here, even in simulation, is that
you'll get a good solution.
But then in the null space, so in the multiple solution dimension, you might see your elbow
walk around a little bit.
And you'll sit there thinking, oh, I found my good solution.
And then you'll see, why is my elbow doing a little dance?
And it's just--
It's the subtlety of the way these things feedback with the numerical precision of the
integrator and stuff like that.
So this is actually a pretty darn good control.
The thing that you want to-- where does it have problems?
I guess some of you know where it has problems.
But what can be a limitation of this?
I just said the pseudo-inverse is magical.
It does the right thing almost always.
Multiple solutions or no solutions.
So it does potentially-- it does really do the best effort.
So if there's no solutions, it'll come up with the best possible solution.
Is that good enough?
If there's multiple solutions, it will find a solution that is the minimum norm.
That sounds pretty good.
When is it not enough?
Oh, sorry.
I didn't see your hand.
Maybe you run into a problem on a singularity [INAUDIBLE]
Right.
OK.
So what happens when this is at a singularity?
So, OK, what does a singularity mean?
I actually have tons of graphics for this.
But it's complicated, always.
So run that.
Open that.
OK.
So this is just the chapter notebook.
You can-- I hope you will run it, work hard on it.
OK.
So let's just visualize the Jacobian.
It's a little bit small.
But I guess what I want you to see is there's a bunch of numbers.
This has got sliders.
So I can open it up.
I can move it around.
I hope you will do that, moving around a little bit.
As I move this around, it's showing me the Jacobian-- how the Jacobian changes.
OK.
So the situation for-- if I worry about when this thing has changes from having good solutions
to having no solutions, for instance, or infinite solutions, what I worry about is the rank
of that matrix.
In particular, since I'm trying to find Q dot-- I will try not to walk-- but if I'm
trying to find Q dot, what I worry about is the row rank of this.
Right.
We said we have seven Q dots and only six desired velocities.
That's actually the good case, right?
So I might have multiple solutions.
What I worry about is when the rank of this gets less than six.
OK.
Now rank is a binary thing, right?
A matrix has some integer rank, right?
It's either five.
It's either six.
OK.
So that is great, but it's rare that you actually drop rank.
Your robot will break before you drop rank.
How about that?
OK.
What actually happens is you start to lose rank.
So what really happens is that as this thing approaches losing rank, the inverse gets poorly
conditioned.
You'll get very big commanded velocities out.
Before you actually lose rank, you'll command a ridiculous velocity on the robot, and it'll
hit a joint limit or a velocity limit, and it'll shut down.
OK.
So what actually matters here is not rank per se.
I like to plot the smallest singular value of that.
OK.
That's going to tell me how big my worst direction is in the other side.
It's not the condition number.
It's really all that matters is how big things are, not the relative between the smallest
and largest singular value.
This is when the smallest singular value goes like that, right?
So you can move it around, right?
So how can I make this thing drop?
So if the smallest singular value gets close to 0, that means when I try to invert it,
I'm going to get really big velocities.
What do you think I can do here?
What should I move around?
It's 0.17.
That's pretty-- 0.18.
That's pretty good right now, right?
Yeah.
Straight up, right?
Pretty much anything I do to straighten the arm, you can watch the numbers are going to
get smaller and smaller and smaller.
I straighten just the elbow there.
If I go and straighten that last-- straighten that last one, things get pretty dicey, right?
So whenever you-- that's an easy one.
There could be other singularities around, but when you're pretty extended and someone's
asking you to be more extended, you're going to get-- things are going to get bad, OK?
So I feel that singularities are-- they're a cool thing.
People talk a lot about them, worry about them.
I feel like they can be mysterious, and I don't want them to be mysterious.
So I tried to make this super simple example, OK?
So this is a two-link pendulum, OK?
I'm just going to make it run through a simple trajectory where it's going to its full extension.
We can easily derive the Jacobian here, OK?
But you can guess.
It gets singular when it gets straight.
So a lot of people ask, is the singularity of the Jacobian real?
It's a reason-- it's like you should spend some time philosophizing.
Are singularities real or that what-- AI surpasses human intelligence?
This is a singularity, not the AI singularity.
Are there good solutions my controller could make, or is it really just-- right?
So this robot is commanding a constant-- it's just-- q is just a constant number for the
shoulder and for the elbow.
It's walking in and out of singularity, no problem.
There's nothing blowing up, right?
But the Jacobian does not singular, OK?
So I mean, I can derive the kinematics.
Let me do the short version of that, OK?
So I think the position of the gripper, then it's just going to be-- so this is just basic
kinematics.
Stop the mesmerizing pendulum, OK?
If I make the-- these things just have-- I'll put this and I'll put this.
Call this theta 1, theta 2.
I'm just trying to figure out the position of that, OK?
I always use right-hand angles, so that would actually be a negative value there.
So my x position, if I'm just worried about in 2D, my x position is just a cosine of theta
1.
My x position of this-- so that's this point here.
My x position of the whole thing is cosine of theta 1 plus theta 2.
On top of that, that's the contribution from the second link.
And I get a sine theta 1 plus sine theta 1 plus theta 2.
So I want to take the Jacobian, this case in the translational coordinates, there's
no change of variables.
There's no like orientations are weird, so I have to do some other thing.
It really is just the partial derivative of this matrix.
So the Jacobian of G just works out to be negative sine theta 1 minus sine theta 1 plus
theta 2 cosine.
It's a matrix, sorry.
Entry here, negative sine theta 1 plus theta 2 cosine theta 1 plus theta 2.
And by the way, in my simple open loop trajectory, the total-- I've designed it so that it's
moving exactly so that the horizontal position of the end effector is a sine wave and the
vertical position stays 0.
Simple enough.
I could have decided on anything, but I wanted to go through.
So this thing looks like 2 cosine minus t.
OK.
How does it go like that?
So clearly, when sine of both of those is 0, that whole row goes to 0.
And this matrix drops rank.
So when straight out, the matrix drops rank.
So if I was doing a controller with a pseudo inverse, things could get bad.
I want to really understand by the end of the lecture how they get bad and how we predict
them.
So the singularities are real.
It really is that the mapping between my positions, my end effector positions and my joint angles
gets into this terrible situation.
But it does not mean your robot is helpless.
It just means-- well, what is it?
Can you think about what it means?
So if I'm here and I want to move my hand back this way, is there any velocity I can
command my joint angles to move myself a velocity back?
What's that?
If I have a desired velocity here, how do I map to a desired velocity of the joint?
You can't.
The only possible velocity there is 0.
That's real.
You can't move with a velocity instantaneously.
But you can accelerate backwards.
So by choosing a joint angle that is not instantaneously achieving my velocity objective, I can move
out and start accelerating, get to a position where I can start commanding velocity.
So thinking about things only in the end effector velocity space does have foibles, if you will,
and quirks.
But it does not mean your robot is helpless.
It just means you have to be a little more clever.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
The question is, if I move everything up to acceleration space, have I just deferred
the problem to the next set of variables?
No.
I think it's actually better in acceleration space.
Now, we'd have to think about exactly what the acceleration-based controller would be
to give a great answer to that.
But you can accelerate instantaneously.
And you cannot command a velocity instantaneously.
OK, so in practice, the thing I worry about is I'm running my Jacobian-based controller.
I get close to dropping rank here.
Because maybe I don't actually want my robot to be at its very, very end.
If I'm just innocently choosing some trajectories, I get sort of close to this.
If that singular value gets close to 0, I might start commanding ridiculous velocity.
Even worse, since my robots are all inevitably going to be velocity-limited, and they're
not thinking about your control objectives, there's a downstream part of my robot that's
saying you commanded joint 7 to be 60 radians per second.
I'm going to clip that.
And it's not going to clip it nicely to-- it's not going to do approximately what it's
trying to do.
It's just going to saturate some of those or fault.
So what happens here is that your solutions start getting arbitrarily wrong, or you've
commanded something really bad.
So what we need is, even though this is good, like the pseudo-inverse is a beautiful mathematical
object, if we want to do our best effort knowing that there are limitations of my robot, like
velocity limits, like joint limits, and other things, then I haven't given-- the pseudo-inverse
didn't have a chance.
I haven't told it about that extra bits of information.
So we need sort of a richer version of the pseudo-inverse that can consume more information
about my problem specification.
It can consume these extra details.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's great.
So the fundamental question is, hold on a second.
I know that torque is Jacobian transpose times a force, an end-effector force.
So if there's this duality here, then if I have a singularity here, aren't I going to
also struggle to compute a torque, right?
Yes.
I think any Jacobian-based approach is going to struggle.
That's true.
Is it true that you can't compute a torque for an arbitrary force?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah?
Yeah.
I will come up with an example to appease you.
I think that's a great question.
You could probably even do it here on this guy.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
There's absolutely that, the question.
But you can move it back this way, right?
If the--
[INAUDIBLE]
But this relationship--
This is real, right?
This is like, go remember.
So why is that not showing this extra--
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So I think that's a good question.
I think that's a good question.
It's solving a simple optimization problem, and we're going to solve harder optimization
problems.
But the way to see this is first to just understand this original operation through the lens of
optimization, and then we can add in some constraints and have a more general solution.
Okay?
Okay.
So this is now differential inverse kinematics, right?
We're solidly in the differential inverse kinematics, but now as optimization.
All right.
So the way to think about what the pseudo-inverse is doing is to think about as it's trying
to find me some v such that-- I'm going to use a kind of a shorthand here to get started--
that this thing is as close as possible-- JGQ dot, yeah, is as close as possible to
my v.
I'll make it-- I'll say Q dot here.
I have two v's on my notes, so I'll stick with the dot.
Okay.
So this is my spatial velocity.
I'm super careful about that.
I'm trying to find Q dot such that this is as close as possible to that.
And this is a standard thing in linear algebra.
You should think of this as when people write sort of, I want to find Ax is approximately
equal to b.
I'll do a backslash operator in MATLAB, or this is sort of a shorthand.
It's the best-- the solution x that is-- so it makes this approximately true.
So how do you actually write that, right?
We're going to write is minimize over Q dot the least squares squared error.
Okay.
So how should you think about that?
I mean, even in the scalar case, it's sort of useful to think about, I guess, right?
So you think about Ax is approximately equal to b.
There's only a few things that Ax and b can do.
So if I have like x and y, I'm trying to make Ax equal to b.
I've got some slope a, right?
I can just compute-- this would be like my x star.
This would be the solution that would find me the x such that a times x equals b.
So what does the generalization of that look like if I think about Ax minus b squared?
Well, you should think about that-- colored chalk opportunity.
You should think about that as saying, well, I'm going to score all the different options
here.
And that quadratic form says, find me the lowest point on this curve.
All right.
So if I'm minimizing Ax minus b, it's going to minimize this curve.
When they're equal, it's equal to 0.
As they get farther apart, it goes up, right?
It's a quadratic form.
Now the interesting thing is to think about what happens if a starts getting small, right?
So my solutions start getting worse.
I need a bigger x to achieve the same b.
And what happens if you were to run through the math-- we'll do the vector case, but you'll
see that the scalar case, you get increasingly far out solutions-- x, of course, because
if your slope goes down, this would be a shallower slope.
And if I go even more shallow here, then the thing I need to get b has some [INAUDIBLE]
potentially.
And the pole is super bright.
OK.
So why is that a helpful view?
Because if we go into more dimensions, I'd like to be able to say how good a solution
is, even when it's not able to achieve the perfect solution.
And I want to say things like, OK, you're not allowed to go past here.
Like you're just not allowed to go past there.
But within the regime over here, pick the smallest point on the curve.
That's a richer class of optimizations, but it's still based on this fundamental idea
of first scoring all the points and then finding the minimum of them.
The way that you can-- so if I were to, for instance, say minimize over x this subject
to, let's say, x is less than or equal to 2, that would be something like that.
It would be a reasonable generalization of that optimization problem.
And we're going to use this in its full glory.
But this is a well-defined optimization.
I've made a scoring function for all of my possible x's.
I've said I'm limiting my search to the place where this is true.
Find me the lowest point.
That's a more robust formulation of that.
I'm able to put more information into that formulation.
So the matrix case is only a little bit more interesting, but super powerful.
I'm just going to minimize over x Ax minus b squared.
The way you do that minimization when things are unconstrained, all you have to do is you
take your cost function-- for these cost functions, these quadratic cost functions, all you need
to do is find the place where the gradient is 0, the minimum.
Since I know that this is a convex bowl pointing up, it's enough to just ask find any point
where the gradient is 0.
How do you do that?
You just take the gradient of this Ax minus b squared, which would look a little bit of
[INAUDIBLE] the whole thing, but it's not too hard to do.
You get a B transpose Ax minus x transpose A transpose B plus b squared.
Take the gradient of this.
You get 2x transpose A transpose, and you want that to be equal to 0.
You solve this for x.
You get-- well, I'll keep it in the transpose.
It's a little easier to see, I guess-- B transpose A A transpose A inverse.
And if you've ever seen the math for the pseudo inverse, this thing here is just the pseudo
inverse, or the transpose of the pseudo inverse.
That's where it comes from.
This is just the same as saying-- and that is why it's a function of only the matrices
A. It doesn't have to know about B to write A plus.
Because the solution is linear in B, you can separate them out.
So the generalization of that picture-- it's a little bit more of a test for my poor artistic
skills, but you should think about this as having some quadratic bowl.
And I had x, y, and my objective here.
Let's call it x2 and x1.
I just said there's a bunch of possible-- I'm going to take every value x.
I'm going to score it by this cost function, and I want to find the minimum of it.
The shape of that quadratic form is given by this A A transpose.
You can see the quadratic form is right there.
That's inside those parentheses.
So the shape of it is given by A transpose A.
So what happens when A starts having small singular values is that this thing starts
elongating just like this.
This picture is exactly the same.
And it can elongate maybe more in some directions or less in some other dimensions.
But this thing starts getting long and broad, and the minimum starts leaving.
It starts getting bigger and bigger.
Simple generalization of that.
Not simple, but a straightforward generalization of that.
I don't know if I'm going to say that.
So now, if I have limits on my problem, I can start putting boundaries in here and say,
still, find me the best-- let's say I don't want to cross-- this is no man's land.
Don't go past some reasonable velocities.
But within those solutions, find me the best by this score function.
So that would be the generalization is minimize subject to some other linear constraints.
It's not the only generalization, but it's the one we're going to use today.
A problem like this that has a convex quadratic objective and linear constraints is called
a quadratic program.
It's an important class of optimization problems.
This is a convex quadratic program.
I know that this bowl is going up.
Quadratic programs are not something that we think of solving with pen and paper, unless
they're very, very small.
But we have super efficient algorithms for finding them.
And we don't hesitate to run them on our robot at high speeds.
So the way that you do this, the way that you get more robust Jacobian-based controllers,
in my view, is you start using a richer language.
You say, find me the one that's doing my desired spatial velocity as closely as possible, but
respects the joint limits, acceleration limits, velocity limits of my robot.
And that's what makes these things more robust.
And there's more.
We'll talk about the last generalization.
The last piece of Drake, we talked about the systems framework.
We talked about the multi-body plant.
And that last big piece of Drake is basically trying to make it really easy to write problems
like this and connect it to the other two pieces.
You have a language where you basically say, I'm going to make a new optimization problem,
mathematical program.
Why do I mean-- mathematical programs, in my mind, are slightly bigger than optimization.
A mathematical program doesn't need to have an objective.
If it's a feasibility problem with no objective, you can still do a lot of mathematics.
But it's basically an optimization problem.
You declare your decision variables.
You can add your constraints.
In these cases, I've added a few two linear constraints in this way.
And then I add my cost function.
You could have done it in any order, of course.
And then you solve.
And you get out, in this case, the solution.
So let me try to visualize that for you.
Again, a little complicated, but worth it, I hope.
I'll find my mesh.url.
All right.
I made a 2D-- I basically took the kooka, and I froze a bunch of joints, and left only
two interesting joints to move around so that I could make it as similar as possible to
that previous example, the two-link pendulum thing.
And I'm going to plot the quadratic function, which is the optimization problem here that's
given exactly by the Jacobian.
I should write the Jacobian version of this here now.
Again, if I haven't already, it's this one here.
Sorry to ask you to stand here.
But it's this problem here, subject to a few constraints on velocities.
So what I plotted there is the cost function, which is this quadratic bowl in two variables
in this case, because that's all I can plot.
And then the red is my constraint.
The green is the optimal [INAUDIBLE] Now, already in this configuration, it's looking
a little dicey up against the velocity limit.
But let's play with that a little bit.
The same thing, I'm going to walk through the singularity, walk back and forth.
There it goes.
Through the singularity and back.
What happens when that arm's straight?
Is that a good enough angle for that?
Right?
Well, again, so it does actually go completely flat, well, depending on how clearly I integrate.
It's getting basically-- what I care about is that it's getting broader and broader and
broader and broader.
And there's a tilt to it, too.
So the optimal solution would have been a very, very large velocity.
But my constraints are saving me.
It's pegging itself at the limit and giving me a reasonable velocity out.
And you can see the Jacobians and all this.
See how it's going super long?
OK.
I mean, that's the simplest case I could visualize.
But that's what's happening when your robots are going straight.
In fact, it might have already happened to you.
If you played with the very first intro chapter differential, my little teleop example, and
you drove it a little too ambitiously towards the edge, it would have said, differential
IK is mad.
Basically, it's like, [MAKES NOISE] and it goes like this.
And it starts-- I mean, it will give solutions, but it will not match your desired velocity.
And you can say that there's hard limits, and it'll actually refuse to give an answer,
depending on what other constraints you have.
OK.
Is that clear?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
The question was, if the actual constraints are not linear, can you-- so you can choose
to try to solve a harder optimization problem.
But the standard choice and the one we make when we're driving our EWA around-- for instance,
the joint limits actually would be a nonlinear function in general.
But we approximate it with an Euler approximation, which makes it a linear constraint.
Acceleration limits are actually linear.
I mean, for any Euler kind of integration step, position and accelerations are linear.
Torque limits are not linear.
That would have to evolve the equations of motion.
The linearization there is a little more dicey, but we tend to not do the torque limits here.
So I want you to just appreciate that this is such a powerful framework.
And we're going to use it more.
This is just a quick introduction to this idea of optimization and quadratic programming.
But I wrote a version here which is trying to say, get as close as possible to the subject
of the constraint.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so the worst case here is if you're up against one limit, like on one joint, right?
And so maybe your second joint moves along as if nothing happened, and your first joint
changes, which means your hand is going off in the wrong direction.
So yes, we're going to eventually have feedback loops coming through this whole system, and
that's what's going to save us.
But even in this open loop framework, because we know about where the limits are, we can
plan for them without any direct feedback.
And we can at least do a better best effort in the beginning.
So for instance, the way that we actually-- when we run the robot, we don't run quite
the-- be as close as possible to your desired velocity in the least squares sense.
We actually do a slightly different objective.
We'd say you want your hand-- so you have some desired velocity.
Try to move your hand in the direction of that velocity.
You must pick joint angles that will move in the direction of that velocity.
And when you hit a limit, you can scale down the whole velocity, but keep the direction
the same, because we don't want our robot walking off into some-- away from the desired
trajectory.
Now, that's a richer formulation, but you can still make it work as a quadratic program.
Let me put it up and see if you can convince yourself.
This is the original proposal, but here's a slightly different one, which says constrain
me to move only in the desired direction.
We're going to maximize, actually, a linear objective.
This is actually a slightly simpler program.
My decision variables are going to be q dot and alpha.
I just want to maximize the scalar alpha subject to this idea.
So the desired spatial velocity is a vector.
I'm allowed to scale that vector, but I must choose a q dot that matches some scaled version
of that vector.
I'll make sure that alpha stays between 0 and 1.
And then I can still add joint velocities.
In fact, it's silly to write this controller.
Unless you have joint velocities or some other constraint, it would limit it.
That Roger?
Does that register?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, no, that's good.
So q dot is a decision variable.
The objective, though, is only in terms of one of the decision variables.
So these are both decision variables.
This is a vector.
This is a scalar.
The objective is only to make alpha as big as possible.
But q dot is-- the problem still defines a solution for q dot because it enters here
in the constraints.
And this is an equality constraint.
So q dot can only live on the set of possible q dots, such that q dot times my current Jacobian
moves my end effector in the direction of my desired spatial velocity.
But it could-- so if alpha is arbitrary, then if I have q dot that's the solution, I could
multiply by 2.
It would still be a solution, right?
OK.
So I could basically take the q dot that would achieve my objective without any constraints
and then scale it down, shrink q dot, but all of the joints by the same scaling in order
to satisfy these constraints.
So now if I go up and I'm about to run into something, let's say I will continue to move
in the right direction.
So actually, I won't do what I just did with my hand.
I would just stop and say, I refuse to deviate from my desired direction.
I would just-- I'd rather stop completely.
OK.
And that's what's happening inside the differential IK that you'll see as the module even in the
first notebook when I just had the teleop.
And I had to make a choice of what controller to run in that teleop and what we often run
in the robot.
This is what you'll get a lot of mileage out of this in the class is just this differential
IK controller.
It takes in-- actually poses in, does the integration for you and the differentiation
and integration for you and runs this kind of control.
Questions?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
I think this is-- so the question is, does this not fail as gracefully?
I was raving about the graceful degradation of pseudo inverse.
The pseudo inverse, for instance-- OK, you're saying compared to this one or compared to
the pseudo inverse?
This one, I see.
So I've just changed what I want as a degradation in performance.
When I have to give up performance, you can choose what you give up.
In this example, it says I want you to give me a spatial velocity out that's just as close
as possible in the least square sense to the desired spatial velocity.
This one is saying I want you to give me one-- I'm willing for it to be less close in the
numbers as long as it stays constrained in the direction.
So it's just a different choice for what I say-- how I want it to degrade when it can't
satisfy it perfectly.
In both cases, when these constraints are slowing-- if I had no constraints here, what's
going to happen?
It's going to choose alpha to be 1.
And it's going to make q dot exactly the spatial velocity.
So it'll solve the problem exactly.
And as these constraints become active, because I'm running up against them here, then alpha
will have to shrink.
And I think of that as a very graceful degradation.
In this case, if there are no limits, then again, it'll find q dot exactly to satisfy
that-- drive this objective to 0.
As it comes on, it will find a different velocity, but it might make my hand move in the wrong
direction.
I mean, you get to specify how you want it to degrade.
That's the beauty.
[END OF TRANSCRIPT]
[BLANK_AUDIO]