[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
We ready?
We good?
Welcome back, everybody.
I just heard-- I guess I was in lecture prep mode,
and I wasn't on piazza.
But I just heard the deep note is having trouble,
so I will look at that right after class.
I didn't realize, but if you're struggling with that,
I will--
I don't know.
I'll do my best to look at it right after class.
So today, we are transitioning into the first perception
set of lectures.
OK.
Now, I mean, the basic setup, I guess,
I can do my standard setup, is that so far, we've
either assumed we knew where the block was immediately,
or I actually, in some of the notebooks,
I had the system pull on the output port that
was the cheat port, I call it, from the manipulation station.
So if you look closely at the manipulation station,
it tells you what you would get from the robot, which
are the IWA positions and the shunk positions.
It doesn't tell you directly--
I mean, there's no sensors saying where the block is yet.
But we have these cheat ports that
will tell you the position and the pose
of any object in the scene.
And so I was using that as a backdoor
to figure out where the brick started
and plan everything relative to that, or I just hardcoded it.
So today, we're going to stop using those.
We're going to instead use the cameras.
So the cameras are the sensors that we have available
to see the world and to figure out where that red brick is.
And thus begins the conversation for perception.
So I mean, maybe it goes without saying,
but computer vision is hard.
It's been hard for a long time.
It got a lot better in the last few years with deep learning.
But if you think about why it's hard
and why it breaks a lot of the optimization type approaches
like we saw for kinematics, I would
say is because if you take the color
values of the pixels in an image,
this is a very bad space.
So RGB, the red, green, blue space,
the color values in an image, they
don't satisfy the sort of--
it's hard to write optimization directly
against the RGB values.
So you can have very nearby RGB values
that mean very different things in terms
of the geometry in the world and vice versa.
So you can change the lighting a lot,
and the brick's still in the same scene.
The RGB values went all over the place.
So because of this, I would say there are two
major branches of perception for robotics.
One of them continues to use geometry
but uses a different type of cameras, which gives
direct geometry information.
I'm going to tell you a little bit about them.
And the other is now sort of the more deep learning-based work.
I've separated into deep perception.
Typically, it can work directly from RGB values,
and it's becoming highly effective.
Now, even in the last year or so,
we're starting to see those two worlds collapse again.
And people are doing like NERF, if people know what NERF is,
or deep SDF.
Or you're seeing deep learning using geometry representations
and trying to combine those two again.
So it's not a surprise, maybe, but I'd
say those two streams are interesting by themselves
and are going to be hopelessly intertwined into the future.
So I mean, I do think, though, it's important.
Some people say deep learning is all you need
to do for perception right now.
And I just don't think that's true.
I think there has been this other parallel revolution,
just as--
maybe not quite as dramatic as the deep learning.
But going on very much in parallel
and getting spectacular results has
been this geometric perception pipeline.
And that's sad, like really comically sad there.
OK.
Huh.
I'm sorry, I shouldn't have unplugged that one.
I just screwed up your stream, did I?
I meant to unplug this one.
Man, the number of technical problems I've managed to have.
[AUDIO OUT]
, let's try.
Kind of ruined my flow, didn't it?
[AUDIO OUT]
It's going to make me register real quick.
That's what I didn't do, I think.
[AUDIO OUT]
Good Lord.
I'll just use my iPhone in a second here.
[AUDIO OUT]
I'm going to lecture off my iPhone.
How about that?
[AUDIO OUT]
That works fine.
It should not be better than the MIT network.
OK.
Sorry about that.
It's going to play the videos a little slower probably.
[AUDIO OUT]
OK, so there's a second revolution-- sorry for that--
based on geometric processing of the visual scene.
So you've probably seen incredible reconstructions
from autonomous driving, driving through town,
and building beautiful maps.
This is sort of the indoor equivalent of the SLAM,
if you know, the simultaneous localization and mapping.
This one is called dynamic fusion.
It's in particular tracking objects
that can change their shape or change their pose relative.
But it's just absolutely stunning
that a handful of years ago, people
started being able to build this sort of quality
reconstruction of a 3D world from a camera
that you can fit in your pocket.
In fact, I've got one in my pocket right here.
Yeah, look at that.
These kind of cameras, right?
I don't always have them in my pocket.
But-- oh, that's not true actually,
because I do always have one in my pocket.
There's one right there too, right?
Which is pretty awesome.
So that has been fueled by a lot of different things.
I mean, robotics is a good enterprise.
But I would say robotics by itself
might not have been enough fuel for this.
But now augmented reality, like Facebook Labs,
is working on this.
It was originally Oculus.
And the people that did this work became Oculus,
became Facebook Reality Labs.
So it's being powered by those kind of revolutions.
So let's just think a little bit about these different types
of sensors, and why are they different than a standard
camera, and why did they help robotics jump into the
perception age, I would say.
There's a couple different types out there.
You've probably heard of LIDAR, the laser range finders.
These are based on time of flight, where they're actually
shooting out an active laser, and then waiting for the
return, and measuring the distance.
And some of these are just crazy good, right?
So even a year ago, there was these 500 meter range luminars
coming out where a car can drive through it.
It can basically see the whole city, it feels like.
And it's just building highly accurate geometric models as
it's driving down the street.
It's crazy good.
And you see these kind of--
I don't know if that's actually processed, or that
could just be a raw return.
Some of the raw returns from these cameras
just look spectacular.
I mean, the resolution degrades the farther you go, but it's
still crazy good.
And when these started happening, this started
powering a lot of the geometric work in robotics
perception.
Stereo imaging is still a thing.
It's an important thing, where you'll see stereo heads that
were the classic approach to building
sensors for perception.
This is actually the Carnegie head, which is stuck in the
middle of Atlas, which is the humanoid robot from at least
the version of Atlas we have upstairs, carried around this
stereo pair head.
And basically, the basic principle, there's two cameras.
And it's comparing the two images, trying to find similar
blocks in the left and right image, and then saying how
different are those blocks in the image using the distance
between the lenses and figuring out the depth.
There's many different ways to do it, but basically, a simple
block matching stereo is a perfectly good way to do it.
Each of these have different pros and cons.
I'll tell you about the ones we picked.
I'll tell you most about the one we picked.
Structured light, it was the Microsoft
Kinect came out.
This was considered a major advance for indoor.
LiDAR was traditionally considered for outdoor
applications, and it works in natural light, whereas the
Kinect was one of the first things that powered the indoor
perception revolution.
And the fact that they became so cheap because they were
sold with game consoles was a big, big deal.
I think that really opened up the number of people that were
playing with them and just really
bootstrapped the research.
So the structured light approach is you're projecting
some image onto the scene, which allows you to then, by
taking a picture, have far more information than you
would have had with just random pixels coming in.
But the one that we're going to use that I have in my
pocket here is an Intel RealSense D415.
They're pretty small, pretty nice.
This is actually a projected texture stereo.
The RealSense line and the Intel line has a handful of
different technologies, but this is the projected texture
stereo version.
So it's basically a stereo camera, except that it's also
got a little projector, obviously, that's just pushing
out some pattern of light.
So that if you were to look at--
if you take stereo images of a purely white wall, then
there's nothing that it could possibly do to compare those
images to get a reasonable depth.
But if you project an invisible pattern, an IR pattern even,
on the wall, then there's still something that it can
see in order to get good depth information.
And in general, it reduces the reliance on the textures in
the world, because it's providing its own texture.
Compared to things like LiDAR and other time of flight
technologies, one of the reasons we like this is
because they don't interfere with each other.
So it actually doesn't care what the--
so compared to the structured light, where it's trying to
set up a certain pattern out, this one's just putting out
any old pattern.
It just wants to have texture.
It doesn't care--
it's not trying to match a specific pattern.
It's just trying to make sure that there's not
sameness everywhere.
So if you have two cameras pointing at the same scene,
and they're both projecting texture, no big deal.
It's still getting good returns.
Whereas a lot of the other cameras before that, you had
to really synchronize your multiple cameras to make sure
they weren't hitting--
sending active pulses at the same time.
It was a major, major pain.
And we do use multiple cameras.
I'll show you in a minute the number of cameras we put
around that dish-loading example.
But this is new news.
This is August 17th this year.
Super sad.
I don't really use emojis, but I almost put a sad emoji on
here, right?
I don't really know what I'm going to do.
But it's really bad news for the field.
I mean, we're bummed.
There's not a great replacement yet.
I mean, there's more technologies out there, but
the RealSense has become a favorite for sure.
And I think we're--
I don't know.
We're just too small as a field to matter.
But they're selling them, but I guess they're
not selling enough.
So I don't know what we'll be using next year in class.
But we've got a bunch of RealSenses.
We're going to hang on to them, keep using them as long
as we can.
OK.
So we have the ability to simulate these cameras, of
course, in the simulation.
But we simulate them in various levels of fidelity.
OK?
So the simplest one, and the one we'll use for most of the
class, is just a standard OpenGL renderer.
OK?
So OpenGL is sort of the basic graphics language that's
existed forever.
It's not particularly fancy in the way it does lighting.
Or it's capable, but not compared to the new game
engine quality technologies.
But it's fast.
And it's got GPU acceleration.
And it's definitely faster than real time.
OK.
So let me just step you through.
This is just a diagram from a very simple system that has an
object, a single object in the scene.
Turns out it's a mustard bottle.
OK.
And so we've got a multi-body plant, which is just holding
the mustard bottle, not doing anything interesting.
We've got the scene graph, which is the geometry engine.
And we now can take an RGB sensor and add a new sensor
into the diagram.
It hooks right up to the scene graph.
OK.
It's just another system.
It reads geometry.
It has a message passing with the scene graph to get the
geometry information.
And it spits out color image, but also depth image in a
couple different channels.
And a label image for when you want to train your machine
learning algorithms.
You can say per pixel what object is it associated with.
And you can have it spit out the pose of the sensor.
OK.
So RGBD for red, green, blue, and depth sensors.
It's just one more channel that gives you a
depth signal back.
OK.
And the images that come out are the standard--
you take the first three channels, the
standard RGB images.
You get something that looks like this out.
There's a little mustard bottle.
And then there's an image that's the same number of
pixels, the same size, which just says for every pixel,
what's the distance to the object in the scene?
The first return, right?
Or NAN if it's too far.
Actually, it's not NAN.
There's a particular integer for that.
OK.
So you'll see this come slowly into MeshCat here.
So in MeshCat, you can push the point clouds out to the
renderer, too.
So first of all, I drew the camera with the camera
coordinates here.
So you can see red, green, blue, remember?
So x, y, z.
Right?
So in order to get the images that we saw, we wanted the
camera oriented like this.
It's a little bit hard to think about.
I put it at a little bit of a tilt in order to get a little
bit of an angle on the shot.
OK?
But you can go in and navigate through MeshCat.
You can turn on and off the geometry from scene graph.
And you can turn on and off the point cloud.
But there's a point cloud in there giving you the same sort
of the raw information, I guess, from the cameras.
Right?
Now, the camera only sees one side of the object.
And that's a big part of what we have to take care of in
perception is the fact that we only get partial views.
Right?
So it's not going to be enough to assume you could see all
parts of the object and match all parts of the object.
When you have occlusions, when you have multiple objects in
the scene, it gets even worse.
And the best perception systems can do a lot with very
partial views.
OK.
I said we like to just not worry about the cameras
interfering.
OK?
But this is a little ridiculous, I would say.
We just didn't want to worry about whether we had enough
cameras or we wanted to avoid partial views as much as
possible, so we put a bunch of cameras all over the place.
And we would do things like use some cameras to train the
other cameras.
There were multiple reasons for it.
But we instrumented the world with plenty of cameras, OK?
Including two on the wrist.
Right?
So right on the wrist of the robot, there's
two right there.
We'll mount them in various places.
The robot that we tried to bring in--
we successfully brought the robot in, but the cage had to
be disassembled.
And the cage had--
the standard cage we had around it was there primarily to hold
the cameras in fixed locations and have a nice view down into
the scene.
So we're going to talk mostly today about relatively
simple-- like clean point clouds.
And thinking about what you do if the point clouds are giving
you pure geometry information.
But next time, we're going to go into the fact that the real
point clouds are pretty messy.
OK?
So I'm just--
introduce the idea of it here, but we're going to dig more
into it with our methods next time.
So this is a simulated depth return for
this kind of a scene.
OK?
And this is what you actually get out of
the real depth camera.
Now you notice it's not Gaussian noise.
OK?
So it's not like I take every pixel and I pull a random
number and I change the depth value by some Gaussian number.
It's much more stereotypical than that.
It tends to happen on the edges of objects, right?
Where the normals are not very incident to the camera.
OK?
That's a typical place where you don't get good returns or
don't get good depth images.
Or if one camera can't-- or if both cameras can't see the
side of an object or something like that.
There's other--
so transparent or reflective surfaces are all-- there's
things like this that are the canonical bad
cases for these cameras.
There was a great project actually by the same Facebook
group where they were mapping the inside of homes and they
wanted to build these beautiful 3D
maps of indoor homes.
And the problem is people have windows and
people have mirrors.
So they actually--
they had a very clever--
I'll actually talk about it later.
But they have a very clever trick for figuring out how to
work with mirrors and windows.
OK, so this is just an example--
another example of-- this is the D415 where Cooney is
looking at some Legos and vegetables and random stuff on
his table, OK?
But if you scroll around the 3D-- the same way I scrolled
around the mustard bottle, he's got the camera above.
The camera's not moving.
This is just looking at the point cloud that's coming out
from different angles.
I would say there's one word that everybody always uses
when they talk about the point clouds out of D415--
lumpy.
Everybody says lumpy.
It's like--
it doesn't seem like a word that would come to--
but I've heard a lot of people say, yeah, yeah, those are
lumpy point clouds.
And it just has this characteristic ripple, OK?
And if your carrots or whatever are like about the
same size as your lumps, things get pretty dicey.
So that wasn't meant to be a joke.
OK.
So that's our setup.
Let's start thinking about how to do work with point clouds
and how to go from depth to point clouds and why, as you
can see here, that thinking about point clouds is actually
a kinematics problem.
So I hope it blends nicely from what we did last time.
OK.
I'll start here.
So there's many representations of 3D data, of
3D geometry, let me say.
OK.
The one that we were just illustrating there is called a
point cloud.
OK.
So typically, this would be a--
let's say a 3 by n matrix, OK, where this is the x, y, z
positions in a Cartesian frame.
And this is the number of pixels or number of points.
OK.
It can also be--
you can also have RGB values.
You can also have normal information.
There are a couple other things that you can--
extra information you can add to the point cloud.
But the first thing we'll think about is just x, y, z
positions in space that are a point that I got from a--
indirectly from a depth camera.
OK.
I mean, a depth image, like we got directly out of the
camera, is also, in some sense, a
representation of 3D geometry.
But it's not enough by itself.
You also need to know, let's say, the camera info.
I'll get more detailed about that later.
But in order to turn that 2D image into a 3D point cloud,
you need to know something about the geometry of the
camera, and potentially even the location in space.
There are other representations of 3D
geometry, too.
I mean, you can do triangular meshes.
Some of you will have heard of signed distance
representations.
And this has led to things like NERF, which I will say
more carefully later.
Voxel grids are another one, or occupancy grids.
OK.
So for the most part, I want you to--
we're going to think about these kind of the same way we
thought about rotations, where there are many, many
different types of representations for the
geometry.
There are ways to go back and forth between them.
And for different algorithms, they have different virtues.
So sometimes we'll choose to use the point cloud directly.
Sometimes it's better to use the depth image or signed
distance function.
The only caveat, the only place that that analogy breaks is
that in the rotation representations, we could go
back and forth without any loss of information.
Whereas here, sometimes you have to be careful.
You might actually lose information when you go across
one of these boundaries.
But in general, I think the healthy attitude--
so oftentimes people will be like, oh, I have a new
algorithm.
I just realized you could do everything in
signed distance functions.
And I think the people that have thought about perception
a long time think, well, the representations are basically
the same.
You're not discovering something.
It's like, really just think about this as a library of
representations you can go back and forth between.
We're going to focus today on the point cloud
representation, because it plays very well with the
kinematics of finding an object, finding our red brick.
OK.
Here's the setup.
I've got some geometry in my world.
Got some multicolored chalk.
OK.
And let's say I've taken my camera.
I'm just going to do it in 2D, because I have a 2D blackboard.
But you can generalize it to 3D easily enough.
So I've got some camera.
And let's just say I was able to see all sides of it to
start.
We'll pretend we had maybe multiple cameras looking at it
and we assembled some point cloud where we got nice,
evenly distributed points from all over the object.
OK.
So we'll call our object O and our object frame O. OK.
So I want to distinguish between two sets of points.
OK.
We're going to think about the points.
Well, we're going to do two things.
We're going to have the points that are coming out of the
camera, which we tend to call those the scene points.
OK.
So if I have a camera and I've taken my depth camera and I've
projected the points into the 3D world, then I'm going to
have a bunch of scene points.
And they're going to come in the camera frame.
OK.
And our job, our task, is to try to figure out the pose of
this object using the scene points that
are coming in here.
Now, there's many ways to do it.
But we're going to start with an algorithm that, since we're
working with points on this side, we're going to go ahead
and represent our object.
Again, we have multiple--
you could think of it as represented as a mesh or by a
sine distance function or lots of different options.
But our object, our known geometry that we're looking
for, I'm going to go ahead and represent that geometry with a
set of points, too.
And we'll call that the model points.
And that's going to be represented in the object
frame.
So basically, you start off.
You know the thing you're looking for.
The way you describe it is by a set of points that I hope to
find in the world.
And then I'm getting scene points actually measured.
And my job is going to be to somehow find the relationship
between these scene points and the model points, both in
terms of the pose and in terms of mapping those two,
figuring out which scene point goes with which model point.
OK.
So let's assume that we know--
this is the camera's pose in the world.
Let's say we know that.
We can measure it.
We can calibrate it.
Our task is going to be to estimate the object's pose in
the world.
Right?
Camera's viewing the world, giving about a
bunch of depth returns.
Now, we're going to make a bunch of
assumptions to start.
OK.
We're going to assume that the only scene points that come in
that are in our point cloud are from the actual object.
It's never like that.
Normally, you have your object.
You have the table.
You have all these spurious points that are coming in.
It's never that simple.
But to start off, let's just assume that we have only the
scene points.
We'll talk about how to generalize that soon.
AUDIENCE: Are we assuming that we know the model points?
PROFESSOR: Yes, we assume that these are known.
This object is known.
Right?
So this would be finding a known object in the scene, not
understanding some new object you've never seen before.
And we're going to make another assumption, huge
assumption, but even this lecture will get around.
OK?
Let's assume that we know the correspondences.
What do we mean by correspondence?
That's an important word that's going to come up over
and over again.
If I have my canonical model, which has some number of
points, my model points, if I had enough colors, I would
make each of these different colors possibly.
But OK.
There's something you're doing immediately with your
impressive vision system is you're realizing that this
point goes with that point, this point
goes with that point.
Right?
You're corresponding the points based on your
understanding of the object.
OK?
These are the correspondences.
And I'm going to just assume, even just to keep the
notation the same, that this is--
I'll call this 0.1, 0.2, 0.3, go around, and I'll assume
that these are correctly ordered so that model point i
actually corresponds to scene point i.
Yeah?
Do you mean that if I line these up, that they actually
match up, or that there's just some relationship that
could satisfy the epsilon on top of--
Yeah, yeah.
So I'm starting with they actually line up, one to one
matching, and we're going to quickly
remove that assumption.
So it's crazy.
That's never going to happen.
OK.
Maybe I'll go over here.
So given our kinematics and our frames and our
understanding, we know that we can put everything into the
world frame, right?
So that the models--
let's see, I'll do--
I can take my model points, which are
specified in object frame.
There's some pose of the object that would transform me
into the world frame.
And similarly, I want that to match the scene points, one to
one matching because I've assumed correspondences.
And the scene points are given by this.
But I can go ahead and just--
because this is known and this is known, I can just
pre-compute that and just work with this as my object.
OK.
So given that, the question is, how do I
reconstruct xw, x, o, in w?
This is very much an inverse kinematics problem.
Right?
Right.
Given the end effectors, it's very much similar to if I had
my robot arm and I had my gripper desired end effector,
I need to figure out what the joint angles are.
OK, here I've got my points that are associated and I want
to figure out what the Q, or in this case it's represented
directly as a pose, of that object is.
Now last time we didn't actually do
inverse kinematics.
Right?
We did forward kinematics, then we did differential
kinematics, then we did differential inverse
kinematics, but we never did inverse kinematics.
Right?
So we did Jacobians, everything.
This time we're actually going to do inverse kinematics.
We're going to actually solve this directly.
Why not differential this time?
Why am I not going to immediately
talk about Jacobians?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Right.
So what would be the closest notion?
So the comment there was that there's not an analogous
notion, I'm saying, that there's not an analogous
notion of the joint measurements, for instance, in
the camera space.
But if I had a current pose, I could ask, what is an
incremental change in my model points relative--
if I were to make an incremental change in this
pose, how do my scene points change?
I could still ask the differential question.
So I think it's possible we could still do differential
kinematics.
And in fact, we will do differential kinematics for
perception when we want to do things like tracking objects.
But unfortunately, we have to solve a harder problem for
perception to start.
The EWA, we always have joint measurements that tell me what
position I'm in right now.
And I can ask, given I'm in this position, what's an
increment going to do?
In the perception problem, the robot has to
wake up at some point.
And for the first time, look at a bunch of points and solve
a harder problem of figuring out where am I at all.
I can't do an incremental change until I have something
to start from.
So I have to solve this sort of more global problem first
in order to start this.
Did I say that well enough?
You guys didn't look totally with me on that.
OK.
Basically, I don't have an initial guess for the pose.
If I had an initial guess, I could say, if I change that
initial guess a little bit, then how would it change?
But I don't have a close initial guess such that local
changes of it are going to get me where I need to be.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Could you explain why this version of the problem
is harder compared to the differential version?
Is it computation complexity or something?
PROFESSOR: The question is, so why is this version of the
problem harder?
Why do I say this is the global problem which is harder?
So the short answer is that basically, the differential
problem is that locally, you're solving a bunch of
linear equations all the time.
And we did write convex problems in order to track it.
So our quadratic programming approach to differential
inverse kinematics was an excellent solution.
When you don't have that initial guess, then you have
to solve the harder problem where it might have multiple
local minima.
And in general, you have to find the needle
in the haystack.
It's not about tracking something that
you've already found.
It's about finding it for the first time.
And because there are lots of different--
we're going to see when we write the equations down why
there are local minima that come up.
But you might think, that clump of points over here is my
brick, no, that could be that point.
There could be something very different that would be close
matches to your points.
So it's a harder problem.
It does translate all the way down to computational
complexity, but that's not the simplest way to see it.
So let's think about this problem here.
I want you to see this as basically a linear problem.
So why is that a linear problem?
So I can write x w o o m i equals psi.
This is given.
We have to solve for this.
You can write this as p o w plus r o w p o m i.
OK.
Where this is the position of the frame,
and this is the rotation of that frame.
And in particular, if we now choose 3 by 3 rotation matrices
as a representation of this, then this equation
is actually a matrix equation.
I'm not just hiding behind spatial algebra
to make that true.
This is actually a matrix, a 3 by 3 matrix,
times a 3 by 1 vector.
And this equation should match.
So I can write this, this being multiplied
like this in this structure.
When I see that, I think the problem I'm trying to solve
is linear in my parameters, my decision parameters.
So I hope you see this as being Ax, maybe
equal to approximately equal to b.
But you have to be a little careful,
because what's in x?
What are the things I'm trying to solve for?
In order to write this out, you have
to shuffle and flip and reorient,
because x is actually holding inside it p w o and r w o
rolled out into a long vector.
A actually has-- what does it have?
It has this hiding inside the A plus a bunch of 1's
to get that term.
And b is that term.
But if I see this, I see a linear set of equations.
Now because, as Alex points out, it's
ridiculous to assume that you have exactly
overlap all the time, asking that to be exactly
equal for a whole bunch of points from a sensor
that we know is going to be a little bit noisy,
we know it's not going to match all the points.
It's too much to say, here's a bunch of equations,
make that equality hold.
So just like last time, we're going
to write the softer version of this as an optimization
problem.
So what I'd like to do instead is roughly this.
I'll see you in just a second.
I'll even just-- I can call my decision variables
whatever I like here.
So p r p plus r.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Ah.
I'm going to get to that in a second.
Yeah.
OK, so we're close to this.
OK?
This is the direct translation from this.
Now Alex made an excellent point,
which I should have repeated, which
is that there's something wrong with the formulation
that I've written here.
If I search over all p's and all r's,
then there's nothing guaranteeing that I'll get
a rotation matrix out.
If I've chosen a 3 by 3 rotation matrices,
then I need something else to guarantee
that I'm going to actually get a rotation matrix out.
Right?
So the conditions to make a rotation matrix
are additional constraints, just like we
added in the QP formulation for the kinematics.
You can write it a bunch of different ways.
Roughly, you need r to be orthonormal.
OK?
And you need the determinant of r to be positive 1.
This is equivalent to saying that r transpose is r inverse.
OK?
But we'll use this form of it.
OK.
Those are the constraints that will guarantee
that if we solve this optimization problem subject
to those constraints, then we'll get a good rotation matrix.
Now this, because of this Ax minus b,
this is a nice quadratic objective in the sense
that it's convex.
Should just say convex.
What is this?
The decision variables are the elements of r.
OK?
So this is actually nine constraints
that I've written in this matrix form,
where all the elements of this thing
have to equal the elements of this thing.
OK?
And each of those nine constraints
is quadratic in the elements of r.
I get r1 times r1 plus whatever.
OK?
So this is nine quadratic equality constraints.
And then this one is actually worse.
Anybody know what the determinant of 3 by 3 matrix
r's are?
What degree-- how the coefficients of r enter that?
You can look up your determined formula,
and you can-- the 3 by 3 determinant
is just a sum of 2 by 2 determinants, whatever,
multiply.
But this is basically cubic in coefficients of r.
OK?
So this one's beautiful.
This up here, beautiful.
As with my optimization hat on, this is beautiful.
This one's like, eh, don't love that.
But we can maybe deal with that.
I know a bit about how to do quadratic equality constraints.
Cubic-- I hate that one.
OK?
So here's what most people do, is we're just going to--
let's pretend that one's not there,
and we'll deal with it later.
OK?
Because it really does make the optimization hard.
That's an ugly nonlinear constraint, the cubic one.
Fortunately, if this is true, if we satisfy this,
then the determinant can actually only be plus or minus
1.
So basically, we'll solve it.
We'll check if the determinant is plus or minus 1.
If it was minus 1, we'll make our correction and resolve.
OK?
And that works out.
Because writing that constraint directly is gross.
OK, so a couple questions, just to make
sure you're following with me.
So if I have 10 points from my object,
how many decision variables do I have?
Mi and Si are-- there's 10 points.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Right.
The number of decision variables does not
change with the number of points.
I've got 3 by 3 matrix here, and 3 by 1 vector here.
All that I'm doing, if I have more variables,
I've just changed my objective function.
I have more terms in this.
They sum up.
OK?
But I still only have nine decision variables.
The number of decision variables does not
depend on the number of points in the scene.
OK.
So even this problem, the quadratically constrained
quadratic objective, that's not a great problem.
OK?
In general, we would have to relax it
to do nice work with it.
It turns out that this particular problem
has a beautiful solution, the closed form solution,
given the singular value decomposition.
It's one of those quirks where there's
a bunch of sets of things we know how to solve beautifully
with optimization.
There's a bunch of things we can solve
a bunch of different ways.
They're all the same set.
And then there's SVD, which solves these weird problems
that I don't know totally how to connect.
This problem, we are going to have a good solution for.
But I want you to have a little bit of geometric--
the same way I tried to draw the QPs last time,
I'm going to try to draw this optimization problem for you
so you can have some intuition about what's happening.
To do that, let's do it in 2D real quick.
OK?
I hope it will also help you work through the mechanics.
So in 2D, remember our rotation matrices
are now 2 by 2 matrices.
We know that they always have the canonical form, right?
The cosine theta, negative sine theta, sine theta, cos theta.
That's just background knowledge.
OK?
But I'm not going to use theta as my decision variables.
That would be a-- if I tried to search over thetas,
then I would have this nonlinear dependence
through cosine and sine of that.
And that would be a harder optimization.
OK?
I want to leverage the fact that this was a linear term here,
which turned into a quadratic objective.
So I have to use the coefficients of r, not theta.
You know, I can't make the coefficients of r
nonlinearly depend on my decisions.
OK?
So I could just do ABCD as my parameterization.
In general, in the 3 by 3 case, that is roughly what you do.
You would fill out the whole 3 by 3 matrix.
OK?
In this case, in 2 by 2, everything's better in 2D.
In 2D, you know if you have an orthonormal matrix,
then you have to have this relationship where I can say--
I know that's going to be true.
In order for the orthonormal vector--
there is exactly one orthonormal vector to this, and it's that.
OK?
So this is going to be my parameterization.
Let's assume that the position is 0 or known,
just so I can plot the--
I make a graph over--
I'm going to basically plot A and B,
and then I want to plot my objectives and my constraints
on top of that.
OK?
So the objective, we said, is going
to be quadratic in the coefficients of A and B.
So A and B, when I multiply things through here,
each term here is going to be linear until I square it.
So what's that going to look like as a function of A and B?
It's going to be a positive quadratic, because it's
this nice squared form.
It's going to look like a nice bowl somewhere in my state
space--
in my variable space here.
So I expect that to look like some bowl,
just like I had last time.
Now, what do the constraints look like?
If I have R, R transpose equals I, that's equivalent--
I write this out.
What is that going to be?
So that's going to give me two different constraints.
I get A squared plus B squared has to equal 1.
What's this guy here?
A squared plus B squared equals 1.
And the off-diagonal-- oops--
the off-diagonal says that AB minus BA equals 0.
That one's vacuously true, so we don't even
need to include it in our optimization.
It happens that saying the determinant of R
equals plus 1 in 2D, it's just this quadratic again,
and it gives me the same constraint.
So I've already got that one covered.
I'm guaranteed to have a determinant of plus 1
because I did this trick.
If I had independently parameterized those,
I would need to have this constraint.
When you have a determinant that's minus 1,
that gives you these rotorotations, they're called.
So that would be like my vector doing a rotation and a flip.
And so by parameterizing this, this is like AB.
This is, if you think about it, is A negative B, or negative BA.
This is-- that's what I've done here,
is parameterized those.
This way, so that's only going to give me positive rotations.
The rotor rotation would have been down here.
I hope I'm not-- I hope I'm saying that well enough
to be useful.
Good, OK, so we have a quadratic objective over B and A.
And we have a constraint, which is a quadratic constraint,
A squared plus B squared equals 1.
So that's going to be the circle, the unit circle on here.
Now, remember that the number of points, that's true no matter
how many scene points I put in.
So I can make a problem, a real problem, in 2D
and have lots of scene points and just build up
this different quadratic objective
and quadratic constraint.
And that's what I've done here.
So I've got a real object that I cast some scene points from.
And I can turn the object, so I move the data points.
I've got theta parameterizing my turn.
That's just for my GUI, really, to change the problem data.
And the quadratic form, in order to minimize that objective,
is moving around.
The cool thing is, it wants to be--
can you see what's happening here?
I hope I can do this without redefining anything.
There we go.
You see what's happening there?
That's the-- that disk is the unit circle constraint just
projected up.
The minimum of that quadratic form, it wants to be at the--
of course, because in order to make those points match
through a rotation, it's going to find a rotation that is--
in order to make those points match,
it's going to find an actual rotation.
It's not going to try to shrink anything.
It's not going to try to expand anything.
So in the noise-free case, it's beautiful and good.
If I rotate the object, then I get a different quadratic form
that moves around.
And that constraint actually doesn't have to do any work.
Now, as soon as you have noise, or you
have bad correspondences, or anything like that,
then what's going to happen is the objective,
in order to match my data, the objective
is going to get more complicated.
And it could move away from the unit circle.
And that constraint is going to pull me back.
Now, we're going to come back to that later,
when we think about a convex relaxation.
Oh, that's cool.
Didn't mean to do that.
New trick.
So in general, we might eventually
relax the unit circle constraint to the unit disk.
So it's easier to write an optimization problem that says
I'm anywhere inside of the circle,
not just on the boundary of the circle.
The boundary of a circle is a non-convex set.
But I can say I'm inside a circle,
including the interior.
And then we're going to see things
like the optimization is tight.
It will give me the right answer if the quadratic form is
pulling me outside.
But when it goes inside, I start getting some errors.
And that's going to be--
even in the most advanced, like, SDP relaxations-- sorry,
the semi-definite programming relaxations of point cloud
registration that you'll read in papers these years that
are still coming out, you're going to see them saying,
oh, it's tight often.
But there's some cases where it's not tight.
It's exactly this picture.
It's when it's sliding inside.
It's not.
OK.
Changing the number of points will change the shape
of my quadratic bowl.
But it doesn't move that constraint.
And in the noise-free case, it's not going to move the minimum.
So that's the picture I want you to have in your head.
OK.
Let's make sure you're fully with me here.
So here's a couple immediate things that come to mind.
My box is symmetric.
It has rotational symmetry, especially--
I mean, even if it's a rectangle,
it's got some symmetry.
If it's a cube, it's got lots of symmetry, right?
So how do symmetries affect the algorithm?
How would they change that picture?
My object was suddenly symmetric, or even circular,
or something.
How would that change that picture?
[INAUDIBLE]
What's that?
We have-- what would it have to do to that picture?
The objective is quadratic.
So it can't go up and then go back down.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
So it's going across both places, right?
Yeah.
This is all the right stuff to think about.
But it can never happen in this case,
because we assumed correspondences.
So there's no such thing as symmetry,
because even if I draw a point that looks like this,
the fact that I had a magic correspondence function,
even if I were to rotate this, it would correspond to--
I've already broken the symmetry by assigning a correspondence.
So the pictures you have in your head about symmetries
in the correspondence case are wrong.
That sounded mean.
We're going to solve the correspondence problem
in a second.
But when you think of that picture,
I would immediately think, OK, how
does it handle the symmetries case?
And you don't have to handle the symmetries case.
It does not handle the symmetries case.
Another fun one.
I won't belabor it, but you think
about what's the minimum number of points
that you need for this problem to have a unique solution.
It's almost what you think, but it
might be a little bit more or less than you think.
You can do it by just counting the number of decision
variables and counting the number of constraints.
If you assume that the points are unique,
so if the points landed on top of each other,
that would be a degenerate case.
But if you assume the points are unique,
then you can just play a counting game
and figure out how many parameters you need.
And it'll give you a slightly different answer
if you use this clever parameterization in 2D
versus the four parameters.
But it's all good.
You can completely understand this.
But let's dig into this a little bit more.
So this correspondence function was just
too big of an assumption.
But that's what made our optimization magically good.
The fact that you can solve that, in fact,
in a closed form with a call to the singular value
decomposition, which is as close as you get numerically,
I guess, to a closed form solution.
That's amazing.
So let's lean on it and come up with an algorithm that
solves for the correspondences and the poses simultaneously.
OK.
The case that we're going to use to think about it
is imagine that you've gotten yourself
close to the right answer.
So I've got my real object and I've got my measured object.
So let's say I'm sort of close.
Then a reasonable heuristic would
be to basically assign the correspondences based
on what's close to me.
The true correspondence is this.
But let's just examine as a heuristic.
Given my current guess, this goes back
to the differential IK case.
So let's think about it sort of in a differential way, where
I've got an initial guess and I want to improve it.
So what if I use as a heuristic--
let me pretend that my correspondences are whichever
point I find on the other one that is closest
in a Euclidean sense.
And maybe the mapping might not be unique.
It could be that I map multiple points to the same--
multiple model points to the same scene point or vice versa.
Typically, you pick one because you search through--
you search through either your model points
and find the closest scene point or vice versa.
OK?
All right.
So let's say we just assign the correspondences that way,
based on the closest points.
What would that look like in our optimization?
Well, in this, we need a slightly refined notation
here.
If I write-- let me call it Cj or Ci for correspondence i
equals j.
OK?
This is a model point i corresponds to scene point j
that I can write that my thing that I'm searching for here--
model-- I'm going to just use the Ci here--
minus Pwsi squared as my objective.
This is just the Euclidean distance.
Right?
So for each C-- for each of these model points,
I can just look through this.
I can just try all of my possible correspondences
and find the closest point.
That would be something like saying that Ci is like an arg
min over j of Mj.
OK?
So just look through the points, find the closest one,
and write it into Ci.
OK?
This is the closest point.
Now, I don't need any constraints here,
because in this case, now this is the decision variable,
and this is fixed.
Right?
So that's not-- I don't have to worry about that not
being a rotation matrix.
That's just fixed.
It's a constant.
OK.
The iterative closest point algorithm,
one of the most famous algorithms in point
registration, is just this.
It's called ICP.
OK?
It just says, take an initial guess of my pose,
solve this problem, OK?
Find the correspondences, then solve that problem,
then solve this problem, then solve that problem.
OK?
And iterate until convergence.
Convergence is simple.
It's an integer-based convergence, right?
Once my correspondences don't change,
because that solves to global optimality,
if the correspondences don't change,
then that one's not going to do any work.
So you have a complete-- it's not like a floating point
convergence.
It's like iterations are done.
No more work to do.
Convergence.
Yes?
Is it a chance to always converge?
Is it guaranteed to always converge?
It is certainly not guaranteed to always converge
to the right solution.
There are local minima.
You can find yourself attached, corresponding
to the wrong points, and unable to get out.
It should always converge, I think.
I can't imagine a case where-- is there a way it would
oscillate?
It's a good question.
I don't know for sure.
But I think the most important point
is it won't necessarily converge to the right solution.
So you can certainly get yourself into traps.
OK, this is a real algorithm.
People use it all the time.
No, not on this side.
This is one step of the algorithm
would be just find the closest points.
I have a shaded blue object, and the other object
being the transformed object in the pink.
Just find the closest point.
And if you're-- this is with known correspondences, I guess.
Then the match is correct, and it
solves the global optimization.
And I made a bunch of cutesy animations.
Oh, that's not mine.
This is the Stanford bunny.
But that's the classic iterative closest point graphic
you could find all over the place.
So there's a lot of points there.
You can do this at scale.
I forgot to stick in my cutesy graphics.
Shoot.
But you can do this at scale.
In order to scale it up, that problem, again,
doesn't get bigger.
The objective gets-- there's more terms in the objective.
But the decision variables doesn't change.
That's fine.
This one, the only thing you want to do
is make that closest point query faster.
So you use clever data structures
to make that closest point query faster.
In particular, we'll use FLAN, which
is a Fast Nearest Neighbor algorithm,
in order to make that work.
But once you do that, it scales to big problems.
And it's practically useful.
So this is a close-up view of the wrist
camera of the dish-loading robot when it's picking up a mug.
Now, why do you think--
right here.
It stops.
You see that little chuk-chuk-chuk-chuk?
And then it goes?
What do you think's happening there?
So it's got a deep perception system, finding mugs,
doing planning.
Gets all close.
But before it picks anything up, it
takes a nice shot with the wrist-mounted camera.
And it does some ICP registration
to align the point clouds right in the hand frame,
kik-kik-kik-kik, in order to grab.
So for real applications, if you will--
I mean, almost real applications, right?
Then this is actually a very good algorithm for--
especially when you are close to a good solution
and you want to refine it.
In general, the deep perception approaches
are going to do better at the global problem of,
I've got-- I don't know where it is in the scene.
But for the local problems, the geometric often
are still state of the art.
And I should say, a couple of things
to note about that application.
So you have to be careful.
Why don't you just get right close to picking the mug up
when you do that, right?
So as you get closer to the geometry,
the depth cameras have a minimum throw, a minimum range, right?
So if you get too close, things start
disappearing from your point cloud.
It's kind of frustrating.
You think, oh, the perfect place for a camera?
I'll put it in my hand.
And then it's like, you can't see anything
because you've got a minimum range, OK?
So there's some sweet spot where you get just--
depending on which camera you've mounted on your hand,
you get to a certain distance.
You take your best possible point cloud, and off you go.
But even when we use-- we still use these kind of algorithms
even for our deep learning pipeline.
So this is an early version of a tool
that has gotten very mature in many labs nowadays,
where in order to train a deep learning system, which
we will do, we have some CAD models.
We have some raw perception data.
Like, we took our drill and put it in the space.
And we just want to come up with ground truth labels
of real world data.
We have a human give our initial guess.
So the human says, it's around here, here, here, three clicks.
And then that's a good enough initial guess
that our ICP can go in and do the rest of the work.
We label the images as saying that I
know that I have pixels there that correspond to the drill.
And then I can back out actually all of the different frames
that I took now know exactly where the drill is.
And you can label-- with a few clicks from the human,
you can give a huge training set to a deep network.
So it really is-- even though it's our starter algorithm,
it really is still a useful algorithm.
Let me just end by pointing out a couple things for today.
We're going to talk more about the noisy case soon.
But let me just-- I think right here on the board,
we already have a couple examples that
would show some of its limitations.
One of those limitations is extreme sensitivity
to outliers.
If I happen to have a beautiful point cloud
around my measured object, and then, I don't know,
two extra points way over here, then in my quadratic form,
I'm going to-- well, sorry.
The original thing-- so if it never corresponds to that,
you're fine.
But if you get to the point where this thing is pulling you
in the wrong direction, then you can
have what looks like a pretty good point cloud,
have one point pulling me in the wrong direction,
totally skew my objective and compromise my results.
So there is a sensitivity of the outliers.
As soon as you get inside where your argmin is only
matching the real object, then things tend to be fairly OK.
But if your closest point captures some outlier,
then things get bad.
And especially because the cost of the outliers,
the cost you penalize basically by the length of these rubber
bands, roughly.
So the bigger the rubber band, the bigger
the relative contribution of a single point.
And we'll talk about some of the other--
what happens in the noisy case and how
you can make it more robust next time, too.
But let me just say that this one,
if we ask the question again, what
happens on a rotationally symmetric object,
this time it's going to be exactly what we
were saying before.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, this SVD formulation is beautiful in L2.
It's harder in L1.
I think what people end up doing--
the question was, why not change this to an L1 objective
so it's less sensitive to outliers?
So if you just did the absolute value, for instance.
So it makes the optimization problem a little bit harder.
What people tend to do is truncated least squares.
So you can solve that as a-- and there's various approaches
to solving for that.
Or you even, in your closest point algorithm,
try to explicitly reject outliers.
Also, we'll talk about RANSAC as another--
there's a couple different approaches.
But normally, it's stick with that.
It's a workhorse.
And do what you need to to clean it up before you hand it to
that.
Think about how the iterative closest point algorithm works
now for a rotationally symmetric.
If I'm off by 90 degrees or 180 degrees,
it's going to find matches.
They're going to be the wrong matches.
But it'll lock itself in and it'll be stuck.
So if you don't care, if you don't
mind rotational symmetries in your answer, that's fine.
But if you were looking for a canonical pose,
ICP won't give it to you.
Cool.
So parts of perception are just kinematics.
And this is our first version of the algorithm.
We'll get more fancy with it in the next couple lectures.
I will go look at DeepNote right now,