So today, we're going to do part two of motion planning.
The emphasis today is going to be on the sample-based versions of motion planning.
Some of you will already be familiar with RRTs and probabilistic roadmaps.
I think once you've seen the idea, it's very natural.
If you haven't seen it yet-- I think many of you haven't seen it yet-- I think it's
very surprising that it works as well as that it's actually a method of choice for so many
roboticists.
I think they're very surprising ideas that once you understand them, they're, I think,
quite easy to use and extend.
So I want to cover those.
I want to talk in particular about how they are related, the pros and cons of these methods
compared to some of the methods we talked about last time.
There's a couple of really nice connections, too.
I want to, in particular, tell you about this time optimal path parameterization, which
is super useful and nice observation.
It's a good thing to know.
And if there's time, I will tell you a bit about some active research that we're doing
in the group right now.
I actually just gave a talk about this the other day.
It's ongoing research for us.
And I think maybe it fits right into the topics we're talking about this week.
So to the extent we have time, I'll tell you about some of the new algorithms we're working
on.
So remember where we're at.
We talked last time about thinking about inverse kinematics as it is still the problem of inverting
the map that you get from forward kinematics.
So you get end effector pose as a function of q.
And now we want to say, find me a q that solves, for instance, for some end effector pose.
But I really wanted to generalize that idea of thinking about it, a much richer specification
than that, about joint limits and collision avoidance and all these things defining that
inverse problem.
Now someone asked a really good question last time, because I showed the interactive inverse
kinematics, roughly what the video is, but in the notebook.
And you can play with it yourself.
And it works pretty well.
Like at real time rates, you can move it around and solve the optimization problem.
And I showed it solves slightly more global problems, where it's reaching around the pole,
and then it would snap around and go to the other side.
So why did I ever tell you about differential kinematics and differential inverse kinematics
and Jacobians?
Like, why don't I just use this all the time?
And that's an important point I wanted to make.
I want to make sure I land.
So even in this video here of Atlas and the way we used Atlas in the competition, we did
not solve IK in the loop and just instantly send the result of IK into the robot.
We never did that.
I would be afraid to do that, because the inverse kinematics solver does potentially
solve a more global problem.
But it can also fail.
It can also just flat out say, I didn't get that one.
Or I get stuck in a local minima and give you a bad answer.
There's also-- I mean, you can improve the formulation by setting up the right costs
and constraints.
But there's really no guarantee, because it's this complicated nonlinear solver, that it's
even going to give you-- if you change the goals or constraints a little bit, if you
made a small change in the problem formulation, you're not guaranteed to get a small change
in the cues that get out.
So you could imagine saying, I want my hand here, my hand here, my hand here.
And all of a sudden, it'll say, OK, I'll do this.
And you don't want to send a big delta Q to your robot.
So almost always, we will solve inverse kinematics and then use trajectory optimization or something
else that can guarantee we'll get a smooth path from the current configuration to the
thing that was solved by inverse kinematics.
And never do we assume-- we always put ourselves in a situation where if IK were to fail, we
still got something to do, or the robot can sit still for a second, and we can try again.
So it's a different situation.
The differential IK is solving a constrained least squares problem that is super reliable.
You can run into limits where it will say, you can't go farther this way.
But it's never the case that your optimizer says, I got stuck.
Or it may be feasible.
I don't know.
So there are different tools.
In particular, the differential IK was useful when we could make fairly simple end effector
trajectories.
And we wanted to then map that into smooth joint trajectories.
And the philosophy here has been now, let's just work directly in joint space.
And we'll add all of the other constraints.
Those are constraints on Q. Instead of working in end effector space, we've moved to joint
space.
OK.
So if there's any-- I just want to make sure those connections are clear.
We talked then about kinematic trajectory optimization as almost being just solving
a bunch of inverse kinematics problems and linking the points together.
It's basically just simultaneously solve a bunch of inverse kinematics problems.
This was the case I told you about.
You can even solve the manipulation problem as a kinematic trajectory optimization problem,
where you just say for some group of points in the middle, the relative transform between
the mug and the hand is going to be fixed.
So you say basically, for decision variables 1 through n, the hand is moving and the mug
stays fixed.
For n through 2n or something like this, the mug will be in the same relative position
of the hand.
And now I have to worry about collisions with the mug in the world too.
And then from 2n to 3n, I can just-- just the hand will move again.
So you can actually do the full manipulation problem in the kinematic trajectory optimization,
if you like.
We talked about how even for relatively benign-looking problems, our 3D-- or sorry, our planar now
three joints, but living in the xz plane, we get these configuration spaces.
The problems that we're formulating are actually wicked geometry problems.
They're wicked geometry problems.
And the fact that the solver can potentially fail is closely related to the fact that we're
asking it to do horrible things.
So that kind of motivates what we're going to do today here.
So I should say it even fails, by the way, those are even with simplified collision geometry.
So I didn't make that point maybe carefully enough last time.
But if you look even at the different EWA models that we have in both in Drake or in
the manipulation repo, there's variants where they have different collision geometries.
But they're always simpler than the full mesh models.
And even then, the collision geometries are very complicated.
So when we're trying to find a path for our sphered EWA into the bookshelf, we're solving
a pretty complicated geometry puzzle.
And it really isn't so different.
This is James back when he was popularizing the RRT, the first algorithm we'll talk about.
He was making the point that these algorithms that we're working on can solve geometry puzzles.
It's kind of not so different.
This is like one that's hard for humans.
But the way we're formulating the problem is we have some complex geometries, complex
non-collision constraints.
And you want to find a path from point A to point B. That's just a complicated geometry
problem.
The fact that this problem and reaching into the shelf are roughly the same through the
lens of these algorithms, I hate that, by the way.
That means we've written down the problem in a really hard way.
And we probably shouldn't.
But that's what we're looking at right now.
So we'll talk about RRTs.
Let me start by just making absolutely sure that I make the connections clear.
So the kinematic trajectory optimization-- my plan was to leave the last slide up while
I started this.
But I could tell it was mesmerizing.
And I'm on plan B. OK, so the kinematic trajectory optimization, where we're basically saying
minimize over q0, q1, just solving lots of q's subject to some-- subject to my constraints.
That's the way I want you to think about kinematic trajectory optimization.
It's doing two things.
So first of all, it's solving the already hard inverse kinematics problem.
It's got to find a solution in that landscape.
But it's also by having to link these constraints that link these together.
It means it's got to find a path through that obstacle field.
When I think of-- if I plot the configuration space q1, q2, and if I plot somehow some obstacles
like this, and I have a start and a goal over here, and I'm trying to find a bunch of points,
in many cases, life is good.
But the kinematic trajectory optimization problem has this other pitfall that we didn't--
I didn't emphasize last time, but it's important to understand relative today, to the algorithms
today, is that the fact that you're putting these constraints-- you're trying to make
these points relate to each other with the additional constraints of calling it a spline
or saying that the distance has to be smaller than some amount, we're introducing additional
hardness into the problem.
So let me think of a good-- if my obstacles looked like, I don't know, a barbell in the
middle here, OK, something like this, and I had my start and my goal, and this is my
obstacle, and I have an initial guess that goes like this, which is infeasible, and the
optimizer now has to try to get out-- get itself out of this problem.
If I was just trying to optimize one point for inverse kinematics to get out of some
collision, then maybe that's a reasonable thing to ask, and it'll try to push out.
We talked about how that is still subtle and hard, but it could sort of expect one-- to
push one or two of these points out, OK?
But what happens when you've got this sort of trajectory that's going through here with
a bunch of points, and it's stuck in the middle of this obstacle, right?
If I go-- if I try to pull the points this way, the trajectory gets worse by most definitions
in the sense that it's in more penetration.
More of the points are going to be infeasible.
If I pull it this way, more of the points are going to be infeasible, OK?
And it seems a big ask to have the solver get out of that local minima and find a different
solution, right?
There are better solutions out there, but the way we've written down the problem of
somehow take gradients, see what you can do to make the thing locally better, that's going
to have problems, OK?
So kinematic trajectory optimization, it actually scales very well.
I'd say thousands of variables are-- variables and constraints are OK.
OK, but the big problem is local minima.
The fact that you can write objectives and get good paths out within some minima is--
there's lots of good things about kinematic trajectory optimization.
But this really-- the killer is that you can really get stuck in local minima.
OK, so enter a very different approach, related but different approach, is these sampling-based
motion planners.
Rather than put all of your bet on sort of one path, one trajectory, and work hard to
improve that trajectory locally, let's try to find as many points as we can that are
collision-free, and then somehow defer or separate the idea of connecting them up, OK?
So there's a few ways to think about why this is a good idea.
But the basic picture I want you to have in your head is if I have this complicated non-convex
problem, whatever shape it happens to be, if I just start sampling almost at random
here, I might sample some points that are in collision, some that are out of collision.
That's a relatively easy problem.
Asking if any one point is in collision or not, collision checking is super fast.
That'll be the bottleneck in some of these algorithms, but still, considering the problem
it's solving, collision checking is fast.
The geometry folks have done their job very well.
And you can ask for many, many points, many, many configurations of your robot.
You can ask a Boolean question, say, am I in collision or not?
OK, so this has inspired a bunch of algorithms which don't try to locally optimize a path,
but instead start sampling in the space and trying to find a path then between these random
samples as almost a second step.
There's two variants I want to tell you about, the two most popular variants.
The first one, I guess I'll start with the rapidly exploring random tree.
I'll come over here.
So the fact that it's random, I've kind of hinted at it.
We'll talk about why it's rapidly exploring.
The data structure that we're thinking about in RRTs is actually a tree.
And you can see the basic steps on my slide up there.
But given some complicated obstacles, given a start, given a goal, the steps of the algorithm
are going to go roughly like this.
I'm going to pick a point at random.
Let me get some colored chalk.
Maybe it's over here.
I could just pick it from this anywhere in this domain.
Maybe I have just a uniform random sampling of points anywhere in the whole region I could
potentially visit.
And the algorithm goes like this.
Given a sample point, find the closest node in the current tree.
I'm going to start with the tree containing exactly one point at the start.
So this would be my closest node in the tree.
And then I'm going to try to expand the tree towards that node.
If that node's close and it's reasonable to connect it directly, then I will.
Otherwise, I will extend the tree up to some maximum length towards that node, add that
to my tree, and repeat.
So if I pick another point, I think my closest point is in the tree, I'll grow this way.
Sometimes I'll pick feasible points.
Sometimes I'll pick infeasible points.
What I won't do is once I've grown my tree here and I've got a sample point here, I won't
grow into the obstacle.
I'll reject.
If I have points that end up in the obstacle, I will just discard them and not add that
to the tree.
You could do that in the original sample, or you could do that at the extent of operation.
And you'll just sort of slowly grow a tree-- actually, rapidly, sorry, not slowly-- rapidly
grow a tree in kind of random directions.
The fancier versions will also grow a tree simultaneously backwards from the goal.
That's bidirectional RRT.
And what's amazing about these algorithms is that they work.
You wouldn't sort of expect to be able to randomly sample in high dimensional spaces.
I mean, on the 2D example on the board, you'd expect that to just work fine and you'll eventually
cover the space.
But sampling in high dimensions is supposed to be bad.
And it is bad eventually.
But what's surprising is for robots as complicated as Atlas or EWAs or stuff like this, you're
already in a fairly high dimensional space.
Your obstacles are pretty complicated objects.
But you can draw enough samples and make enough edges in that high dimensional space with
a simple algorithm like this that people find very meaningful paths very quickly with an
algorithm like this.
It's really-- when this was first coming on the scene, I was very surprised that that
would be practical.
But it works surprisingly well.
So there's a few things to understand about it.
Well, first of all, we can-- of course, I've got simple versions of it that you can run.
Here's the simplest version, which is really no obstacles whatsoever.
I'm just going to do exactly this algorithm in an open field and see what happens.
And unfortunately, I left it there.
But watch the way it grows.
There's something sort of fascinating about the way this algorithm grows.
It has this property buried in its name that the tree, when it starts, actually very quickly
grows out to fill the entire space and then goes through kind of as if it's in a second
pass.
There's no difference in the algorithm.
There's no change in the algorithm.
It's just the simple steps.
But it sort of has this interpretation that it'll go in and fill in the details as the
tree gets more dense, which is a very compelling property for something that's trying to find
a path and then possibly make it better or find the small, narrow passages later.
So there's a bunch of ways to think about how that property comes about.
I think I have the right slide for it right here.
Let me think about it.
OK.
Yes.
So let's look at this one.
I went out of order a little bit.
The analysis of RRTs talks about their Voronoi bias.
To some extent, we're inventing properties that the very simple algorithm has.
But it's an interesting way to think about the growth of the algorithm.
So first of all, what's a Voronoi region?
You guys know what a Voronoi diagram is for a set of points?
If I have a bunch of points in a 2D space, and I want to draw the Voronoi diagram, if
you just look at SciPy or MATLAB and you just call it Voronoi, then what is it going to
do?
The Voronoi regions are the regions that are associated, given some distance metric.
We'll just use the Euclidean distance metric on the board and in a lot of our problems.
I want to say, what is the area on this 2D plane?
What are the set of points that are closest by that distance metric to this point, that
are closest to this point, that are closest to this point?
If you draw those regions, then you end up with a partition of the two-dimensional space,
the Voronoi partition.
The boundaries of the partition are always the lines in the Euclidean norm.
They're the lines that separate these points.
So between any two points that are neighbors in this diagram, you expect to see those lines
defining the regions.
And if you draw these lines out, then this defines the Voronoi partition of the space.
And this region here, when you're done carving it up, are all of the points that, by whatever
distance metric, are closest to this point.
Now there's no-- so actually, calling this in SciPy is a little bit of expense of an
operation, especially if you have lots of points.
You can plot it, but maybe it's not something you want to throw in the middle of your algorithm.
The RRT algorithm, which I listed, has no call to Voronoi anywhere in the algorithm.
But it has an interpretation.
Because the algorithm samples uniformly in the space, the probability-- and then it grows
from the closest point.
So all it's doing is the nearest neighbor queries from the sample points.
Because of that, the size of the Voronoi region is proportional to the probability of sampling
and extending from this node.
If I sample from a uniform and I find the closest distance, then the size of the Voronoi
region is proportional to the probability of grabbing that node and extending.
So I do have a Voronoi bias.
The points that have a big Voronoi region have a higher probability of being extended,
which means I'll have a higher probability of growing that region.
And then I'll split up that space, and I'll have a smaller Voronoi region.
So this simple algorithm of just saying sample at random, find the closest, then extend has
this property that it will go from some original region, the original point.
It'll start growing out quickly.
Because the edges in the initial picture, the edges of the graph have the big Voronoi
regions.
So it's much more likely that you will pull yourself out than collapse yourself in.
And then as it proceeds, the smaller regions on the inside will have a higher probability
of getting picked, and you'll fill in the details.
It all comes from the super simple algorithm.
It comes out implicitly.
And what's interesting is that the algorithm is, again, very simple.
That's, I think, part of its appeal.
It's one of the things that made it great.
But other similarly simple algorithms don't work as well as that.
For instance, this one on the left here, if I just said pick a point at random, like pick
in my tree, let's say, pick one of the elements in my tree at random and grow it in a random
direction, that sounds pretty similar, actually, to the RRT algorithm.
And you get up like these hairballs, like the thing that the cat coughs up.
It does not rapidly explore the space.
There's something essential about picking a sub-goal in the space and then trying to
grow towards it that gives this expansion bias.
It is not the same to pick a point on the tree and grow in a random direction.
That doesn't have the same sort of pull into the free space.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
So if you're-- there's a bazillion variants.
So let me just caveat with that.
The basic algorithm says that if you're-- it would basically put a maximum extend distance.
If the point is so close to your node that it's under that extend distance, it will only
extend to the distance to that actual node.
But if it's beyond that, it will truncate it and expand partially up to the maximum
distance.
So initially, you get a lot of them that are at the full extension.
And then as you get deeper, you'll get a lot more of the small edges.
Good question.
Super simple algorithm, highly effective.
Highly effective.
OK?
Yeah, there really are a bazillion variants of it.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Awesome.
So the question is exactly what are the terminated-- how does the algorithm end?
So there are a couple of ways to do it.
You could just hope that the tree eventually gets to the goal.
And as soon as you do, then you'll terminate when you're in some radius of the goal.
That's the algorithm you suggested, which is a perfectly good one.
Because in order to bias towards the goal, you'd like to somehow try to trend a little
bit towards the goal but still explore everything.
A common variant, small variant on what you said, would be to sample at random 90% of
the time.
And 10% of the time, use the goal as my sample point.
That gives a goal-directed bias to the tree.
And then the bidirectional variant is-- because even that is a little bit-- you're pulling
yourself very strongly towards a particular goal.
It gets better if you grow the tree from both ends.
And then the goal bias is rather pick a point on the other tree to grow towards.
And then all you're trying to do is get anywhere on these two trees to connect.
And that gives you the end conditions.
Great question.
Now Rachel added some words in the piece set about the RRT dance.
So it is-- actually, there was a particular version, like the funniest robot video I remember
seeing where I was like, that's the RRT dance.
I couldn't find it last night.
I was bummed.
But here's what happens.
The thing that you get out of these algorithms are random trajectories.
And if you were to apply them directly, then your robot picks things up like this.
And it looks ridiculous.
So you normally don't do that.
So normally, you would take your output of your RRT and smooth it a little bit.
So at least cut the rough corners.
But it's still-- it found some path through the space.
And it can really do pretty strange things often.
So there is that about it.
You can kind of recognize a robot that is using RRT as its primary algorithm by-- it's
like, why did it do that?
It's almost always there's a randomized planner behind it.
Actually, the one that I thought-- I always thought was the best, but I couldn't find
the video.
And it turns out-- there's one time, I will admit, that I said, that's got to be an RRT.
And it turned out it wasn't an RRT.
It was just really, really committed undergrads, apparently.
But the chimp robot from CMU in the DARPA Robotics Challenge is this awesome robot.
Getting into it out of the car is really hard.
They have continuous rotary joints.
So they had this amazing feature that they would use a lot of their actuators that could
spin more than 180 continuous rotation joints.
The way that robot got into and out of the car was the most transformer-looking, crazy,
convoluted thing I've ever seen.
And I was like, that's got to be an RRT.
And it turns out, no, no, no.
That was just a long night for some students.
[LAUGHTER]
Is CMU undergrads?
She says, OK.
So there's a few times where I've been wrong.
But most of the time, if you see the craziness, the RRT dance is pretty recognizable.
So let's just think for a minute about some of the things that are good and bad about
this compared to the kinematic trajectory optimization.
So to some extent, this will not scale as high in dimensions as the kinematic trajectory
optimization.
The kinematic trajectory optimization, thousands of variables and constraints, you should think
of that-- in my mind, I think of that as there's a big, high-dimensional space.
And I'm focusing all of my attention on a single path through that space.
So no matter how high-dimensional the space is, the dimension of my problem is like the
number of points I put on my space, roughly.
I've made a path.
And I'm roughly immune to how big the state space is.
I mean, of course, the decision variables get a little bit bigger.
But that doesn't really-- the complexity of the problem grows like a path, which is one-dimensional
no matter how many joints your robots have.
Making a path this way with sampling, the space-- you're asking to solve a harder problem.
And it grows worse and worse and worse with the dimensions of the space.
However, I think there are some amazing things about this algorithm.
One of the things I hate about the kinematic trajectory optimization problem is that you
always have to-- almost always-- have to choose the number of points.
When you start the problem, you say, I'm going to find a path of length 10 to get from the
start to the goal.
This algorithm has no such constraint.
If it takes 100 points to get to the goal, so be it.
If it's 10, so be it.
It's going to-- it'll be random every time you run it.
But I think that's a very powerful difference in these algorithms.
The fact that the path can grow or shrink depending on the geometry of the problem,
I think is a very nice feature of these algorithms compared to the trajectory optimization problems.
This one requires me to potentially have gradients of even my collision constraints.
This one, I only need binary collision checks.
All I have to ask is the thing that contact engines have been optimized for years to do,
answer the question, is MIA collision or not?
So that's a huge feature.
You can use any collision engine out of the box to answer that question.
These are highly parallelizable.
And you can push these-- you can do a lot of those collision checks in parallel.
The higher performance algorithms are going to be doing lots of collision checks in parallel
lots all the time in the background.
The checks are fast, but they can still dominate your runtime of your algorithm.
So the good algorithms do that in parallel.
The sampling-based algorithms are good for inequality constraints, if you will, being
inside a region or not being inside a region.
But they're kind of lousy for equality constraints.
So if you have dynamic constraints, there's a whole field of trying to put dynamic constraints
into this.
Dynamic constraints are harder.
It's less natural.
Ironically, the RRT was sort of born out of a motivation of trying to make this better.
And it is better than it was before the RRT, but these are still hard.
So there's lots of different ways to think about it.
But so typically-- so we think about it a lot in walking robots, for instance.
So you might have-- if momentum or something was a constraint-- even in manipulation, if
I was going to try to-- if the way to get this over to you is to throw it, the path
that this follows in the middle is not an arbitrary path.
Based on whatever I picked now, there's equations of motion constraints that are going to define
the path during the segment where it's out of my hand and on the way to you.
That's a dynamic constraint.
I think the feature of it is that it's an equality constraint.
There's a specific answer, a specific path that parts of your variables need to follow.
And these are harder to put into the randomized framework.
The other leading algorithm or class of algorithms in sample-based motion planning is-- it actually
came first, technically, chronologically.
It's sort of morally equivalent to this in the sense that we're going to lean on the
sampling and build data structures through the space.
But it's optimized for a slightly different workflow-- probabilistic roadmaps.
And the key setting where this one shines is if you have a multi-query setting where
geometry obstacles don't change much.
And I'm solving for multiple paths.
The algorithm is similarly simple.
I put the code on the board just because it's like 16 lines, including all the endifs.
It's these super simple algorithms.
The picture tells the story, I think, better.
The algorithm samples points at random.
Every time you sample, you just look for not just one neighbor in a tree.
You look for any neighbors in any direction within some radius.
And you connect up, and you make a graph instead of a tree.
So you just try to make a dense roadmap graph in the obstacle-free space of your problem.
Then when it comes time to actually solve, you can do that in sort of a pre-computation
step.
Just try to find lots of roads in my complicated environment.
And then when it comes time to actually plan, if you've got an initial sample point of start
and a goal, then the problem is reduced to find a small-- do the minimal amount of planning
to just connect me back to my existing roadmap, and then solve a discrete graph search problem
to get me the rest of the way there.
We're very good at discrete graph search.
It's those continuous variables that get you.
So this is very good if you're going to solve repeated problems.
You can imagine that every time I've solved a new problem, I might as well throw that
new edge into the graph.
So I kind of get better and better and better, a denser and denser map.
And I can reach all the places that I would like to reach.
I should say both of these algorithms have this property called probabilistic completeness.
So a planning algorithm is called complete if it is guaranteed to find a path, in this
case.
A path planning algorithm is guaranteed to be-- it's called complete if it's guaranteed
to find a path if it exists.
And both of these algorithms have the property that they are guaranteed to find a path if
it exists with probability 1 as the number of samples goes to infinity.
So if you're willing to just keep sampling, it will eventually find a path if it exists,
which is a pretty weak thing to say.
We kind of lean on that a lot.
We say, oh, this will eventually work.
But it's actually almost-- even the silly algorithm that makes a hairball is technically
probabilistically complete.
So it's kind of a weak thing to say.
But yeah, it's good to have something to lean on.
For both of these algorithms, the hard case are when you get to high dimensions and when
you get to narrow passages that are sort of unlikely that you're going to find consecutive
samples that guide you down some narrow passage.
So the standard bad example is something like a bug trap.
I only made this one a little bit narrow.
So imagine I have a start inside here.
And I'm going to grow my RRT.
And I'm trying to get out of the-- I have a goal that's outside of my little bug trap.
You know why these are called the bug traps, right?
You can catch a fly or-- typically, you would make a funnel if you really wanted to catch
a bug, but make it easy to get into and hard to get out of.
I'll just run that again so I don't have to reset my-- OK.
But you can imagine if in order to get out, you have to find a path that requires sampling
from a small region many times, that's the bad case.
The narrow passages and corridors are the hard case for the sample-based algorithms,
right?
It will very slowly make progress down the exit hallway here.
With very high probability, it'll sample somewhere in here, OK, as it slowly gets-- once it gets
out, it's off to the races again.
But there are problems that are not intentionally challenging like that.
They're not constructed by someone trying to make a hard case.
They just happen because of the geometry of your robot that look a lot like that.
And that's where the randomized algorithms can struggle.
Any other questions about sort of the randomized planning family?
I mean, it's important to me that the basic ideas come through.
You should know that there's a huge number of variants, OK?
But I actually think talking about all the variances isn't-- I mean, I think the only
way to really start getting in is to start coding them up.
And there are only a few lines of code to write.
And you can appreciate the heuristics that people start coming up with and the way to
make these things performant, things like that.
Yes?
The high-level summary of RRT would be like, we have this continuous space, and we want
to make a [INAUDIBLE] graph, and then we run for it [INAUDIBLE]
That's the probabilistic roadmap?
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE]
The RRT, by making a tree, by the data structure being a tree, the path problem is trivial,
right?
You have a single ancestor.
You have to walk backwards up the tree to find your way back to the initial conditions.
If you're doing the bidirectional, even then, you find the point in the middle where you've
connected, and you just walk in both directions up the tree.
So the RRT-- just the question to repeat was, should I be thinking about the RRT also doing
the shortest path on the graph?
You don't have to do that for the RRT, right?
In the probabilistic roadmap, that is an extra step.
You have a graph, so you can reuse it.
You can go in multiple directions.
You can imagine in the RRT, if I had a new start or a new goal, I have to just start
over from scratch, right?
So you've done a lot of sampling.
You've made a lot of edges that you're not using again.
And if you generalize that to start even wiring your second tree to the first tree, you've
got a graph.
And then you get the graph search problem buried inside it.
I have a question about the collision test.
Sure.
So are we just checking the collision on the pollen?
So if there was an element of collision on the pollen, do we do fine earth sampling along
the path?
Good.
So the question was about the details of the collision checking here.
And there's maybe two points to make regarding your question here.
So first of all, there are cases here where I have a tree that gets me here.
I've got a sample point here.
This is out of collision.
I might make an edge that goes directly through.
You have to be careful to not add those edges.
There are a number of ways that people try to avoid cutting those corners and adding
those edges.
They could also actually, by the way, happen right through the middle, which is kind of
embarrassing when you sample across and you walk right through the middle just because
you didn't happen to sample in the collision that was in the middle.
So the simplest answer to the question is every time you add an edge or lazily later,
after the fact, you can go through and make sure you're happy by checking a bunch of samples
along the actual edge.
If you do it at graph construction, then you might be spending a lot of time adding every
edge.
A lot of times nowadays people will wait until they found a path and then certify their path
by checking just along the path, that extra cost.
There are other ways to do it, too, which leads me to the second point that your question
raises for me.
So this is a point in the configuration space.
So the collision check in the code is not point versus geometry.
This is the robot is put in some configuration.
The robot has some geometry.
The obstacles are in some configuration.
So I'm doing a complicated collision check, even though I'm drawing it as a point in the
configuration space.
So this is a potentially mesh on mesh collision check.
So there are ways, there are other heuristics, for instance, where if I have a point here
and a point here I'm trying to connect, if this point corresponds to, let's say, my robot
in this configuration, this point corresponds to the robot in this configuration, then people
do things like, let's make the convex hull of both of those configurations and say, well,
what if my robot, if I use the convex hull geometry of both of those regions, and if
that convex hull is not in collision with the world, then I'm feeling pretty good that
all the intermediate points are not.
That's still a heuristic.
You could have a narrow thing coming in or whatever, but it's potentially nicer than
sampling.
It depends on your geometry engine.
There are other ways that maybe I'll get to at the end, which can try to be even more
careful about avoiding those collisions.
Awesome.
Oh, sorry.
Andy.
Yeah.
So it's a great question.
So the probabilistic completeness in practice, what does that mean?
What are the termination conditions?
So there's a couple of answers to that.
The simplest answer is you tend to put a maximum number of points.
You hope you find a solution much sooner than that.
You run out of points, and then you say, maybe no path exists.
The problem with probabilistic completeness is it will never say no.
You never know that no path exists.
There are other algorithms that can give you this no answer that would make you stop trying.
So typically, you set a time limit, and then change your formulation a little bit and try
again.
Yes.
So because of that, would you also not be comfortable running a sampling-based planner
on a real robot in real time?
Like you mentioned, for pneumatic optimization, you would not be comfortable typing that to
the robot.
Right, right.
So the question is, would I be comfortable running this on Atlas or something like that?
Right.
You cannot put it-- I would not put it in a pipeline where it must find an answer in order
to be successful unless I started-- there are cases where you could.
For instance, if you-- in an autonomous car, people do use these kind of algorithms in
autonomous cars.
You would want to make sure you have one path a priori that can solve the problem, even
if it's hit the brakes or something like that.
If you have some solution that will definitely work, then you can potentially use these algorithms
to find something more interesting, more better, accomplishing a harder objective, as long
as you have a fallback.
But I think the problem, as stated, must be solved.
This one will not guarantee you solve it in any bounded amount of time.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yep.
OK.
So the question is, if I say that this one needs the gradients and this one doesn't need
the gradients, but in both cases, I need to avoid the edges by potentially sampling a
lot, how are they different?
Right?
Yeah.
So the question is basically, let's say I'm in penetration.
I've got some point that's in or even some part of my edge that's in.
How do I get out?
OK.
This one is trying to use some sort of gradient information to try to make a decision about
which way to change the decision variables in order to get out of penetration.
It can apply that only at the discrete samples.
It can apply that on a constraint that's implemented on the convex hull or many points, subpoints.
But in some sense, the constraints I've written against my optimization problem, which have
gradients, are defined along that whole edge.
And I'm trying to move the edge out.
This one, I just say, that edge was no good.
I'm going to go to a different one.
And so there's really no sense that I have to push this one out and fix it.
I'll just discard it.
Right?
So that has a weaker requirement on the collusion checker.
Great questions.
Thank you for asking.
So as the RRT dance discussion sort of suggested, a very common thing, if you think about this
as solving maybe a harder problem than kinematic trajectory optimization can solve.
But kinematic trajectory optimization often gives better trajectories once it's found
a solution.
There's a standard pipeline, which could be to find any solution, just find a feasible
path with my RRT, and then run kinematic trajectory optimization in order to get something satisfying
that's out of constraint.
There are also much lighter weight versions of the kinematic-- you don't have to solve
the full kinematic trajectory optimization problem.
You'll explore a few of the ideas on your problem set.
But there's some even just pretty simple short circuit rewiring algorithms that will clean
up some obviously bad edges and simplify an RRT plan, or just do local smoothing with--
the kinematic trajectory optimization, if you're trying to make this point better by
some cost or constraint, it might change this point.
All of the decision variables are active for all of the constraints.
And it might be that you're going to change all of the variables in order to improve your
quality of solution over here.
And you can make the problem less optimal, but simpler and faster if you just make local
changes and say, OK, well, if I just want to consider these three points, and I want
to make them a little bit better, these three points make them a little better.
So there's a whole class of algorithms that will sort of locally improve the paths that
you get out of RRT.
You still get some dancing, but a little less.
But there's one algorithm in particular that I just think is so good that I want to make
sure I tell you about it, which is based on time optimal path parameterization.
So let's think about all the possible constraints that we might have on our robot.
We've listed them before.
So we have the non-penetration constraints, collision avoidance, joint limits, velocity,
acceleration.
You guys know what the derivatives are?
Did I say that before?
What's the derivative of acceleration, time derivative of acceleration?
You know the next ones?
Yeah, snap, crackle, I kid you not, pop.
Those are the derivatives of a position trajectory.
You could put constraints on any of them, saying my acceleration has to stay in some
limit.
I actually was talking to somebody the other day saying that the FANUC will shut down if
your jerk exceeds some limit.
If you don't include the jerk limits in your trajectory profile, then a particular arm
could potentially just power down or refuse to execute.
But there's also torque limits.
And if you're manipulating things, there's also things like friction limits.
If I want to move my robot fast through the environment and I'm holding this eraser, it
might be that the speed that I move at is dominated by when the eraser is going to slip
out of my hand.
So the randomized algorithms, RRT and PRM, are really good at these geometric parts,
the non-penetration and joint limits.
You have to work to get them to do more.
And I'd say they're not as good at these, especially the torque limits and friction
limits.
But there's this super nice observation, which is that if you have a joint trajectory-- first
of all, in a lot of our manipulation planning problems with these types of constraints,
it is the case that if you go slower, there's always a solution that works.
You can avoid these constraints by just moving slowly enough.
That's not always true.
And if I'm trying to lift something that's too heavy for my torque, then if I plan a
trajectory that goes slowly, it's still not going to work.
But in many problems, these can be ignored if you're willing to go slowly enough.
So it's become common and powerful to solve the problem in two stages, which is use your
kinematic motion planner to think about these kind of problems, these constraints, and then
afterwards try to rescale the time, just optimize the time along that path in order to handle
these different constraints.
And it happens that once you know Q, these constraints become nice again.
If you try to solve them jointly, it's a really hard problem.
But if you're willing to separate here, it's a suboptimal-- any time you break the optimization
into two steps, you are potentially becoming less optimal for it.
But this one is so good because the time optimal path parameterizations really, really work
nicely.
So let me make sure I tell you why that's so good.
Another key observation here, when I write the dynamics of my manipulators, which I've
done a bunch, even with contact.
In fact, this is the way I've always written it because we haven't needed more structure
there yet.
But we're going to exploit the fact that there's actually even more structure there.
It's not an arbitrary function of Q and Q dot.
You can always write this as-- we know that it's always quadratic, or you can always express
it as a quadratic in Q dot.
So these are the equations of my manipulator.
If I want to have a torque limit, if this is my torque, for instance, torque command,
and I have some limit there, or if I have some friction limit here, maybe some-- then
I have to think about these multibody equations in order to think about those constraints.
The observation, all of the ugliness in this equation, and it is ugly, comes in Q. All
the bad nonlinearities are the functions of Q. If you know Q, then the problem actually
gets pretty easy again.
So if I know Q, but I might not know Q double dot, then I might not know Q dot because I
don't know how fast I'm going to execute my Q trajectory.
Then I can write nice constraints against Q, Q dot, Q double dot, not Q, only Q dot,
Q double dot, torque, friction limits, by locking in Q. That's why it's so powerful
to separate those two parts of the problem.
And the way it works is with these time optimal parameterizations.
So if I think if I had, let's say, Q of t from, for instance, my RRT smoothed a little
bit, and it's defined for t in, say, 0 to t final, whatever time I picked, I'd like
to rescale time.
I'm going to define a rescaling, which is a trajectory, S of t, a function S of t, if
you will, which maps from 0 of t final into some new scaled time.
This is-- you can represent it with a piecewise polynomial.
This is a function.
This is just a scalar function.
You could represent it with a piecewise polynomial, for instance.
Given this rescaling, we're going to talk about our rescaled Q. I think on the board,
I'm going to just pick a totally different letter instead of trying to put some glyph
on Q.
I'll just say the rescaled Q is R.
And let me say that R of S-- do I want to say it this way or the other way?
I'll say R of t is Q of S of t, the rescaled version of Q.
And the great thing is that R dot of t is a simple function of the original trajectory
and the rescaling.
So R dot of t-- you can think of this as being partial Q, partial S, partial S, partial t.
So I'll write that as Q dot of t, S dot of t.
Similarly, R double dot of t is going to be Q dot of t S double dot of t-- got to use
the chain rule here-- plus Q double dot-- or sorry, yeah, Q double dot of t S dot squared
of t.
And if I put that back in, if I wanted to write my manipulator equations now in terms
of R, and I had R double dot of t here, but I'm going to go ahead and immediately substitute
in Q. So it'll be a little weird to look like it's got both R's and Q's kicking around,
but that's where we want to be.
I get this-- what do I get here?
I get S dot Q dot transpose C prime R Q dot S dot.
You get the point.
The derivatives of Q enter in this nice way.
And this function is linear in S dot squared and S double dot, and U, and friction.
And then there's one other sort of observation, which is that the time derivative of S dot
squared is 2S double dot, I guess.
So even those two variables are sort of related by a linear set of constraints.
That's a long way to say, if I know the Q, then I can actually solve optimization problems
of the form, get to me to the goal as fast as possible, subject to position limits, velocity--
sorry, subject to velocity limits, acceleration limits, jerk limits, torque limits, friction
limits, and solve that as a second pass by speeding up or slowing down my trajectory
using this re-parameterization.
Super clever.
I really, really like it.
Does that make sense?
OK.
Let me-- I have a little bit of time to tell you about a few of the sort of edge case versions
of this.
So first of all, people really use this.
There's a company now, Real-Time Robotics, started by George Kandadaris and his students.
I left the audio on.
Maybe I'm thinking that's a bad idea now.
There's a red button there.
I'll narrate for you.
And the motion planning doesn't start until they press the red button.
This is called Real-Time Robotics.
They took this probabilistic roadmap idea, and they basically did all the collision checking
and all the roadmap construction on not even a GPU, on special purpose chips, FPGA, I think,
and basically made it so you can just run lightning fast PRMs.
And they can adjust the collision geometries on the fly.
So someone walks into the workspace, and they can just basically solve PRMs at real-time
rates.
I mean, the downside is you need the extra compute, the extra hardware.
But if you're willing to do this, this is just a fantastic solution to make these things
solve very hard planning problems in real-time with specialized hardware.
You too can have a startup.
There's a huge wealth of open source code for these motion planning.
So OMPL is the one that you should know about first.
It's a library that started by Lydia Kavraki's group and Mark Moll.
And I think it has nice implementations of almost all of the variants that have made
it.
So it's really a good place to learn about the lots of different options that people
have for motion planning.
People have connected it with Drake collision checkers and stuff like that if you wanted
to try to use it.
I will say that we-- yes, there's a whole list of the geometric and kinematic planners.
This is on the OMPL website.
They have RRT, PRM, the lazy versions.
They have all kinds of different versions.
You could spend time just understanding the different variants.
But there's nice implementations of most of them available here.
I will say that we have them in Drake, too, sort of.
So this is kind of a funny thing.
It says TRI Anzu wish list.
So this is-- we have a bunch of really good code that's not in the public Drake yet, just
because it takes a lot of time.
Like, the standards for getting something up into Drake are high and it takes time.
So we have this sort of like, hey, we have really good code for this.
We haven't made it public yet, just because it takes time.
If you want it, upvote it.
And you should feel free to do that.
But that is actually-- even last time, I realized I said that we had the kinematic trajectory
planning.
I forgot that's still on this list.
The kinematic trajectory optimization I talked about last time is actually waiting to be
upvoted.
And I am-- just like we're reducing your p-sets a little bit, I'm a little bit shifting mode
where I'm trying to help you on your projects.
So if you upvote these, I will probably help polish them up and get them into Drake so
you guys can use them.
So yeah, but you have to tell me early what you need the most.
There's one of me and lots of you.
So I can only pick a few.
But that kinematic trajectory optimization class that we talked about last time, it really--
it's actually on the wish list.
I forgot.
But it is exactly what I said.
And there's all the nice-- there's the bi-RRT planners, the bi-directional RRT, TRRT, the
roadmaps, a bunch of-- the variants that we've found the most useful, optimizing versions
and the like, are waiting to be pushed when we have people that need them enough.
OK.
Let me just end by giving you a taste of some of the work we're doing now.
I actually presented this just the other day.
I consider it very exciting, ongoing research.
I'm going to have a long meeting about it, actually, in half an hour.
So it's this idea of shortest path on graphs of convex sets.
And I can tell you basically-- now, you've seen the basic setup of the PRM and everything.
The picture is quite simple to understand.
We said that the PRMs work well, but they do maybe the PRM dance.
They're a little bit-- it's hard to do optimization inside the discrete graph.
We actually know a lot about how to solve graph problems, graph search problems, with
optimization as well as with the standard, like, if you know about A* and depth-first
and breadth-first.
There's a class of algorithms there, but there's also ways to solve it with linear programming,
for instance.
And I've been trying to find, with Pablo and Jack, and to be a-- I'd say deeper connections
between the things that work well in search and things that will work well in optimization.
Even the little thing I said about how the number of points is-- you have to be specified
ahead of time here really bugs me.
It's like we haven't figured out how to write the optimization problems correctly yet, if
that's the problem.
And search scales to huge dimensions, but somehow optimization scales in a different
way.
There must be ways to find the nice sweet spot.
So we've been thinking now about a generalization of this problem, which fits right into the
planning picture, where you think about it as a classic graph search problem with one
change, which is that every time you visit a node in the graph, you're also allowed to
pick one vector from a continuous set, a convex continuous set.
So if you wanted to form a shortest path problem on the graph of these convex sets, then maybe
the shortest path from the start to the goal now visits these elements, depending on what
your objective is or your distance function is.
That's the key idea.
Turns out there are good ways to connect the best ideas from combinatorial optimization
with some of the ideas from planning, if you think about it this way, we found.
So this is an old version that inspired it, where we think about a PRM-like algorithm,
where instead of just making a point every time you sample, every time you pick a sample,
you're going to make a region.
So try to find-- we're drawing these points in space.
Every time you pick a point, try to grow a big region of free space.
And then we're going to make a graph of these intersecting regions, and then plan quickly
through the graph.
Because of the optimization aspect of things, we can handle a lot of the dynamic limits
very well.
But we can also do some of the global planning from the PRM kind of style.
So there's an algorithm inside called Iris.
We have a newer version of this, too, which is trying to, given a sample point in a complicated
space, find a big approximate convex-- approximately optimal convex decomposition, which is just
find a big region around my sample point that's collision-free.
And we use optimization to do that.
We use optimization for everything, so not surprising.
And then to David's question, we don't have to sample densely along the trajectories.
If you have regions, then you can actually write explicit constraints saying my entire
path is collision-free.
If you have a polynomial, for instance, the problem of writing a polynomial over some
finite domain being inside a region, you can write with convex optimization.
Or if you have a B-spline, the B-spline, you can use the convex hull property to keep it
inside the region.
So you can actually get the guaranteed collision-free planning.
And then by virtue of connecting to the graph search kind of things, we can do global optimization
up to the fact that we're missing-- we haven't filled all of the convex regions until we
sample.
So it's probabilistically complete in the sense that we have to make all those regions.
But for any decomposition, it's global.
So we did all kinds of stuff decomposing this space.
Even for Atlas, we would try to make convex decompositions of the terrain so it could
walk on.
The perception system would start by breaking up the regions into places where you could
potentially touch or step on.
And we've been doing this in a lot of different projects.
But the old formulations were expensive, let's say.
So it would generate-- we were using mixed integer optimization.
We're still using mixed integer optimization.
But the optimization problems were big and slow.
And they added what I would call a false combinatorial complexity.
The same way that-- I don't like the way we had to choose the number of points ahead of
time here.
There's even a worse thing in some of these formulations where basically for every point
on the path, I had to pick which region it was inside.
And so it's like if I'm just going from here to here, every single point I have to decide
if maybe I'm still over here.
And that's just somehow the wrong combinatorics of the problem.
Really it should be like I just decided I'm going to go left.
So all of my points should be looking over here.
Or I decided if I should go right.
It's somehow a much simpler problem than rather than saying every point has to independently
choose which set it's an element of.
And that just meant our solvers were slow.
And we're complaining about this one day with Pablo Perreo, who's a fantastic-- like absolute
tops in optimization, fantastic collaborator.
We had this conversation.
It was really good.
He said, OK, we know from combinatorial optimization that if you're just trying to solve the graph
problem, then there's a linear programming formulation that is tight.
And he says, your problem's way harder than that.
I don't expect it to be tight.
But where exactly-- which step is breaking?
What is the step that makes your problem not tight?
And when we dug in and we thought about it, we ended up with this new formulation where
we're going to lean on the formulations, the LP formulations of shortest path.
But we're going to do it with the sets.
I'm going to not go through the full formulation.
But I'm happy to talk to anybody who's interested.
And you can turn this problem now into a formulation that looks a lot like the LP formulation.
And it solves way faster.
And let me see if I can get the-- I'll just run it.
I've got code here.
So we've got this new formulation.
It might even be running already, where I can just solve the global motion planning
problem.
This is not a hard one.
This is an illustration of it.
I can solve these global optimization problems really fast.
I don't have to specify a priori the number of points.
It comes out of the shortest path problem formulation.
So that problem that I've always complained about is partially resolved here.
I'm just moving this starting to go around.
And the really cool thing is, because of the stronger constraints we're able to-- and the
way we were able to think about it, even if I just solve a convex relaxation of the problem,
it's tight often for simple problems.
We know that it's not always tight.
But basically, I can solve-- there's a weird case I could tell you all about.
That's actually not broken.
That's a correct answer.
And it's still tight.
But basically, I can still solve, in many cases, a linear program and get global motion
planning.
So we're thinking about the implications of this.
So here's the fun example.
So let's say I want to have a path from the start to the goal.
Now if I thought of this as a graph search, you'd say this is just a trivial problem.
For a graph algorithm, that would be fine.
But I'm going to try to find a continuous path, as if I had a humanoid walking through
the maze.
So that's a slightly harder problem.
That's like the Euclidean shortest path problem.
And we can find, with a convex optimization, these really hard paths now.
So I'm super excited about these things.
It's changed the way I think about some of these problems.
And I think it's a nice connection between the trajectory optimization from Tuesday and
the randomized algorithms from today.
There's lots of nice things about it.
But even when we're solving some of the problems we solved before, it's like thousands of times
faster than it was before.
Anyhow, and the way we put it all together-- let me just say that we use B-splines to make
the convex constraints now.
And we use configuration space reasoning.
And we do time optimal rescaling afterwards to take the trajectory, the torque constraints.
So all the stuff we've been talking about this week comes right into the best version
of the algorithm we have.
This is just a fun example that I should be careful showing you, because it was sent to
me at 3 AM before my talk last week.
And Mark probably has better by now.
But solving complicated, bimanual, deep collision kind of algorithms with basically convex optimization
plus a little bit of rounding is-- I don't know.
I'm excited about it.
So we're working hard on that.
OK, awesome.
At the risk of you immediately discarding any thoughts about motion planning, I'll say
that next week is reinforcement learning.
So we'll go on to the next piece.
But that was the end of the motion planning part.
but at the same time, gives us an opportunity to be innovative and innovative as well.