OK, welcome back.
So this is the last boutique lecture.
And it will include, actually, a little bit of just reflecting
on what we did over the course.
I find it's useful to sort of say it back in a slightly
different way at the end, I hope.
But we're going to talk today a little bit
about soft robotics.
I don't want to say we're going to cover all that there is
to say about soft robotics.
And its implication for manipulation
and for tactile sensing.
So when we started way back, lecture two,
we talked about robot hardware.
We talked about the EWA, why the EWA was cool.
I also showed a bunch of cool hands,
including some very unconventional hands.
One was made out of jamming grippers, like coffee beans.
And some of them are unquestionably soft.
So this was just one of the ones that I showed
was doing pretty dexterous manipulation
with pretty floppy fingers.
So I want to explore with you today
what it is about being soft that could be good, what
are the pros and the cons, and give you
a quick sense of what's out there
and what people are doing.
So I mean, I've been interested in soft for a pretty long time.
But there were a few--
I think it's kind of a punctuated evolution
of my relationship with soft.
And in particular, there were a couple results out there
that really captured my imagination.
This is one by Alex Alsbach, who--
oh, I didn't mean to leave the music on.
Sorry for that.
I normally turn those off.
OK.
He was working at Disney.
And he built this inflated Dynamixel sort of robot
with inflatable paws and an inflatable chest.
And there was something-- he showed this at a humanoids
conference that I was attending.
And there was just something about the way
that this is interacting with the little Mickey Mouse
toy and the apple that at the time,
when robots were going [MAKES RIDGID NOISE]
with their rigid hands--
this seemed so natural to me.
This really captivated me.
Having interactions like that with the world
is potentially game-changingly different, in my opinion,
than having these rigid objects that
are trying to do exact perception
and trying to be accurate.
This is just a very different way to interact with the world.
And Alex went on to build hands based on this kind of ideology.
You could have bubbles as fingers.
And you can imagine scaling that down.
And actually, when TRI started, I was so captivated with this
that I immediately recruited Alex to come start a soft
robotics team at TRI.
So he's the one that's behind the soft robotics stuff
that I've shown you from TRI.
And you'll see a few more of those.
And he's just down the street.
He was in the building earlier today.
And he's a great guy.
But this really, for me, was one of the first times
where I thought, jeez, it's not just
that that's a cool technology.
But that really-- maybe I'm programming my robots wrong
because we're touching things with these rigid fingers.
And I should really be embracing the softness sooner rather
than later because it might change
my computational pipeline.
So there's a lot of things that people say about soft.
And it's like every soft robotics paper
sort of starts off with a list of great things
about being soft.
But some of them, I think, are said a little too quickly.
Or I just want to dig in with you a little bit
about what is good and bad about being soft.
So benefits of being soft, I guess.
So one thing that people often say very quickly
is that soft robots are inherently safe.
Ironically, I had a conversation today
about someone telling me how they were injured by a soft
robot.
But that was apparently in response
to me saying I was going to say this in lecture.
OK.
But this is a standard sort of motivation for being soft
is that you can just sort of be inherently safe.
But I want to question that a little bit
and just make sure we understand that.
Another big one that people talk about
is that soft robots can be inherently less
dependent on perception or geometric models,
somehow be robust to-- in particular,
people talk about the geometric uncertainty.
So what do I mean by that?
So the Mickey Mouse mouse little stuffed animal
is not something that is like they have an accurate point
cloud of that they're doing rigid point cloud
registration of and estimating its pose in order to--
they've got a simple scripted motion of the hand
in that example or the apple.
And they just kind of put the object roughly
in the right spot.
And they've got to put a different object roughly
And it would have done pretty much the right thing.
And that is probably quite different than what
would have happened with a rigid hand.
But again, I think we should dig in a little bit
to why that happens or how broad that claim deserves to be.
There's lots of other motivations out there.
Some people say soft has the potential to be very durable.
I think we're still--
we're going through this revolution of fabrication
technologies.
And some of the early ones weren't that durable.
But there's now-- you'll see videos
of people driving over their soft robot with a car
or hitting them with a hammer and stuff like that.
That's standard fare for a soft robotics project.
I've seen them-- you put it on the barbecue,
and they light it on fire.
And it's like, oh, my soft robot still works.
That's cool.
I think there is a real potential for them
to be low cost, possibly even self-healing.
I don't have as much to say about the fabrication
part of it.
But I do think that is an interesting motivation.
And I think we are seeing--
I mean, we have seen over the last 10 years,
and we'll continue to see a revolution in fabrication
that I think does strongly motivate soft robotics.
But let's think about at least some of the first two
a little bit more critically from a modeling and dynamics
and control point of view.
And the model-- the way I would love for you
to think with me about this for a little bit
is actually I think there's a very simple model that
can get pretty far.
So let's say I have an object to be--
maybe it's on wheels if you want to think about it.
I want objects that can only move horizontally.
So we'll call this our manipuland.
And we'll have our--
maybe our hand.
We have two hands.
We'll do bimanual stuff.
And because I like to keep the geometry simple,
I'll have a point finger.
[TAPPING]
Right?
And these things are only moving--
the only degrees of freedom are left to right of the hands,
right?
And I want to manipulate the manipuland.
And maybe you can see where I'm going here.
I want to compare this version, which
is a pretty rigid picture, and I'm just
driving the hand around, with the same picture,
but now if I have my point contact here
and I attach my finger to my hand with a spring.
And maybe it's even a spring and a damper
if you like your mechanical drawings a little bit more
complete.
I could put a damper here between my hand and my finger.
And my manipuland, right?
Object is a little shorter to right.
And let's think a little bit critically
about the differences between those two systems, right?
Can we actually say that a system that has a spring in it
is inherently more safe, is inherently
more robust to geometric uncertainty?
Does it have all these attributes that we say?
OK, so if I were to take this and write my rigid body
mechanics for either of these two,
and I were to now bring this hand in contact
with the manipuland, then what happens?
At the moment of contact-- let's maybe think about first
the moment of contact.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
The rigid model is going to have an impulsive event, right?
If this is strictly rigid and you're not
allowed to penetrate, and you have a velocity
before the contact and you're not
allowed to have velocity after the contact,
then you must have had an impulsive collision
at the moment of contact.
It could be elastic, it could be inelastic,
but there's no question that something
happened in zero time in order to keep you
from going inside the object.
So the rigid has an impulsive collision.
Now in this one, the purely soft one here,
if I have a point finger here that is massless--
if I assume for a minute it's massless,
this is like assuming a spherical cow.
It's very useful, but a little silly.
Then if this is massless and I have a perfect spring here,
then I don't have an impulsive collision.
Right?
So you could argue in that sense that maybe it's
better for the object to not have that impulsive force that
hits it all of a sudden.
You can make those collisions larger or smaller
depending on your momentum, I guess,
at the moment of collision.
But it is true that if you can remove that mass completely,
then you get rid of the impulse.
And really, I want to make sure that I'm clear.
This is an artificial scenario.
This never actually happens.
Really, we always have something that looks more like this.
Right?
And we have some mass of my finger here.
And we have some imperfect spring
that has a stiffness k, maybe a damping b, let's say.
And I have a mass of my hand here.
OK.
So this is the perfect model case.
But I think in reality, we should be thinking rather,
what is the relative mass of the finger before the spring
and after the spring?
Huh?
OK, and then what is the relative spring constant,
or relative stiffness?
How large, how stiff is my spring?
Right?
And that, of course, only matters relative to the mass,
again, to give you a total resonant frequency.
Or all the characteristic dynamics
are going to depend on the ratios of mass and the spring
constant.
OK, so I think the analogy to be more fair
would be, how much benefit is it to have
my mass of my finger particularly low
in my stiffness low compared to the mass of my robot?
And you could tell that in a design like this,
this is trying to make the mass of the finger
look more like the mass of the latex making the bubble,
and the stiffness quite soft, where the bubble deflects
easily and potentially over a large deformation
before you have the immediate effects of the hand.
At the moment of collision.
That part seems reasonable?
OK.
What about at steady state?
Like, what about my steady state forces?
Like, once I'm in collision now, and I'm
applying some force on the hand here, from my whole robot,
what forces can I apply in steady state?
[WRITING ON BOARD]
How do the masses of my finger and the stiffness of my spring
relative to my hand affect my steady state forces?
[WRITING ON BOARD]
They don't, right?
Once I've hit a rest length, my new rest length of the spring,
then the forces I'm applying here
are being completely imparted here.
So in steady state, there's no difference, effectively.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
So if your robot has enough strength to crush, I guess,
Mickey Mouse, then your soft robot has that strength,
and your hard robot has that strength.
So inherent safety maybe is not fair at steady state,
I would say.
And maybe even more importantly would
be that springs can be dangerous.
I mean, you can store energy in springs, right?
So you could potentially take a pretty soft looking thing
and kind of load it up, make it into a catapult,
and fire off some pretty large forces if you're not careful.
So I always balk a little bit when
people say that soft is inherently safe.
I think you have to do a little bit more
to get safety from soft.
Dissipation, I think, does inherently
pull energy out of the system.
If you have damping in your soft element, which
most soft things do, then that pulls energy out.
And that is inherently a stabilizing and maybe
a safer point of view.
But I think stiffness alone doesn't make you safe.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
It's kind of a strange thing to write, but I'll leave it.
OK.
There's a trade off, of course, right?
So if you do make these things soft,
then you can reduce your impact impulse, right?
You don't change your steady state.
Dissipation can remove.
But you give something up if you add a soft spring
between your actuators and the world, right?
What do you give up in the linear systems sense?
There's a word that some of you know, I'm sure.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, control.
Not officially controllability is Boolean,
but you could somehow reduce your controlled bandwidth,
would be the-- right?
So what do I mean by that?
Let me just finish the thought real quick.
But if my goal, in the linear system sense,
if my goal is to make this execute,
let's say, a sine wave trajectory,
and I'd like to look at what my finger has
to do as the frequency of that sine wave gets larger, right?
The work that I'm going to have to do goes up fast
if I have a very soft actuator.
And what that implies, then, is that if somebody surprises you
with a disturbance or something, your ability
to respond and accurately control
the high frequency behavior of this system is poor.
Your control authority at high frequencies, I guess,
is what really gets you, right?
Because you've given up something with the softness,
right?
So if you have a hard robot, infinite bandwidth and control
authority, then you should always
be able to outperform a soft robot.
You could always act like you're soft, right?
So in practice, when we're putting this in,
it's somehow admitting that our bandwidth is, in practice,
limited in a meaningful regime.
Sorry, yes, please.
I'm wondering if there's another side of that point.
Yeah.
The bandwidth that's required to drive a soft robot
is also lower than in a stiff case.
Like, thinking about the task of grasping
the egg with a rigid robot, you need instant bandwidth
to not grasp that one perfectly rooted egg.
Good.
So you need-- you could probably do a one person
control loop with a soft robot to get a really soft spring
to still grasp the egg.
Good.
So there was a comment for those hearing about,
what if I'm trying to hold an egg, right?
And I have an egg-like example coming in a minute.
So yeah.
Is it that maybe if I have a soft robot,
the requirement on my bandwidth is less,
and therefore I can get away with the softness?
Yeah, I think I agree with the spirit of your comment.
I might say that the task demands
a certain amount of bandwidth.
And many of the tasks we try to do with soft robots
don't require high bandwidth, right?
I might say it a little bit differently.
But those two do play together.
I think the place where soft wins
is when your bandwidth requirements are low.
And actually, probably for a lot of things
we do in manipulation, our bandwidth requirements
are very low, right?
Certainly holding an egg, I wouldn't
think would be a particularly high frequency thing, right?
So if you're contacting it, it's a delta function,
then what you would do is have a real high bandwidth
to close the region.
OK, great, great.
So I said if you had a perfect stiff robot,
couldn't you always do better?
And so you're pointing out that a contact event is ideally
a delta function in practice, because things
aren't perfectly stiff.
It's going to be a very short time event, right?
So you're right.
I think you need very high bandwidth
to perform incredibly well through a contact event,
like exceedingly high bandwidth.
And so therefore, why try?
Why not let the mechanical system
handle that initial contact event,
and then you do your thing after the fact?
Completely agree.
That's a very good way to think about it.
OK.
OK, so in this picture--
I know a very simple picture, but I think hopefully
a helpful picture--
so we talked a little bit about the safety claim
and maybe the bandwidth we mentioned quickly here.
Is there a sense in which it's robust to geometric uncertainty
in this picture, right?
Is one sort of more or less robust
to geometric uncertainty?
I mean, that's a claim people--
it's sort of easy to make when you see a video like this.
How does it play out in this simple diagram?
.
Yeah, please.
I'm thinking about the case where you've already
established a graph, and I'm thinking
about varying the shape.
In the soft state, I would expect
some sort of conduit properties on the force.
Like, if you establish a graph and you change the shape,
the force should only change proportional to the change
in shape.
Because you're just changing the length of your spring,
and that should change the force you're using.
But if you have a completely rigid graph,
and you establish it, and you shrunk the object a little bit,
you expect a [INAUDIBLE]
OK, good.
So your thought experiment here, to summarize,
is that imagine I'm in contact, and I've
made a contact with my rigid or very stiff thing,
and I suddenly shrunk or expanded the geometry.
That's nice.
Then, yeah, this is going to have--
I mean, again, I guess this never exists, right?
So we're in the very stiff case is more thoughtful.
It could have a large reaction force
that gets generated.
So in some sense, your sensitivity of your controller
might be higher because of this geometric uncertainty.
I mean, I think even in the super simple case,
if you thought this was a 2-centimeter wide brick,
and it's actually a 1.9-centimeter brick,
you could end up right here and just try to lift it up
and completely miss.
Or if you were trying to push inside it,
you would be exerting very large forces
and fighting against it.
I agree.
But I actually think the bigger case--
let's see.
I want to distinguish softness from position and force
control.
These are comparable ideas, and they're separable ideas.
So once we have this idea that everything is--
at least maybe the stiffness is very large if I have a kuka,
with a metal exterior.
But there's a stiffness there.
And we always put at least a rubber pad or something
between our metal and our contact.
Position control, I think, is going
to be vulnerable to geometric perception errors.
But force control is pretty good.
We saw examples of flipping up boxes
without really estimating anything.
And I think it's healthy in this picture
to think about this as a force sensor.
In fact, most force sensors are somehow
having some material of known stiffness,
and you're measuring the deflection of that material.
If you have a known spring stiffness,
and you can measure this deflection,
then you've got a force sensor.
So I think in this simple picture,
you can achieve robustness to geometry
just by being in a force control mode
instead of being in a position control mode.
And I think maybe, in my mind, the argument
for geometric robustness is somehow not as great.
I could do this.
Maybe my ability to do force sensing
might be more or less, depending on k.
But I don't think I need to be a bubble to be better
immune to perception errors.
So let's make our diagram a little bit more rich,
because I do think geometric robustness is a real thing.
But I think we need a more expressive picture to see it.
OK, so I hope you're OK with these sort of silly diagrams.
OK, let's say I've got my hand, my object, my hand here.
And instead of one point finger, let's
make an entire array of point fingers.
They can have dampers, too.
And on this side, too, of course.
Now things get more interesting.
So let's say I start squeezing my hand together.
And let's say I'm large k, the stiff regime.
And I don't know-- I mean, in this case,
I haven't even given my hand the ability
to do well with a lot of geometric information.
But-- or if I just had geometric uncertainty,
and I was choosing my pose as I was coming in,
you could get a similar picture.
Well, let's think about the type of contact
that you'd get if you just start squeezing your hand together,
and you have a pretty stiff set of springs.
I think it'd be pretty easy to-- let me exaggerate it here.
Like, I've got some object here.
It'd be pretty easy to get in a situation
where you're in contact sort of in one or two places here.
You know, the first part of your weird finger-looking thing
is in contact.
And the rest of them, they're sort of no contact.
Right?
Is that picture clear?
OK.
Now, the picture, of course, changes.
If I'm in a very soft regime, you
could imagine for some stiffnesses and some objects
or whatever being in a situation where
the same forces that produced this situation in a stiff
regime could produce this very different situation
in a soft regime, where you might have a larger force there
because it's compressed the spring more,
but I'll have forces everywhere.
Maybe proportionate.
I should be more careful to make them proportional,
but I think you get my drift.
OK.
So why does that matter?
Well, let's say we're going to start lifting the object up,
if our goal is to lift the object up.
What amount of squeezing force do
I need to apply in order to successfully lift the object up?
I need to have enough vertical force to fight gravity.
Every one of my contacts is limited by friction.
So at every point of contact here,
I've got some friction cone.
Maybe they're uniform everywhere
in this first example here.
In order to successfully--
I've got the same thing happening on this side.
Right?
In order to successfully achieve lift-off,
the vertical component of my force coming up here,
which has to stay inside the friction cone
if I don't want to slip, is going to be limited.
My force tangential is going to be
less than or equal to mu of my force normal
by the static friction law.
Right?
That's my friction cone.
OK.
I'm going to have to squeeze hard.
In this regime, I might have to squeeze hard
in order to achieve enough friction in order
to get up high.
In this regime, where I have more possible contacts,
I can potentially, even with the same material properties,
the same friction properties, I could potentially
squeeze less to achieve the same lift-off.
OK.
Now, that could have stability implications
in a number of different ways.
But it seems at least indicative that maybe this
would be a better grasp.
I think the real picture is actually more subtle than that.
Right?
I kind of tried to pick arrows to draw
that were roughly landing on the normal surfaces there.
But I mean, I've also got some contacts, potentially,
here that have friction cones that
are using the same coefficient of friction,
but potentially on very different normals.
Right?
And I think, actually, the world of possible contact forces
opens up pretty quickly.
So now I'm firmly in the camp where
if I can contact an object like this,
with a whole, in the continuum, a whole patch of contact
instead of a point contact, then my ability
to manipulate the object seems improved.
Let me be careful.
You could still argue the counterpoint
that you've given something up.
Right?
If you wanted to somehow explicitly control the contact
forces, and you're making contact
in all these different places with all
these different normals, then to be
able to regulate exactly the normal force
might be almost impossible now, because you wouldn't be able
to know exactly what forces.
But to achieve some sufficient force to pick it up,
or to resist a wrench, that would
be another standard thing, would be if someone came and knocked
this, how likely is it to pop out of my hand,
or something like this.
A grasp that has substantial patch contact
seems like a better grasp most of the time.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
OK, so I think, for me, the difference from point contact
to surface, or people call it patch, contact patches,
contact, is a really big deal.
And I think that's where a lot of the benefits of softness
for geometric robustness and the like come from.
And I think it's what kind of captured my imagination when
I saw these videos, right?
Is that you just really didn't have
to know the pose of the object.
You didn't even have to know where it was.
But you're going to have this like huggable, loving embrace,
almost automatically, with like an open loop arm motion.
It's pretty good.
Let me go out of order, because I screwed up.
So I guess one more point before I go on
to the sensing aspect of it.
Let's compare back in these pictures here.
Maybe I'll work with this one.
Let's compare sensing or stiffness of the spring,
let's say, right at the skin versus something more distal.
So I've talked about EWA having elastic joints.
And when we talked about-- and some of you
have been asked in your project, how do I do contact sensing?
How do I know when I'm in contact with the wall,
for instance, if I'm writing or something like this,
with the EWA?
And the answer is, you look at the joint torques,
the external torques on the joint.
That's where your contact sensors are on EWA.
You could, of course, take your EWA
and put another sensor at the end,
or in the hand, or something.
But by default, the EWA gives you some ability
to do it in the joints.
So what is the picture difference here?
So maybe I have my skin, if I will,
down here with a low mass, and a k here.
And then I've got my finger, or my distal links.
And then I have my elbow or something up here,
or my main forearm, a more distal link.
I'm still just thinking about the one dimensional,
easy to think about, mass spring damper sort of case.
My claim is that if I were to put some sort of rubber tips
or something on the end of the EWA,
then I can do some amount of force control and sensing.
And people do very successfully with EWA,
using this as my force sensor.
Using the fact that there's a stiffness in the joint,
and this is my force sensor.
And I'd like to sort of contrast that
with if you were to try to put your softness and your sensor
more co-located with the contact.
And it's not-- I mean, it's a subtle argument
that talks about bandwidth.
It talks about all the things we talked about.
And you can do it in the linear systems sense.
But I think overall, there are, I think,
advantages to having a contact sensor that
is more co-located with the actual event,
and keeping your actual initial contact mass very low.
So this is something that when I showed you this video before
from Terry, where he was using this bubble sensor that I was
talking about to do writing, he had ignored the EWA joint
sensors and was just demonstrating
that using the skin as a contact force sensor
was sufficient to close a control loop that
would allow him to write on the board.
So I think our tactile sensor's ability to do that
and how do we close feedback loops,
that's a growing technology.
But I think it's an exciting one.
I think we can potentially move our softness and our sensing
closer and closer to the point of interest.
OK, that's just one way to think about softness,
and hopefully a helpful one.
Let's think about the sensing aspect of it.
So we have amazing skin.
And I actually put a picture of the skin.
Towards the end, we'll talk about what's
missing from our robot sensors.
But I guess my introduction--
I studied it back when I was a grad student.
I was in the neuroscience department,
and I took the classes on the basic brain and cognitive
science classes, where we learned about the sensory
system and all of the incredible sensors
you have in your fingertip, and everywhere,
but especially your fingertips.
So what are the possible signals we could get out
of a tactile sensor on a robot?
I mean, I used to--
when I was working on walking, I would
have been happy if I just had a reliable binary contact,
no contact, binary switch.
We did a lot of work in walking, just like,
if you could just tell me with any higher accuracy
when my foot hits the ground, I would already be happy.
Maybe that's still a little bit true today.
We've implied here that--
and I think a common request would
be to have some sort of force sensing
from your tactile sensors.
And I think there's a characteristically different
amount of request from a sensor to give a normal force
versus a sheer force.
But there's other things, too.
People have built robot sensors that
try to estimate temperature, to estimate--
we could talk about the physics of it,
but to try to somehow recognize texture or roughness,
for instance.
These are all, if you wanted to--
if I reached into a toolbox and wanted to find with my--
I can't see inside the toolbox, and I
wanted to use my exquisite tactile sensing
to find the right wrench, let's say.
If I feel something that doesn't feel very metal--
I mean, metal feels cold and has a certain roughness.
And I've got a strong signal, not just from the geometry,
but also from all these other signals.
So this would have been probably the beginnings
of my list a few years ago.
But something really did change fairly recently,
where I think more and more we're thinking about--
these are all things that you might think about when
you think about tactile sensors as measuring a point.
But if you like my silly diagram at the top there,
I think there's really something to be
said for thinking about tactile sensing as a geometry sensor,
and possibly even a dense geometry sensor.
And that was a pretty big change for me to think.
Maybe even if I'm buttoning--
I don't have any buttons on this shirt.
But if I had a shirt with buttons
and I wanted to button it, what do you
think you're using with your fingertips?
Are you trying to estimate the forces
that you're applying to the button?
Or are you getting a sense that the button's
going through the hole by virtue of feeling
some sort of geometry?
I don't know if I completely know the answer,
but it feels like a pretty good geometry.
It feels like geometry is pretty important in a lot
of the things, the thought experiments
that Ted Adelson had me run through when we started
talking a lot about this.
And Ted, I think, had a great impact
when he introduced this geometry view of tactile sensing, which
I'm going back to my--
here we go.
So Ted introduced this-- well, with Kimo--
introduced this sensor gel site.
Many of you probably heard about it.
But let me just sing its praises for a minute.
So basically, they asked the question of,
what happens if I put a camera behind the skin?
How well could I do with that?
And how could I make that really effective?
And there's a couple subtleties about making that effective.
So one of the things that makes that effective
is you'd like to have the camera worry
about the geometry of the contact,
but not worry about all of the RGB complexity of the world,
or the lighting conditions of the world,
or anything like that.
So what they did is they made this small gel layer, hence
gel site.
They found a nice way to paint the coatings, the top layer
of this, so that when you depressed, let's say,
an Oreo, hypothetically, onto this gel layer,
the image from the other side was a beautiful rendering
of the geometry of the contact, without all
of the complexity of lighting conditions
or the complexity of real world vision, let's say.
So that's a reasonable thing to try to do.
And what they showed was that it had a lot of really nice
properties.
So in Ted's lab, there's all kinds of different goos
or whatever.
And it's super fun.
There's enough of it floating around MIT these days.
You can probably get your hands on some
and just start putting your own finger
and put a dollar bill on there.
You can see the hair on your finger
or the grains of a dollar bill through this thing.
And one of the reasons that it's nice that the RGB signal doesn't
come through is that they were, at the time,
doing strictly geometric reconstructions
using photogrammetry.
So in a controlled lighting situation,
with the RGB of the world excluded,
they could just put a red, green, and blue light
in known locations and do a classic computer vision
trick for extracting depth from that now colored image.
And it's just awesome.
You could just see everything.
This is beautiful geometry sensor.
That's a pretty big pad to be sticking on your fingertip.
But people have been scaling it down.
And I think the vision is that we'll
have these things scaled down.
So if you have dense geometry available,
a dense geometry available in your fingertip,
then I think it connects back pretty quickly
to all of the things we already talked about
in the geometric perception lectures.
So as an example, remember we talked about Dart,
where we had point cloud measurements coming in.
We talked about non-penetration constraints.
And then we did our real-time pose estimation and tracking.
That was just one of the algorithms
we talked about in the geometric perception.
And that was based on this idea of having a depth camera that
was looking at the scene.
We got our point cloud.
We also had our free space constraints,
all these things you hopefully remember a bit about from Dart.
If you have a dense geometry sensor in your fingertip,
then it's like you just have one more incredible depth
sensor available inside your finger.
But it's got a short maximum range.
That's OK.
I mean, that gives it a lovable limitation, I guess.
But it gives you information that's not
available from other sensors.
So when we started playing with Gelsight with TED,
that was the point that we tried to make,
Greg made, was that if you have a dense geometry
sensor in your fingertip, it snaps right
into the geometric perception pipelines.
And you can do pose estimation, tracking,
you name it, directly through your combination
of head-mounted sensors and dense geometry
sensors in your fingertips.
So as an example of an application
that was enabled by that, if you wanted
to do an insertion that required some kinematic accuracy,
and you wanted to track the position of the screwdriver
that had to fit in a relatively small hole,
then-- I mean, the first thing that happens,
we've talked about before, is that whenever
you start touching things, your head-mounted cameras often
quickly get occluded by your hand.
But even more so, you can get more accuracy
from these very local dense sensors
in order to take out any of the remaining uncertainty
and do finer scale insertions.
What's the difference between the left and the right
[INAUDIBLE]
This one's ignoring Gelsight, using Gelsight and ignoring
Gelsight.
Maybe it wasn't as profound as we had originally
imagined when we made it, but this one is basically
missing the hole, and this one's going to make the hole.
By the way, why did it make the hole?
I remember it being more profound,
but that was the with and without Gelsight.
That's one in a series of works that people
have done with Gelsight.
Alberto's lab has taken Gelsight and made a more robust version
of it in Gelslim.
You can see these similarly architected sensors.
Gelslim has got a really--
I mean, we used to rip the Gelsight off the finger
all the time.
Again, I love Gelsight, but let me just make the point.
So it's kind of frustrating to have
this exquisite geometry sensing right here,
but then if you happen to reach in
and it doesn't hit exactly where your sensor is,
then not only are you blind, but you've ripped the sensor off.
So that was kind of frustrating.
And that was just the state of the sensor when it started.
This one's got a much tougher fabric.
It's removed all of the, I think, the frailty on the edges.
It's still limited to making contact on the sensor.
The geometry is also different.
So the photogrammetry, I believe, is gone in this version.
I think Rachel can correct me if I'm wrong,
but I think they've switched mostly
to doing depth reconstruction using deep learning approaches
to reconstruction because the photogrammetry required
a particular geometry of the red, green, and blue sensors.
And that was constraining in the geometries
that you could build your sensors.
And this, I think, used a longer throw
and gave up on the strict photogrammetry reconstruction.
Is that true?
Yeah.
And the work here, by the way, is also awesome.
I mean, not only did it use the tactile sensors,
but it used it to do cool things,
showing feedback control of where objects being moved
were observed as requiring different action.
And it even has, you could say, a task and motion planning
level at the top to be very robust.
This sensor here is also inspired by gel site.
It's a different approach.
Again, living with the two-fingered gripper
is kind of limited but beautiful in what you can do.
You can do a lot of things with a good brain and a simple hand.
On the inside of this is a dot pattern.
And we've got a depth camera inside here.
So we actually have a connect--
it's a PicoFlex inside here that is actually doing
explicit depth reconstruction.
And then we put dot patterns on here
in order to get shear and other forces.
And this is super robust.
And we've done a lot of cool manipulation with it,
including one of the things you do
is you say, I'm immune to the transparency of wine glasses.
And I'm subtle to the touch.
So we can do things like stacking wine glasses.
So I do think we're in this sort of series of very cool advances
in sensing.
The geometry sensing is part of the story.
But we do actually have these other types of sensors.
Or let's say camera-based geometry sensing
is only part of this.
I told you about Puno.
This is just the hand on Puno.
And we have this sort of bigger ambition
of building out full Baymax-like humanoid that's
making contact all over the place
and using tactile sensing all over the body.
This is the project that Alex is leading at TRI.
And just as another example, there's
a whole bunch of different ways to measure geometry or force,
which, of course, if you know the stiffness of your sensor,
are related.
This one is an inductive sensing in the chest, actually.
So when you are picking up a massive water
bottle with your chest, then we have a sparser--
I mean, humans also have a lot more density
in their tactile sensing in the hands
than in the other parts of their body.
And so I think a simpler, cheaper technology
is warranted.
And even along the arms, we're just
using pressure sensors in the air pockets covering the arms.
Inductive sensing has been used.
Capacitive sensing has been used.
Resistive sensing-- basically, every possibility, right?
Force-sensing resistors have been used often.
They all have their different pros and cons.
I'll try that one more time, just in case I get lucky.
But maybe I don't get to show you the IIT iCub.
I believe it's this one.
Very cool initial sensing skin.
I would say one of the most advanced systems-level
integration of sensing skin technology on a humanoid robot
is this from the Italian Institute of Technology,
the iCub skin.
I encourage you to check it out.
They not only built nice tactile sensors that could be arrayed,
but they just--
just incredible engineering to make these huge arrays that
could be formed to the skin of the body.
And they just had a whole humanoid with beautiful skin.
And there's videos of them applying forces and controlling
the robot on a full humanoid.
Extremely cool.
CSAIL is a pretty-- or MIT is a pretty good place, I guess,
for tactile sensing.
Voytchek's group has also been doing novel tactile sensors.
So this is one of a series of things
where they've basically been sewing dense--
I think this was FSR at the time--
force sensitive material into fabric.
And they have smart carpets now.
They have smart gloves.
And they have just great instrumentation.
I think the possibilities for robots
to be completely coated with dense sensors,
for humans to have a more immersive VR/AR experience
with these kind of sensors.
I mean, tactile sensing is just, I think, finally coming of age.
It's actually kind of weird that it took so long.
Everybody has known forever how important tactile sensing is.
And it just took a very long time.
Ted used to say, I've got this great tactile sensor.
And I go to the roboticists.
And I say, I've got this great tactile sensor.
And they're like, we don't know what to do with it.
That's great information.
And we don't know what to do with it if you gave it to us.
So maybe, I guess, the roboticists
are finally waking up.
But let me-- I'll finish here by saying that the human skin is
actually incredible.
And there are many other things that you
can do that the human skin does that we're not doing, I think,
in most of our tactile sensing yet.
So let me just point out a few subtleties
in these tactile sensors.
So I won't name all of my anatomy anymore.
I don't think I could without--
I mean, I remember all the corpuscles and Purkinje's
and stuff, but just barely.
Some of them measure force.
Some of them measure temperature.
Some of them measure vibration.
So actually, the signal that you'd
get if I were to try to measure the roughness of this,
there's a part of it, possibly, that
is about the spatial forces that you feel along your finger.
And the fact that your skin has curves and stuff
certainly matters.
But there's also a big part of your signal
that comes in the time domain.
Then you have high frequency vibrations
that are actually a strong indicator of the roughness
of your fabric and stuff like that.
So these are things that are totally
baked into our human sensing.
I mean, people talk about it in research,
but I think they're not mainstream in robotics yet.
So I do think robustness is less of an issue now,
but it's still an issue, I think, as is surface area,
or let's say surface coverage.
This story I said of somehow ripping off a gel site
or reaching into the toolbox and having
the first contact between my hand and the world
be not where my sensor happens to have incredible resolution,
but somehow on the edge of the sensor where
I had some plastic housing.
And actually, that's the part that almost always
bumps into things first.
These are still, I think, practical issues that are
getting better and better, but they're still real.
Sensing slip is a super interesting one.
Everybody thinks if I have tactile sensing,
then I can be more robust because I
can sense when things slip.
Actually, Francois had a great example of it.
He really wanted to close the feedback loop on slip.
That was the project with the ABB arm in Alberto's lab.
And I remember him saying at his defense, it's just too hard.
Basically, slip happens fast.
Slip is an instantaneous event, I guess.
You've gone from static friction to a sliding friction regime.
And in most cases, with the bandwidth
of our sensing plus control, by the time something slips,
it's too late.
So people talk a lot about--
so I've seen very few successes of control systems
that react to a slip in order to recover.
People talk about trying to predict slip.
They talk-- there's a notion of incipient slip,
where you're on the verge of slipping,
and you try to detect pre-slip events and avoid them
and stuff like this.
But I think it's too much to say that tactile sensing gives you
the ability to recover from slip.
And maybe in very--
like if something slides extremely slowly out
of my hand, then maybe.
But blocks falling out of my grasp and stuff
happens pretty fast.
And there are a few others that are--
this is just my random list of other things I wanted to say.
Sorry.
But I've always wondered--
and people have often talked about proximity sensing
versus contact sensing.
And there's been projects through the years
that pop up and produce a new proximity
sensor versus contact sensor.
So as humans, our tactile sensing
is limited that we don't feel things until they actually
make contact with us.
Almost.
We do have hair as mammals.
So we do actually get a little bit from that.
And it's interesting that you should
think about what signal your hair is good for.
I think it's not only for warmth and other things,
but you can maybe tell if there's something coming
by a little bit of aerodynamics on your hair.
You can certainly feel as your hair is bent out of the way.
It's pretty amazing stuff that happens here
because of this instrumentation at the bottom of your hair
follicles.
But there's really--
I mean, we talked about gel sites having a limited throw
at the skin, and that being a good thing in terms
of making the sensing simpler.
But why shouldn't our robots go ahead and detect something
before it makes contact?
Why shouldn't we bury in our skin
things that sense the approach of something,
the proximity of something?
It's interesting.
It just seems like an obviously good thing to do.
And it hasn't really taken off.
I mean, I could list a couple of possible reasons why.
I don't know if people here know why.
But I mean, I think it is--
I've heard from people that do it that it's
hard to make a proximity sensor that works uniformly
for all types of objects, like to have something that would
respond to a metal and a wood and whatever,
like a lot of technologies that are behind the skin
and are using non-vision-based techniques
are sensitive to material properties.
Some things are magnetic or whatever.
But I wouldn't be surprised if in a few years
we are sensing contact before it happens.
It seems like just an obviously good idea.
OK.
So that was a--
I didn't do my chip demo.
But I thank you for bringing the chips, by the way.
I was just going to make the point
that I could squeeze a potato chip in a rigid object,
and it would break.
And I could squeeze it in this.
I'll at least squeeze it in this.
It's the distributed contact point, right?
So this is the standard thing, would be the egg.
It's good for the egg.
It's good for the potato chip.
It's not just like I can produce more forces.
But it's pretty nice to sort of distribute the load
across an entire surface.
It's good for the object you're hugging, too, right?
I could put a lot of force, normal force on this,
and the chip's fine.
And I've got a few broken chips from playing
with my rigid clamp just before lecture,
and some grease on my fingers.
Yes?
So the question that I have is we
started off talking about all these really cool open loop
achievements with software like things
like the thing manipulates the cube without any feedback.
What was the gap that led to all this tactile [INAUDIBLE]??
We get all these great results with remote.
Yeah.
I mean, for a long time, and maybe even still today,
like the soft robotics journals, wherever,
there's incredible fabrication technology, incredible results.
I can hit my thing with a hammer.
I can put it on the charcoal grill.
And then it says control is future work, right?
Sorry.
I think it's still true.
But everybody knows that you should do control.
I think the things you can do in open loop
are enveloping grasps work really, really well.
But there's a whole bunch of things in manipulation
that is more than enveloping grasps.
That's been a theme over the--
if you wanted to do the type of stuff, even the bottle turning,
the stuff that Rachel was showing,
or any number of things we've shown over the term,
you've got to do something more than just the open loop
stable.
You want to be able to react to your environment,
dig into the toolbox, and find the wrench.
There's all kinds of motivations for that.
I do think that we don't have all those pieces.
I mean, deep learning-- so geometric perception
works well with tactile, once you have dense geometry.
You can combine-- also in the deep pipeline,
you can bring your tactile sensors in,
especially if they're dense geometry,
and you can put them through a convolutional network.
And that works pretty well.
Yunzhu in our group has done some pretty incredible things
with that.
Other people have as well.
So I think it's coming.
But we haven't seen, I think, its full power yet.
Yes?
So I'm curious.
You said we-- that you get more capabilities if we have proximity
sensors.
But I'm just having a hard time imagining what
you'd be able to do with proximity sensors that you
couldn't already get with a hand-mounted camera,
besides avoiding occlusion.
Good question.
So what about proximity versus a hand-mounted camera?
But I think hand-mounted cameras have been less useful
than I expected.
And I think the-- certainly depth cameras
have a maximum range, and they also have a minimum range.
And that minimum range--
oftentimes, when you talk to the manufacturers,
they're like, well, we just never--
nobody ever asked us to make a shorter minimum range.
We were always worried about pushing out the maximum,
never shortening the minimum.
So there's probably hardware improvements
that, if it became a priority, could be done.
But even RGB techniques, it seems
like, once you get pretty close, the RGB signal
is just not as good.
Maybe your camera is getting blurry,
but also just the field of view is very small.
So there-- and then, once you're in contact,
I think you can start getting local but interesting geometry
again.
But there seems to be this intermediate space, where
you're too close for a camera to be super useful.
You're not touching in contact yet.
So maybe we will have cameras looking out all over our bodies.
That's a possible future.
And maybe-- and just--
and rely on the RGB.
And maybe, just because the price point of iPhones
bringing down cameras and stuff, maybe that's the reason--
that's the way it's going to go.
It's a good question.
OK.
The big points-- I think you can think a lot
about the mechanics of softness, the benefits or trade-offs
of softness, even with linear spring mass damper systems.
I really think that a lot of people
have used that kind of model to great effect
to think about the pros and cons of softness.
The real world has more interesting geometry
and the like, but a lot of the lessons transfer.
And the fact that tactiles can be a geometry sensor,
I think, is just a really cool connection to the type of tools
we've already talked about.
You can do pose estimation tracking,
but you can also do shape estimation.
There's object detection.
All of the sort of classical perception techniques
you can think about doing with tactile.
It's a little different because you
have very local features as opposed to global features,
but the same kind of ideas work.
All right, so let me end by just kind of giving an overview,
kind of a wrap-up of what we've done over the term,
just to put a bow on it here.
OK.
We've done a lot of things.
And I appreciate-- I mean, I sort of
feel like the class is taking material that maybe should be
is still sort of like research seminar class,
and it's trying to present it as a textbook class.
And we're somewhere in between, and there's some rough edges,
and I appreciate your patience.
But it's pretty fun to sort of be
in a field that's kind of on the verge of those two things.
So let's just lay the landscape a little differently
than I did in the chapters, just to think about that.
So we talked about kinematics, dynamics, simulation.
That was definitely a big theme.
In simulation, I emphasized the signals and systems
view of the world.
And some of you hate that this week.
But it's good.
No, I mean, but I do think that to scale
to very complex systems.
I mean, you hear from the big players that
are trying to build these massively complex systems
and have a level of robustness, that somehow that way
of arranging all the different components together
is, I think, a very scalable and robust.
I mean, Simulink is not a successful product
for so many years without reason.
And I think in manipulation, everything snaps in two.
We're seeing that over and over again.
So you got a taste of that.
I hope you didn't dislike it too much.
And then we had sort of the manipulator view of the world,
where we talked about the manipulator control ideas
from differential IK to force control and hybrid control
to stiffness control.
That's about how do you move your arm around,
ignoring all the complexity of the world,
regulate forces and the like.
We talked about planning sort of in that view of the world
too, about RRTs, trajectory optimization.
And that was-- our focus in the planning
was, again, about sort of the robot's view of the world
with its eyes closed.
How do you get from point A to point B?
If you've brought in some obstacles,
maybe you're going to plan around the obstacles.
But it was thinking mostly about the motion of the robot,
not the motion of the world.
We, of course, talked a bunch about perception with a big--
I wanted to emphasize first some of the geometry
and the geometric perception from ICP, Dart, et cetera,
for pose estimation.
But we also talked a bit about dense reconstructions.
That came up a bunch.
I never spent a lecture on it, but it kept coming up.
And then, of course, the revolution in perception
that's come from deep learning, segmentation,
pose estimation, but also new representations.
I think the thing I'm most excited about with the deep
learning approaches is that we can get fundamentally--
we don't have to go all the way through to pose.
And we can potentially estimate much less than a full shape
or pose estimation algorithm.
Maybe it's just the key points.
That was a simple example.
But maybe it's just some latent representation
that isn't even human intelligible that
comes out of a deep learning system,
but is enough to do good control.
And then when we talked about controlling--
moving the actual objects in the world,
affecting the world more, when we got deeper into that,
the major approach we talked about was RL.
We did it before, of course, by relatively simple--
I'm going to come into contact, close my hand,
and go like this.
But when we started getting richer emphasis
on the control of the environment,
we started talking mostly about RL, reinforcement learning,
and all of its different variants.
But maybe slightly more general, I
tried to emphasize the general awesomeness of, I think,
visual motor policies.
And whether you get them from RL or imitation learning
or model-based RL or model-free RL,
I think the opportunity to connect
these types of rich sensing, possibly
through novel representations, directly to control policies
is just so awesome.
And it's something that we're going
to see more and more of.
We talked about high-level task planning.
Rachel gave a great lecture last week.
We talked about it a little bit early on,
from strips and PDIDL, state machines, and behavior trees,
and then TAMP last week.
Actually, I told Rachel after her lecture
that watching her talk about it, I really--
I think next year, I think this has got to be even a more
core piece of the class.
I think we've got to move it up.
And it's just such an important piece of the manipulation
pipeline to scale to much more complicated tasks.
I think I felt really inspired by that.
So those are, in my mind, the core components
that we've been talking about.
And we've talked tactile and other things have added on,
I hope, some elements.
But like I say, it's pretty fun to be in a place
right now where it sort of feels like we have a curriculum
for manipulation.
And those tools will get more and more mature.
And the core concepts will be more and more mature.
And I hope that maybe there's value.
I hope the value that this class can bring
is that trying to put these under sort of the same umbrella
and same symbols most of the time
and same code most of the time.
So I mean, I think the number one thing
I want you to walk away with is that it's a super vibrant
research community.
It's a super vibrant problem.
I mean, the number of people in industry
that care about manipulation is just skyrocketing.
I think the potential for it to maybe to get grand,
to shape the future of humanity, the future of work, life off
Earth, I don't know.
It's pretty important stuff.
Maybe there are other important things out there, too.
But this is pretty important.
So yeah, maybe this will be a foundation for you.
And I hope some of you continue on and push on and give us
feedback so that we can keep making the course better.
Good.
Well, your turn next.
So Thursday, we will do the project videos.
And I think everybody knows the deal.
But I hope many of you will come here to watch with us.
We'll do a viewing session.
We have the room till 5 if we need it.
And we'll get oohs and ahs and questions
if you're here to answer them.
And we have time.
And I'll see you then.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]