[SIDE CONVERSATION]
OK.
Welcome back, everybody.
Today we're going to do our third and kind of wrap up
lecture on the first exposure we have to geometric perception.
We'll come back again when we talk about the connections
from deep perception and geometric perception.
But just to make sure the roadmap is clear, I hope,
we started talking about the idea of you've got two point
clouds.
You just want to find the pose that
allows those point clouds to come into registration.
And mostly came up with the iterative closest point
algorithm as our mainstay.
In particular, that beautiful fact
that you can call the singular value decomposition to just
solve for the pose.
That's like the magical step.
And then you use that in an iterative algorithm.
Day two, we started embracing some
of the messiness of point clouds from outliers and partial
views.
And the key idea was that even if you go from scene to model
or model to scene, at some point not all your points
are going to match.
And you have to deal with that.
So you have to somehow have some non-matches.
And we talked about a couple of different ways to do that,
including sort of generalizing the notion of correspondence
with some of the soft correspondence ideas.
We're going to build on that a bit more today.
But today I really want to talk about, I guess,
the limitations in that basic problem formulation.
It doesn't solve all the problems
that we wanted to solve.
It doesn't give us the ability to say everything
we know about the problem.
And therefore, the algorithm, even the best possible point
registration algorithm, I hope to convince you,
can't give you the answer you want all the time.
It's like you're not telling the algorithm everything
you know about the world.
So we're going to try to tell it a few more things.
But because of that, we're going to lose our beautiful SVD
magic in the middle and have to resort
to less powerful but more general solvers.
So how can it be less powerful?
So it'll eat up a larger class of problems.
You can put in more types of costs and constraints,
but you will be able to solve them with less reliability.
And then we'll see how that plays out
into some pose estimation algorithms that
can consume more of what we know about the world
and do a nice job.
And we'll try to wrap up the pose estimation pass.
So here, let me set that up and try to just convince you
that we haven't told the algorithm everything.
And this is basically what happens.
The first time you go to implement your beautiful point
correspondence algorithm in a manipulation problem,
I showed you the lumpy point clouds.
That's real.
You've got something you're going to pick up off the table.
And inevitably, you've got, I don't know,
some coffee mug sitting on the table.
And you've got your camera here.
And you're getting some nice returns off the camera.
And your algorithm comes back and says, I found the pose.
And it's like inside the table.
And you think, come on.
I know the pose.
I know the mug's not inside the table.
But you didn't tell the algorithm.
It might actually be that the optimal fit to the points that
match the CAD model, given the data that you've got,
could be this pose.
That if the point registration algorithm was perfect,
but your data was a little noisy or other things,
it could actually be that the best fit here dramatically
violates some other constraint, just
because you haven't told the algorithm about the fact
that mugs don't typically reside inside tables.
And more generally, things should not be in penetration.
Similarly, you'll run the algorithm another time.
And you'll get some mug floating in space.
And you think, OK, I know that the mug's not
floating in space.
But how do I tell the algorithm that mugs
don't float in space?
So this one, I would say, is we have
to figure out a way to talk about non-penetration.
Constraints is typically how we formulate it.
[SIGHS]
This one, how would you--
I mean, what makes that a bad solution?
It's more than just geometry.
It's got something about physics.
And there's probably some assumption required there
that the world is static before I started touching it.
So something like a static stability,
or static equilibrium, let me just say--
it doesn't have to be stable, but--
would be another type of constraint
that I might want to tell my algorithm about,
which we haven't done yet.
And there's even, I'd say, one more big one
that I want to make sure we capture today,
which the point set registration formulation just
doesn't have room for yet.
And we have to extend it.
Maybe I won't use a mug for this.
I'll use a different shape.
But let's say I have a box here, and a camera here.
And I get beautiful returns here.
And the posed estimation says, yeah, I've got your box.
Fit my error-- you know, zero error.
There it is right there.
And the thing that you know that you didn't tell the algorithm
about is that if I have a camera here and a point here,
that means that there can't be any geometry there.
So this would be the free space constraints.
There's just extra information that
wasn't contained if your only problem formulation is
match the point clouds that you didn't
tell where the camera was.
So it couldn't possibly have known
that you wanted this solution instead of this solution.
OK?
So those are three examples, but you can come up with more too.
And in general, I actually very much
enjoy the game of trying to figure out
how much of these kind of problems
you can fit into a strong optimization,
you know, a convex optimization framework.
And I would say that's one of the advanced topics
I'll mention at the end.
But let's step back and not worry
about that from the beginning.
And we'll just accept that we're going to write messier
optimization problems and use more general solvers.
OK?
But we'll be able to write these constraints
and think about how they work.
And then we'll revisit at the end
of whether there's any question of whether we
can fit this into a more beautiful optimization
framework or whether we even need to.
There's one more example which I guess I want to say,
just because I'm a little on the fence about whether I should
say it now or later.
Because this one could be shoved into SVD framework,
but let me just-- it bugs me about the standard point set
registration, right?
So imagine I have, I don't know, a door.
OK?
I've got a room and the door's open or something.
And I'm getting returns on the door.
OK?
That's a terrible drawing of a door.
And let's say there's a handle here on the door.
If I have a camera looking at the door,
just some partial view of the door, for instance, right?
I'm going to get a bunch of returns all over the door.
OK?
But if I get a few returns on that handle,
that feature is so important that it tells me
so much more than the rest of the things on the door.
Right?
If I got a small snapshot of just like this part of the door,
I wouldn't have any idea where the rest of the door was.
But if I got a small snapshot that
contained part of the handle, I'd
know pretty darn well where the whole door is.
Right?
And that happens in other ways, too.
So imagine I have like a table with my lumpy point
cloud coming off.
And I've got a book sitting on the table.
Right?
So I've got some thin book, OK?
Let's say.
And I've got points coming all over the place.
OK?
And I've got like a few points just on the edge of the book.
Just a few, right?
But you can get a very good score in ICP
if you move that book all around.
Right?
You're still matching most of the points.
Those few points on the edge give you
so much more information about the pose than the rest of it.
Right?
So somehow, you know something about that
that you haven't told the algorithm about.
Now, the reason I was hesitant--
there is a version.
You can certainly put weights on the points.
You can say some points in my point cloud
are more important than others and stick that
into the ICP framework.
But the point is that you don't even know a priori.
There's something else you know, which
is that the points on the edge of the object
are somehow more important.
If you encode that in for that object, you can be OK.
But there's something sort of like more than just
like pure geometry that's required.
There's some understanding of features and other things
that happens here.
So we need a more general set of tools.
So as beautiful as SVD is as a solution, and as fast as it is,
I think it maybe has constrained our thinking a little bit.
We just try to find ways to stick everything into it.
So let's just think about what's the more general view
of optimization, which is typically
called nonlinear optimization, especially
if the functions are smooth.
But just for clarity here, try to say nonconvex optimization.
So let me spend a few minutes telling you what that class is
and what are the implications of leaving convex
and going to nonconvex.
OK?
So far, we've been thinking about problems that mostly
have been convex, at least the optimization sub parts.
So in the ICP, the pose estimation
was SVD or convex optimization.
And the finding the points, you could say, was not a convex,
but that was just a brute force optimization.
But all that pose part has been using
convex-type formulations.
And similarly, even in the quadratic programming,
we did for the kinematics, right?
And we did that in the kinematics section.
It's been hiding around here.
But there are other linear programs.
A lot of these problems that we've been thinking about
have nice optimization formulations.
Now, the picture for a quadratic program, but is more general,
is that I've got some, I'd say, even a convex quadratic,
positive definite quadratic, is I've
got some decision variables.
If I'm going to min over x, f of x, if f of x is quadratic,
then I want it to be a positive quadratic
and have some nice, full, safe objective,
with the key observation being that there's a unique--
I don't even care if it's unique.
I just want to have that, let's say, all minima are
global minima.
So I can write strong algorithms that
will find the optimal solution to the problem
when f is somehow a convex function.
And similarly, if I start writing constraints,
if f is a convex function, and if this is a convex set,
then I have these nice algorithms
that will find me global solutions to my problems.
So now I have to decide how far to go into that rabbit hole,
but I'm going to try staying here.
Tell me if you have questions or anything.
There's certainly plenty of things to know about that.
So we've restricted ourselves so far
to formulations of the point set registration that could
fit in this sort of a framework.
The more general, if f of x is more arbitrary,
but let's say a smooth but non-linear, non-convex
function, then the picture can look more arbitrary.
And you'd like to be able to find
the minimum of that objective, but in practice,
oftentimes algorithms are going to get stuck in local minima.
OK.
So what I want you to have is have
sort of a practical understanding
of the implications of going from--
when I'm talking about convex optimizations,
I should expect to find global solutions.
When I start talking about non-linear,
non-convex optimizations, I have to worry
about a couple of things.
First of all, I have to worry that the solution I get
may or may not be optimal.
It could be worse.
It could be that a solution exists,
and my solver doesn't even find it because it's stuck here.
If I have a constraint saying, I must be inside this set,
and I start my search over here, and I get stuck here,
it might be that there is a solution to the problem that
would satisfy my constraints, and I didn't find it.
And in general, where the notion of sort of an initial guess
wasn't even part of our language here, for these problems,
it does become part of the language.
So all that sounds pretty lousy, but the--
but the good news is I get to express richer problems
because I have a much larger vocabulary of functions
I can put in f and g and do reasonable optimization on.
Oftentimes, you'd like them to be smooth or continuous.
You'd like them to be differentiable,
but even that can be relaxed in some case.
So I saw some feedback on--
I really enjoy reading the feedback, by the way.
So every time when you guys are filling out the surveys,
know that those are being read and appreciated.
Some people said you want to see more examples even in code
about translating some of the ideas on the board to code.
So I can just connect this with the types of things
that you write in code.
So Drake has this mathematical program stuff
you've started to use.
And I want you to appreciate that there's
a handful of different ways that you can add costs
and constraints to the system.
So if I have a mathematical program
and I make a decision variable x,
write a new continuous variable x,
that's roughly what I've done here, just declared
a decision variable.
What it might help you to know, and you might already
appreciate, might not have realized,
is that this thing that it returns, x,
is actually a pretty powerful symbolic variable.
We have a big symbolic engine sitting behind Drake.
So you can treat that as just a placeholder for the decision
variables, kind of a name for the decision variables,
but you can also do symbolic things with it.
So even if your cost function was quadratic,
in the simple case, in the convex case,
we give you a handful of different ways
that you can add the costs and the constraints
into the problem.
You could use this sort of specific add quadratic cost
method and tell it the coefficients of the matrices.
And that's the most structured thing you can hand Drake.
It then does fast numerical operations,
but it knows that the problem is convex.
And it can check that it's a convex quadratic.
When you type in something like add cost or add quadratic cost
and you pass in just math on that variable x,
this is turning it into a symbolic expression.
You might see that in your error messages, symbolic expression,
which then when mathematical program eats that up,
it actually will check.
If it's a symbolic expression you pass in,
it will actually check, is that a quadratic?
Is it a linear?
Is it convex?
And if it was convex, it will shuffle it
into the right bin of costs and constraints
so that it knows you've got a convex problem.
OK.
If you get to the end and you call solve
and you have only added costs and constraints
that mathematical program knows are convex,
then it will dispatch you to a specialized convex optimization
solver, right?
Garobi or Mosec if you've got the licenses installed
or even one of the open source ones if you're just--
I guess on deep note, most of you
are using the open source ones, which are not as good,
but they're free.
That's just the way it is, right?
And the difference is substantial in the cost.
But know that it's doing a lot of work behind the scenes
to try to figure out if these problems are convex or not.
And there's a handful of tools out here
that try to do this kind of thing.
Stephen Boyd likes to call it disciplined convex
optimization.
We'll see the whole group that works with him
calls this disciplined convex optimization, where
they try to ask you to write costs and constraints
in a disciplined way.
And the software does its best to hold the high standards
and formulate problems the right way.
And Drake's trying to do that too.
OK.
You can also add arbitrary costs.
So you can say make a function, which just takes my x in
and does some math and returns it.
And in this function, you could potentially
be calling multi-body plant everything.
Oh, yeah.
Alex.
[INAUDIBLE]
Not all of them.
Right.
We have our own set, and I would say it's not as disciplined.
But it's on that path.
The question was, do we actually use the disciplined convex
optimization rules?
Not all of them.
OK, so I could make an arbitrary function here.
And this doesn't have to be quadratic.
I could have put anything-- actually,
the add cost doesn't have to be quadratic,
but it has to be something that I can do sort
of symbolically in this case.
Here I could write actually arbitrary code,
because x doesn't come in as a symbolic variable.
It comes in as a autodiff variable.
And so anything that I can autodiff through--
autodiff means automatic differentiation.
We have an automatic differentiation library already
behind there, too.
So functions that might not have a symbolic form
will often have a differentiable form that it'll crawl through.
I'm afraid that if you know autodiff, that made sense.
And if you don't know autodiff, that didn't make sense.
But hopefully-- I mean, the basic idea
that if I have a variable here that contains, let's say,
a double value for x, but also the gradients of x,
and I pass that through, and on each line
I do the chain rule in software, I can actually
crawl through even complicated functions
here, as long as I've got automatic differentiation
for those functions.
If you add cost this way into the mathematical program,
it doesn't have the ability to know
whether it's quadratic or not.
So if you add this cost, even though you've
added a quadratic, since it's no longer--
it only has a local understanding of the function.
It's only able to evaluate at x and its derivatives.
You can write more expressive functions here,
but you've lost the structure.
When you get to the end of this, even
though the function is a quadratic cost,
it will actually, when you call solve,
have to call a less performance solver.
It'll call our nonlinear optimizer,
which is typically SNOPT, in the examples you use.
The big thing, though, that's going to happen
is that today we're going to start adding
more and more of these costs, which don't have a convex form.
You can't call them the better solvers, if you will.
SNOPT's a good solver, but it's solving a bigger
class of problems, so it can't be as strong.
But we're going to fill out more of these general forms.
Yeah?
Can you add quadratic costs for my cost?
Like, if you need to guess when you already have a position,
and what do you know is quadratic or not?
So you can call-- so you wouldn't do it inside my cost?
Yeah, outside.
Yeah, yeah.
You can definitely add--
there are different ways.
I mean, you would tend to go through this.
So I will often write, like, multi-body plant code,
which takes the quadratic, whether it's
a Jacobian or something like that,
and then calls add quadratic cost directly.
And you'll actually see that we have a library of the types
of constraints that we're doing here.
We actually have a library of constraints
that will add, for instance, non-penetration constraints.
And it will do all the right things behind the scenes
to add them the best possible way
to the mathematical program.
One of the big things that's important to realize
is that when you're solving a nonlinear optimization,
I think it's mostly good that Drake just does
the thing behind the scenes, and you don't have to worry about
whether you're solving it.
But if you realize that you're solving it,
there is another step you could do
in the nonlinear optimization, which I forgot
to put on the slide here.
But you could do prog.setInitialGuess x,
like 32 or something.
So when you're in this problem, it
doesn't matter where your initial guess is.
You'll find the right solution.
And the solvers actually don't--
many of the solvers don't even take advantage.
They don't even have an interface
where you would specify the initial guess.
Some do, but all the interior point methods
don't, classically.
But in this one, it can obviously matter a great deal
whether you have a good initial guess.
So there is an interface where you can call setInitialGuess,
and it will set up everything to go from there.
Yes?
Could you describe maybe at a high level
some of the strategies in the nonlinear optimization
application?
Yeah, totally.
The question was, what strategies
do the nonlinear optimization use?
There's really, I think, two really big ones to know.
The first one would be gradient descent.
You could think of stochastic gradient descent
if you've heard of that from the learning world.
But in general, if you take a gradient of this
and you move in the direction of the gradient,
the picture in 1D isn't quite rich enough
to fully show the value of the gradient,
but basically you go downhill.
When you have constraints, too, gradient descent
needs to be adjusted.
You either do a projected gradient descent
or something else.
And that depends on how easily you
can project on your constraints.
So in practice, oftentimes for constrained
nonlinear optimization, a preferred approach
is to do a second order method, which
uses the gradient and a local approximation of the Hessian.
And they basically will take a local quadratic approximation.
They turn it into a QP.
And they'll solve it as if it's a QP.
And then they'll update.
So this would make, let's say, a local approximation like this.
It'll come here.
It'll get a new initial guess.
It'll make a new local approximation.
It can still get stuck in that same local minima.
But the reason to do that is because you can also
linearize these constraints and do a nice update that
takes into account both the objective and the constraints.
So that would be called sequential quadratic programming.
And the one SQP.
And that is what the main solver that you'll
use without even appreciating in class,
but SNOPT is the solver that gets called
in the Drake binaries for that.
There's a bunch of other ideas.
And people tend to--
there's actually, I'd say, a movement
to do a little bit less of the constrained optimization
and to instead take those constraints
and turn them into a penalty method.
And so you do unconstrained optimization.
Some people think that's faster or more robust.
There's ways to do that more rigorously.
But this is, I think, the simplest answer
to your question.
Sure.
Any other questions at that level?
So how often do problems with real-world robotics
come down to not being able to do the full optimization
that you would expect?
So the question is, in general real-world robotics,
how much do you end up doing nonlinear optimization
versus convex optimization, roughly?
I think a lot of problems are being solved
with nonlinear optimization.
Trajectory optimization is one I know you've seen
and we'll see later in this class.
A lot of the motion planning type problems
are going to be these kind of problems.
I think the problems that we're going to talk about today
are going to be these types of problems.
It's a special thing when you can
find a formulation for a really complex problem that
fits into this.
Part of my career has been trying to do that,
with some success.
So I think life gets--
I mean, it's almost tantamount-- it
used to be that you wouldn't consider
a problem to be solved until you had a closed form solution.
But I think even the most rigorous mathematicians are now
like, if you can find a convex parameterization,
then you've gotten pretty close to solving the problem.
So we try to move things from here to here,
but I think a lot, in reality, we're down here a lot.
Pose graph optimization and SLAM, that's all down here.
A lot of the canonical robotics problems
are kind of stuck down here.
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, I'm sorry.
OK.
That was a long answer to the wrong question.
But OK.
So yeah, so the question is, how much
does local minima affect my--
do I get stuck because of--
OK, I'll tell you a firsthand experience.
Atlas is our 400-pound humanoid.
We're in the DARPA Robotics Challenge, right?
We had beautiful optimization that
could make the robot run all these things,
trajectory optimization.
But it was a nonlinear optimization,
and I couldn't be sure that it was going to run in real time.
We didn't run a single one of those at the DARPA Challenge,
except for inverse kinematics to reach into some places.
But basically, in the lab, we knew how to make the robot run.
At the day of the competition, when everybody's watching,
I could not take the chance that it's running along.
And in midair, it says, oops, can't find a solution.
You know, pfft, right?
So that's my experience.
Now, autonomous cars often are doing this,
and they don't always have guarantees.
I mean, there's ways that you have local guarantees,
and there's wrappers around it.
But there's a surprising number of practical applications
where people are solving approximations
of nonlinear model predictive control.
In that case, they have a chance of getting stuck,
but they put Band-Aids around it to make it OK.
Good.
OK, so we're leaving our beautiful land of global minima
and going into this messier land.
But we're going to be able to write these constraints
that we need, I think.
So let's do pose estimation with nonlinear optimization.
And rather than just start from scratch
with a new formulation that's nonlinear,
let me just try to walk us and say,
how could we take the ICP kind of formulation
and start taking advantage of this?
And then we'll throw in some new constraints.
OK, so before, we wrote problems like minimize p, r,
in the real numbers 3 by 3, p plus r.
Someone asked about the squared.
It's always least squares.
OK, and then we had to add the extra constraints, right?
So let's consider-- that was the known correspondence.
One of the reasons we chose to use the rotation matrix
representation of that was because we
could make this quadratic objective
and then use that SVD solution.
Let's see what happens if we now change our parameterization
and we end up with a nonlinear problem.
I'll do the 2D version first.
So what is that going to look like?
If I did min-- I'm just going to focus on the-- we can always
take that into account, too.
But let me just focus on the rotations.
So if I, instead of doing r here,
if I put in the rotation matrix and I parameterized it
by theta-- so remember, in 2D, the rotation matrix
has this favorite form.
So I did that matrix times this.
What constraints do I need?
I don't need any constraints, right?
The only reason I needed constraints here
is because I used too many parameters
to specify my rotation matrix.
Here it's a scalar.
And I will only get valid rotations
given any theta I put in.
I don't need any constraints.
So now I've traded my constraints,
gotten away with my constraints, but I
have a nonlinear objective.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
So it's kind of interesting to ask, how much worse is this?
What does that do to the problem?
I think in these simple problems,
we can kind of understand it.
So let's do that.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
In particular, I'd like to ask the question,
does that problem have local minimum?
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
I write this two different ways.
Actually, when I wrote this, I was like,
I'd normally write it the other way.
These are two different spellings
of the same constraint.
So if I just multiply by r on the other side--
I need a transpose here.
That's what I need.
Good.
r transpose equals r inverse.
Otherwise, that would only be the identity.
That would have been insufficient.
Yes.
So the question is, do I have any local minima here?
I know I've walked back and forth.
I'm sorry.
OK.
Let me work it out on a simple example.
Imagine my object of interest is actually just a circle.
It's not very circular.
I could do better, at least with the center.
OK.
So I've got a lot of points here.
But let me-- I won't make every different color.
But let me just do a couple--
just make it clear that there's sort of known correspondences.
OK.
I need a lot more colors of chalk if I wanted to do that.
OK, and so now I've got a new sighting of this object
where I have-- well, I have it in a different pose.
OK.
Let's go all the way around, of course.
But I have known correspondences from here to here,
here to here.
If I were to do--
write this objective, then what happens?
So I can even take the simpler case
of putting them, assuming that there's only
a change in rotation.
The translations, always you can take out--
sorry.
Anytime you have an unconstrained optimization,
you can solve away the Ps.
That was hidden in the derivation of the SVD.
If you studied it in the notes, they went through that.
But if you have an unconstrained optimization,
you can actually solve-- given any r,
you can solve for Ps, so you can get rid of the Ps.
Sorry, Celia.
Is that what--
CELIA: No.
That was your question?
OK, good.
OK.
So we can actually, in this case,
if this is right on top-- so my blue, my other blue--
how do I draw this without it being too confusing?
One more color will help, I'm sure.
So I had this blue here.
My correspondence was right there.
The inside of this expression is the square distance
between those two points.
That's what I'm summing up.
And as I go around the circle, my objective over there
is just the sum of the square distance.
So this one I can actually just figure out.
So the geometry is not too hard.
This is the radius of my circle, r.
This is also r.
So that distance, I can just use the law of cosines.
So in general, you guys remember the law of cosines, right?
So let's make sure I remember the law of cosines.
c squared minus 2ab cos theta.
So this is theta.
So that's for an arbitrary abc theta, right?
That's the relationship of c to--
so in this case, what is the distance going to be?
It's going to be distance squared, which
is the inside of my objective.
It's going to be r squared plus r squared minus 2rr.
So r squared cosine theta.
And it's going to be that same distance for all those points.
OK?
So this one I can even just write in as 2r squared 1
minus cos theta.
So I can-- I'm going to get n of them
by total ICP objective given theta.
So if you plot that as a function of theta,
let me even plot it as a function of-- I'll
write theta minus theta estimated minus theta actual.
How about that?
I used one of them as kind of 0 in this case,
but it would be a little bit more accurate to say
the error in my theta.
That's just going to look like 1 minus cos, right?
Scaled by my number of points and r,
but this looks like 1 minus cos.
So that is a nonlinear objective.
It has many minima at 2 pi, though.
So in this case, in 2D, parameterizing by theta,
it's fine, right?
So it happens that all minima are global minima, right?
That's a trendy thing to say.
All minima are global minima.
So now, that gets a little worse in 3D.
That's not true in 3D, I don't think.
I know it certainly-- yeah, I think it can't be true.
But the real thing that's going to make it more complicated
is if we have unknown correspondences.
Unknown correspondences are going to cause all kinds of--
the same way they did in the ICP problems,
it's the correspondences that will cause these local minima.
So I don't mean to say that Poe's estimation always
has local minima, but I simply mean
to say it's not crazy to parameterize things with theta.
You can do pretty good things.
You can kind of expect that if I were to optimize directly
on theta, do some gradients, certainly
in these simple problems, it's going to work.
This problem, I think, is actually not--
this formulation is not as limited as maybe I
made it sound, right?
So if I took any object, really, any set of points,
there's going to be some points on this thing.
They all have some-- if I rotate that,
I could have done exactly the same computation.
It's just that I'd have a different radius
r for all of the points.
So I'd have a slightly different thing.
But actually, in 2D, it doesn't have
to be a circle for that math to work.
Yeah?
Is this conclusion that all of the minima
are just like the-- all of them get, like,
some theta around the points?
Or some noise to the--
[INAUDIBLE]
I mean, certainly not arbitrary noise, right?
I think the question would be, what
could we say about the robustness of that estimator?
The question was, does this hold in a case
where you have real messy points?
Right.
I think it'd be an interesting question to ask.
I mean, this is a pretty robust objective, right?
So it probably would be fairly tolerant to noise.
But certainly, you could pick a noise threshold
that would be too big for it to handle.
And that's going to depend on probably
the distance between the--
what would it depend on?
I mean, it's really--
if I were to just add noise to that objective,
I mean, it's going to be fairly tolerant, I think.
It'd be fun to do the proper analysis.
OK, so everything's better in 2D.
If I haven't said that before, it's like everything works.
Physics engines are slightly fast in 2D.
Like, friction's easy in 2D.
Pose estimation's easy in 2D.
If the world was flat, we'd be done.
Unfortunately, everything gets messy in 3D.
All this Euler angles aren't great.
It comes up and makes this problem less good.
But in 2D, I think we can already
see that it's the correspondences that
are the biggest source of challenge
that cause these nonlinear optimizations to get stuck.
The fundamental idea that we've changed
to a nonlinear optimization, I think, is not a problem.
So let's think about how do we do the correspondences,
given we have a nonlinear optimization toolbox.
We did it before in alternations.
Even our generalized correspondence,
the coherent point drift algorithm,
was setting the soft correspondences
with the Gaussian in one step and then
doing an optimization, solving the--
everything we did before was kind of alternations.
Almost everything we did before.
So given this richer vocabulary--
[WRITING ON BOARD]
Last time, we did the generalized correspondences.
Remember, we said, OK, I'm going to search over my pose.
But I'm going to do a sum over i and j
over every possible correspondence.
But I'll weight them.
[WRITING ON BOARD]
And CPD, the coherent point drift,
chose to set those in the alternating step
as a Gaussian function.
But if we want to actually solve them jointly now,
I can write something basically like that.
But I can use any nonlinear function.
So what if I do instead minimize over x sum over ij,
just sum any function l.
This would be my nonlinear objective.
OK.
Could even just be a function of the distances, typically.
And people do this.
And they choose all kinds of different functions.
So you might have seen l--
I mean, l could be a Gaussian kernel.
And then you get something that's very similar to this.
I said, given the distance between my points,
look up, given that distance, how much
do I want to penalize them?
So if I took the Gaussian kernel, which is here,
that's roughly what CPD was doing.
It's doing it with a pre-multiplication, which
is slightly different.
But the intent is the same, is that you
want to have a roughly quadratic form for points that
are nearby.
And you want it to taper off when you go far away,
so that outliers don't get too high of a coefficient on them.
Basically, once it gets a certain distance away,
it doesn't matter if it's 2 or 6.
It's all the same.
Huber loss doesn't taper off as sharply as the others.
But it still tapers more than a quadratic.
The truncated least squares is what Teaser--
actually, Teaser's name is some truncated least squares
are some of the letters in the Teaser acronym.
There's a bunch of different functions that you might use.
Once we're in the land of nonlinear optimization,
you can just pick.
And if you can compute those distances,
and you can compute, for instance, the gradients
or whatever you need for the solver
to do that optimization, then you
can get some of these benefits of actually doing
a generalized correspondence and having some resistance
to outliers, because the distance--
the effect of points at a different distance
is neutralized.
Let me make sure I make that point.
So let's look at the truncated least squares.
That's the most straightforward here.
It goes up to 1.
And then any other points at the same distance are exactly 1.
So what does that do in an optimization?
That means if I have points that are outside my distance of 1,
they have no impact on my optimization solution.
Does that make sense?
If the point was at 2 or 2.1, it doesn't change the cost.
So because the cost is flat in the place where that point is,
that means it adds cost, but it adds a constant cost
no matter where it is out there.
So it has no effect on the optimal solution
when it's completely flat.
And these have decaying effects.
So they're marginal effect as you go up.
OK, so this is great.
So we can do--
this can now have more significant local minima,
but we can jointly estimate the correspondences,
do this more robust correspondence.
And we can somehow reject outliers
with choosing a loss function that tapers.
So why would you do one versus the other?
I mean, SVD, you would think, is a particularly fast, scalable,
numerically stable algorithm.
So you'd want to-- my bias had been to lean on that.
But more recently, people are arguing
that the nonlinear solvers for pose estimation
can be as efficient or as fast as the original SVD solvers.
And the reason is that I think we can--
I'm going to show you some tricks for precomputing
some quantities that make this function evaluation very fast.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
It's embedded here in L. So by virtue of L being the Gaussian,
you're saying, does this term need to still be there?
But you're trying to solve [INAUDIBLE]
Ah.
I'm not explicitly solving--
I should say, I don't ever have C as a decision variable.
I should say, how about we say correspondence free?
I think that would be a better--
you're right.
That would be a better way to say it.
I don't make any explicit--
I'm doing all to all correspondences, basically.
For every possible correspondence,
I'm going to compute this function.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
That depends on how we parameterize x.
So when x is the spatial notation, whatever,
I could still parameterize that only with theta.
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question was, if I'm using one of these quasi
convex functions, what can I say?
So can I get rid of p?
Is that one of your questions?
Or you're thinking about all the implications through there?
Which part of the implications are you thinking about?
I'm saying, would you still have at least a quasi convex
problem if you did a chain of the law
and did all the all correspond?
Oh, I see.
So you want to keep x as a rotation matrix in this case.
And so I think you would have--
and the question is--
I just threw my microphone that way.
I put my microphone back.
That was pretty good.
OK, so the question is, if I did use x
and I had the rotation matrix constraints,
this looks like a quasi convex objective.
Can I do anything good with that?
In general, as soon as you deviate from the SVD,
you have to do something more.
So in order to embrace those rotation matrix constraints,
you're going to have to do an SDP relaxation or something.
So it really is like this narrow ledge
that as soon as you walk away from, things get worse.
Not to say we couldn't do something clever there,
but I don't know it as a known result for me.
Let me tell you the clever trick.
It's really a nice trick.
And it goes back to this--
there are different ways to represent geometry, meshes,
or point clouds, or different methods.
And some of them make some of these queries very, very fast.
In particular, the one that makes this one very, very fast
is a sine distance function.
If you use a sine distance function or even just
a distance field computation, then you
can make these--
put them on the GPU, do things in real time,
and get to the point where you don't
care if your solver is a little bit slower than SVD.
I can do big point clouds fast.
Roughly, I want the distance--
if I have my model already specified,
and I'm going to be doing lots and lots of lookups of what
are my scene points relative to my model,
what's the distance from my scene points to my model,
why not compute an efficient data structure around my model
that makes it very fast to look up?
You don't have to do a search over all the model points
or anything like this.
Just pre-compute the heck out of it.
Make a grid in 3D where you've already
computed all the distances once.
And then it just becomes a lookup.
That's exactly what a sine distance function is.
So if I have a bunch of points here in my model,
I'm going to do queries.
I'm going to do lots of queries of the same--
what's the closest minimum distance from this
to the model points?
But I can just pre-compute level sense of all the distances
of-- this would be all the distances of distance 1,
let's say.
And then I'll go out like this, and up like this.
I can just pre-compute an entire distance field
in the more general sense.
So it turns a search between model and scene points
into a lookup.
Because everything's in 3D, you can just pre-compute it all.
It's just 3D geometry.
Now, the cool thing is this is even--
I mean, it's kind of ugly field that you
end up computing if you're doing point-to-point matching.
But if you're doing point-to-mesh or point-to-object,
then these things start looking more beautiful.
So point-to, let's say, mesh--
the same way we talked about point-to-face before.
But if I had just a box, then I can pre-compute these distance
fields.
Do the right thing.
It'll be a circle around the corner here.
That's the points of minimal distance, or distance 1.
And then I can just pre-compute these things, all my level
sets.
And in practice, the way people represent this
is they will make a grid in 3D and compute
the value of the grid.
And then a lookup is just an interpolation
between the neighboring points.
And you can get a beautiful sine distance function out.
Now, I say distance field here.
I said sine distance here.
So the big question is, what do you do on the inside?
The question is, is this distance 1?
Or is it distance negative 1?
Sine distance functions would have negative 1 here and 1
out here.
And you can pre-compute either of them.
It depends what your objective is.
When we get to non-penetration, then it
makes sense to distinguish between being inside the object
or being outside the object.
If you're really just doing point correspondences,
then maybe the distance is enough.
I think that idea of pre-computing-- yeah, please.
Is the function continuous?
I mean, there are points here.
So the question is, are you talking about continuous
in what direction or whatever?
I think there are points here where the distance is
going to be continuous.
The point it references can be discontinuous.
But the actual distance is continuous.
Right?
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
So the question is, what about the representation
on disk, if you will, of-- if I actually
sample this on a finite grid and then interpolate it at runtime,
then typically you'll have piecewise--
it'll typically be continuous but piecewise.
So it'll be continuous but discontinuous first derivatives.
Yeah.
I think the thing-- the first time you see this functions,
I think the idea that you could pre-compute that
is pretty straightforward.
The thing that surprises me is how rich
that representation can be.
Like some of these incredibly-- I mean,
I guess if you've seen NERF these days, right?
That you're already convinced.
But how compelling-- that's neural radiance fields,
which we'll talk about later.
But how incredibly rich that specification can be.
Even with a fairly coarse grid, if you do the right algorithms,
typically something called fast marching cubes,
you can find the level set.
In particular, you can find the zero level set of the object.
And you just represent an object actually
by the values on a voxel grid.
And you can get beautiful reconstruction.
So I think I have the bunny.
Right?
Like a fairly coarse sine distance function
can be interpolated into a really beautiful rich geometry
just by doing the right algorithm
to find the zero level set through this function.
OK.
So this idea of pre-computing sine distance functions
really makes these lookups super fast.
But we need one or two more steps
here to make that fully work.
The sine distance function tells me for any one model point,
for any one scene point, what is the distance to the model?
OK.
I wrote up here all to all correspondences.
The way to think about the SDF version,
which looks like a scarier optimization,
but we're in nonlinear optimization land.
We write scary things down sometimes.
So it would be min over j.
OK.
So the first thing we do is we just
take for each scene point the closest point on my model.
And only the closest point on my model
is what contributes to my total cost.
And that is the moral analogy to having a sine distance
function, where for each scene point,
you compute the value in the sine distance function.
And you contribute that to your cost.
And you can take gradients of sine distance functions
and things like that.
Right?
Maybe the root of your question before.
So you can use these in the solver,
in a nonlinear solver.
Sine distance functions are sort of inherently non-convex.
So I guess unless it's a sphere or something.
But I mean, I guess, yeah.
This could be a warped thing.
But I think they tend to be used for objects
that are complicated.
I guess they're not inherently non-convex.
That was maybe an overstatement.
So this thing here is really just the distance.
And you can make very efficient GPU implementations, too.
Where you just take a point cloud and dump it down
into the GPU computer of all and come back.
All right.
So what have we done so far?
We said nonlinear optimization lets us write
some richer objectives.
We talked about parameterizing with theta instead of with r.
That's one advantage.
And we talked about doing this sort of correspondence-free,
if you will, version by using these more messy functions.
But we can maybe make them fast.
We haven't gotten back yet.
But now we will to the non-penetration, free space,
and other constraints.
So think about the non-penetration constraints.
So if I have two bodies that I'm
trying to find the pose of at the same time,
or I'm trying to find the joint angles of my robot,
for instance, or if I just have even just one I'm
trying to find the pose, and I just
don't want it to be in contact with the table,
then in general, that is a piece of computational geometry.
So you can compute the sign distance between two bodies,
or let's say closest distance.
And if you think about that, that's
an ugly computational geometry problem.
So it's maybe this distance here.
But you can imagine all the different cases
where if I move those around, that thing
can jump around continuously.
So you need a geometry engine and your computational geometry
friend to make that sort of a query available.
So we have them in there.
So you say, in Drake, you can just say, give me geometry A,
geometry B, compute the distance or the sign distance
pair of the closest points between bodies.
It doesn't support all the bodies you'd want.
Sometimes it'll say, we haven't done that one yet.
But all the ones we've needed for our robotics applications
have been filled in.
Some of them have-- all the ones we
needed for our optimization have analytical gradients.
And that's an increasing list, but a lot of work.
Now, it's a little bit misleading here.
So the way that that function works--
so you have a scene graph object.
You need a context, basically, to get a query
object in the code here.
And then you can ask for collision distance.
That's just to say, even though that method takes only
geometry A and geometry B, in order
to even ask the questions, you instantiated
a class which you had to tell it to pose, the current pose.
So it's really a function-- think of it
as a function of the context and body A and body B.
And then it'll return the distance.
Now, you can write my nonlinear constraint.
So I can say def nonpenetration, given my parameters Q.
And you can set up my-- do all that setup
that I sort of suggested, and then call collision distance.
Give me a d and return d.
And that's close to what we want to do.
And you basically say, I want the penetration
to be greater than some value.
It would be a constraint.
So if I said--
maybe I'll call this my penetration.
And then the constraint I'll add is, minimize some objective
subject to penetration or assigned distance.
I should call it SDF.
How about that?
SDF of Q is greater than some minimum distance.
There's a lot of work that goes into those constraints.
But it all fits in the mathematical framework
we're talking about here.
So once you land in the land of nonlinear optimization,
you can just say, I'd like to search
over the possible solutions where
the distance between those two objects is--
you could say greater than or equal to 0.
You could say greater than or equal to some threshold.
And it will only--
the solver will do its best to only find solutions
that satisfy that constraint.
You will find, and we will explore,
and when we get to the more simulation part,
if your initial guess has these things completely overlapping
and deep penetration, then the gradients are no good.
And the solver is just going to say, I didn't find a solution.
Sorry, I'm stuck.
Robot falls down.
But for reasonable initial guesses,
this can work very well.
You don't have to do all this work.
For most of these queries, we have
the thing you use in your dynamics engine.
But then we also have a version of it
that is ready to use in a mathematical program.
So you can just say, add the constraint
that the distance between all the bodies
is greater than some number.
And it's just one line in your mathematical program.
So it's just like prog.addConstraint,
minimumDistance.
And it does a boatload of work behind the scenes.
But it provides those non-penetration constraints.
So that's how you get the mug out of the table
if you have a guess that starts with the mug not deeply
in the table.
And the reason for that is just that this nonlinear optimization
is not guaranteed to succeed.
Static stability, we'll talk about more
when we talk about the simulation engines next time.
But you can imagine computing basic physical quantities
and asking for--
I think if you look down here, you'll
see there's static equilibrium constraints that are also
available for you to add.
We'll make sure we understand what that has to do
with some of the physics.
But you can imagine just adding a constraint saying
that there are a set of forces that satisfy Newton's laws
and establish force balance on all the bodies.
And that would get me from having my mugs floating back
down to the table.
Every one of those makes the optimization harder.
But every one of them adds some information
that you didn't give the point set registration algorithm.
OK.
The last one, though, that we don't
have in any of the library here is this free space constraint.
So how do you tell the algorithm that you have a free space?
How would you write that in an optimization?
What are you computing?
I've got my box here.
Got a bunch of points here.
And I don't want it to match anything up here.
What do you do?
[WRITING]
I mean, it's actually-- there's a simple solution.
It took a while for me to get my head around it.
But once you have it, it's like, oh, that's
really elegant and simple.
But it's already interesting just
to think that the information here is partly
about free space.
But it's also-- I think this is a good example that you
can lose information when you go back and forth
between different geometry representations.
So in our pipeline, we went from a depth image plus the camera
position--
let's say camera pose--
to a point cloud, which felt like a good thing to do.
We've been doing a lot of work with point clouds.
But we lost something in that transformation.
We lost this camera pose.
So we're getting it back now.
How do you write it in the optimization?
I've got a vector here.
I want them to be--
I don't know.
Maybe I find a separating hyperplane.
What do you do?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
OK, so you're saying take the shortest
distance between the object.
And then what do you want to say about that?
[INAUDIBLE]
So you're saying-- OK, I think I see what you're saying.
You're saying that a query point-- basically,
if I had the whole body, then the shortest distance
between there and the camera had better
be the one I matched on.
It shouldn't be some other part of my body.
[INAUDIBLE]
Right, right.
OK, that's good.
Yeah?
Alex?
[INAUDIBLE]
So let me say that back to you here.
So a lot of times in convex optimization,
we can separate two things by finding
a line that separates them, something like this.
In fact, there might be many separating hyperplanes
that separate this from here.
So what are you going to do?
So that's an idea of a separating hyperplane.
What are you going to do with it?
[INAUDIBLE]
I mean, so you're going to push it this way.
But how does that mean that my other body shouldn't be--
you're, again, going to say that you
want the separating hyperplane to go through that point.
[INAUDIBLE]
The other points.
Yeah, right.
I mean, I think that-- right, so if all of your-- for every point
I see.
So there's a separating hyperplane between this.
It goes through this point that separates you
from every other point.
I think something like that might work.
Let me tell you the one that Tanner Schmidt did in his dark
paper.
There's a great paper called "Dynamic Articulated Real Time
Tracking."
He took the convex hull of the return points and the camera--
not the convex hull.
I'm sorry, he did the image here,
but then he completed it with the camera.
So he-- it's not the convex hull.
This object here.
And he treated that like another body.
And he said, I want to have one more non-penetration
constraint, saying that my free space, which
is this thing here, doesn't penetrate that thing.
I wouldn't be surprised if you could do better
with a separating hyperplane something.
But that fits right into the--
I mean, we've already got a bunch of non-penetration
constraints flying around.
So adding one more and putting it
into this fast GPU implementation
was a pretty reasonable thing to do.
OK, so these are weaker optimizations
that we're writing down here.
But they can take-- they solve-- they are allowed--
they take more information than we have about the problem.
So if you were to ask me today, which of these algorithms
should I use, I actually hope if you ask me again in a year
or two that we'll have convex optimizations that
do all these nice extra information.
But we don't today.
And I think the value of that information
is so high, so important, that I think I would today
trade-- take the weaker algorithm
and take advantage of that stronger information.
Or possibly interleave.
Maybe at least get an initial guess out of one
to start the other or something like that.
OK, and then let me just sort of back up
a little bit from the whole geometric perception
outline here.
So we've talked a lot about the geometry and the point
correspondences and even adding these constraints.
But unfortunately-- I mean, I wish
this was the whole perception problem.
But unfortunately, there's a lot more to perception
than geometry.
Like, in fact, I mean, depth sensors are so good.
It was interesting.
I mean, we went through this phase
where basically we were not even using the color
values in our camera.
We were just doing all this depth,
all this geometric perception.
Deep learning started happening.
It got a lot better.
And I remember asking-- there was a couple years
after that started.
I remember asking some of my students working on perception.
I said, if you had to give up either depth or RGB,
which would you give up?
And I remember when that switched.
It was like, you can take my depth.
I want the RGB.
There's just so much value in the colors
and the statistics of the scene that
isn't available just in the x, y, z positions of the points.
So that's one thing that we're going
to see the value of the more statistical approach.
Basically, the deep learning version of this
is that the reason the mug is on the table
is because I saw a lot of mugs that were on the table.
Like, oftentimes in my images, there
was a mug right around there.
And there wasn't really that many up there.
And just from the statistics of having seen a lot of images,
you get some of these priors.
And at some point, that works really well.
The geometric stuff works extremely well
when you're close to a good solution, where
the local approximations can be good or can be nearly convex.
And the global point correspondence problem
is still hard in my mind.
So I think a very nice marriage of these two
is to use your statistics, use your deep learning
to get an initial guess.
But I think you'll--
I mean, people argue about this.
But I just don't see how you could possibly
get the accuracy that you can get out of a depth
sensor that gets sub-millimeter accuracy snapping
into the point clouds.
The geometry is just so accurate that I
think most roboticists are still using the geometric perception
for that end game.
Now, you could argue that one shouldn't be accurate,
need to be accurate in order to be
successful in manipulation.
And I'm actually sympathetic to that.
But robots aren't working very well yet.
I'm not going to tie my hand behind my back.
Let me just-- if I can be accurate for my sensor,
I'm going to do that until I can get that to work.
Maybe there's a future where our controllers and our planners
are good enough that we don't have to be accurate.
But, jeez, depth sensors are really nice.
And this is really, I think, a nice way to see the world.
OK, so we'll go back.
We'll go to-- so the transition to the next lecture
is that we've been thinking about mostly
like one object in the scene, we get
to graduate to cluttered scenes on Thursday.